<post>
  <author>byvlos</author>
  <date>2020-01-07T21:38:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ekpcmb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_06/fdhzq14/</link>
  <title>Well-off, Smart, Healthy, and Empty</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Well, I told the story on my other account in another subreddit the other day, but deleted it after realizing it spilled too much private personal details. But, I mean, why do I feel like my life is meaningless? Because basically my whole life I have been at a severe disadvantage for achieving all of the normal healthy goals that humans hold, and I feel that the society around me actively sabotaged my ability to achieve these goals. </p>
      <p>Yes, I am relatively physically healthy, intelligent, young-ish, and with a materially comfortable job (it's not fulfilling, but I believe that 'fulfilling job' is a myth not consistent with history). But what's the point of it all if I'm doing it all alone. I had to move to a strange city in a foreign country to build my career. I have no family here. I have no social ties here. I am sufficiently different from the local mainstream culture that I don't have any community or neighbourhood solidarity or whatever. I have enough uncertainty in my future that I can't even take the steps to put down roots if I wanted to, because my visa status could be revoked at any time, and I need to get on a more stable and long term status before planning anything else (best case scenario this is three years out). </p>
      <p>At a larger level, there is so much background hostility towards me, everywhere and always, that it poses a considerable tax on my emotional health, causes tons of people to disrespect me and treat me like shit, and makes me feel doubly cautious and reserved about meeting new people. In order to build relationships with anyone, at all, I basically have to be ok with them occasionally just sounding off on how people who look like me are responsible for every evil in society, and how I owe them an infinite debt just to begin paying it off. It is difficult to feel like you are valued by your fellow man when all your fellow men joke about murdering you because of identity politics. </p>
      <p>Meanwhile as for relationships, I am basically hopeless. People talk a big talk about how I'm a great catch on paper, but for some reason nobody ever thinks so in reality. Between work, not having an existing social life for background events, and being confused and directionless, I have basically no mechanism to meet women. And for the ones I do meet, well, a lifetime of culture war and feminist rhetoric has crippled my ability to be an actually attractive man, due to internalizing an instinctive opposition towards the traditional male gender role. As a result, being attractive feels deeply uncomfortable to me and the obvious consequences result. </p>
      <p>So where does that leave me? It leaves me in a life where I have enough money to pay for whatever I want (at the current point in time, if I liquidated all of my assets, I could comfortably survive without working for a decade), but <em><strong>nothing else</strong></em>. I have no local community. I have no close family. I have no partner. I have no ties. I have no roots. And, more crushingly, I am stuck on a trajectory where none of this will change, and I am fast losing my window of opportunity to change this, ever. </p>
      <p>Contrast to what I imagine the past was like, or eg what my parents' experience was. They got to live their whole lives in the same place, and that place being the same place that their family has made a home for at least three generations now. They didn't have to cut all ties and up and move somewhere else just to have a shot at paying rent. They belonged to a healthy church community full of instant friends, extended relatives, and a strong social support net. They had social scripts that everybody learned, and that everyone was supposed to follow, and while these scripts were oppressive to extreme outliers, they generally ensured that young men and women were on the right path to pairing up and making families, without a decade of flailing around trying and failing to figure out how they're supposed to do all this shit properly. </p>
      <p>In short, they had <em>people who care about them</em> and they had <em>guidance through the stages of life</em>. I have neither of those things. I have had to figure out my path through the world completely and utterly on my own, with no advice, with no assistance, with no support. And, unsurprisingly, I am not good at it. So the end result is one in which every day I go to my cushy job, talk to computers and convince them to do dumb analytics or whatever, and go home. At home, I watch my bank balance rise, I eat a box of maccy cheese, drink or smoke or something, play two hours of the same video games I've been playing since 2011, and then go to sleep stuck in a spiral of existential horror, knowing that every day of my life for the next forty years will be exactly like this, and I will die childless, alone, unloved, disrespected, with no meaningful achievements, with nothing interesting to be proud of, with a gigantic pile of money but nothing of value to show for it</p>
      <p>The real mystery here is why, faced with such a thing, more people <em>don't</em> feel hopeless</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>