<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2019-12-31T23:04:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ehhmq2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_30/fcoj1yf/</link>
  <title>Ai and Benjamin Explore Locked Doors</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Okay...but doesn't it strike you as the tiniest bit...unhealthy...from a cultural/societal perspective that all those people are armed... in a small church?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I imagine a parallel conversation happening between an American and a Japanese person.  Let us call them Ai and Benjamin, for the sake of this hypothetical example.</p>
      <p>A: Wait a minute.  When you leave your house, you lock the door?</p>
      <p>B: Of course we do.  It's simple.  Most of us do it without even thinking about it.</p>
      <p>A: But...doesn't it strike you as the tiniest bit...unhealthy...from a cultural/societal perspective that you can't trust your neighbors not to burglarize your home while you're at work?</p>
      <p>B: Well, it costs so little.  Just 15 seconds of your time every morning when you leave and enter your home.  Aren't you better off safe than sorry?  Even if my trust my neighbor, there will always be <em>some</em> members of society who are willing to steal from others, and I'd rather not make myself an easy victim. I mean, there aren't very many thieves out there, but the risk is always there, so why <em>not</em> lock your door?</p>
      <p>A: There are lots of reasons not to lock your door!  For example, when maintenance people or repair people need to get into your house to fix something while you are out, how are they supposed to get in?  I'm sure that whatever solution you have to that problem is much more cumbersome than just leaving the door unlocked.  Plus, locks are expensive, and sometimes need to be replaced.  And besides the financial cost of replacing a broken lock, a broken lock might prevent you from getting into your home.  Or maybe the lock works fine, but you lose your keys when you are out, and you lock yourself out of your home.  Plus, I've heard that this aura of mistrust that Americans have has led to situations <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Louis_Gates_arrest_controversy">where people have gotten arrested by police when trying to enter their own homes</a>.  It seems deeply unhealthy.  I don't understand why or how Americans can live like this.</p>
      <p>B: Well, a few years ago my neighbor left his door unlocked, and someone entered his home and stole a laptop computer from him.</p>
      <p>A: And yet you still live in this neighborhood?  Why?  Why did your neighbor not immediately move after this incident?  It seems terrifying to live a society where you are constantly in fear of people entering your home and stealing your possessions. I just found out that there are people who are so scared of their fellow American citizens that they create locks not just for their home, but for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gated_community">entire neighborhoods</a> where you're not able to enter without a key.</p>
      <p>B: I mean, this is just a basic fact of life.  Sometimes people try to steal from you.  Some people go to extreme measures, like living in a gated community, or buying an expensive security system.  I personally think this is overkill, I just lock my door when I go out.  I don't see why this is such a big deal to you.</p>
      <p>A: And I don't understand how you Americans can possibly feel safe in a country where people entering your home and stealing from you is such a big problem that you feel the need to lock your door every day.</p>
      <p>B: Well, some people do actually leave their doors unlocked.  I had a friend who did that for several years when she lived in a nice upscale neighborhood, and never had any problems.</p>
      <p>A: See!  I knew it!  You don't need locks after all!  I'm sure that if Americans adopted the norm of simply not locking their doors, they'd come to realize how paranoid and neurotic they were being, and that life is fine even if you don't have a lock for your door.</p>
      <p>B: But one of the reasons that people like her can get away with leaving their doors unlocked is a sort of "herd immunity" effect.  If she widely publicized the fact that she left her door unlocked and published her address online, she'd probably get robbed.  But because her house was in a neighborhood where lots of people have theft-prevention methods in place, the expected value of a thief trying to enter a home in that neighborhood is kept relatively low.  If <em>everyone</em> left their doors unlocked, then thieves could just go around all day entering homes without as much fear of reprisal. In fact, that's actually a problem in <a href="https://www.thecrimson.com/article/2016/9/27/laptop-theft/">college dorms, where lots of students don't lock their rooms, and thus some thieves have discovered that they can enter a dorm and quickly make off with a dozen laptops</a> without much difficulty.  A similar thing happens in some businesses, like <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=apple+store+robbery">Apple stores</a> where they have thousands of dollars in display units that thieves can come and quickly make off with.  It's become something of an epidemic.  The best way to prevent is by not making yourself an easy target, and the easiest way to do that is by putting a lock on your door.</p>
      <p>A: Wow, I didn't realize that things were so bad in America.</p>
      <p>B: *shrugs*  This is just the way things are here.  You get used to it.  Putting a lock on my door seems a lot easier than trying to get an entire nation of people to not steal from each other.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>