<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-01-03T01:32:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ehhmq2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_30/fcw1r5p/</link>
  <title>On MOOCs and Motivation</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Just my quick hot take on MOOCs as an academic: there's this idea that MOOCs will allow for us to make education a lot cheaper and more accessible thereby giving more people access to the education and skills they need on an ongoing basis throughout their lives. That is a worthy goal and I hope MOOCs succeed. However, as others have noted, if you just want to get good at coding or learn about the history of the thirty years war or how to become a better writer or how to get into graphic design, you can get most if not all of the way there already without MOOCs, just using internet resources. It's a bit mysterious, then, why so few people bother doing this.</p>
      <p>The simple answer in my view is that the most important variable in improving students' performance is sustaining their engagement and motivation, and this is already a daunting challenge for in-person teaching. I've taught at a mostly blue collar-family/immigrant inner city school and at a super prestigious college, and in both cases (and generalising crudely) most students seemed to regard classes as an annoyance and a hassle, and at best as a form of entertainment, and dropout rates were high and increasing. There's no way most of them would have the willpower and drive to stick with a MOOC. They barely had the willpower to stick with their program of study even when living on-site and continually surrounded by classmates and teachers.</p>
      <p>But there are ways of fighting back against this. With a charismatic instructor, exciting course design, and lots of personal attention given to students, it's definitely possible  to bolster students' lackluster innate drive with externally moored feelings of collegiality, solidarity, and responsibility among students and between them and the instructor. In other words: you may not care about Durkheim, but you'll stay up till 3am writing about him because you care about your instructor's good opinion of you and/or not letting down your groupmates.</p>
      <p>I don't see this working well for MOOCs - I feel far fewer qualms about disappointing an instructor or classmate I've only seen online than one who took me out to coffee yesterday for an hour to discuss how I can improve as a writer. So in terms of highly motivating modes of instruction, MOOCs aren't going to be able to compete with traditional education. But likewise, if the goal isn't specifically to get students invested in the material but to just pump information out into the airwaves and hope that 5% of people finish the course, then I don't see that MOOCs offer a great deal over and above just letting that intrinsically motivated 5% engage in self study using our amazing online resources and forums.</p>
      <p>That comes across as more pessimistic than I mean to - I can definitely imagine some highly motivated people would benefit from a more structured online learning environment, while still not requiring the kind of intensive and expensive in-person monitoring you get in a traditional university education. Hell, I'm one of them - I've used Duolingo more 6 months every day, for example. But the vast majority of friends I know who've tried it did it for a couple of weeks top. So I think that MOOCs have real promise for a very specific market rather than being the future of education.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>