<post>
  <author>j9461701</author>
  <date>2020-01-05T19:19:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ekd036/there_is_no_case_for_the_humanities/fdayy4w/</link>
  <title>The Decline of the Seven Liberal Arts</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The seven liberal arts had a wide mandate covering most of what we consider the humanities, as well as mathematics in all its branches and the physical and natural sciences. Alongside the arts were the three highers — theology, law, and medicine — which had a more professional orientation and sat in an occasionally uneasy truce with the arts.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Wait no this isn't actually true. The seven liberal arts were:</p>
      <p>Grammar, logic, rhetoric, arithmetic, geometry, music, and astronomy</p>
      <p>These are all vastly more utilitarian subjects than modern humanities classes.  They were supposed to train a freeman (or maybe a free woman wearing a moustache) how to be a functional member of society. That's why they're called the <em>liberal</em> arts - liberal, as in liber, as in "free". As in the arts a free man should know. As contrasted against the artes illiberales, which are pursued for economic benefit. </p>
      <p>The goal isn't to teach you how to smoke a pipe while thinking deeply about Italian romance novels, but how to defend yourself in court (logic + rheteric), maintain a ledger of debts and payments (arithmetic), write coherent letters (grammer), extract dating information from constellations (astronomy). Music was originally called harmonics, and was not about learning to play music but instead understanding how one should <em>write</em> music. Which is why music was packaged with the artes reales (astronomy, geometry, arithematic), or the mathematical-physical arts. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>We do not need to spend our time justifying our existence. All we need to do is put our hand to the plow. Scholarship has built institutions before and will do so again. Universities have declined and come to flourish once more. The humanities, which predate the university and may well survive it, will endure — even if there is no case to defend them.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I mean sure except not really. The humanities may have faltered financially before, but it has never faltered <em>culturally</em> like it currently has. Everoyne regarding English degrees as a dumb waste of time is more dangerous than 1,000 university bankruptcies, because it destroys the only reason aristocratic fancy pants have to send their children off. If getting a humanities degree marks one as a 'sucker', then the humanities' reputation - all it has left - is gone and may never come back.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>