<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-01-08T21:32:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ekpcmb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_06/fdl93v2/</link>
  <title>A Conservative Judiciary; a Progressive Armageddon: Meditations on a Potential “Constitutional” Coup</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Part 1</p>
      <p>
        <strong>A Conservative Judiciary; a Progressive Armageddon: Meditations on a Potential “Constitutional” Coup</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I don’t think people outside of right wing circles understand just how monomaniacally obsessed with the courts the right is. </p>
      <p>People will say “Oh, the supreme court appointments really informed the evangelical vote for Trump”  but then they’ll point to other Trump problems and be exasperated with those same evangelicals for supporting him in a way that just Betrays how much they don’t understand.</p>
      <p>For the modern Right the supreme court and the judiciary isn’t just an equal branch of government to the presidency and the Congress.... it is the government.</p>
      <p>The average right wing partisan or intellectual would gladly trade years, if not entire terms, of the presidency for their justices of choice. Hell if you made the offer “instead of Bush Sr. Having his term, Bush Jr. having his two terms, and Trump getting elected (4 presidential terms), you’d give those 16 years to the Clintons (no term limits, switch off when they feel like)  but you get to replace the 5 most liberal justices of the supreme court with conservative justices of your picking” they’d almost certainly make that trade. </p>
      <p>They’d surrender the presidency for 30 years if only they could have the courts. </p>
      <p>And really can you blame them?</p>
      <p>The vast majority of  the most important changes in politics, especially to social conservatives, since 1970 have come through the courts. Abortion, Gay Marriage, The vast majority of Discrimination “Law”, almost every culture war defeat conservatives have suffered, has come not through the democratic will of a majority of the population but through the Judicial Fiat of (often) 5 of 9 appointed Lawyers who (more often than not) have never won an election to anything.</p>
      <p>But there’s more! The court’s, and especially the supreme court’s, job is to “interpret” the constitution and peoples fundamental rights and then to “defend” those “principles” from the ”excesses” of the legislature and the state.</p>
      <p>Or put simply Constitutional Law is superior to ordinary law (that is actually passed by the legislature, signed off by the president, ect.), if an ordinary law violates con law its automatically void, and the supreme court decided what Constitutional Law is. Full stop.</p>
      <p>Sure you could pass an amendment (good luck), but who’s going to “interpret” how that amendment gets applied. </p>
      <p>Essentially as long as they can avoid provoking a coup, or an amendment abolishing them, the 9 justices of the supreme court enjoy defacto dictator status. The only limits being how plausibly they can make their whims sound like they are really there in the constitution/natural law/human liberty/precedent, ect., and thus avoid provoking that coup.</p>
      <p>There is a real asymmetry here, Whereas progressive politics insists on its modernness, new-found rationality, and (increasingly) its break from precedent and the historical rule(s) of “old white men”, conservatives insist on their place in a long tradition that stretches back to the founding and before, their esteem for the founding principles, the principles of a free  and liberal (in the Classical sense!) republic, and the constitution in particular.</p>
      <p>now which side do you think would have an advantage in a game where the only rules are “make it plausibly sound like its in the constitution or demanded by historical ideals”?</p>
      <p>As much as conservatives complain about the progressive bent of the court from the 60s to today, the progressives actually couldn’t use the the court that effectively. Sure They practiced judicial activism as hard as they could,  but it was an uphill battle: </p>
      <p>Abortion: ok you stopped the government from enforcing a law; Gay Marriage: OK you broadened the definition of a legal institution which mostly affects some tax incentives; Discrimination law: OK you managed to apply the civil rights Act and not block a congressional action you agree with; Countless expansions of executive power: OK you didn’t act to block other branches of government.</p>
      <p>Most of the progressive agenda are simply things you can’t get through the court without stretching its mandate past the limits: increased taxes (the constitution was painfully specific about who had to do that), Banning Guns (a supreme court could refuse to uphold 2A but it couldn’t institute a Ban by itself; how many prosecutors does the judiciary have?), regulating CO2 emissions (you could maybe get lawsuits for damages out of the most progressive court conceivable).</p>
      <p>Sure you could skew minor decisions in the direction your party favours, but this is true of every position of authority. The simple truth is progressive policy preferences, almost without fail, demand vast new bureaucracies that the court is almost singularly unable to create on its own, except for some private institutions it can foist liability on.</p>
      <p>The Conservative-Libertarian fusionist right however has a vastly different policy program, the correct language and values to achieve it through the court, and is uniquely focussed on things the courts could achieve acting alone.</p>
      <p>...</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Continue to Part 2 below (do not reply to this comment)</strong>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>