<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2020-01-08T21:31:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ekpcmb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_06/fdl900v/</link>
  <title>Background on U.S. - Iran Tensions</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Right, so. I’d like to register my understanding of the current tension between Iran and the US.</p>
      <p>Conventional war between us will unfold with ghastly predictability- our army kicks the piss out of theirs, at which point we get bogged down in a horrific insurgency that we have zero chance of defeating and which will make the worst days of Iraq look like a touch football game in middle school.</p>
      <p>We know this. Iran knows this. So traditionally, we very carefully make sure not to invade Iran, and they in turn very carefully ensure they do not provoke an invasion.</p>
      <p>The problem is the Bomb. Every country with a nuclear weapon has a Get Out of Free Card when it comes to being invaded. Iran is incentivized to make one, because then the basic equation that governs their foreign policy changes in their favor.</p>
      <p>If they acquired the Bomb, one of two things will happen. Either they’ll flex their muscles and assert their power by closing the Strait of Hormuz, which is like crushing the nuts of the world economy in a steel vice, or they’ll stay chill... at which point the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia who they have a regional Cold War with will try to acquire the Bomb too to even the scale. The first option is the nightmare scenario that keeps John Bolton’s mustache awake at night. The second isn’t much better- two nuclear armed bands of religious fanatics who hate each other and have boundless faith in God. With luck, the winds will change and 80% of the fallout will drift to some other continent, but either way you can kiss the global supply chain goodbye.</p>
      <p>Iran is and always has been about 4-6 months of hard work away from constructing a usable nuclear bomb; 4-6 months is the perpetual Doomsday Clock that occasionally comes to life and ticks its way towards that aforementioned invasion that every knows will be a disaster for everyone. But the simple fact is that America is incentivized to invade <em>anyway</em> if Iran starts that Doomsday Clock ticking too long; it’ll be fucking awful, but still easier than invading a country with a nuke, and still better than a nuclear exchange.</p>
      <p>And in the meantime, the Cold War between Iran and KSA simmers on by proxy, keeping the hate and power politics alive and well and making sure everybody is on edge all the time.</p>
      <p>It is, to put it bluntly, a fucked up situation for all players.</p>
      <p>Obama found a way out- the Nuclear Deal. He took a sword out and hacked away at the Gordian Knot, separating the feud between Iran and the KSA/USA from the question of nuclear armament entirely. They were now officially two different questions.</p>
      <p>Iran had to agree to destroy what progress they had made in developing the Bomb, promise not to start up again, and allow observers into their country in perpetuity to monitor them to prevent sneaky Bomb making. In exchange, they get increased access to the world market, the freedom to pursue nuclear energy distinct from weaponry, and a great big stack of cash- the holdings we froze back when they first dare piss us off in 1979. If at any time they barred the observers or fucked around trying to start up the 4-6 months clock again, all sanctions would kick back in and we would be free to go back to plan A- invasion, piss kicking, horrific insurgency, etc.</p>
      <p>It was a stroke of diplomatic genius- the nearest parallel I can think of is perhaps Nixon going to China. It didn’t even cost us much- we were still free to go on the warpath if we needed to, and the cash we paid out was Iranian to start with. The only problem with it was that a goodly portion of the increased revenue and the fat stack of cash would be used to fund terrorism and tyranny by Iran’s allies in the region. But fuck it, says I. Better an extra couple of bombs in Beirut and Sadr City than nuclear holocaust.</p>
      <p>And it worked. Shit calmed down. Inspectors went in and verified good faith compliance on the Iranians’ part. There were hiccups- Iranians were found with stuff they shouldn’t have, plants were shut down, stocks disposed  of. But it <em>worked</em>.</p>
      <p>And then Trump unilaterally backed out of the agreement and imposed sanctions anyway. And acted outraged when the Iranians failed to uphold their end of the deal- the deal that he’d unilaterally backed out of.</p>
      <p>All the rest of it- the Embassy attacks, Suleimani getting got, the missiles, the diplomatic posturing, the Twitter slapfights- whatever. Same difference. Maybe shit might have kicked off, maybe not. Six of one, half dozen of the other.</p>
      <p>Trump has welded the regional Cold War back to Iranian nuclear weapons again. That means we are back to where we started, perpetually 4-6 months away from a horrific invasion that will ruin everybody involved. Except now there’s fresh blood to avenge and more broken promises hanging around our neck and less international support for cracking down on Iran.</p>
      <p>I do not believe that Trump fucked up at all by killing Suleimani or by talking tough when the Iranians shrieked about it. Killing Suleimani wasn’t dumb, unless the rumors that he was lured into the kill zone with talks of truce are accurate- even then, killing the Maestro conducting the orchestra of Iranian Guerrilla Warfare would have been a worthy objective marred by a dishonorable method, which may sound irrelevant but will bite us in the ass next time we need to negotiate in good faith for realsies. So fingers crossed that the Iraqi PM was talking bullshit.</p>
      <p>But I do believe that Trump fucked up by tearing the guts out of the Iran Nuclear Deal with no alternative to fall back on other than the Doomsday Clock of the status quo. In my opinion he has fucked up Iranian-American relations for a generation, until the preteens of today grow up and become the old men who direct policy when their elders and the elders’ sons die off. With luck, everybody will stay rational and self-interested and keep poking each other in the eye at sustainably relaxed  levels until a new rapport can be established.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>