<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2020-01-10T02:34:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ekpcmb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_06/fdpa9o1/</link>
  <title>Who Checks the Checks and Balances?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I’m going to bypass talking about all of your points because I find them too accurate to argue with and grab one quote from you that I want to expound on-</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Many people will object that the AUMF is so broad as to grant the President an unlimited ability to bypass Congress and do anything he wants in the Middle East. Critically, that does not make it illegal. It means Congress wrote a blank check and are upset that the President is trying to cash it.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Having extremely liberal friends and and family and a couple of progressive friends and family, I have seen a fair amount of this attitude- the idea not only that there ought to be some kind of overarching authority monitoring those in power for overreach and abuses, but that <em>there actually is</em> some kind of overarching authority monitoring and they’re all outraged that this power is not doing its job by allowing The Latest News From This Administration And From Other Political Arenas to have occurred.</p>
      <p>This attitude is also present online (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/politics/">source</a>)</p>
      <p>It is an instinctive view so disconnected from reality that I find myself staggered anew every time I encounter it.</p>
      <p>Of course there is no overarching power to step in if President Trump does something bad. Trump <em>is</em> the fucking overarching power. What the fuck did you think the election is about, whose painting gets to be hung next in the White House?</p>
      <p>Literally the whole system of government across the three branches is taking the power of life and death and placing it into the hands of a few hundred people to act in your stead. If they act badly, no one will ever step and and tell them not to; deciding who gets to be the step-in-and-stop-people person is what we vote for for the Chief Executive, deciding what specifically that person shall stop and hassle people for is why you vote for senators and congressmen, and of course the awesome power of the high office of Telling the People-Stoppers and the Law-Setters What They’re Doing Wrong Person is too powerful and sacred to be left to the mob.</p>
      <p>Like, that’s all there is. No one is double checking the machinery but us. Once you invest power in somebody, they get to use it. This is some heavy shit, and like any other engine it’ll go wrong and wreck itself if you stop paying attention to it long enough.</p>
      <p>This is why people used to grab weapons and demand the right to vote- it wasn’t just based on some noble principle or persuasive bit of moral rhetoric. People hated who had the power to stop and hassle them, and found that the law supported the tyrant and never them. Democracy was as natural as rebellion, and the would be rebels who waited for some higher power to step in and stop the People-Stopper died in chains.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>