<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-01-06T18:04:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ekpcmb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_06/fde92np/</link>
  <title>On Loneliness, Adolescence, and the Drive for Connection</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>What do people here think would be the consequence of a dramatic increase in youth antidepressant usage?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>...while I recognize that correlation is not causation, aren't we <em>looking at</em> a world where there has <em>already been</em> a dramatic increase in youth antidepressant usage?  "Antidepressants cause suicide" is an idea in circulation, broadly taken as a signal of low-status conspiracy theory but also one that has received a fair bit of scholarly attention.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>What factors do you think are driving the current increase in youth suicides? Aside from method, what do you think drives the disparity in male vs female suicides today?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It is almost certainly a Moloch problem, <em>however</em>, I am willing to stick my Freudian neck out a little and state my suspicion that it is substantially about the relationship between the biological and social status of sex and sexuality.  Starting from pretty early in adolescence, almost all males, and many females, experience dramatic biological drive to participate in procreative activity.  But culturally we make it essentially impossible for them to do so in socially constructive ways.  New Atheism sometimes talked about this in terms of religiously-induced shame (and you can still find occasional discussions of this in places like ex-Christian and ex-Muslim support sites) but the problem is much more deeply ingrained than that.  Western societies continue to reject traditional guiding frameworks for socially-acceptable routes to procreative fulfillment, while failing to replace those frameworks with any realistic alternatives.  Early sexual encounters are increasingly either parasocial (via pornography or social media) or drug-and-alcohol encouraged, and with increasingly fraught questions of consent.  Young people are having less sex (and fewer babies) than they had in the past (antidepressants often complicate this also, hmm) even as sexualized media proliferates.  Individualism's triumph over familial commitments deprive even long-term monogamous pairs of certainty and stability, casting the worth of historical partner trade-offs into doubt.</p>
      <p>I can remember how much I wanted children when I was younger, but I admit I can no longer remember what it <em>felt</em> like to want children.  I just remember that I <em>did</em> feel it.  I can remember that I felt paralyzingly lonely as an adolescent, and looking back on those years it seems like <em>utter bullshit</em>.  I had so many friends!  I can count them and name them!  These days I pretty much never feel lonely, though I have far fewer close relationships than I did when I was young.  It is pretty widely understood that sex drive fades with age, but the <em>social</em> roles that biological drive plays are much more complicated, I think, than merely procreative, and I think they manifest in a lot of weird and unpredictable ways.</p>
      <p>Children and adults, for most of human history, were a pretty integrated group.  Children worked alongside their parents, mostly, from the time they were born until they could be trusted to work independently.  Sexual activity has always been somewhat complicated but generally there was a great deal of communal support in making the transition from child to adult--often, in the form of elaborate rituals and celebrations.  These days, we wedge adolescents into a vast sexual wasteland where they are treated neither as children (to be shielded from sex and sexuality by virtue of their innocence) nor adults (fully permitted to engage in consensual endeavors and fully bear the consequences of doing so).  Not only that, we also routinely expand that wasteland, raising the age at which we find it socially acceptable to freely engage in sexual activity, to marry, to have children, and so forth.</p>
      <p>I do not think sex is the only issue, in other words, but I think the state of sex paints a pretty bleak picture for contemporary adolescence generally.  Not everyone experiences procreative urges, but all of us, in some way or another, go looking for meaning and value and purpose in life.  We are social animals.  Maturation and family formation are hardwired by our biology.  Putting those forces under social pressure can shape them (and distort them), but it cannot eliminate them.  "If I can't be with you now and forever then I'd rather just die" has been a sentiment in romantic drama for as long as there has been romantic drama; we mock it when it manifests in media today, but our young people still feel it, because that's how young people think, sometimes.  That we mock them for it likely does not improve the world for them.  They need society's guidance, and our empathy--even when they deny that they need it.  We generally give them neither.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>