<post>
  <author>tfowler11</author>
  <date>2019-12-31T03:21:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ehhmq2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_30/fcm2h9g/</link>
  <title>Negligence in Police Firearms Training</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>According to the article (and if it's wrong, the point falls), the  shooter was taken down by a "member of the church's security team". If  that's the case, it's not really a central example of "good guys with  guns" which usually is meant to evoke a bystander rather than a security  team. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The security member was apparently rather competent but its still "a good guy with a gun".  Even cops are (and cops, and some armed private security, are often not nearly as well trained as people think they are.  </p>
      <p>----</p>
      <p>...Here’s the dirty little secret about police  training…it rarely  happens.  If the common citizen knew how poorly  trained the average cop  is there would be complete anarchy.  Most  agencies have a wholly  inadequate firearms training  program.  In talking to cops around my  state as a firearms instructor  for the last 15 years, I’ve found that  most departments do very little  firearms training. Shooting more than  100 rounds per year is unusual. </p>
      <p>In Ohio, officers only have to pass a 25-round ridiculously easy   “qualification test” one time per year.  Beyond that, the state requires   between one and four hours (depending on the year) of continuing   education training.  None of that has to be firearms related.  Because  the state doesn’t mandate in service firearms training, lazy police  executives often say “<em>The state says 25 rounds a year is all we need to do, so that’s all we will do.”</em></p>
      <p>Here’s another part of the equation: with few exceptions,  office-bound police  administrators almost universally hate shooting.   It’s an arena where  they can be shown up by the low ranking patrol  officers.  It makes them  feel inadequate.  It’s easier to sit in an air  conditioned office with  bars or eagles on their shoulders pretending to  be competent than it  is to actually acquire the firearms competency they  need.  In training police officers all around the country, it is rare  for me to see anyone above the rank of Sergeant shooting in my classes.</p>
      <p>I had one chief (who wasn’t a bad shooter) actually tell me: <em>“Guns are loud and dirty.  I don’t like them.”</em>  How diligent do you think this chief will be when it comes to making his officers train with their pistols?</p>
      <p>Cops in Ohio don’t have to shoot in low level light.  All stages of   the current qualification are shot in full light conditions.  Since the   state doesn’t require officers to demonstrate their skills, most   departments don’t train them.</p>
      <p>If the departments do train in low  light tactics, they shoot a few  rounds at a stationary target after  some remedial instruction on  flashlight shooting techniques.  The  officers fire a magazine or two  using their flashlights and then  promptly forget the skill until a few  years later when the cycle is  repeated.</p>
      <p>In this type of low light training,  there is no stress.  There are no  demands placed on the student and  there is no scenario-based element  whatsoever.  Officers need to learn  to shoot in the dark, but they also  need to learn how to search in the  dark, handle people in the dark,  handcuff suspects in the dark, and  cover their partners in the dark.   That training is exceedingly rare.</p>
      <p>Besides a lack of a state mandate and “budgetary concerns” the other  significant problem in police training is the instructor  training/certification process.  In my two-week police firearms  instructor course, the lead instructor made the statement:</p>
      <p>
        <em>“Every one of you was sent here by  your department.  Your chief must  think you will be a good instructor or  he wouldn’t have sent you.  Who  am I to disagree with his assessment?   I trust your chiefs.  Everyone will pass this course.”</em>
      </p>
      <p>So we have an “instructor” course taught by a man who was so fat that  he couldn’t even demonstrate some of the required firing positions,  with absolutely no standards, that everyone automatically passes.  The  class was worthless.</p>
      <p>But that is all the “training” that most of the police  instructors  get.  They think it’s the pinnacle of their education.  It  isn’t.  Any  commercial shooting school will yield better firearms  handling skills  and shooting abilities than most police “instructor” schools.  Yet few  cops will spend their own money to seek out better training on their  own.</p>
      <p>The result ends up being that well-intentioned, but poorly trained  “instructors” get minimal training time to pass on what little knowledge  they have to officers who know (and often care) even less.</p>
      <p>Is there any wonder why we have negligent shootings?  It’s not the   fault of a flashlight switch.  It’s the result of non-existent or   completely inept training...</p>
      <p>
        <a href="http://www.activeresponsetraining.net/weapon-mounted-lights-and-a-dirty-little-police-secret">http://www.activeresponsetraining.net/weapon-mounted-lights-and-a-dirty-little-police-secret</a>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>