<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-05-01T13:03:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/myr3n7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_26_2021/gwjbmvj/</link>
  <title>Reflections on the English Class System (1/2)</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <h3>
        <strong>Reflections on the English Class System</strong>
      </h3>
      <p>When I first moved to the UK seven years ago, I had a pretty blase view - like many outsiders, I'm sure - of the English class system. '<em>Every nation</em>, of course, has a class system', I thought. America certainly does. Britain would be no different, but was also unlikely to be anything special. The reality is quite different. Class in Britain is unique in the developed, and indeed much of the developing world. It is codified and uncodified, the product of both institutional inertia and the ongoing stake <em>the vast majority</em> of the public has in their own specific class identity. </p>
      <p>For all of Britain's many issues, I also think the class system is uniquely successful, especially when it comes to assimilating new elites and conserving the power of the existing upper classes alongside them. I use British and English here somewhat interchangeably - but where I use English it is usually because some other countries in the UK (especially Scotland but also Northern Ireland) have specific local class dynamics and national/religious identities with which I am less familiar.  </p>
      <h3>
        <strong>Class as Identity</strong>
      </h3>
      <p>America has many upper classes, none of which is necessarily objectively dominant in every social sphere. What counts as more or less upper class in a New England yacht club is different to that which counts at a Miami beach club, which in turn is different to what counts at an Idaho retreat for Silicon Valley venture capitalists, which in turn is different to what counts in Hollywood. The American upper class has some shared interests, but it is not a universal clique (it contains cliques). There are objective standards of <em>power</em> and <em>influence</em>, but not of class. All of the above might be big Democratic Party donors, but that doesn't make them the same social cluster. Nevertheless, they still all sit - to varying degrees - at the top of the American pyramid. </p>
      <p>In Britain, class is a pure identity that becomes more universal as one rises the class hierarchy - the upper middle and upper class are increasingly multiracial and even religiously diverse, but they speak the same way, attend the same schools, and have many of the same hobbies. They are a clique. There is a climbable hierarchy, but it requires careful action over multiple generations, and many who can choose not to climb it. This manifests itself perhaps most suddenly to outsiders upon realizing that, for Brits, there are working class billionaires and upper class university adjuncts struggling to feed themselves, but that is really only a small part of it. In Britain, social class - more than region, income, race, religion, profession, national identity/patriotism or any other status differentiator - is the primary determinant not just of the way outsiders judge people, but of the way people see themselves. Brits may dispute it, but this is merely because they have so fully internalized their class identity that they can no longer identify it as separate from who they are. Class furnishes British people with their hobbies and interests, with their conversation topics, with their political views (not their <em>votes</em>, which are often malleable, but their priorities), with their weltanschauung entirely. </p>
      <h3>
        <strong>A Brief Overview of English Class</strong>
      </h3>
      <p>The English (and, to a large extent, British) class system is split into three main groups, each with many sub-categories. These correlate broadly with, but as we have seen do not <em>necessitate</em> (except in one case, which I will note below) economic status, though the relationship is not necessarily causal (as we will once again discuss later). The population size estimates are my own. </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            <strong>Working class (~82-90% of the population)</strong>
          </p>
          <p>The working class comprises the vast bulk of the British population, including almost everybody who attends state (public, for Americans) school. In recent decades, some political movements, notably Blair's Labour, have attempted to import the American definition of 'middle class' into the UK, but most people - especially working class Brits - know this is fake. The sum total of regional accents in England (and also to a significant extent in the rest of the nation) are working class, as the middle and upper classes usually speak with similar (received pronounciation - henceforth RP) accents wherever they are from or live. Working class people heavily police each other, and heavy mockery ensues any attempt by somebody working class to rise above their station by pretending to be of a higher class or adopting an RP accent. Working class subgroups are differentiated by region, profession, home ownership or lack thereof, income and wealth and many other factors. </p>
          <p>This group does comprise the native underclass, but it also comprises decamillionaire football/soccer players, business tycoons, wealthy tradesmen and the majority (but not entirety) of small business owners. Working class Brits broadly prefer soccer to cricket and rugby, although this isn't universally true. They are much more tied to their region than those in above them. They tend not to go to university, and have lower rates of university attendance even when they have money - white working class men have the lowest university attendance rate in the UK. The archetypal member of the British working class is the 'white van man' ie. small-time wheeler-dealer, maybe running a construction business or working as a plumber, always trying to hustle his way to more success, loves drinking at the pub with the boys, goes on vacation to drink in Spain once or twice a year and comes back red as a tomato, if he does well one month he'll go out and buy a £2000 TV, and upgrade to the £100/month HD sports package on TV.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <strong>Middle Class (9-15% of the population)</strong>
          </p>
          <p>Note the capital 'C' in class. This is because Middle Class in the UK is both a descriptor of things, stores, phrases and so on alongside a class descriptor. Certain stores (for example the beloved department store John Lewis), certain trips (spending one's summer vacation in Tuscany or the Provence instead of Spain) and certain activities (cycling) are often decried as "so middle class". The middle class refers largely to knowledge workers who mostly went to elite state or private schools (together maybe 9% of the population) and then university, followed by 'white collar' work in a big city (mostly London) - it includes doctors, most bankers, most lawyers, but also many people who work in media, journalism, TV production, big tech, government, academia and so on. Some are wealthy and some are poorer (many will earn less than the plumber 'white van man'), but they almost all have RP accents we mentioned earlier. This grouping is immensely diverse, and contains within both liberals and conservatives, cosmopolitan, Guardian or Vice-reading progressives and the rural middle classes, college deans and successful restaurant owners. It aligns to <em>some extent</em> with what one might call the PMC in the United States, but it also includes things like successful farmers who send their kids to boarding school, which probably woulnd't be included in the US. </p>
          <p>The middle classes are the object of immense ridicule by the classes above and below them, but quietly run the nation and are often happy with their 'lot'. Middle class status in Britain is always multigenerational but relatively easily obtained - it essentially requires that one have enough money to send one's child to usually minor private schools from a young age, where they will learn to speak in the correct way and to join Britain's professional classes. This is a choice that, as mentioned, many more affluent working class people <em>choose not to make</em>, but some do. It is possible to drop out of the middle class over several generations if nobody in the family can afford to send the next generation to private school, but this is <em>quite</em> rare because usually in England grandparents and relatives will help out.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>