<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-05-03T13:33:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/n3pe45/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_03_2021/gws4mmz/</link>
  <title>"Gen X is now the face of American power, and just happens to be ruling the country in partnership with its first true Silent Generation President."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>In Defense of the Boomers, First Victims of the Culture War</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Spurred by a discussion in the Sunday thread yesterday, I actually think the Baby Boomers are arguably the most scapegoated generation in American history, and don’t deserve even the remotest amount of the opprobrium directed toward them. I’ll tackle this on two fronts - the typically liberal/progressive criticism that the baby boomers had an economic free ride in the glorious postwar years of endless prosperity when anyone with a pulse could get a good job and buy a big house, and subsequently destroyed the jobs market, the environment etc etc.., and the typically conservative criticism that boomers spurred a cultural revolution that saw promiscuity, divorce and single motherhood become the norm, religiosity declined, immigration shoot up and social ties fray. </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>“The Me Generation”. The typical progressive criticism of baby boomers is that they benefited from the postwar boom, found employment easy and benefited from huge upswings in American quality of life over long and easy careers. </p>
          <p>The reality is quite different. Most baby boomers finish high school or college in the 1970s or early 1980s, and practically none of them begin their careers before the postwar boom is over. Most early boomers start their careers during the oil crisis, stagflation, sky high interest rates, daily hysterical chatter about the Soviets actually maybe winning the Cold War, the fallout from Vietnam, high unemployment, high gas prices, and a huge climate of doom and gloom exacerbated by skyrocketing crime rates and urban blight in all of America’s major cities. If they do well enough to get on the career ladder they deal with the recession of the early 90s, and then the dotcom burst in 2001 melting their savings and investments. Then comes 2008. The archetypal baby boomer is at the peak of their earning power in 2008 - and suddenly faces unemployment (much more difficult to get hired again once you’re 50+) and a huge fall in the value of their investments. Many boomers who lose their professional/white collar jobs won’t get hired again in the same role as they’re replaced by Gen X during the 2010s boom years, slashing their lifetime earning potential drastically. Even for those who keep their jobs, their peak earning years happen during the biggest financial crisis in almost a century. Boomers start and end their careers in a time of economic hardship, while the generation before them (the Silent Generation - born 1926 to 1946) and the generation after (Gen X, born 1962-1982 or so) see in <em>many</em> cases their peak career earnings during the good times. Gen X, not Boomers, benefit most from the generationally good bull run of 2009-2021, and also start their careers in the halcyon days of the Reagan-Clinton years. They’re also young enough in 2008 to recover in a way many Boomers can’t. </p>
          <p>When it comes to the environment, the culture of consumer consumption many an environmentalist youth decries wasn’t created by the boomers, but by the Silent Generation, who come of age in the postwar years. Who was driving a huge gas guzzling Cadillac to their suburban home in 1966? Was it the boomers, the oldest of whom were barely 20 years old? Hardly. When Ronald Reagan (born 1911) pulled the solar panels off the roof of the White House, this was hardly the act of 25 year olds.. The snowbirds with their Florida second homes and their polluting cruise ship travel tended until very recently to be older than the Boomers too, with birthdates more likely to be in the 192_ and 193_ and early 194_ range than in the 50s and early 60s. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>“The ‘68 Generation”. The Boomers inherited a world that, though not unaffected by modernity, had to some extent come to terms with it. Marriage was for life. Promiscuity was discouraged, entertainment was moral. Sure, small urban subcultures broke the rules - both at the top and bottom of society - but this had always been the case. The vast edifice of middle and working class morality remained solid, until the boomers broke it. </p>
          <p>Except of course, this is kind of bullshit. Divorce rates start spiking in the late ‘60s, when the vast majority of boomers are (far) too young to get married. The Moynihan Report, which forewarned of the huge rise in single motherhood and family dysfunction in urban communities, was published in 1965, before all but the oldest boomers would have possibly become single mothers. And the sexual revolution of ‘68 and onward - in media, in publishing, on television, and in politics, was hardly being pushed by boomers who at the latest were barely out of college, but by people then in their thirties and forties, who tend to have powerful roles in all societies during periods of major economic expansion (look at all the 35-48 year olds in powerful positions in Silicon Valley now). Hugh Hefner was born in 1926. So was Donald Draper. Ted Kennedy, the primary architect and congressional promoter of the 1965 immigration bill, was born in 1932 (Hart and Cellar were older). Leaving aside that most Boomers were hardly cultural revolutionaries anyway, 18 year olds weren’t driving national policy in the ‘60s. </p>
          <p>While Boomers may have ended up with high divorce rates and promiscuity and teenage pregnancy, this happened because of the world they grew up in, in a culture created by people like Hefner. Similarly, weekly church attendance begins falling (especially for Catholics) in the early-mid 50s, when boomers would either have gone/not gone with their family or weren’t even born. And as for promiscuity, that begins to rise for non-college educated men and all women <a href="https://ifstudies.org/ifs-admin/resources/figure2new-1-w640.png">born in the late 1920s and early 1930s</a>, some fifteen years before the Boomers’ birth. Once again, the Silent Generation slides into view. </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>In fact, if you want to draw a certain narrative, you might argue that boomers and their millennial children, both graduated into tough economic circumstances, and respectively about to have their retirement and mid-careers fucked by the next huge recession, are victims of the generations that preceded them. The Silent Generation, who presided over huge transformations in cultural life and enjoyed two decades of unparalleled American economic dominance at the start of their careers, and Gen X, who took obscure academic ideas about critical theory (some of which, yes, had been promulgated by boomer and earlier intellectuals) and turned them into mainstream social views, built the modern protest movement, and graduated from protests at the WTO and the Gulf War to Pussy Hats and Girlboss refrigerator magnets and In This House We Believe ornaments while reeling in unprecedented stock market gains and getting rich off America’s new economy. Gen X is now the face of American power, and just happens to be ruling the country in partnership with its first true Silent Generation President - one Joseph Biden (born 1942).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>