<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-05-01T13:04:05Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/myr3n7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_26_2021/gwjbo4e/</link>
  <title>Reflections on the English Class System (2/2)</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>[cont.d]</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            <strong>The Upper Middle and Upper Classes (1-2% of the population)</strong>
          </p>
          <p>These were once very distinct groups, and still are to a degree, but for most people (even at the 'top') in Britain, they are functionally part of the same broad class grouping. Upper Middle and Upper class people attend similar (sometimes the same, although there are preferences - day vs boarding, for example) schools (the most elite boarding schools are out of reach for almost all in the Middle Class) and universities to the Middle Class, and speak with similar (though not perfectly identical) accents. Telling them apart is more challenging. It's the difference between saying "Pleasure to meet you" and "How do you do", between using the word "Scent" and "Perfume" and - most importantly - between saying "What?" and "Pardon?" (foreigners, guess which is which). For a hilarious and long and very very accurate look at these little - but immensely important - signifiers, see <a href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2608173/So-CLASS-YOU-A-wickedly-funny-perceptive-new-book-answer-hinges-favourite-marmalade-buy-M-S.html">this</a>. </p>
          <p>The Upper Middle and Upper classes often run in similar circles, although there are many sub-groupings, not least between gentry and aristocracy, and between urban and rural elites, and even between different groups of nobles, from arrivistes whose ancestors were merely ennobled a century or two ago to the truly ancient families. Some true upper class have titles, but in the UK most do not - although they will probably be relatively closely related to someone who does. Complicating this is that the government awards life titles of Baron and Baroness (which are non-hereditary) to people of all classes to sit in the House of Lords - this does not affect someone's class status. Eg. Baron Alan Sugar is considered a 'working class billionaire' and is also a life peer. </p>
          <p>To be Upper Middle Class in Britain requires - unlike any other grouping - a certain level of wealth. Not necessarily extraordinary wealth, but 1% wealth (the 99th percentile is £6m in the UK, or $8.3m). A Middle Class person of second or higher generation who learns the right class signifiers, adopts the right hobbies (riding, shooting) and who maintains in most cases a suitable country house (still very important and a huge financial drain) can become Upper Middle Class, although they may have to wait one more generation after that for their kids to truly make it. The hereditary upper class have their place secured by status, and so can be poorer, but the British aristocracy have actually done very well over the last 40 years due to a combination of EU (and now UK) farming subsidies, huge land price increases and the boom in London real estate, in which many made a great deal of money - indeed Central London is still largely owned by five noble families, who are some of the richest in the country. This grouping tends to be as much at home in the country as in the city. </p>
          <p>This grouping also includes many of the very wealthy foreigners who make London their home, from Russian oligarchs to the Arab royals, whom the old British elite like very much because the Arabs are quite deferential to them and fund the entire game of polo, which many enjoy. British aristos love foreign money, as long as it is substantial and as long as it respects or admires them. The world's super rich send their kids to those very same elite boarding schools we just discussed, forming many lifelong friendships. Britain's upper class now manages the wealth of that same third-world elite they once ruled, and this is a lucrative enough profession that it has preserved <em>their</em> fortunes quite handsomely. Even though the world of Downton Abbey no longer exists exactly as depicted (mainly because great houses now require only a fraction of the staff to run), I have attended shooting weekends and grand balls in aristocratic houses that have just undergone ten million dollar restorations that are arguably their direct continuity. Quietly, the rumors of the demise of Britain's old ruling class are very much exaggerated. </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <hr />
      <p>In Part Two next week I will discuss in more depth class/social climbing in British society, its merits and demerits, and with a comparison to conversion to Judaism argue that Britain's <em>elite</em> has perfected an assimilation technique even as it fails to assimilate into the <em>working class</em> millions of recent migrants from Eastern Europe and the Indian Subcontinent.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>