<post>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2021-05-03T23:45:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/n3pe45/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_03_2021/gwugcii/</link>
  <title>A Clever Business Management Advice</title>
  <category>
    <li>economics</li>
    <li>civilization</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="https://hungarytoday.hu/hungary-pfizer-chaos-friday-vaccination/">Pfizer Becomes Accessible to Everyone, Chaos Overwhelms Hungary’s Vaccination Program Once Again</a>
      </p>
      <p>This story just tells so much about Hungary, they should put this in those textbooks on cross-cultural understanding and stuff.</p>
      <p>Orbán really is a genius, he lives and breathes populism.</p>
      <p>There's a clever business management advice that you should deliver bad news at once and get it over with quickly, but deliver good news gradually, drip feeding it over a longer period of time, to maximize subjective psychological satisfaction of your subordinates. Orbán is doing exactly this with covid. He's gradually easing the restrictions <em>and</em> (next genius move) he ties these steps to vaccination numbers. Gradually, step by step, at 2.5M, 3M, 3.5M, and 4M first jabs he eased various aspects of the restrictions, each time declaring another victory, another battle won in the war. It's not tied to infection numbers or death numbers like in Germany. Infections and death are negative and sad, vaccinations are positive and uplifting. Furthermore, Hungary is really high up in terms of first jabs per million people (due to the approval and buying of Chinese and Russian vaccines), so tying the opening steps to vaccination milestones allows driving this point home even better: Hungary does better in vaccinations than the EU overall and <em>this</em> directly allows us to enjoy these things (which are just the basic freedoms of normal times, not some kind of premium luxuries).</p>
      <p>Anyways, so he cooked up this idea of having the next step in opening at 4M jabs. But he had planned that this would happen by last Friday so that hotels can already operate over the weekend and a football match can take place with viewers on Saturday. But there were not yet 4M people vaccinated so he comes up with the next "genius" idea: just for one day, he allowed everyone to get the Pfizer shot instead of the Chinese Sinopharm or AstraZeneca.</p>
      <p>Pfizer has become something of a "status symbol". Rich people and people with connections (and football players of course) somehow manage to get it for themselves, while the proles are left with Chinese and Russian ones, at least that's the perception. And especially some young people make it into a political statement to get a Western vaccine, being pro-EU etc. (Edit: it's not pure vanity though, people also expect better travel options with Western vaccines. ) </p>
      <p>So Pfizer is on, but "only today", he announced in his radio interview Friday morning. Everyone immediately tried to register and the website promptly crashed because of course it's not properly set up to handle this many people. And then of course the government said it was an overloading "cyberattack". Anyways, there's no website now, so no appointments, what to do? People figured out - through formal and informal channels - where Pfizer vaccination is happening nearby and rushed there to find that lots of people are already queueing outside these facilities. But if something is free and you have to use some "tricks" to figure out how to get it, it becomes irresistibly attractive to the Hungarian soul. (Just look at <a href="https://youtu.be/pSUp27dwueA?t=169">this video</a> from 2009, when a supermarket decided that on a certain Sunday from 7 to 9 pm they would sell some crappy cheese for about 2 €/kg and the police had to send the crowd home eventually when they started fighting over the damn cheese. No, it's not about the cheese, it's about the principle! To be able to say that you got the cheap cheese, like a trophy, you got one up over the system!)</p>
      <p>So they gave out about 100K Pfizer shots that day (leaving some people disappointed and going home empty shouldered), yielding the magical 4 million total shots!</p>
      <p>Now don't ask me how these first jabs on Friday can have any actual effect on whether or not the soccer match will be safe to play in front of a crowd on Saturday. But 4M jabs it is! Another victory proudly announced on TV, <a href="https://i.imgur.com/SvhdeZA.png">posted on Facebook (screenshot)</a>, hotels could open on the weekend and the soccer match was held with viewers!</p>
      <p>Next up: further opening regulations at 4.5 million. At 5 million, wedding parties will be allowed, too.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>