<post>
  <author>darwin2500</author>
  <date>2020-06-16T22:48:35Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fv2c0o6/</link>
  <title>On Pulling Down Statues</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Another way of saying this is that it's a powerful symbolic gesture that's extremely evocative - and, yeah, it is, that's why they're doing it.</p>
      <p>We've talked about the euphemism treadmill around here before: why bother opposing the use of one offensive word, when the word you replace it with is just going to be considered offensive and get opposed again in 10 years?  Isn't that an absurd wast of time?</p>
      <p>My defense has always been: the point of opposing these words isn't to eradicate that set of vowels from the vocabulary, the point is to <em>actively oppose discrimination and bigotry</em> by using your opposition to those terms as a powerful signal of your allegiances and moral preferences.  </p>
      <p>When you correct a kid on the playground for calling someone a faggot derogatively, you're not <em>just</em> trying to get them to use a new word, you're <em>also</em> taking advantage of the situation to teach them that being gay is not a shameful thing and that they shouldn't be using that <em>idea</em> as an insult.  It doesn't even matter if they weren't <em>intending</em> to use the word in order to insult gay people specifically; the fact that they learned to use that word as an insult is a manifestation of normally-cloaked systemic homophobia sneaking up into the visible spectrum, and taking the opportunity to beat it back down in front of everyone is an attack on the roots of the problem, that reinforces more tolerant ideals.</p>
      <p>Same thing here.  It doesn't even really matter if the person being depicted 'really' deserves to be remembered or not, or if their statue was put up with racist intentions, or anything like that.  What matters is that symbolic actions which demonstrate depth of commitment and escalate the attention being paid to a situation are an important tactical tool in pursuit of creating a national conversation and persuading people to consider your perspective.  And in terms of powerful escalatory symbolic actions, breaking publicly-owned statues is much preferable to breaking privately-owned windows, or 'punching nazis', or whatever.</p>
      <p>There's little difference between attacking these statues in protest, and burning the flag in protest (again, as long as they're public goods).  People got really mad about burning the flag too, and tried to ban the act for a long time.  I think it's an important freedom and a legitimate signal, and I think obsessing over whether the specific person depicted in the statue 'deserved it' is very much missing the forest for the trees.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>