<post>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2020-06-18T01:54:55Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fv6u2i3/</link>
  <title></title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Decades on, it's leaked out of Academia and is burning down our cities.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Questionable. Motte readers may think it's obviously the same culture war, but perhaps it isn't. What if it's rather like the Hungarian joke:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>A mouse and an elephant are crossing a bridge. The mouse proudly proclaims: you hear how loud we are tramping?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The point being, the current events may be an independent, deeper phenomenon of blacks being dissatisfied with their place in society despite decades of promises of progress. That despite the civil rights movement's optimism, the utopia hasn't come, and there is just newer and newer tricky rhetoric and word twisting and upper class white people coming up with newest euphemisms, which the average black has never cared or known about.</p>
      <p>What if the whole high-status woke movement has just sat on this other deeper thing, this sea of dissatisfied low-status blacks and is basically like the immune system of the high-status classes, a moderating force. A way to signal to the black masses that there you have your leadership, in the woke people, in leftist activism, etc. You don't have to actually organize yourselves, we have already worked it out for you here is the academic critical theory, just follow us, and let's make sure we get well paid jobs in various committees and all will be good.</p>
      <p>What if it's all a defense mechanism of high American society?</p>
      <p>Basically, America wipes out indigenous peoples, subjugates masses of people from a different continent for centuries, then cynically sets them free from slavery, letting them out into the world, with no proper seed wealth, then when after decades of freedom they realize this isn't actually getting better, they explode and riot. Then the benevolent woke civilizing force descends and tells them that the solution is to follow their ideology, pride, love, peace, diversity, kumbaya. Or even more implicitly, just sow the assumption that the two movements are one and the same.</p>
      <p>I mean, imagine if the woke movement didn't exist, if social media, if HR departments, if tech companies didn't have these slogans... Because I'm pretty sure they don't actually care about trans people, about blacks etc. Trans people are &lt;0.1% in the population. Blacks are about 1% among tech company employees, but they are everywhere in advertisement material. It's a lie. These movements don't speak for who they claim to speak for. Lots of gays and trans people proclaim that they never signed up for being represented by these people and ideologies. They are being used as pawns.</p>
      <p>If it wasn't so, if the high classes hadn't adopted this thin clothing of wokeness, the powder keg would be way more explosive.</p>
      <p>An actual black movement would be way more scary to the status quo, one that does not operate in fancy language rules and buzzwords and academic gibberish critical theory, but one that argues based on economics, facts and would demand cutting all obscurantism. It would be more unpredictable. What if blacks rose up in a consistent and organized way and would not put up with nice messages from the supposedly woke / black-friendly media and tech industry? Scary.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>