<post>
  <author>HlynkaCG</author>
  <date>2020-06-17T01:21:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fv2s7x8/</link>
  <title></title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Is the emotional response you outlined above a maladaptive side effect of you being willing but unable to dissociate your identify from “grumpy redneck”, or do you find value and positivity in identifying that way and consciously choose to continue doing so?  </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>That's an interesting question. This might get a bit rambly as I'm going to try to tie a couple different threads together that have been going through my head over the course of the recent unrest. That said, on first pass, yes I do find value and positivity in it.  </p>
      <p>For context, I grew up in the rust belt, spent my 20s and early 30s bouncing around the world first in the military and later working for a Humanitarian NGO, before finally settling down in a decent-size town along the I-10 corridor. To put it bluntly find it difficult to reconcile the world outside my window with a lot of the stories I keep seeing here and in the media. I look at the people at my church, at work, at my regular watering-hole etc... around a third of them are black, and yet everybody seems to be getting along. I keep hearing about how America has a crime problem and a race problem but I'm not <em>seeing it</em>, and while I expect someone will interject about how that's just my privilege talking, I remain skeptical. I don't think America has a problem, I think Chicago has a problem, I think New York, LA, and San Francisco have a problem, and I think that thier problem is largely of thier own making. I'm not going to claim that the South is blameless (it aint), but when I read about how <a href="https://www.esquire.com/news-politics/a20809/spike-lee-1092/">Spike Lee "hates my cracker ass"</a> and always gives interacial couples the stink-eye, I want to ask who's the one fanning the flames of racial resentment here? When I see Hollywood feminists going-on about "rape-culture" and "exploitation of women" I want to tell them, you were the ones buddying-up to Harvey Weinstein and making excuses for Bill Clinton back in the day, not I. If some Ivy League grad tells me to check my privilege I'm just going to laugh in thier face. You have to have lost to know where I've been. I feel like a lot of these issues boil down to culture and to that end, when you refer to my "grievance-laden honor culture that brought its treasonous adherents nothing but misery" my gut reaction is something to the effect of "look to the plank in your own eye."  </p>
      <p>Now granted, the above may not sound very positive, but I do think there is value and positivity there. Unfortunately this also one of those areas where I feel like the progressive's domination of the media and acedemia, specifically their assumption that anything real must make inductive sense, has made the specific mechanism difficult to explain to someone who hasn't experienced it. About 6 months back a user called <a href="/u/Melincourt">/u/Melincourt</a> wrote a peice on "Trusting Gilfoyle". <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/e4u7a6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_02/f9hq0gc/?context=3">The whole thing</a> is worth a read but I would like  to highlight a specific line that I feel illustrates what I'm trying to get at in the same way that shadow can used to illustrate light.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>That's why that 'aesthetic' type of person never plays iterative games-- 'always cheat' wins in prisoners dilemmas of one or two rounds before others stop trusting you. They always lose in multiples and get exiled by networks of mostly cooperative players enriching mostly cooperative players. Con-men and assholes have to change towns all the time, they can't belong anywhere before everyone catches on. They are controlling about privacy and personal facts and feel exposed by their own humanity, that's why Gilfoyle never smiles lol. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>If this is the "light" what is the shadow? The shadow smiles, the shadow embraces it's humanity, it hangs around and plays the iterative games. The Shadow knows what evil lurks in the hearts of men ;-). I am a semi-shaved murder-ape who genuinely enjoys the smell of blood and I'm ok with that. For all the secular left and the alt-right's promises of emancipation through anonymity are they happier? are they better? The impression I get is "no". For all the vaunted joys of freedom, and material wealth what I see is a whole lot of misery, depression, enuui, and talk of people shitting in the commons. For all the talk about the stifling oppression of small town life, I actually like the fact that I know who the cops are and that they know me. Everyone Knowing where the other guy sleeps seems to have a dampening effect on inter personal conflicts. My take is that if you optomize for Gilfoyles edgelords and con-men, you'll get a community full of Gilfoyles edgelords and con-men, and such a community is not going to be a nice place to live. Meanwhile, when you foster a norm of "say what you mean and mean what you say" things seem to have a way working out. Do you like Blues music? Do you like BBQ? Do you like Butter, Beer, and (American) Football? If so, pull up a seat at the bar, We'll get along fine. All y'all are trying to make the US more like Sillicon Valley where I'd rather make it more like a Waffle House.</p>
      <p>Edit: Spelling punctuation and formatting</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>