<post>
  <author>iprayiam</author>
  <date>2020-06-18T14:04:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fv8emxi/</link>
  <title>Sex Discrimination and the Civil Right's Act</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There's three issues here. None of which require supporting someone firing a person for being gay. However, to be be fair that I'm not arguing in bad faith, I will admit that there are probably?some people on the right who want that, though I have never encountered that view IRL.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>As discussed better in the other replies, this basically opens the door to sexual harassment laws being used to silence any dissent from LGBT orthodoxy in one's free time. Adding extreme legal force to cancel culture's already monstrous reign.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>In many ways this is further affront to free association, and the very idea of "protected classes" is illiberal in many ways. For example, it would be similarly (I'll grant not equally) egregious for an employer to fire someone for liking Harry Potter more than Star Wars.</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>But we should be able to oppose such a firing without wanting it protected in the Civil Rights act. This kind of scope creep basically enshrines a form of legal armor that should be sorted out on a more local and democratic level. Protecting your employment status is better done without the bulldozer of the Supreme Court.</p>
      <p>As an extension of this point, I think there's a lot of raw emotion on the right that LGBT is completely culturally ascendant and still demanding more legal privileges while claiming to be a minority group. Agree with this take or not, but I think theres some emotional reality there. Plenty of people who want to protect LGBT's basic freedoms and would be shocked by a bigotted firing, but who don't want the culture war continually rubbed in their face and what amounts to gas-lighting about who is the underclass and who is not.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>In many respects this further enshrines an epistemic prior that it is illegal to see men and women as fundamentally different on any level. The right is too fish-in-water to really push back on the original problems with classifying gender discrimination as the same as race discrimination to begin with, so they are IMHO pushing back on LGBT as a proxy.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>For the past several decades, anti-sex discrimination has been the <em>wink wink</em> standard, but nobody minded stereotypical exceptions: Different bathrooms, maternity leave, casting biological females for female roles, sex different dress codes, gendered sports teams, Boy Scouts vs Girl Scouts, etc. Suddenly the closing of those distinctions has gone to warp speed, especially with transgender causes.</p>
      <p>Roll, it all the way back, and I think most people on the right would admit in privacy that the entire idea of total equal sex protection in employment never made sense to begin with. It was too broad a brush. </p>
      <p>For example, imagine a woman wants to open a nail salon with all female employees, because she thinks there is something fundamentally different about the experience of a female manicurist. Whether you agree with her take or not, it shouldn't be a hugely controversial opinion that this is an acceptable position to have and she should be free to do so as  a default (without some special exemption.)</p>
      <p>Not only is that an illegal opinion, it is quickly becoming dangerous wrong think that must be cancelled. Saying no no that's not allowed, is an epistemic attack on the recognition of any sexual dimorphism. And no matter how many people will toe the PC line, deep down, I think most people find it ridiculous and not really comparable to race protections, even if they won't even admit it to themselves.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>