<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-06-18T14:03:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fv8ei9c/</link>
  <title>NRx's Blindspot - Its Treatment of Women</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>What, then, is to be done?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Your post covers a <em>lot</em> of ground, and quotes some stuff I'm not sure it's ideal (or necessary to your point) to have quoted here.  But one thing that always stands out to me is the way "veteran NRx" bloggers tend to smear women as a group while emphasizing a sort of libertarian individualism for men.  It's a tremendous, gaping hole in their reasoning because the vast majority of women who abandon men are doing it for basically libertarian individualistic reasons.  You can't tell men "unless you're willing to leave everything behind and 'trade up' to blue collar work in rural America, stop complaining" and then be <em>surprised</em> when women leave everything behind to 'trade up' to a more independent lifestyle, or a wealthier or better-looking sex partner, or whatever.  You can't tell one group "relentlessly pursue your apparent self-interest" and then be pissed off (or even <em>surprised</em>) when some other group relentlessly pursues their apparent self-interest.</p>
      <p>While the trendlines are not encouraging, it's <em>still the case</em> that most people marry monogamously, raise a kid or two, and never get divorced (this last claim is a bit tricky to pin down, as I think a slight majority of marriages do end in divorce but only because of habitual divorcees running up the numbers--happy to be corrected on this point).</p>
      <p>There is one trend among women that I think might help to explain some of the <em>outcomes</em> under discussion; women are as a group more religious than men, and Radical Leftism appears to be emerging as a sort of pseudo-religion to which women, more than men, are converting <em>en masse</em>.  For NRx-types who subscribe to the evo-psych of women being the social hearth-keepers and men being the strong solo hunter-farmers, there's probably some plausible finger-pointing to be done at the liberal and radical Left's tendency to be philosophically (and sometimes dogmatically) anti-family.</p>
      <p>What I <em>don't</em> see is a lot of men deciding to <em>go back to church</em> as a result of all this.  The overlap between the "New Atheism" crowd and the various MRA, NRx, alphabet-soup of disillusioned and angry men has put a lot of young men in a double bind: they are too committed to atheism to make a faith-based commitment to a community of people who share their practical values, but too committed to classical liberalism (as I would argue they should be!) to go full-SJW.  But what women (again, as a group) most often want are costly signals of a man's commitment to "the community" or "the cause."</p>
      <p>Just as in the 1990s there was a wave of "spiritual but not religious" that swept through a lot of young people, it is entirely possible to be "religious but not spiritual."  I don't know that abandoning cities wholesale and looking for blue collar work in rural communities is actually going to deliver the fulfillment this guy seems to think it can deliver.  For some people, it probably will.  But you don't get the "full package" of benefits in rural America, such as they are, by picking up some manual labor and a rifle.  You've got to pick up a Bible, too.  For people who find that a bridge too far, answers almost certainly lie elsewhere.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>