<post>
  <author>Rabitology</author>
  <date>2020-06-16T05:24:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fuzenpo/</link>
  <title>You Don't Hate the Flag</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Expatriate Southerner here.  Probably the last generation that cared much for the Lost Cause was the conveniently-named Lost Generation.  The Depression, FDR, WW2 and the Cold War unified America the way that little has before or since and erased a large number of regional and ethnic identifications from Norwegians in the upper plains to Italians in NYC.  This included Southerners.  My Greatest Generation grandfather was American before he was Southern.</p>
      <p>Later in the 1970's and 80's after the Civil Rights movement and social disruptions of the 60's had settled, American pop culture underwent a phase of romantic infatuation with the South.  Every year saw the release of a half-dozen movies set in the South, Southern Rock was climbing the charts with the Allman Brothers and Lynard Skynard and the Dukes of Hazzard were ramp-jumping all over prime time in a car named after Robert E. Lee with a Confederate battle flag painted on the roof.  That wasn't much of a shock.  The battle flag was everywhere in the south and out of it, where it was taken as a symbol of rock-and-roll rebellion.  Guns and Roses performed in front of a giant battle flag.  So did Tom Petty.  So did Pantera.  When the <em>Dukes of Hazzard</em> movie came out <em>in 2005</em>, guess what was painted on the roof of the General Lee?</p>
      <p>So, the battle flag has gone from nostalgiac to forgotten to cool to evil all in a century.  You can forgive a Southerner's head for spinning.  We're a little slow.</p>
      <p>From my perspective, it's just a flag, and a flag is a symbol, and a symbol is always a proxy for something else.  And in this case, I don't think the associations are that complex.  People attack the flag to attack the South, because the South is a strong Republican voting block, and it keeps the more enlightened coastal enclaves from complete political dominance of the country.  I don't think it's any more complex than that, and if the South went back to being a quaint dem-voting backwater,  animosity to the battle flag would likewise disappear.</p>
      <p>So why do Southerners defend the flag?  They know you don't really hate a piece of cloth; you hate <em>them</em>.</p>
      <p>As a further note to your sister: everything she thinks is good today will be bad tomorrow.  Every generation has to learn the hard way, mine included.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>