<post>
  <author>solowng</author>
  <date>2020-06-18T13:31:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fv8b7he/</link>
  <title>A True Hillbilly Eliegy</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>My apologies for taking so long to deliver part two but this took some (failed) effort to condense. From another raised in a "diseased, grievance-laden honor culture" processing the fact that I grew up in a crazy outlier situation has been a trip. I was one of those rare "talented and gifted" success stories (sort of...I graduated cum laude from an SEC school on scholarship but assimilated into the townie working class but I'm okay with that.) but like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iEy-xTbcr2A">JD Vance</a> (You only have to listen to the first minute.) while I don't sound like an ignorant hick I know nothing about wine and was in fact kind of offended when a bunch of SF Bay people expressed disbelief that I'm from rural Alabama. Maybe Georgia, they said, apparently unaware that Alabama has nice new south suburbs as well, aka. Shelby County. </p>
      <p>No, I did grow up in rural Alabama, in an unincorporated community that was rapidly transitioning into a drug-addled white trashville as the old people who grew up farming there like my grandparents were dying out. More of my elementary school classmates dropped out of high school than graduated from college. A depressing number graduated functionally illiterate. I remember the day my road was paved, the day Dale Earnhardt died, and grew up listening to <em>Devil Without a Cause</em> and <em>Cocky</em> era Kid Rock. </p>
      <p>Unlike JD Vance, I don't <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jv5pGTG_Kjc">remember my mom being arrested</a> but it's happened a few times for assault and the only thing sparing me from paying her rent is a bullshit disability pension from the VA. What my family lacked in genuine poverty (in contrast to self-inflicted financial dysfunction) or hard drug abuse it made up for with Borderline Personality Disorder and ridiculous levels of familial conflict and domestic violence. I'm privileged enough to have done a <a href="https://medium.com/@MegB/why-i-dont-won-t-facilitate-privilege-walks-anymore-and-what-i-do-instead-380c95490e10">privilege walk</a> (twice, actually!) but couldn't help but notice that the questions didn't really get into how bad things can get. Skip to the six minute mark in the second video, where Lindsay Vance struggles to look the camera/Megyn Kelly in the eye as she says that she should've done more for her brother and you'll see something painfully relatable to me because I'm the older brother to two sisters I couldn't save and when therapists or social worker types trot out the "talented and gifted" line (Why do they do this?) I am upset because my sisters were not and didn't deserve to have that used as a cudgel against them by our mother. I also deeply resent the implication (sometimes explicitly stated by these people) that I am obligated to be a wild success or do something heroic with my life because I feel like that's asking for more than I'm able to give. </p>
      <p>I’ve spent more time looking into my own shadows than most people and would dare argue that not having done so is likely the mark of a privileged life (or an unexamined one, at least). I once had a therapist throw up his hands and ask how I was still alive during the consultation, a question I initially found insulting but the answer is illuminating and can summarized in one word: spite. Committing suicide as a teenager or accidentally killing myself with drugs in my early 20s would’ve been me handing my mother the holy grail of victim cards and I refuse to give her that. There will never be justice, a tearful reconciliation, or even the barest acknowledgement of wrongdoing but she will not win and that means that I have to survive <em>and</em> not be an asshole to people who don’t deserve it. The power reversal between us that happened in my early 20s was jarring. Suddenly she started dancing around me like she’d spent the last 20 years terrified of me. IMO that behavior is an unspoken and probably unconscious expression of truth. Somewhere deep down she knows exactly what she did, what she taught me, and what that means. I wasn’t merely her favorite child but the one most like her, my sisters having taken after their fathers. We are the monsters in the room and the only thing separating us is that I have a conscience and she doesn’t. She’s not inhuman, just inhumane and her lack of ability to feel empathy or remorse doom her to never learn from her interpersonal mistakes. She’s middle aged now, her femme fatale days are behind her, and she’s looking at a lonely rest of her life on disability being genuinely baffled as to why her daughters want nothing to do with her. It’s fucking sad. </p>
      <p>Having plumbed the depths of the shadows let’s talk about the Civil War and Jim Crow. As a southerner I have my own bones to pick with Jefferson Davis, brave with the lives of people like me and for what? At the same time I begrudgingly respect that many of those planters in fact put their money where their mouths were and fought like Germans. The actual Germans would discover this to their horror in WWII when the U.S. Army dealt with them like they did the Confederates, by showing up with overwhelming materiel superiority. I am reminded of Confederate general D.H. Hill’s <a href="https://civilwartalk.com/threads/3-26-2020-wild-claims.169667/">alleged statement</a> that given Union artillery and Confederate infantry he’d whip the world. </p>
      <p>Moving on to Jim Crow I’m going to be blunt here. It’s something that can’t be undone. No amount of statues being torn down or twitter mob cancellations are going to un-bomb the 16th Street Baptist Church or bring the GM jobs back to Flint. We’re stuck with it, we’re going to have to find a productive way to deal with it, and I don’t think that my millennial peers dredging up grievances they didn’t live to experience is particularly helpful. Like you, I am struck by a conspicuous absence of ground level hatred in the roughly 50/50 southern city I live in. Our truce has held. Maybe it’s because the locals here better know the stakes of breaking it. I’d like to think it’s because we who work for a living, like football, BBQ, and muscle cars in fact have a lot in common and want the same things in life for ourselves and our families even if our skin color, pop culture proclivities, and southern accents are different.</p>
      <p>Finally, I am scared by this authoritarian, all-encompassing escalation of the culture war by people who IMO know not what they’re doing and severely lack perspective. I’ve lived in a world where no attack was off limits and the right to remain silent did not exist before and I really don’t want to go back there.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>