<post>
  <author>Standard_Order</author>
  <date>2020-06-16T04:08:03Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fuz8bv5/</link>
  <title>Pre-WWII Allied Propagana Against the Germans</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think your definitions of "good" and "evil" are uselessly utilitarian, but spring-boarding off one specific bit of your comment:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>the enemy (Nazis specifically, not the good West German anti-communist NATO members) was demonized as uniquely evil</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Can I take the chance to recommend to everyone the 17-minute documentary <em>Hitler Lives?</em> It was directed by Don Siegel (of <em>Dirty Harry</em> and <em>Invasion of the Body Snatchers</em>), adapted from a film written by Theodor Geisel (aka Dr. Seuss), and won an Academy Award in 1945. The whole thing is on Youtube here: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qEYeJKCFQgA">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qEYeJKCFQgA</a></p>
      <p>It's a rather entertaining dose of post-War Allies propaganda. The thesis is that the Nazis were bad specifically because Germans are uniquely inclined to conquer the world, from the evil Otto von Habsburg to the bloodthirsty Kaiser Wilhelm II. It justifies the division of Germany as a necessary effort to ensure that the perfidious Hans will never again try to rise up and conquer the world. As Curtis Yarvin put it when recommending it in <a href="https://youtu.be/6GW-YMa68o4?t=1304">the <em>Unregistered</em> podcast</a>, it frames WWII as "a race war in self defense against the Germans."</p>
      <p>In the knowledge of what we later discovered about the Holocaust, should the United States have intervened in World War II? It's indisputable; in fact, they should have intervened much more quickly and totally.* But that's not what happened. <em>From the perspective of the Allies at that time</em>, when the Holocaust was still a deeply hidden secret: Were they justified in getting involved? Or, like in the Spanish-American and Iraq Wars, was American intervention founded in propaganda and motivated by profit and petty hatred? Nicholson Baker's book <em>Human Smoke</em> defends the pacifist thesis quite robustly. I'm only halfway through, but the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2008-mar-09-bk-kurlansky9-story.html">LA Times</a> and <a href="http://archive.is/YQio4">NY Times</a> reviews more or less hit the nail on the head.</p>
      <p>Yesterday I enjoyed <a href="/r/TheMotte/comments/gysmxy/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_08_2020/furtzes/?context=2">some back-and-forth</a> over my condemnation of Churchill. Nazism was a terrible evil and of course neo-Nazis are deluded, but that doesn't take away from the fact that Churchill is guilty of (as <a href="/u/ninjin-">u/ninjin-</a> neatly, if incredulously, summarized) "prolonging the war for personal posterity." In an age when revisionism is perfectly acceptable for almost every war in history, it's a tragedy that WWII and the Civil War are still so untouchable. What can you do.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>* (Although in that podcast I linked, the host Thaddeus Russell alleges that "it's a majority opinion among European historians that US intervention sort of guaranteed the Holocaust happening," a claim which I have not investigated but that I suggest is supported by the plans which <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/01/30/book-review-eichmann-in-jerusalem/">Scott described</a> as the "First Solution," "Second Solution," etc.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>