<post>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2020-06-24T20:47:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvw26df/</link>
  <title>You Couldn't Be You If You Weren't Wh You Are</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Yes. Is it fair that some kids get an abusive alcoholic parent while another gets an industrious, caring one? No. People of course know this, it's not some weird special realization. "life's unfair" as any random person off the street will tell you.</p>
      <p>Two philosophies clash here: one, which implicitly has a mental model whereby there is some soul repository in another plane of existence and each blank fresh soul gets slotted into some random newborn in the world. Hence it makes sense to say "I was lucky to be born here". You the soul randomly got assigned to a body in your country, which was pure luck. Or as Dawkins says, we are all so immeasurably lucky to have been born at all, most possible humans a never born at all! Only a tiny fraction of all possible human genetic codes are ever born. This also requires imagining that all potential humans "exist" in some other pláne of existence and some get born but the unlucky ones stay "on the shelf" forever.</p>
      <p>Another, much rarer and foreign view is that each kid is like a copy of their parents. There is no fundamentally new thing coming into this plane of existence when a baby is born. Just like when bacteria divide, they are copies of the original. The two new bacteria aren't "lucky" to have gotten to that particular colony. They never moved, they were never placed there. They are the old bacterium just now in a new form.
A kid born to rich parents is not lucky, they are the perpetuation of the parent's physical existence. We are in some sense the physical extensions of our parents.</p>
      <p>Saying that you were lucky to be born in your country is like saying you were lucky to have woken up in your bed. The reason is object permanence, not luck.</p>
      <p>You couldn't be you if you weren't who you are. It is paradoxical to be thankful or spiteful for the fact of being who you are because there is no alternative for anybody to be anyone else. If I was Ben Affleck then I wouldn't be me, I would be Ben Affleck and would act like Ben Affleck. There is no soul slotted in my brain that could be moved into Affleck's head to "correct" my initial bad luck of being slotted in this body.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>