<post>
  <author>Faceh</author>
  <date>2020-06-24T15:22:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvuxs7u/</link>
  <title>Civilizational Decline and the Value of Tradition</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <strong>I've never come across a comprehensive explanation/quantification of said 'decline',</strong> or why tradition actually is a solution.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The big ones are the decline in marriage rates, rise in single-parenthood despite overall decine in birth rates, the dissolution of so many social groups that people previously relied upon (see: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowling_Alone">Bowling Alone</a>), rising suicide rates, and increasing political polarization/decreasing national unity.</p>
      <p>These are all factors that, so the right believes, show that the very fabric of the nation is fraying to the point where, on current trajectory, there will be no way to hold the nation together anymore and it will fall to some other power that DOES manage to hold itself together.</p>
      <p>I apologize for not linking to the actual stats on each of those, but I am very confident that they are available with minimal effort.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I've never come across a comprehensive explanation/quantification of said 'decline' or <strong>why tradition actually is a solution.</strong></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is a difficult one to grasp out of hand, but concepts like <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Chesterton%27s_Fence">Chesterton's Fence</a>, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lindy_effect">Lindy Effect</a>, and the confluence of evolutionary biology and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_learning">Cultural Learning</a> all help get at the basic idea.</p>
      <p>Any true 'tradition' that has been practiced for a long period of time has 'survived' many shocks and disasters, and almost by definition the people who have practiced the tradition have survived while those who chose not to or <em>opposed</em> the tradition have not survived, or at least have faded from view.</p>
      <p>Thus, you could conclude that this tradition is performing some <em>important</em> function, one that ensures the survival of the people, their nation, and their genes. However, because the tradition is preventing [bad thing] from happening, over time the people may actually forget what the 'purpose' of it is, and skeptics may start to declare there is no need for the tradition anymore. Nonetheless, the tradition continues to protect the people from [bad thing], which was held at bay but never fully eradicated.</p>
      <p>Imagine, for instance, that there wasn't a scientific edifice to support the use of vaccines but instead getting your kids vaccinated was just a 'tradition' that people engaged in without too much questioning. Then imagine (or just look at anti-vaxxers) that people said "we keep vaccinating our kids but its not clear why. They never show any beneficial effects from it and the kids think it hurts, why do we do that to them?" Since nobody is old enough to remember the ravaging diseases that used to plague humanity, nobody really groks the downside risk of no vaccines.</p>
      <p>Eventually, vaccination becomes a minority practice, and slowly and subtley, more kids get sick, more kids die, and after a couple decades we now have a full on revival of old diseases, but since it happened so slowly nobody was quite able to notice the cause... except some crazy coots who screamed about vaccinations being a core part of their culture and that unspecified bad things would come from ceasing the practice. Maybe they even invoke religion: "God wants you to stick your kids with needles, and he promised to send plagues if you don't!!!" Of course we dismiss these folks, they're obviously insane right-wing extremist religious fundamentalists.</p>
      <p>The theory is that many extant traditions are <em>exactly that,</em> learned behaviors to avoid some bad outcome that nobody actually remembers but, thanks to your culture passing down the traditions, they are protected nonetheless.</p>
      <p>And so as more and more traditions are watered down or eliminated, these bad things that we have long forgotten start to rear up again. And in many cases their impact is subtle and hard to tease out, and so it will not be obvious, right away, that we've screwed up.</p>
      <p>So the leap that one has to make is that the loss of certain traditions MAY be causing some of the negative effects we are observing today, and that returning to these traditions could solve these ills.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>