<post>
  <author>georgioz</author>
  <date>2020-06-25T11:29:02Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/heu5of/why_i_grew_my_ego/fvy0k71/</link>
  <title>The Roll of Small Talk in Eastern Europe</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I also think it's worth noting that "humble" and "confident" aren't mutually exclusive. The most successful people, imo, are both.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Exactly. The main advantage of this culture is that there is no expectation of emotional labor on your side. If somebody asks "How are you" you are not expected to answer "Everything is great" despite having a shitty day at home or at work. Therefore we have more neutral greetings akin to Hello or Goodbye. </p>
      <p>You reserve "how are you" type of greetings to colleagues or at least acquaintances. And even then the answer is often factual. For example "How are you Peter?". "Oh, I cant complain. Although having to work from home with three kids is hard". "Oh yeah, Yesterday I was talking to Petra who has four kids and I feel for you guys. I had several 1on1 calls and to be honest I do not mind kids playing in the background. If anything I think it is quite cute."</p>
      <p>Or something like: "How are you Marek? I am fine. I just learned that I am about to be promoted." "Oh, this is great to hear. I really liked your work and especially your presentation on the last project and I am not surprised that you were promoted. Congrats". </p>
      <p>So to some extent it is an emotional labor but we are used to have small-talk around some concrete and often personal topics. Which means that if you do not know the other person and want to play it safe just don't ask about how they are doing if you do not know anything about them. And if you do, then be prepared to use your general knowledge to accompany your emotional/rhetorical skills. </p>
      <p>Or to put it differently, in USA it seems that there is hard border between fake interest and small talk and your personal experience/knowledge and true personality. In Eastern Europe small-talk is a continuum. It is kind of a "test" without strong barrier between stranger and close friend. So you sometimes get some surprising small-talk hooks that you can take to elevate the relationship to next level. And there are no guidelines of "polite conversation". You are on your own and either make it or don't. This is often surprising for Americans that are more used to compartmentalize and who run on idioms. They think that the other person is rude while in fact it is them that  did not pass the test to be awarded the warm reciprocity as they were "outed" as fakes. And the other person does not feel obligated to make the emotional labor. Either be official and  disattached (and there is nothing bad about that) or be warm and fuzzy - but then don't be surprised if the other person is not in the mood. In short, the "Eastern European" culture is quick to provide feedback to what is appropriate and what is not. We do not care about your intent. Just learn how to express yourself. On the plus side if you are a "dick" you will find likeminded people down the road. On the down side, if you are a true dick you will find likeminded persons. But then don't complain that you are a dick. </p>
      <p>And the last comment is the huge difference in service industries. I have a family member who was trained as a waiter in 1960s. The school of thought was that waiter should be invisible - like you see them in movies from aristocratic societies. Good waiter is somebody who knows when somebody wants to order something unobtrusively. The assumption is that group of friends want to talk to each other and you just facilitate the conversation so they have everything that they need. The american service is different. Your waiter introduces herself (Why should you care? You will know her if you are a patron and only then will she make small-talk with you), she has her sales pitch. I expect professional and somber face - not a fake smile and comments on nice weahter. You do not know that we came to support our friend who's girlfriend ditch him and we are in no mood to talk weather or whatnot. She then blindly barges into the conversation making some show and pretending to be your friend (Where are you guys from? Slovakia? Amazing. Did you guys saw the <em>local tourist attraction</em>? And BTW can I offer you this house special when we established this rapport?). To me this is terrible service. I feel as if I am bad for occupying seat that is there to make money - which also makes sense from the side of the waiter who is nervous that if you do not order enough this will make here tips low so she has to be pushy and everybody pretends as this is okay. </p>
      <p>I expect waiter to sit us without a show, give us menus and maybe throw two or three sentences on what is special today that she recommends. She then asks for drinks. Then she comes back to get orders passively - and only make sales pitch to somebody who does not know what to order. If she is good she can throw some jokes depending on how she reads the crowd. She <em>writes</em> everything and repeats orders for everyone. Then she brings the food and asks for next round of drinks. And then she returns in appropriate time for another round of drinks and asks for deserts - again she can say one or two sentences about what is fresh or popular. Then she only comes back to ask for rounds of drinks/snacks unobtrusively. And this is all I want. </p>
      <p>As another example - if you order a beer in Czechia they will "refill" (bring another beer) automatically when you emptied your cup (you can decline and then they will take the beer to next patron no questions asked). There are waiters who make swoops of the pub and do that specifically and they just mark the beers on some piece of paper. And they let people at the table enjoy time with their friends. And only your main waiter asks for deserts/snacks - and you just ask this swooper to call this waiter if you need it. To me this is ideal service.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>