<post>
  <author>greatjasoni</author>
  <date>2020-06-24T21:02:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvw3xnf/</link>
  <title>Re-Iventintg Philosphy - (I still don't recognize the image)</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm going to make a series of wildly condescending sounding assumptions here but I'm trying to be as nice as possible, please don't take it personally: I think the inferential gap is too wide to have a productive conversation about this. I'd have to really think about how to meaningfully refute this line of thinking because there are layers and layers of assumptions to unpack here. I think your picture of epistemology is something like <a href="https://zennist.typepad.com/.a/6a00d83451d26869e20240a4cf849d200b-pi">this image</a>. Eventually you'll notice what the image is of and wont be able to unsee it, but you have to live through that first. </p>
      <p>You strike me as someone smart but not terribly well read because they're too young. (Your stance on Aristotle kind of gives this away.) You'll quickly think up decent sounding refutations to every answer you hear here and wont notice the glaring flaws because you haven't noticed the underlying pattern in reality you're missing. It doesn't even matter what you read. But eventually you develop the introspection to see that rigorously deriving coherent ideology out of pure facts is a pipe dream. This realization usually comes after you've gone through a few phases shifting from ideology to ideology. After you've read enough serious works of philosophy you'll have a realistic image of what they ought to look like instead of this ideal you've constructed without having read them. It's an intellectual equivalent of eating from the tree in paradise and losing your innocence.</p>
      <p>Your understanding of how meaning is conveyed in writing seems to rely on something you picked up in school guides on how to write essays to make them easy to grade. Moldbug diagnoses this more generally in <a href="https://youtu.be/qGN44yXgbGQ?t=523">this clip</a> in reference to your ideology in particular. You're reinventing the wheel to justify your own worldview in rejection of the standard worldview you've been fed, by using the exact framework taught to you by those you're rejecting. Knowledge is more complicated than that ideal. You can go so much further.</p>
      <p>I could sit here and talk about how all knowledge rests on a series of self referential cultural assumptions that go back to the founding of civilization (which in turn go back even further to pre-writing cultural baggage like language which in turn goes back to biology), how not knowing what the background cultural assumptions are means you're doomed to be stuck in them until you've read through the canon, how facts can be cherrypicked to build any arbitrary narrative, how you can make an arbitrarily convincing argument for anything, how any series of empirical facts must ultimately always assume unfalsifiable claims, how the limited human mind must always make simplifying assumptions to understand reality, etc. But none of that is going to make any sense to someone who has invented a framework where they're always correct. Some of the other posters have pointed these exact claims out already but again I think the inferential gap is too far to argue them directly. </p>
      <p>What you seem to be reinventing here is a contrived nascent version of Logical Positivism as another poster pointed out. This wont directly refute that but you can read Scott Alexander's book review of one of the books that killed this philosophical movement <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200113091152/https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/01/08/book-review-the-structure-of-scientific-revolutions/">here</a>. Specifically I think Khun's concept of a <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/thomas-kuhn/">Paradigm</a> would be really helpful here in showing how facts always depend on culture even in the sciences. </p>
      <p>Another thing that might be helpful is attempting to write out all your political beliefs up to this standard you're holding yourself and see how far you can get. One of the big issues with logical positivism is that they couldn't formulate a version of it that didn't exclude vast swaths of the sciences. It's far too strict of a criteria for useful knowledge. It's easy to criticize someone like Moldbug for making unjustified assertions, and indeed he is guilty of doing it far too often, but you'll quickly find this isn't a realistic standard. </p>
      <p>As an aside, what is meant by art is not the same as propaganda. They're completely different things and Moldbug is explicitly against propaganda. As absurd as it sounds, the last thing Moldbug wants to do is convince someone to <a href="https://www.unqualified-reservations.org/2009/10/gentle-introduction-to-unqualified/">spread an ideology</a>. BAP is trying to realize an aesthetic vision, not convince anyone, as explicitly stated in the excerpt you quoted.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>