<post>
  <author>HumanDrinkingTea</author>
  <date>2020-06-24T18:08:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/he96rm/star_slate_codex_deleted_because_of_nyt_article/fvvi9oe/</link>
  <title>The Humility of Scott Axlexander</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>There are certainly a bunch of random far-leftists out there who believe Scott is a ~Nazi</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>For what it's worth, I don't know how left one needs to be in order to be considered "far-left" but I'm pretty far left and am a huge fan of SSC. I'm also a woman who aligns with feminist ideology, but to be fair there are different strains of feminism and I likely don't belong to the same strain that is particularly critical of Scott. I've been to <a href="/r/SneerClub">r/SneerClub</a> and see where they're coming from, but I vehemently disagree with their interpretations of his work. </p>
      <p>I do think that the rationalist community as a whole has a blind spot regarding the issues that POC and women face, but I think that one potentially fatal flaw among some individuals in modern American social justice movements is not distinguishing good faith actors from bad faith actors. I have trouble believing that Scott is anything but a good faith actor, and while I am only an occasional lurker of this sub, I do suspect that the moderators here on <a href="/r/TheMotte">r/TheMotte</a> do their best to limit bad faith actors. </p>
      <p>At his core, I think that Scott is a humble guy who is aware of how his own perspective is limited. I get the sense that the Sneer Club (and whoever his other detractors are) believe that this humility is disingenuous. As a long time casual reader of his blog, I have found no reason to think that anything about him is disingenuous. He clearly values nuance and will apply as much of a nuanced perspective as he reasonably can.</p>
      <p>I think there is a wider issue at play, though-- no nuance is <em>enough</em> nuance. No matter how nuanced Scott tries to be, he will be missing some level of complexity. Despite his leftist leanings, the fact that he is speaking from the perspective of a well educated white man in the techno-sphere means that the complexity and nuance that is lost is mostly likely going to be the sort of nuance that might not be lost if someone were writing on the same topic but had a less privileged background than Scott. </p>
      <p>I personally feel that Scott's practice as a psychiatrist allows him to have a better understanding of world outside of his bubble, and it allows him to have a broader view of the world than most people who frequent his blog. Nevertheless, I do believe he has blind spots, as all people do, but for the most part I think the quality of his work speaks for itself and is worth a read regardless.</p>
      <p>The notion that Scott is a sexist nazi is laughable. I believe that such beliefs are fringe. That being said, I <em>totally</em> believe that the culture within the SSC and adjacent communities reinforce sexist and racist structures (in the same manner that silicon valley reinforces it-- by disregarding the experiences of minorities while elevating their own and mindlessly believing that their perception is reflective of some sort of objective reality when it is in fact reflective of the subjective experience of a person who has a particular status in society). I also believe that this is an idea that should be talked about within the community and considered an area of concern. Unfortunately, I have mentioned such a concern in the past (in like one or two comments I made a long time ago and I can't remember whether it was this subreddit or the SSC subreddit) and I noticed that I got a lot of backlash from public posters but a lot of support in PM's from other people like me who are mostly lurkers but love Scott's work. I don't know what that says about this community, but it certainly says <em>something</em>.</p>
      <p>The latter, of course, is why I understand where the attacks from the left are coming from. However, I have also seen enough commitment to open-mindedness and growth from both Scott and the community as a whole that I believe that his blog and these communities really are one of the few places on the internet where rational discourse (for the most part) can flourish, and where those of us who are "nerds" can feel at home.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>