<post>
  <author>Mantergeistmann</author>
  <date>2020-06-24T04:00:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvtgoz9/</link>
  <title>Why People Don't Admire the Marvels of Civil Engineering</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I have three theories: theory one is that we've become jaded as a people. We surround ourselves with wonders, and have no idea how they work, or why, but take it for granted that they do. The internet. Cheap air travel. Household appliances. Satellites. Hell, modern logistics. We take it for granted that a parcel from across the Atlantic will get here - reliably - in a few days. That we can communicate with anyone at any time, go anywhere at any time. That our vehicles are maintenance free (at least for us civilians), and don't break. I remember reading an article about airline crashes, and it mentions that the ones that happen nowadays are rare and flukes, because you no longer have ordinary issues like "the propeller fell off in mid air." When we build a skyscraper, a bridge, a port, it's not an achievement - it's what's expected. The bare minimum. Like a straight A student, another A is meaningless, and a B is downright disappointing. </p>
      <p>Theory 2 is that we no longer appreciate things, because we don't know how they work. It's sufficiently advanced to most of us as to be magic. Do you know the cost and coordination required to put down 100 miles of railway? How many parts go into a skyscraper? I sure don't! In general, people used to be close enough to work of some sort (or know people who are) to have some inkling of what went into things. I recall a story (possibly apocryphal) of an old car owner's manual, where the recommended user maintenance was to basically disassemble half the engine and put it back together again, once every year or so. Our modern cars are significantly better than that, but most people have no idea just how much better, or how impressive it is.</p>
      <p>Theory 3: you just can't do it on your own anymore. Sure, there are startups for the small stuff, but for anything impressive, it takes a corporation. We have a few massive companies doing everything, which makes it full and faceless, and removes the excitement. If you think about the 20s and 30s, some of the best fighter planes of that time were originally designed for racing competitions. Can you imagine that today? The sheer time and investment it takes to build a fighter jets is... Excessive. And I'd imagine that most large-scale projects are even more prohibitive for small companies. I haven't done the research, but I'd imagine that just a few giant construction companies/conglomerates are in charge of the vast majority of large-scale projects. The one place this doesn't seem to be true is space, but that might just be a profit thing, and the failures to get a private space program (or several) set up seem to have killed enthusiasm. Perhaps once somebody makes it profitable and gets some competition, we'll start hearing about it more.</p>
      <p>I don't know which (if any) of these are true, but they all seem somewhat plausible.</p>
      <p>Damn, forgot a fourth: media and culture. Being a builder, especially of public works projects, just isn't cool or represented. Even architects only make the public eye if they're quirky rather than work-a-day practical and beautiful in that manner. I'm reminded of the episode of Lark Rise to Candleford (a lovely little slow-paced costume drama), where the one wealthy character really wants to be a public benefactor, and put up a clock for the town. It's a big deal, both for himself and for the town! But I can't really see too many characters like that anymore, at least not getting sympathetic/cool characterization. The people who build aren't going to be the heroes of a Netflix series anytime soon. Although I'm not sure that was ever really the case, culturally, at least not in the TV era.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>