<post>
  <author>questionnmark</author>
  <date>2020-06-24T20:15:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvvy3ah/</link>
  <title>1971: The Year Oil Production Peaked</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think I know this one! </p>
      <p>It was the point where <a href="https://www.eia.gov/todayinenergy/images/2016.11.07/main.png">oil production peaked</a> in the USA. Basically from then on out if one group wanted to grow their share of the economic pie then the other group(s) had to lose. The whole  'culture war' is in my opinion a lie pulled over people's eyes to blind them from the truth. Basically a whole bunch of different things happened at the same time which privileged particular sectors -- the professional and management and capitalist classes (PMCC) -- whilst everyone else saw a fall in relative prosperity.  This I believe is one of the most important concepts that almost nobody understands, and at the same time explains so much about the cause of so many of our particular issues. I don't believe in class consciousness whereby the PMCC collectively decided to act in a way that would screw over everybody else, but I earnestly believe that they acted in a way that they thought would improve the situation after the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1970s">terrible economic upheavals of the 1970's</a>. </p>
      <p>​</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The 1970s were perhaps the worst decade of most industrialized countries' economic performance since the Great Depression.[7] Although there was no severe economic depression as witnessed in the 1930s, economic growth rates were considerably lower than previous decades. As a result, the 1970s adversely distinguished itself from the prosperous postwar period between 1945 and 1973. The oil shocks of 1973 and 1979 added to the existing ailments and conjured high inflation throughout much of the world for the rest of the decade. U.S. manufacturing industries began to decline as a result, with the United States running its last trade surplus (as of 2009) in 1975.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>At that point a large majority of the easy productivity gains had already been implemented and the consequences to the environment were becoming unbearable to the general public. Implementing the <em>much needed</em> environmental protections and outsourcing much of the dirty polluting industries to other countries was actually a pretty logical next step to improving the environmental situation in America. I don't think <em>anybody</em> wants to go back to a situation where rivers catch on fire or people are choking on air pollution. Aside from those who owned or operated these industries most of the PMCC and the rest of the public seem to generally agree that this is a good thing. </p>
      <p>In order to continue economic growth and prosperity the complexity of the economic system had to increase. Economists like to call this transition a transition to a 'service economy', but I believe that is actually the wrong word/concept. What we got instead was a 'specialist/complex' economy which privileges those that have a relevant and specialised skillset. The explosion of the number of job types is a testament to this change, as is the demand for a large number of university graduates. The reason for this complexity and specialization is that efficiency comes at a cost of complexity and specialization is the means by which this complexity barrier was overcome. I drive a Volkswagen golf for instance -- an absolutely brilliant car in a number of ways -- but the MQB platform to build those cars cheaply and efficiently cost a staggering 60 <em>BILLION</em> dollars. </p>
      <p>I could go on and on and on. But basically the culture war is in effect a battle over scarce resources between different groups because once the economy switched over from a universal growth platform to a more zero sum system identity politics started to matter a whole lot more. The changes benefited the PMCC at the expense of everyone else, hence the reason you get that divergence in the graph (although the graph above exaggerates the problem).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>