<post>
  <author>ThirteenValleys</author>
  <date>2020-06-22T23:02:04Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvoqal0/</link>
  <title>Binary Political Weapons</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_chemical_weapon">binary chemical weapon</a> is a device in which the toxic or deadly chemical in question comes from the combination of two harmless or only mildly dangerous chemicals, making them much safer to manufacture, transport, and prepare; the danger doesn't come until the weapon is activated. A famous pop cultural example is Tim Burton's 1989 <em>Batman</em> movie, in which the Joker poisons multiple hygiene and cleaning products and releases them into stores, only for Batman to realize that the products are only dangerous when used in certain, specific combinations. </p>
      <p>It occurred to me that a lot of the political arguments that drive me crazy take this form; two arguments that are, on their own, not particularly disagreeable, but when combined (and people who believe one often do believe the other) produce a more horrifying conclusion or implication. </p>
      <p>Take the two arguments "everything is political" and "marginalized people need to be heard regarding our political decisions." I think the first one is <em>annoying</em>, and often hypocritical, but I think it's more or less true; many decisions or actions not normally characterized as "political" rest on various assumptions about rights, justice, ownership, what those concepts mean and who they apply to, etc. </p>
      <p>And the second one, for all the abuse it takes around here, I don't think it's illegitimate either; just a disagreement about <em>who</em> is marginalized. Complaints about progressives enforcing their mores on everyone else map neatly to the oppressor/oppressed dynamic, and being afraid to speak out for fear of destruction sounds pretty marginalized to me. </p>
      <p>But put those two arguments together and you get "Everything is political, and marginalized people need to be our first concern when making political decisions, therefore people who we do not define as marginalized (and disputing that definition is denying marginalized peoples' voices!) have no right to complain about <em>anything,</em> and furthermore there is <em>nowhere</em> they can go that will be outside of our purview and beyond our judgment." A far more chilling conclusion than either one, separately. </p>
      <p>Another example, in which both ingredients are by themselves mildly toxic but not <em>completely</em> indefensible and combine to form something <em>really</em> toxic: "Violence is acceptable/necessary to stop the spread of far right ideologies (AKA 'Punch a Nazi')" and "Far rightism/racism/fascism can be found everywhere, in 'proto' and 'crypto' forms, and even mildly centrist or conservative opinions are just a gateway drug to them." These arguments are pretty dicey independently (and I'm sure that <em>actual</em> far rightists say the same about progressivism and communism and so forth), but put together you get "We reserve the right to destroy anyone or anything, and face no judgment because it was either fascist or crypto-fascist, and we were thus morally justified in stopping it." </p>
      <p>Some examples from other ideologies, because I don't think this is a progressive/SJ-exclusive thing: </p>
      <p>Libertarian: "Every social dispute should be resolved with payment/contracts, etc. not government force" + "Poor people do not deserve any special protection or status beyond what they can manage on their own" = "If you're poor enough,  you basically have no rights and no recourse." </p>
      <p>New Right: "Preservation of order and civilization is of paramount importance" + "Some groups' low-IQ-induced anti-social behavior makes them a threat to order and civilization" = "These groups need to be kept in line by force." </p>
      <p>The problem here is, of course, that your interlocutor might believe both things at once but be unaware of the implications, leading them to think that you're the crazy one trying to distract from whatever you're talking about with something irrelevant. For a sufficiently cunning/cynical interlocutor, they may exploit this intentionally.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>