<post>
  <author>ymeskhout</author>
  <date>2020-06-25T04:00:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvx9iz4/</link>
  <title>Analyzing the Flynn Case in Light of Proscecutor Prerogative</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Maybe pertinent information for you to know is that I'm a criminal defense attorney.</p>
      <p>I didn't make this clear in my comment, but I don't believe that anyone was deceived by Flynn. But the law doesn't care anyway. My response was to explain why he was <em>only</em> charged with ยง1001 violation. This is close, but not quite, to what we in the business call a "fictional plea". We get these all the time, almost always through negotiations.</p>
      <p>One small example. A client was steadily stealing chips from a casino over a long period of time. She was a card dealer in her 60s who never had so much as a speeding ticket but she stole enough money that it qualified for a felony. They intentionally filed it as an <em>attempted</em> felony, which turned it into a misdemeanor, but on the condition that she pleads guilty to the <em>attempt</em> (even though she actually did steal the money, not just attempt). The deal was if she refused to plead guilty, then they would refile it as a felony and proceed accordingly. But because of her lack of history, the prosecutor said he felt sorry for her so he offered to modify the charge even further to attempted property destruction, instead of attempted theft, because the former would be less likely to affect her ability to get a job. Stealing money is <em>sort of</em> property destruction? I guess?</p>
      <p>We all agreed. The prosecutor got a conviction (likely enough to scare my client for life), the casino got their money back through restitution, and my client avoided a felony conviction.</p>
      <p>In another case, a gunfight involving half a dozen people shooting at each other and several getting hit and everyone involved gets charged with <em>only</em> unlawful possession of a firearm instead of attempted murder. The prosecutors acknowledge privately there is a plausible claim of self-defense, and the criminal histories of those involved is lengthy enough that any conviction no matter what would lead to a very long sentence anyway. They said plead guilty to this or we'll move with first degree assault if you go to trial.</p>
      <p>That's why I'm not surprised with how Flynn was treated, vis a vis the pleas and the indictments. Just because he wasn't charged or convicted of something, doesn't mean he didn't do it, especially if the non-charging was conditional on a plea and prosecutorial assistance. And we don't have access to every conversation that took place between his attorneys and the prosecutors (almost all my negotiations are by phone or in person). And even so, the claim that courts cannot consider uncharged allegations is just flat out false. Maybe they <em>shouldn't</em>, but in sentencing hearings the rules of evidence are nearly <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/rules/frcrmp/rule_32">non-existent</a>. In especially egregious cases, sometimes the judges <a href="https://www.themarshallproject.org/2018/07/23/punished-for-crimes-not-proven">take into account crimes that a jury specifically acquitted</a>.</p>
      <p>I bring all this up to explain that I'm steeped enough in the industry to not be surprised by the misconduct of the prosecutors in this case. But the bottom line is still that Flynn is likely to walk <em>not</em> because his case is the apotheosis of injustice, but because he's friends with Trump. Letting him walk does not address prosecutorial misconduct, it just reinforces the benefits of nepotism.</p>
      <p>I would be personally thrilled if this episode was an example of a profession having a reckoning with itself, because the list of long-overdue reforms in the area is endless. But I don't believe this is the case. The basis for my "genuinely worried" test is to gauge the motivation behind this move. If the motive is corrupt, i.e. preferential treatment because of high-connection, then it's not changing anything, and simply reinforcing well-established injustices that manifest along lines of class and wealth. If the motive is to fight against injustice, that's great! Because then it means genuine reform that affects more than just top-tier Generals is on its way. But if the latter is true, then we would see either legislation or department-level guidance.</p>
      <p>That is not what is happening, therefore I don't have any good reason to believe this isn't just a manifestation of corrupt preferential treatment which would only serve to reinforce the current status quo (prosecutorial misconduct and all).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>