<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2020-10-06T14:10:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g7w9gti/</link>
  <title>Kyle Rittenhouse as Model of Young Men's Suicidal Overconfidence</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Alright, it is morning and I am now calm enough to respond.</p>
      <p>So I tried hunting down my comments from when this shit was first posted to prove to you how I perceived Rittenhouse’s actions that night, but it’s been more than a month and reddit is about as searchable as El Dorado so whatever.</p>
      <p>Long story short, from the moment Rosenbaum tried to jump him onwards, the only fault I found in his decision making was when he did not successfully kill Grosskreutz; it would have been reasonable and somewhat safer for him to have followed up with more shots until the enemy gunman was on the ground.</p>
      <p>I did not hammer in my perception of Rittenhouse’s actions in my comment up there because I assumed that anyone around here who was interested in the subject remembered me from last time. Call it a bad assumption if you want. But either way, let’s have no nonsense about me slamming Rittenhouse for an unjustified shoot.</p>
      <p>What truly enraged me about your response (and made me take a twelve hour breather to not get banned) was this bit-</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>His goal, as I'm sure you understand, was to protect his community from mob violence. You're criticizing him for not staying home as though his goal was to save his own skin, when he was obviously engaging in an altruistic act despite the fact that it was not in his own best interests. He put his own safety on the line in order to defend his community, plain and simple. Then you come along and snark, as though you're superior to him because you sat on your couch when he was outside taking risks for others. You act like you know something he doesn't.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Let us take hold of the narrative here for a moment. You are painting Rittenhouse as a Heinleinian model of the citizen soldier and thereby rubber stamp your approval upon every bad decision he made before Rosenbaum attacked.</p>
      <p>Rittenhouse is not a citizen soldier. He is not a community defender. He has sworn no oaths, submitted to no discipline, signed no contract designating what he shall and shall not protect. He is a legal child. He had as much responsibility to quell rioters as he has to uncover cartel smuggling operations or recover kidnapping victims. He <em>assumed</em> the responsibility of showing up armed to the riots, and I contend that he did it less because he’s Johnny fucking Rico learning the true meaning of citizenship, and more because young men are drawn to the excitement of chaos and are suicidally overconfident that they’ll survive it.</p>
      <p>I did not play the Vet card idly; you challenged me directly. “What do I know that he doesn’t?” Well, I know what the hip bone looks like when it’s torn out of the body. I’ve dealt with strung out psychos screaming at me from six feet away. I know how to absorb an ROE from a higher authority and use it to inform my decision making process under stress. He did not, had never, and does not respectively. Which means he was fundamentally unsuited for the job he went and did- unclear on the consequences, inept at conflict deescalation, and possessed of no formally invested authority.</p>
      <p>You also ask say-</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>[...W]hat you're saying, quite clearly, is that in the event Rosenbaum or the rest of the mob had murdered him, you would assign the primary blame in [sic] the crime to Rittenhouse.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Careless phrasing- I can distinguish between keeping criminal liability on the murders while still maintaining that Rittenhouse volunteered to be subject to it. In any case, you skipped over the part where I <em>did</em> blame the other three dorks who got shot for showing up to a riot, even though two of them thought they were doing a good deed by chasing down a crazed killer.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>