<post>
  <author>RemarkableStatistics</author>
  <date>2020-10-02T06:57:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g7dm4gt/</link>
  <title>A Critique of Critical Theory In Response to Adam Neely</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The entire premise of the argument is flawed because cultural supremacy is not racial supremacy.  This is part of a larger critique of critical theory that is expanded on at the bottom.  I'll put this aside for now, but it is of utmost importance.</p>
      <h1>Impressions</h1>
      <p>To nitpick, his point at 2:25 is false.  One of the most popular and acclaimed symphonies is the western canon is the New World Symphony by Dvorak.  This was a symphony written for America during his time in America with influence from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symphony_No._9_(Dvo%C5%99%C3%A1k)#Influences">Native American and African American music</a> and even took Europe by storm.  </p>
      <p>The argument is basically the same as one often made about Philosophy departments.  The conclusion that I tend to circle around to is this: In order to study a discipline there needs to be a historical canon of work that represents the 'best' that the discipline has to offer.  'Best' doesn't necessarily mean anything, but you have to chose something.  For obvious practical purposes, one might as well chose something that is relevant to the cultural history of the prevailing culture.</p>
      <p>Once you have a canon, teaching music theory is straight forward, just as with philosophy.  Without a canon, every class becomes a fragmented "cultural comparison" course which is difficult to teach and does not reach any conclusions without an independent basis to work from(and there is no such basis).  Adding to the chaos, every hack musician suddenly has a legitimate claim that they themselves exemplify the most sophisticated form of this new 'music theory'.</p>
      <p>For Philosophy, the western philosophical canon is to my knowledge the only cultural philosophical canon that could distinguish itself from theology.  Beyond that, it has developed in much more sophisticated(but not necessarily more profound) ways far and beyond any other tradition.</p>
      <p>But, of course, music is more ubiquitous than philosophy.  Every culture has music.  Music theory shouldn't necessarily be restricted to one type of music.  And there is less of a need for arbitrary restrictions on music than on philosophy.</p>
      <p>Because of this observation, I agree with the sentiment of many points, such as: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"we have claimed that it(18th century European music) is "music theory", not "western music theory", not "White music theory", but "music theory" for all music of the world.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>However, I am extremely suspect of this:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"[Beethoven] wasn't a bad composer; he was an above average composer"</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is like saying that Notre-Dame is an above-average building.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>People are loathe to admit that every culture has not only a rich musical tradition, but a rich tradition of music theory.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>But none as sophisticated and influential upon our culture, and extensively compared amongst each other (thereby constituting a coherent canon) as that of the selected European traditions.</p>
      <p>We don't study Indian music for the same reason that we don't study medieval European music.  It's just not that relevant to us.  </p>
      <p>Studying music theory is somewhat like studying 300 year old Spanish, but it is also like studying Latin. </p>
      <p>It's fair to say that one doesn't understand the current musical tradition in America without learning about Wagner.  If you wonder why modern composers tend to write scores for movies rather than write symphonies, read about Wagner.</p>
      <p>However, I generally agree that some have an undue fetish for "classical" music.  Also, I completely agree with this:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Using one culture's music theory as a foil to another as a means to understanding both of them better is something that we just don't do in the west.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <h1>Critical Theory</h1>
      <p>Coming back to the thrust and tone of the argument: it's all dressed up in critical theory.  This person sarcastically mocks the fact that critical race theory (in particular the propositions that America is inherently racist or evil and that any race is inherently racist or evil) was deemed anti-American.  I have a growing intolerance for smug sarcasm in this day and age.  It is a tool for falsely elevating oneself above something one don't like without any explanation or argument.  Please <em>do</em> explain why these things should be taught to federal employees(or to anyone at all), Mr music man.  But no, slap "White Supremacy" onto the title and don't address it head on.  If you think Bach is more worthy of study than some Indian musician nobody in America has ever heard of, then you are complicit in "White Supremacy".  You may now freely associate with your fellow skinheads without threat of further social stigma. </p>
      <p>It's frustrating to agree with various points and then have to back up and critique the philosophy that underpins it all.</p>
      <p>The most comprehensive critique I have heard of critical theorists comes from Noam Chomsky of all people:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2cqTE_bPh7M">Video 1: Noam Chomsky on French Intellectual Culture &amp; Post-Modernism</a>
      </p>
      <p>Chomsky points out the insular nature of the culture of French intellectuals from which post-modernism was spawned.  A choice quote:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I was in Paris a couple of years ago to give a talk.  During the Q&amp;A, one young man got up and asked a rather plaintive question: "Bertrand Russell tells us we should look for the Truth.  But the [French] Philosophers tell us that there is no Truth.  So what should we do?"  You don't hear this type of question anywhere else in the world except where this [post-modern]influence has spread.  It's mostly confined to comparative literature departments, so if they talk to each other in incomprehensible rhetoric, then nobody cares.  The place it has been really harmful is in the third world among intellectuals...  The level of irrationality that grows out of this undermines the opportunities for doing something really significant and important.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The question asked by the man and Chomsky's remark is possibly the most relatable counter to post-modernism I've heard.
It's no longer just in literature departments.  Offshoots of this philosophy are being enacted in all powerful institutions in America.  It is well shielded against critiques because it is borne of critiques.</p>
      <p>Chomsky describes the culture surrounding post-modernism in more detail:
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OjQA0e0UYzI">Video 2: Noam Chomsky - Postmodernism</a></p>
      <p>I don't think much more needs to be said about it.  Many have correctly pointed out that it is a repackaging of Marxist theory (Marxism is simply the most convenient mode of transportation for applying critical theory to a capitalist society).  I'll add some nuance by saying that post-modernism nominally claims to reject "grand narratives" while accepting the grand narrative of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historicism">historicism</a> wholesale and uncritically.  No more really needs to be said about the incoherence of post-modern critical theory.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>