<post>
  <author>rifhen</author>
  <date>2020-10-03T23:02:05Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g7kmscc/</link>
  <title>Politicians are getting better at their jobs over time and it’s destroying our society</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Politicians are getting better at their jobs over time and it’s destroying our society.  That’s my thesis statement.  I don’t hold it that strongly and don’t have any evidence  other than my own impressions.  But here is my case:</p>
      <p>1) By better at their jobs I don’t mean better at governing the country.  I mean better at contesting elections.</p>
      <p>2) It would make sense for politicians to get better at contesting elections over time.  The rest of us have gotten better at what we do since the 18th century.  They have more statistical tools available to them now.  The nation has more disposable income to throw at winning elections, and as government has become more and more involved in our lives winning elections has become more and more valuable to different interests.</p>
      <p>3) Let’s consider Presidential elections.  Have the parties gotten better at contesting the electoral college (not the popular vote)?  Trump vs Clinton was extremely close.  A relatively few votes in a few states and Clinton would be president.  Obama/Romney, Bush/Kerry, Bush/Gore were all very close, Bush/Gore almost imaginable so.  When I was a child Reagan carried 49 states in his re-election campaign.  It’s very hard for me to imagine that happening today.</p>
      <p>4) Trump famously said that he could shoot someone in the middle of the street and his supporters wouldn’t care.  To state it differently, when Nixon got caught up in Watergate, it really seemed to matter.  He would have had a tough time being re-elected.  It doesn’t seem to matter very much now who the candidates are - any election is going to be close.  Why is that?  People have become deeply politicized.</p>
      <p>5) I majored in political science years ago.  I don’t claim any great expertise, but one of the things I concluded from studying these issues was that people don’t really change their minds.  Elections are won by turning out people inclined to vote for you (not the same thing as the base) while minimizing the turnout from your opponent.  One thing that puzzled me when I was younger was why national political candidates didn’t seem to understand that.  Let me give you some examples: HW Bush and Bob Dole.  Really, Chairman Mao could probably done as well turning out red tribe as Bob Dole.  </p>
      <p>6) Trump’s takeover of the Republican Party reminds me a lot of the famous 80s corporate takeovers.  There was a big and obvious market for what he is selling that no one seemed to want to fill.  You might think he’s despicable, but he’s giving a voice to thoughts that a lot of people have had for a long time and that have gone without representation.</p>
      <p>7) Note it doesn’t have to be the case that there has been a straight line increase in the “skill” of the parties since the founding.  I know there were very close elections early on.  But if you look at the period since WW2, things just seem like they have become very tight.</p>
      <p>8) I have young children, and it is shocking to see how effective marketers have become at selling them products.  A 30 min commercial can send them into a frenzy to buy the most idiotic products.  Why would that skill, if it exists, not bleed over into politics?</p>
      <p>9) I want to kind of bait and switch here, because when I say politicians I don’t mean or don’t only mean the people we vote for themselves.  Rather I mean the broader enterprises involved with getting them elected.  I’m thinking of the Karl Roe’s working in the darkness.</p>
      <p>10) If they are getting better at contesting elections, what does that mean?  Think about how you feel when your favorite team loses a close ball game.  The anguish can be intense.  Damn that ref, if that one call had gone the other way, we would have won.  I think I prefer being blown out.  Moreover, what they’re getting good at is riling people up enough to get them to come out to vote.  Just like my children, they have to get us to feel some strong emotion or otherwise appeal to a very primal part of our brains.  I.e. not our rational thoughts.  They have to get us afraid, or ticked off.  </p>
      <p>11) Do you see the parallels between my concern here and the concerns some have with AI?  This invisible hand of the political market, which will drive greater and greater “efficiency” over time, has no stopping point.  We will be more and more mobilized until eventually we’ve been mobilized for total war.</p>
      <p>In a lot of ways I’m not saying anything new.  The men who set up our government were afraid of democracy for just this reason.  They talk about the “party spirit” that would be created.  And they were drawing on a long line of thought.  If you want to be amused, go read Plato’s description of democracy and the “democratic man” in the Republic.  We’re living at the bottom of their slippery slope.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>