<post>
  <author>Standard_Order</author>
  <date>2020-10-04T14:37:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g7ommr7/</link>
  <title>Problematizing Chess</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Okay, ULPT: Chess is one of the easier targets out there, just write a big Twitter thread about how it’s a game for chuds:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>Start off with saying/implying that chess was a little-known game before the Nazis got obsessed with it. <a href="https://www.chesshistory.com/winter/extra/nazi.html">Helpful link of Nazi chess stuff;</a> slip in a screenshot of that dumb TV show where Nazi officers play human chess in a concentration camp</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>It was popularized in the US by the first American champion, notorious white supremacist and anti-Semite Bobby Fischer</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>"Who cares, it’s a harmless game!" Unlike more elegant games like Go which promote critical thinking/whatever, chess’ rules are completely arbitrary, so getting good at chess doesn’t make your kids smarter in any other sense</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>NOT TO MENTION it’s embedded with white supremacist assumptions. “White (light-skinned) moves first” which reflects India’s caste system and was reinforced through racist rhetoric after the game was stolen by Europeans. If you let your kids play, these ideas will seep into their subconscious</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Example of this is the use of chess-related rhetoric (pawns, checkmate) by far-right conspiracy theorists like <a href="https://twitter.com/standardorder/status/1308680399997087744">Alex Jones</a></p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Why is this important now? Chess is experiencing a huge popularity surge among young, lonely, terminally-online white men who watch Twitch streamers. Cite Gamergate or times Twitch women have been harassed as examples of how horrible this audience is</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>They idolize Fischer and current champion Magnus Carlsen — pull screenshots from <em>Magnus</em> to highlight how colonialist it is to fetishize a white European who “conquered” India.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Quote tweet <a href="https://twitter.com/standardorder/status/1305331842510401536">this</a> as an example of how neo-Nazis glamorize chess skill</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Who’s profiting? Big chess companies like chess.com who also implicitly condone problematic behavior by staying partnered with chess masters like <a href="/r/chess/comments/i8hptf/">this one</a> who have made openly racist comments (maybe better to find a male example; chess masters are a bunch of babies, very easy to make the case that they’re toxic people for Impressionable Kids to look up to)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>End of thread: Okay, chess is bad. What’s the alternative? Now plug 3-5 of your favorite new games, Hex or whatever, and highlight how the companies that make them are properly woke</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Ideally you’d do this after you already had 100-300 wokerati followers, but it doesn’t matter if the thread doesn’t gain any currency (although I’ll gladly signal boost it). The fact is that now it’s <em>out there</em>, and you can start linking to it from your alts on related forums. Talk as if it’s common knowledge that chess is a right-wing construct, then link to it as support for what you’re saying; no one will go through the effort of debunking it. Give it a few months, maybe a bigger influencer will copy your idea and repost the thread, and then it’ll slowly disseminate into common knowledge. When people think they’re Dunking on Trump by playing Hex or whatever, there’ll be a lot more of them for you to play with.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>