<post>
  <author>zzzyxas</author>
  <date>2020-10-02T07:55:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g7dptn7/</link>
  <title>A Dive Into Musical Tradition and Theory</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It is an absolutely true fact that the western musical tradition has kind of dominated other musical traditions into obscurity.
Like, you can listen to something like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MTlbR_Ox_7M">Horizons</a> and it's clearly from a different tradition that fundamentally thinks about music differently, but even though there's many nonwestern traditions, they sum to &lt;1% of the music you'll hear in almost any western context.</p>
      <p>(To contrast, compare <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NPDCsi1mbhE">Tempus est Iocundum (medieval)</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j-X5z4UH9v0">Tempus est Iocundum (Carmina Burana)</a>. These things sound very, very different, being several centuries apart, but are also very obviously from the same tradition.)</p>
      <p>It is absolutely reasonable to demand that there exist music theory courses to give other musical traditions treatment equal to the western tradition.
It is eminently reasonable to ask that current "introduction to music theory" courses be renamed to "introduction to western music theory". (I'm fine with their current name, insofar as I think it's obvious that the "western' is implied, but have no strong objections to making it explicit.)</p>
      <p>
        <em>That said</em>, the claim that the music theory is just the music that eighteenth century Europeans like is less defensible.
There's this whole massive western musical tradition that kind of cuts out; hard disagree that "music theory" can be replaced by "the harmonic style of 18th century european musicians".</p>
      <p>The western musical tradition started at least in the fourteenth century and has evolved continuously, to the present day.
There is a line unbroken from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qXMZoKofu7g">Josquin</a> to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kHtwF-gpluc">Joplin</a>.
The claim that "music theory" works for <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9INrvk6AxzU">Handel</a>, but not Hetfield, is asinine.
Is there counterpoint in Metallica?
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OXm5G5CbhM8">Yes there is!</a>.</p>
      <p>Speaking of Josquin, notice how the selection I chose is spiritual?
Talking about the history of the western musical tradition while omitting the Catholic Church is like talking about the history of America and omitting England.
There's a reason the western musical tradition got big enough to dominate every other musical tradition to obscurity, and that reason is that the Catholic Church did it.
Making it about white supremacy is kind of a stretch: slaves made their own distinct contribution to the western tradition (e.g. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z5nQW1dXn2E">Down to the River to Pray</a>) and, approximately as soon as slavery ended, free African Americans started making their own distinct contributions (American Civil War ended in 1865 and Joplin was born in 1868).</p>
      <p>To be sure, today's musical landscape would also look different if, for instance, western imperialism hadn't taken the very large western musical tradition developed by the Catholic Church and exported it all over the globe.
But there's a flipside to that, which is that all over the globe has contributed back to the western tradition.
More than any other tradition, through historical happenstance, the western tradition has become everyone's tradition.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Miscellany</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Bach/Mozart/Beethoven aren't held up as The Greatest Composers Ever because of their Germanity. The greatest composers of the particular era that Neely is focusing on were German because that's where Vienna was. If he had arbitrarily picked a different period, he would have come up with Italy, or Russia, or maybe France. Being surprised that the greatest composers of that particular era came from Germany is like being surprised that a lot of contemporary academic work comes out of Boston and San Francisco. Also, Handel, the eighteenth-century composer of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9INrvk6AxzU">one of the most widely-recognized pieces of classical music</a>, was British. Like, Bach/Mozart/Beethoven are certainly important, but for someone with Neely's background to focus on them to the exclusion of the rest of the western musical tradition that was occurring before them, after them, and at the same time but in different places requires willing ignorance.</li>
        <li>I'm not a jazzy, but I suspect the reason that vanilla music theory courses start with (white) baroque/classical music instead of (black) jazz is much the same reason that we teach algebra before calculus. Certainly, the jazzies I know started with western classical music, as did the musicians who created jazz.</li>
        <li>1960s American was not the first people to try to make a universal, mathematically primitive music theory; that sort of thing was very much in the wheelhouse of eighteenth century Europeans. And, in fact, there is a bit of universal mathematics in music: tones with frequencies that form low-reducing whole-number rations (e.g. 330 Hz and 440 Hz) sound consonant. I don't think there's a way to get from the few truly universal axiom-isn't-the-right-word to something like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5IXMpUhuBMs">Rite of Spring</a>—music absolutely is absolutely culturally dependent in a big way—but that doesn't mean that there isn't some amount of mathematically-primitive universality there, and Neely is educated enough he should know better.</li>
        <li>I don't personally like rap, but it is completely obvious that there is musicality there (for illustration, see (vaguely nsfw) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5IXMpUhuBMs">Cooking by the Book ft. Lil Jon</a>). It is completely reasonable to personally consider something like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kGEG4JiOqew">4'33</a> not music; trying to create a bright line of things that are and are not music, less so. I would have, however, accepted less-typical [western] music.</li>
        <li>Who the literal fuck, in the twenty-first century, writes "the reason 'Teenage Dream' went to No. 1 and remains in radio rotation is that it is a textbook example of the excellence and supremacy of the rules of Western music theory"? Leave aside the absolute failure to read the room of any contemporary English-speaking culture; "Teenage Dream" is competing exclusively against others pieces written in the western tradition. It would be like giving a bunch of people Nike shoes, having them run a race, pointing at the winner and attributing their win to the shoes. Did GPT-3, but with extra training from /pol/, write that? Seriously, that sort of word vomit is so nonsensical that incoherence is a plausible alternative to white supremacy.</li>
        <li>The Shenker stuff is way above my pay grade (I'm a performer who's picked up random bits of theory and history as a matter of course, not a graduate student in music theory), but it all sounds plausible enough. I have no problem believing that influential music theorists of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries were literal Nazis. I have much more trouble with the idea that they represent all, or even most, of music theory.</li>
        <li>There is a relationship between music and class; knowledge and talent of classical music is a comically strong class signifier. Classical instruments are expensive, on par with a car, both in terms of up-front cost and maintenance. (Granted, if you're not a pro, a <em>used</em> car, but still.)</li>
      </ul>
      <hr />
      <p>Summary</p>
      <p>There's an absolutely valid point here about how the popular conception of what music is is actually a conception about western music.
And there's certainly substantial gains to be had by learning more from other traditions; Horizons is <em>excellent</em>.
But I also suspect this claim isn't particularly novel claim to most western musicians or anyone else who has seriously thought about it for more than five minutes—although, credit where it's due, most viewers of Neely's video wouldn't have otherwise.</p>
      <p>The more controversial claim—that music theory is white supremacist—I come away skeptical of.
This isn't to say that western music hasn't been developed and used for white supremacist purposes, which I have no trouble believing.
At the same time, there's so much more (the western musical tradition is <em>big</em>) that framing it substantially as a white supremacist thing is excessively reductive.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>I've linked to the King's Singers twice here, and that was after substantial restraint because I am a King's Singers fanboy.
Their most recent album, Finding Harmony, is a collection of songs from cultures all over the world that people sang to bring themselves together in times of strife.
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KYaQhgmOT24">O, chì, chì mi na mòrbheanna</a> from that album is my single favorite sound recording of all time.
The King's Singers took the western musical tradition and used it as a tool to try to find unity in a world becoming increasingly divided.
I'd like more of that.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>