<post>
  <author>greatjasoni</author>
  <date>2020-09-30T03:37:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g750lzm/</link>
  <title>What Should Public Political Discourse Look Like?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>What should public political discourse look like? <a href="/u/Kulakrevolt">/u/Kulakrevolt</a> made the point that despite the outlandishness of this debate, it had the highest density of information of any debate in memory. I've heard for years that American politics is too dumbed down. Debates were a contest to see who could speak slowest with the nicest hair, in a firm but not too condescending tone to make old pensioners feel safe. In contrast we got Trump and Biden wading into the minutiae while talking over each other. There were no vague 12 point plans peppered with slogans. This is what many have been asking for for years: a politics of substance over style.</p>
      <p>I think we should all be careful what we wish for. This debate was horrid because the issues are horrid. Any performance less bombastic than Trump's wouldn't reflect how the right wing base feels about the issues. Any accusation weaker than "you are the worst president we've ever had" wouldn't have captured the disdain the left has for Trump. </p>
      <p>Or maybe not. Maybe this is an idiosyncrasy of Donald Trump and the current climate, and we could have a debate with a similar level of information content without stooping so low. I'm not sure how to establish this but I suspect they're coupled. I think this is the price we pay for honesty. Both candidates constantly lied, but the discussion was real. This is far more honest than whatever pretense we had decades ago. Back then, the semantic content of any particular speech act was irrelevant. It was just background noise meant to signal the proper buzzwords and canned quipps. Instead, for once we had a real glimpse into the dark heart of the culture war.</p>
      <p>I'd rather not see it. I want to go back. I want Romneys haircut and Barracks cool demeanor. They didn't need to discuss policy. The president hardly has anything to do with it anyways. They put on a show to signal civility and competence. We all knew it was a show but it was an important step in the ritual. This felt like someone accidentally crossed the wires with reality and forgot to cancel the ritual. If there was no debate tonight would anything have been lost? Is anyone here glad they watched that? Was it worth seeing this substance? I'd rather we all got to retain our innocence as quokkas, where agencies no one has ever heard of staffed with experts hammer out the actual points of policy with no regard for the theatrics whatsoever. I hope that's what we return to once this all blows over. This mixing of symbolic and real doesn't bode well. Trump told Biden antifa would overthrow him. We have lots of civil war discussion brewing around here. The ritual of gesturing at civil discourse with policy for 5 year olds kept the beast asleep. This is what happens when politics actually reflects the sentiments of the people. The sham debates were a social technology meant to keep politics at bay, and we need them back as soon as possible. </p>
      <p>(Let me know if this should be in the debate thread. It's abstract enough that I figured it should technically be separate. I'm not particularly interested in the specifics of the debate here.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>