<post>
  <author>kreuzguy</author>
  <date>2020-09-29T22:30:37Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g743nmy/</link>
  <title>Summarizing "The Son Also Rises"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I am about to finish reading "The Son Also Rises: Surnames and the History of Social Mobility" and my main reaction is: "Wow, this has to be the most powerful social science-related book that I've ever read. Perhaps it is the most important ever written!". It is simple, elegant and very persuasive, which is the opposite of what you frequently encounter when diving into this field. The main proposition of the book is that social mobility hasn't changed for the last centuries: the velocity through which families descend from high class (or ascend from low class) has been the same, doesn't matter if it is in Medieval England or in contemporaneous and capitalistic UK.</p>
      <p>"Wait, that can't be right. A lot of things changed over the last centuries: free education, market-driven meritocracy, free healthcare, etc. That's just not possible."</p>
      <p>I share your rush to disqualify that proposition as extremely improbable, but that's literally what it is: a rush. We are just scratching the surface. Not only the rate of social mobility remained the same in England, but it appears to be the same in every country the author looked into (there is one exception, which I will elaborate later, if my laziness allows). Chile, England, United States, China, Japan, and even Sweden! They all share this same rate of mobility, and this velocity is the same in all epochs and it is the same whether you are rich or poor.</p>
      <p>"This is... strange. What about those studies that show how mobility in Scandinavian countries are much higher than in USA?"</p>
      <p>The author argues that the methods usually used to estimate social mobility end up overestimating it. They usually use one metric for social status (income is the main one) and, therefore, are very noisy, especially when applied to individuals. A perhaps nice illustration is to think about a rich kid who ends up studying Philosophy in a top university and working as a Professor at an Ivy League. If we only use income to attest someone's social status, we might very well be right to say that he or she descended in status. But that doesn't sound correct. What we really want is to incorporate all metrics of social status in the analysis (university attendance, wealth, occupation, neighborhood, etc.) and that is where Gregory Clark diverges from the mainstream. He uses surnames to investigate how families status progresses through time. "If the Smiths were occupying medical positions at twice the rate we would expect assuming random sorting in 1760, what would we expect to happen in the next generation? And in the next? And in the next?" At the end, the author achieves a kind of universal number: the children's social status correlate 0.7-0.8 with their parents. No matter the culture, the historical shocks or the institutional changes, this correlation holds.</p>
      <p>I think I will end here and strongly suggest everyone to read this amazing piece of work. It was missed from my radar for so long, and I am glad I finally read it. This is not something I think I will be able to digest properly for a very long time, though. Maybe in some years I will be able to make sense of all of this and harmonize it with my worldview.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>