<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-09-30T04:27:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g755813/</link>
  <title>  “My armor is contempt. My shield is disgust. My sword is hatred.”</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="/u/greatjasoni">u/greatjasoni</a>, I’m so flattered you took my (aggressive) contrarianism so intellectually seriously.</p>
      <p>To repaste my comment that prompted it:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>They’re talking about the issues, specifically... not pussy footing around, not meditating on Eagles, not Twirling towards freedom... they’re hammering specifics directly and uncompromisingly.</p>
        <p>I wish every second of US politics could be like this</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>I stand by that. </p>
      <p>The reason so many people found this debate disgusting is because the business of governing is disgusting.</p>
      <p>Every single policy involves Imposing large costs on one person or group so as to grant benefits to others... whether this be regular tax and spend, Regulation, the criminalization of activities, warfare, the myriad ways financial regulations exist to redistribute wealth to the connected, the vast systems of “Welfare” that somehow seem to always ignore the most vulnerable in favour of the well organized voter block...</p>
      <p>It is disgusting and you should feel disgusted.</p>
      <p>You shouldn’t get to hide in suave carefully constructed images whether they be hair, a reassuring tone of voice, sweet nothings about eagles or the better nature of US... for whatever value of “us” you think we’re discussing...</p>
      <p>No we’re discussing who lives and who dies... we’re discussing which thousands of  screaming desperates we’re going to save, and which we’re going to sacrifice, we’re discussing How many children we’re going to bomb and starve to death with blockades because we think it might save others, we are discussing who gets to keep their house and keep their family together and who will face utter ruin... either do to losing a benefit or an opportunity, or because a tax or regulation makes them non-viable...</p>
      <p>You hear the budget numbers and figures that wash over you and think mere money is under discussion... when the only currency ever under discussion in politics is blood.</p>
      <p>And it is disgusting. It is painful. It is something you want to look away from and my sincerest desire is to grab our collective hair shove your face in it and scream “Look at it!”</p>
      <p>Politics is trolley problems stacked on trolley problems in a grimdark tale that would be unbearable were it populated by righteous incorruptible sci-fi captains... but we don’t have incorruptible thoughtful captains... we have our political class.</p>
      <p>Instead of merely being horrifying and Unthinkable choices  that would shake honest people genuinely trying to make  the best choice... we have the corrupt and cynical seeking to prosper... whether this be the burnt out amoral cynics of our favourite war stories.. or the farcical incompetents we imagine swearing oaths and assuming the mantles of Leadership of the free world... </p>
      <p>Kirk and Picard would be broken by most of these choices, morally infected... and instead we have the glorified call centre workers that are congressmen making these calls (seriously look up the amount of time your congressman just spends phone banking asking for donations).</p>
      <p>It is a system that deserves our disgust...these are Question we should hate eachother over... these are leaders who deserve our death wishes... this is a scenario we should be recoiling from... an entire system and field of human activity that should not exist...</p>
      <p>And that is why I am an AnarchoCapitalist... because I aim to make it not exist. </p>
      <p>I wish every second of American politics could be so honest and pure, so true to the issues and unwavering in its surprising intellectual honesty... i wish every politician could be so resolute in their principles and daring in their willingness to engage with the issues on their merits... I wish all our leaders could be like Biden and Trump, and I probably admire the two of them more than any other politicians in my lifetime... A true contest of the greats this election... Giants unmatched in our history...</p>
      <p>And I wish you could see it unblinkingly.... with an open mind and heart... this honest and rigorous civic debate.</p>
      <p>Because then you would see that the problem isn’t bad ideas, or stupid voters, or incompetent leaders, or lack of substance, or not even corruption... it is the very idea that this Democracy, this democratic will, this “we the people”, is legitimate to decide who will be sacrificed and who will be saved... </p>
      <p>if you tried to do half these things on your own they would call you a criminal and madman, if you tried to do these things with your friends they’d call you a gang or terrorists at best... and yet as the decision making structure gets even more incoherent and stakes even more dangerous and horrifying... somehow its become an uplifting affair... an exercise of what is noblest in us.. a beauteous spreading of our eagle-like wings, as we dance and twirl towards freedom...</p>
      <p>I’m quite glad the illusion is shattering... and hope this Disgust might take deeper route. That you might join me.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>“My armor is contempt. My shield is disgust. My sword is hatred.”</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>