<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2020-09-28T17:15:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g6yz0ol/</link>
  <title>Enola Holmes: An Honest Piece of Propaganda</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I just watched <em>Enola Holmes</em> with my wife last night and this struck me a bit. I meant to do a half-effort analysis of it here at some point so I guess here is as good a time as any.</p>
      <p>To contrast the film, let us remember <em>Die Hard</em>. Extreme Leftist Terrorists take a building full of businessmen hostage and start issuing demands to release various Marxist prisoners worldwide. Big twist, they are actually totally apolitical and just want the money.</p>
      <p>They were the Bad Guys in the same way that arrogant businessmen are the bad guys- they’re greedy, soulless dicks in contrast to McLane’s working class grit. “Common thieves”, in the parlance of the film.</p>
      <p>In <em>Enola Holmes</em>, <span class="md-spoiler-text">the bad guys are explicitly reactionary conservatives. At first we think they’re common thieves trying to murder their way to a small fortune, but it turns out they were trying to adjust the vote in the House of Lords to defeat an vaguely described but definitely progressive reform bill.</span></p>
      <p>Almost the exact opposite, you see.</p>
      <p>Of note is the explicitly feminist ideals of the title character- a strong and independent young woman clashes with the expectations and gender roles of society, and stands her ground courageously and makes society alter itself to accommodate her and everyone like her. <span class="md-spoiler-text">We are never given the contents of the reform bill- I have no ideas if it’s quasi-socialist in nature, or purely about women’s suffrage, or what have you. It doesn’t matter- what matters is the contrast. The baddies are trying to keep Victorian/Edwardian society as it is at any cost, and the good guys are trying to modernize it to fit today’s culture.</span></p>
      <p>I was actually impressed at how the bad guys’ had an actual, coherent worldview that informed their decisions and affected their villainy, and that none of the murders were pointless or just present to paint them as evil. Actually, <span class="md-spoiler-text">since Enola’s mom seems to be a feminist terrorist committed to direct action by stockpiling bombs in London and the story appears to applaud her for it</span>, murder is clearly not a mark of evil like it would be in a more simplistic story. What matters most in this moral compass is <em>what you are killing over.</em> Violence in defense of the correct ideology (feminism, social independence, following your dreams and ambitions free of interference from the patriarchy) is courage; violence in defense of the wrong ideology (<span class="md-spoiler-text">patriotism, regressive social policies, preserving the privileges of the upper classes</span>) is villainy. This actually appeals to me greatly since this is basically the praxis of how morality works in real life too. Killing to preserve democracy worldwide is good; killing to give the <em>Deutsche Volk</em> some <em>Lebensraum</em> is bad. And so do debates spiral on over who the bad guy was when we nuked the IJE out of existence, or whether the Provos were justified in setting off bombs on London buses, or whether an Israeli soldier can gun down a Palestinian teenager with a brick in good conscience. Consideration of ideology, I think, really should come first, long long <em>long</em> before debating the ethical problems of the tactics chosen or weapons used.</p>
      <p>In that sense, <em>Enola Holmes</em> is that most honest kind of propaganda- one that insists that the world works on objective moral rules, and that right and wrong are neither messy nor blurred. It will not try to trick your brain by posing conservatives in swastikas or having them eat babies or twirl their mustaches maliciously. It simply asserts that they’re bad people because they believe bad things, and ignores you with a shrug if you disagree.</p>
      <p>Honestly, I wish all cultural output was that frank and upfront about what assumptions they posit about the universe. You can take umbrage at the many assertions of <em>Enola Holmes</em>, but if you want to attack its underhandedness in delivery you’ll find yourself without a leg to stand on.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>