<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-09-29T13:55:02Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g725j1r/</link>
  <title>The Mobilizing of the Media Against Trump</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I am <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ijs526/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_31_2020/g3htp21/">on record</a> with a prediction that Joe Biden will be the next President of the United States.  I do not see a path to victory for Trump.  Of course, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ijs526/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_31_2020/g3htyrs/">I've been wrong about that before</a>, so, you know.  Make of that what you will.</p>
      <p>But the Democratic <a href="http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=67">prospiracy</a> is taking no chances, and now appear to be unloading everything they have. Yesterday it was <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/trump-taxes-returns-new-york-times-report-takeaways/">Trump's tax returns</a>; this morning it is <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jemimamcevoy/2020/09/28/report-trump-2016-campaign-sought-to-dissuade-blacks-from-voting-listed-millions-for-deterrence/#16860082616a">Cambridge Analytica revisited</a>, with a spicy racial twist.  Both stories have been labeled "fake news" by Trump's campaign.  It has <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/trumps-taxes-have-probably-already-been-hacked/">long been assumed</a> that <em>someone</em> had already obtained Trump's tax returns, and now we see that the information was indeed stolen, leaked, or otherwise illegally disseminated at some point (the Times denies that the leak was "illegal," and perhaps they are telling the truth, but given the state of federal law I would be shocked if there was not <em>any</em> statute to cover whatever it was that moved those returns from the IRS to the NYT).  An attack of this nature on the privacy of an American President is totally unprecedented, but then, every other President since Richard Nixon has been releasing their tax returns in a bid to appear transparent, honest, etc.  The Cambridge Analytica data has also been out there for years, only to appear <em>now</em>.</p>
      <p>No, you can't look at Trump's tax returns.  And no, you can't look at the CA data.  But some journalists have, and they assure you that <a href="https://editorial.dailywire.com/news/nyt-bombshell-report-on-trump-taxes-missing-one-key-word-illegal/">Trump has done nothing illegal</a>. Or--sorry, most do their best to <em>avoid</em> pointing out that, after four years of <a href="https://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2016/10/donald-trump-taxes-russia-214405">baseless insinuations</a>, Trump's actual tax returns could not support a <em>New York Times</em> story more biting than</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/trump-taxes-returns-new-york-times-report-takeaways/">Mr. Trump paid an annual average $1.4 million in federal taxes from 2000 to 2017</a>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Which actually sounds like a lot, and so they point out instead that in <em>some</em> of those years, Trump paid very little in taxes indeed.</p>
      <p>Now, I am not a tax lawyer, but I have enough tax knowledge to know that this may be the biggest non-story the <em>New York Times</em> has ever put to print.  Structuring <em>income</em> taxes around vast <em>wealth</em>, especially wealth that comes in the form of property, is <em>complicated</em>.  Unless you already have a good understanding of basis, adjusted basis, depreciation, deductions, business expenses, and so forth, you're not going to understand what is being discussed.  People are going to see headlines telling them that Donald Trump paid less in taxes than they pay to rent a studio flat, and some of them will presumably be outraged by that.  (That many of those people pay no income tax at all, no one seems to notice.)</p>
      <p>Likewise the Cambridge Analytica data apparently shows no particular efforts to suppress voters <em>by race</em>, but only shows that racial minorities were over-represented in categories targeted to discourage participation--presumably, on the assumption that these people could not be swayed from voting Democrat, and therefore should merely be discouraged from supporting Clinton.  But since racial minorities (especially black Americans) are heavily overrepresented among Democrats, any efforts to dampen Democratic enthusiasm for the election would fall disproportionately on minority voters.  It's a non-story.</p>
      <p>But it's <em>news</em>, or it is being treated as news--while Biden's various errors over the years are <em>not news</em>.  They have already been litigated in the court of public opinion.  There's nothing new to say about him, because he hasn't been a part of the government since early 2017.  The role he played in <em>creating</em> the tax laws that governed Donald Trump's returns has been mentioned, a little, but only in right-wing circles already primed to notice such things.</p>
      <p>A couple of my co-workers are assuring me that <em>this</em> is the end for Trump, as they assure me every time another Trump "bombshell" lands on their news feeds.  But these are not bombshells, and what's more, I suspect they're totally unnecessary to the aim of electoral victory for Joe Biden.  After four years of relentlessly attacking Trump for every misstep real <em>and</em> imagined, the leftward news media has seen to it that the opposition is mobilized and anxious for a chance to express their displeasure through more than mere arson.  And all it has cost us is a further-fracturing of the American polis.</p>
      <p>So, none of the foregoing should come as much surprise to any regulars here.  I do not think I have offered any great insights (unless you, like the journalists at the <em>New York Times</em>, simply do not understand tax law). Rather, <a href="https://www.hpmor.com/chapter/108">to understand the object of an obscure plot, observe its consequences and ask who might have intended them.</a> A military friend of mine recently opined that Americans are shockingly complacent about the state of our national security apparatus, perhaps by dint of having never lived through a period of history where we really <em>needed</em> it.  Since the end of the Cold War, those who have most wished to do us harm have been mostly incapable of actually accomplishing that goal.  But it seems to me that the people arguing that e.g. Russia "wants Trump to win" or China "wants Biden to win" have fundamentally misunderstood what Russia, China, Iran, etc. actually want, and are actually pursuing.  Those nations want, and pursue, regional and global hegemony.  The primary obstacle to their ambitions is, and has for decades been, the United States of America.  Who might have intended the destabilization and fragmentation of the American polis?</p>
      <p>I honestly have a hard time narrowing down that list.  And the amazing thing is, they, too, could constitute a sort of prospiracy.  In terms of sheer numbers, it would be trivial for them, each working independently, to introduce just a little more chaos into the virtual forums where Americans increasingly spend our "community" time.  We invented and built the tool--the Internet--by which we have invited the whole world to participate in our meme-scape.  Back around the turn of the century, I think the dream was that expanding the marketplace of ideas in this way would result in greater prosperity for all... and actually I think that in many ways, the dream has been realized.  But there are other dreams, in other places, and it is not clear that we Americans have settled on a new one, as of yet.  This may be why "Make America Great Again" struck such a resonance with people; say what you will about Donald Trump, the man can dream.  The danger of a Biden administration is conversely clear: if elected as the anti-Trump, he heralds no dream, only the end of a dream.  The "positive" platform of the Democratic Party is itself in a bit of disarray, as the liberal and radical wings squabble over the presumed spoils of Trump's impending defeat.  Forget wheels within wheels--we are become a nation of divisions within divisions.</p>
      <p>And there are a lot of things I could say about that, but the only one that seems to matter, with the election just a moon away, is that it all seems so shockingly <em>unnecessary</em>.  From RBG to ACB, from Trump to Biden, from Right to Left, none of these are unprecedented transitions in our nation's history.  There is no <em>necessity</em> to the acrimony, the riots, the yellow journalism.  Biden would likely have won <em>anyway</em>, and if not--what of it?  I was assured that Donald Trump would put Muslims and gays in concentration camps and then start World War III with North Korea, Iran, China, maybe Russia depending on the day... instead I got global peace and a roaring economy clothes-lined by a black swan pathogen.</p>
      <p>Given a different electoral outcome in 2016, I think it very likely that we would today be pretty much where we are, I guess is what I'm saying.  At the urging of certain among our "elite" we've taken to hating one another <em>so much</em>--and it has profited us nothing.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>