<post>
  <author>self_made_human</author>
  <date>2020-09-28T10:25:57Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g6xu4tc/</link>
  <title>Experience as a Front-Line Doctor in India</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>My experience as a front-line doctor in a 3rd World Country:</strong>
      </p>
      <p>After finishing med school, doctors in India do a year of internship in a hospital. The US MD system gives me a splitting headache, so I'll compare it to the Foundation Year 1 of UK MBBS doctors as a 1:1 equivalent.</p>
      <p>At this stage, you are nominally a qualified doctor, with a provisional certificate, and are allowed to practise under the eye of a senior.</p>
      <p>Of course, the degree of autonomy is high, as our seniors are overworked and understaffed, so we're mostly left to our own devices unless something very unfamiliar shows up. In some cases, the interns outright run the show, with the Post Grads showing up once or twice a week, not that we had to go through that ourselves. </p>
      <p>I personally went from the freezer to the fire, with no frying pan in between, going from a rather provincial, rural and low occupancy hospital to one that's just about the busiest in the whole country. Let's recap my experience here so far-</p>
      <p>India has a mixed healthcare system, as by law, all citizens are entitled to free medical care at any government hospital. Given the relative poverty of the country, they do roaring business, while the middle class and above prefer to visit private clinics and hospitals due to lower congestion and less headache in general.</p>
      <p>Think of it like the NHS, but poor in everything except potential patients haha.</p>
      <p>Now, Government hospitals get a <em>bad rep</em> in this country. There's a good reason why most people who can afford it prefer private care. They're insanely crowded, with doctor:patient ratios that are rounding errors, and many of them have near permanent camps on premises where the family of the patients stay due to an inability to afford better. </p>
      <p>Noisy, dirty, overcrowded. All of these are true.</p>
      <p>But somehow, the fucking things <em>work</em>.</p>
      <p>Before I started work here, I had no personal experience with them, having studied at  and visited private clinics all my life. I was expecting the absolute worst, and gritting my teeth hoping to make it through the year.</p>
      <p>Let's just say that my arrival at the <strong>Medicine Ward</strong> did little to disillusion me.</p>
      <p>Every available bed had a patient crammed onto it, and trying to cross the ward was an exercise in hop scotch, or crossing a minefield. It was 50:50 whether you'd step on one of patients who had been shunted to the floor, or a pile of poop.</p>
      <p>Thankfully (?) it turned out to be <em>cat</em> poop.</p>
      <p>You'd think you'd visited the lair of a combined hoarder/crazy cat lady, there about 2 of them for every patient, they walked around like they owned the place, ate the leftovers, and lubricated the floors.</p>
      <p>On my first day, I heard two senior doctors remarking on a remarkably mishappen kitten, with bulbous eyeballs, and how the rest of the litter was turning off.</p>
      <p>It quickly dawned on me that you couldn't expect any better from cats raised on a diet of human blood and teratogenic drugs from the disposal bins where 'proper waste disposal' was more of a suggestion than a firm guideline.</p>
      <p>Now, if you think the doctors were living a life of luxury while their patients cosplayed for Oliver Twist, you couldn't be further from the mark.</p>
      <p>Our single room for the oncalls was barely cleaner than the wards, and only had the minor benefit of air-conditioning.</p>
      <p>In exchange for cats, it had an abundance of cockroaches, aping a rather crappy Tom and Jerry knockoff called Oggie and the Cockroaches, because Cat and Rat is <em>passe</em>, but Cat and Cockroach isn't.</p>
      <p>For the first 2 weeks with 24 hour duties, I didn't sleep a moment, for fear of being overrun. Sleep did win over in the end, but I spent quite a bit of time fruitlessly spraying insecticides to no discernable effect. The immigration from the ward was far too strong.</p>
      <p>You'd go on rounds, and have a roughly 25% chance of finding a dead patient, who had passed away quietly and unremarkably in the humid night, exhaling away their last breath with the blessing of silence to their neighbors, who tossed, turned and moaned in the heat.</p>
      <p>I convinced myself the deaths didn't hurt me, until about a month in, when I found one of our John Does dead on the floor, and then, half an hour later, just as I was about to reach a patient in order to check his pressure and pulse before our rounds, I was met by grievous wails. His daughter was sobbing next to her, begging me *"Why?" as I dropped to the floor, and confirmed that he was indeed dead.</p>
      <p>I knew it wasn't my fault, the man had enough comorbidities to be a medical curiosity, but when I went back to the room, I found my eyes burning with angry tears, and a sob from my chest as I realized my impotence in the vast scheme of things.</p>
      <p>There was nobody to console me, and I haven't cried since.</p>
      <p>I left the ward bitter. And definitely with toxoplasmosis.</p>
      <p>But happily enough, this is where the horror stories end.</p>
      <p>In the rest of my rotations, in Surgery, Gynecology, and Orthopedics, I was impressed by the general cleanliness and efficiency of the place.</p>
      <p>99% of our patients received timely, adequate care, pretty much all the drugs on the WHO's essential medications list was available, and we never lacked for access to all the other medical paraphernalia such as IV cannulas, urobags etc.</p>
      <p>Surgeries were done swiftly, competently and with <strong>strict</strong> asepsis, especially orthopedics, where we were scared to breathe for fear of being yelled at for contaminating something haha.</p>
      <p>Some of the benefits to practicing here were-</p>
      <p>1) Defensive medicine hasn't become ubiquitous here. Sure, we're on the hook, but the sheer litigiousness that plagues the US hasn't made it to this subcontinent. Barring gross incompetence, patients here mostly grin and bear it.</p>
      <p>2) Oh Jesus I've seen enough patients here for two lifetimes, whatever deficiencies existed in my clinical knowledge were treated as firmly as dropping a baby with scurvy into a swimming pool filled with lemons.</p>
      <p>3)Dealing with insurance was a non-issue, everyone was treated for free, I take it this is a serious pain for US doctors? </p>
      <p>4) Very competent teachers. You sort of have to be, to even keep your head above water.</p>
      <p>The cons, however-</p>
      <p>1) You've never experienced the true extent and horror of crippling poverty until you've been at a government hospital. For many, <strong>free</strong> Healthcare is a cost too high to bear, as affording transport from whatever rural village they came from stretched their resources to breaking point. I've seen so many tense up when I tell them that they need a medication that isn't freely available, and try to beg and bargain for a free replacement. Sadly, there often isn't any..</p>
      <p>2) Insanely rude and disrespectful behavior towards patients and their companions is everywhere. Minor errors will get them yelled at, half the time nobody is willing to clear any confusions they might have. They might simply be unable to navigate instructions written in English.
I've seen women get <em>slapped</em> by female doctors  in gynecology, if they were being uncooperative in the midst of labor.</p>
      <p>To an extent, I understand this, even if I don't condone it. When you have 5 minutes at most per patient, a line several hundred long, and you're forced to deal with severe stupidity, it's <em>very very easy</em> to just <strong>snap</strong>. Thankfully, I never felt the urge to lay hands on patients myself, let alone give into it.. </p>
      <p>3)Due to insufficient non-medical staff, the family and friends of patients are expected to handle all the gruntwork of getting X-rays done, arranging for blood bags to be brought etc. If you don't have someone around to handle this, you're really, really fucked. You might be able to hire someone to do it, but given our demographics.. They simply went untreated or treated very late when someone was cajoled into doing it. </p>
      <p>4) GPs get no respect here. Not having an MD after your MBBS is seen as a sign of serious deficiency, and fuels a self-fulfilling cycle. </p>
      <p>5) <strong>I DON'T GET PAID</strong>. Not a cent. This is because I chose to leave my old hospital and switch to the big city, a move that deprived me to my right of a salary. So not only am I overworked, I'm not even paid. I knew this before going, but I can't say it didn't hurt not having disposable income. </p>
      <p>To sum it up: I think I made the right decision going here. I've seen the Ur-Example of Medicine, up close and personal. It's been painful, and I wish I got paid, but take the good with the bad.</p>
      <p>Either way, I intend to emigrate to the UK, I don't really fit in, culturally or memetically speaking here, and after running the Rat Race and sort of winning, all I've become is Dr. Rat. Scott Alexander, who I believe takes no introduction, inspired me to get into Psychiatry. (That and reasonable working hours!) I manged to miss my psychiatry rotation because all non-emergency admissions were closed while COVID was shaking out, but hey, it sure sounded nice. </p>
      <p>I hope that this account was somewhat illuminating, especially since I doubt this topic ever came up here.</p>
      <p>And for those who claim that the US can't afford Medicare for All, a country with 4 times the population and about 0 times the money manages fine. And the NHS exists, as a thing.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>