<post>
  <author>Soulburster</author>
  <date>2020-09-28T20:52:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g6zsgem/</link>
  <title>How many people should you hang in a real game of Werewolf?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>How many people should you hang in a real game of Werewolf?</p>
      <p>Some people think that what fuels conspiracy theories are the things that you find out really are true. Finding out that CIA <em>truly did</em> drug people might lead you to believe the rest of the theory. But any properly constructed conspiracy theory has those bits in them to flash for the rubes, you still don't really buy it.</p>
      <p>You know what <em>actually</em> fuels them? Finding out that things <em>might</em> be true.</p>
      <p>Everyone has heard the debacles about Sweden. Trump's comments, you know, maybe some of the old Tim Pool reporting, some sketchy articles about the "rape capital" and so on. There's always been a push in Sweden against those things, the comments are wrong, the reports lie and the statistics are misrepresented, and it's because Sweden is a good place with good people, so those things shouldn't be true. And on all levels of politics, from local to county to state, the nationalist party has been slowly blossoming but never reaching heights that would give them any actual power. It's uncouth to claim Sweden has more problems than other countries, we didn't even elect Trump!</p>
      <p>Recently, acting chief of police Mats Löfving came out with some brazen comments. He said a lot of things, but the really spicy one was that the criminal families that plague the Swedish underground very likely has people in politics. And investigators trying to map these out found that the police force, in many of the places where these families first started taking hold and gaining power, faced cuts and reshuffles and conflicting orders. It's not a Kodak Moment, exactly, but the shadows do look a lot like aliens. That's enough for a 12-parter on Youtube, no doubt. Leave a like, comment and subscribe if you think that Sweden's government is secretly run by the Abergils!</p>
      <p>In a game of Werewolf, you always have less information than the monsters. And anyone that either claims to know too much about what would be best for all of you, or someone that tries to derail any investigation into what you should do, they are prime decorations for the gallows. The prime minister of Sweden, Stefan Löfven, has given a lot of short interviews about what has been said. And while he's not denying the words, he has been trying to steer the conversation into being about whether this is a sign of racism, assuming that these criminal families consists of mostly immigrants from out-of-Europe-countries. A sentiment that is being echoed by a lot of faces within their coalition.</p>
      <p>And suddenly, everyone is looking around the room and thinking "maybe we should hang <em>everyone</em> just to make sure there are no werewolves left?"</p>
      <p>In a country considered by its citizens to be one of the least corrupt places on Earth, where do you even start when the highest authority in your country says that it's possible, just maybe, the theories about how politicians in Sweden are willingly blind, how they not just allow but <em>want</em> it to happen, how they constantly pull in all other directions as to confound the issue... They might be true. They might be part of the actual mob. Everyone knows the form of the dance that follows: "Who can know, right", "I'm Just Asking Questions", "you gotta admit it's enticing"... The dresses are lowbrow and crass, but certainly the choreography is nice.</p>
      <p>The problem with the system, after all, is not that they tell you what to think. You're always allowed to hotly debate the conclusions, don't worry, we have moderators standing by in case anyone gets uncivil. What can't be allowed is that you decide on your own what questions to pose. And suddenly, there's a question of what parts of the Swedish image is painted by corruption that wants to be asked, but there are no gardens here for such a plant to grow. What could fuel conspiracy-adled high octane paranoia more than reflections at the bottom of the well showing an actual cabal?</p>
      <p>We all thought we were playing a round of only Villagers, but now you are saying there might be Werewolves? I'm not even sure we included a Seer.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>