<post>
  <author>The-Rotting-Word</author>
  <date>2020-09-26T18:40:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6ph243/</link>
  <title>Comparing Programmers to HR</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The programmers that get accused en masse of sexism are by and large the same, culturally, as those accusing them of sexism. Often enough they're literally the same people.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't know about that. I think that at least on one social axis, they're very different. Specifically, the things/people axis. Programmers etc., derive their importance from their direct or "physical" utility: Their ability to write code that does what it's supposed to. HR etc., derive their importance from "social" utility, what other people think about them: Their ability to get people to do what they say (but, critically, without them actually having the prestige necessary to comfortably do this).</p>
      <p>So e.g., an insult to a programmer isn't a big deal, unless it's an insult to their ability to code, which is a put up or shut up type of insult. You think I can't code? Well, I'll prove you wrong by writing this piece of code. Can't argue with that. So shove your insult up your ass. You can keep calling me a whatever all you want, it doesn't actually affect me in any way, and, bro? It honestly just makes you look pathetic.</p>
      <p>But insult an HR manager and their ability to put food on their table is under direct threat. What exactly do you do around here? Why should I listen to you? And the reason you should listen to them isn't because they know what they're talking about, but because if you don't then bad things happen to you. But if they can't get bad things to happen to you, because nobody listens to them, then their word means nothing. They can't do their job. So bad things must happen to you when you don't listen.</p>
      <p>So we get these insane interactions, where a programmer will make a joke to another programmer next to a HR manager who finds the joke unacceptable, and because it was made near them that means the person making the joke doesn't respect its unacceptability; doesn't respect the manager; doesn't listen to her; the manager's foodsource is under threat. So she must attack him to protect her position and ability to do her job.</p>
      <p>The whole concept of HR itself is just such a surreal joke. You can't get people to listen to someone who they don't respect, at least not without fear, and they're not going to respect someone who doesn't know what they're doing. So HR necessarily devolves into a nightmare of malignant people constantly abusing everyone, because that's the only way they're able to do their job.</p>
      <p>I think there's also another dynamic happening, and that's frankly that I think the HR side is a big scam that comes under threat any time a 'programmer' stumbles into the HR arena. Like with James Damore. Now, under my "it's a big scam" premise, when HR sends out questions for how to improve gender representation or whatever, what they're after is not solutions to that problem. Solving the problem would put them out of a job. What they actually want, is a bunch of handwaving bullshit that can be made to look like it's solving the problem, without actually making it any better. Maybe even making it worse, thus making themselves seem even more important. Then the programmer comes in, not realizing this (even people who were on Damore's side would call him socially retarded for failing this; the scam is so obvious to everyone). He starts trying to actually solve the problem rather than perpetuate it. Now, he has become a threat to their ability to put food on their table, and must be eliminated. Which he was.</p>
      <p>People call this "social awkwardness" or something similar. And certainly, almost by definition, people doing this almost <em>have to be</em> socially awkward: They have to be someone who doesn't realize that it's a scam, and so naively tries to actually solve the problem (either that, or they have to be so powerful as to be able to get away with it). But I don't think "social awkwardness" is <em>directly</em> the thing that gets these people in trouble, but rather that their social awkwardness naively blinds them to the scam. But of course, it will correlate strongly with attracting HR's ire, and so plausibly look like the actual problem. So, you see, the reason that Hypothetical Man was fired wasn't because he posed a threat to us, but because he did all these socially awkward things, which are obviously unacceptable in the workplace...</p>
      <p>The HR types themselves are also incredibly socially awkward. I would even go so far as to call many of them profoundly socially retarded. Go look at the shit they write on twitter. At all the sexual scandals they end up in. But they're not a threat, so it's okay. So an openly racist person can be hired by whatever outlet they want, as long as they're the right kind of racist. The social retardation or awkwardness isn't the problem.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>