<post>
  <author>TheLadyInViolet</author>
  <date>2020-09-30T23:17:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g78bz04/</link>
  <title>The Many Uses of "Non-Binary"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think that the term "non-binary" is used by a lot of different people to describe a lot of different things.</p>
      <p>For some people, it simply means being trans and/or intersex. Their choice to identify as non-binary as opposed to "trans woman" or "intersex woman" is more of a matter of perspective than anything else, an acknowledgement of the fact that they aren't fully male or fully female in a strict sense. A binary trans woman might say "Sure, I was assigned male at birth and have male genitalia, but my brain is female and my secondary sex characteristics are female and I outwardly look like a woman, so for all intents and purposes, I'm a woman." A non-binary person in a similar situation might say "Well, I have a mix of male and female characteristics, so I can't earnestly identify as a man or woman, I'm something else in-between." </p>
      <p>People with gender dysphoria may also identify as non-binary because they're confused about their feelings, or because they're reluctant to fully commit to medically and/or socially transitioning. This is particularly common among trans people who are just starting to come to terms with their gender identity, or in the early stages of hormone therapy; generally, these sorts of "non-binary" people tend to drop the label and start identifying as binary trans men or women once they're full-time and feel secure about themselves. I've also seen the label used by some gender non-conforming trans people who don't fit the stereotypes associated with the gender they transitioned to (e.g. trans women who could be described as "tomboys" and have a lot of traditionally male interests and hobbies, trans men who could be described as "dandies" and still wear flamboyant outfits and lipstick and nail polish).</p>
      <p>For other people, it means that they don't have a strong internal sense of gender one way or another. Imagine there are two nodes in the brain, a 'male' node and a 'female' node. For a man, the male node would be operating at high-capacity, and the female node would be operating at low-capacity. For a woman, it would be the other way around. This would hold true even for binary trans people: A trans woman would still have a high-capacity female node and a low-capacity male node, they just wouldn't match the rest of her body. But some people might have both nodes running at low-capacity, or both nodes running at high-capacity. As an analogy, consider a room with two lights, one red and one blue. There are only two objects there - so yes, gender <em>is</em> a binary - but the room itself might end up being red-tinted, blue-tinted, purple-tinted, or dark depending on which lights are on and which lights are off. These people usually desire to medically transition too, though not always in the same ways as binary trans people: For instance, they may be fine with having female breasts and male facial hair, and there are even surgeries to convert male or female genitals into "neutrois" genitals.</p>
      <p>And finally, there are some people who don't have any kind of dysphoria, and identify as non-binary for largely social reasons. These people really do seem to view their gender identity as more of a fashion statement than anything else: Gender non-conforming males who like to put on makeup and wear dresses and dye their hair bright colors, gender non-conforming females who like to cut their hair short and wear suits, and so forth. For these people, being non-binary is about gender roles rather than gender identity per se, they generally have little desire to medically or legally transition, and they may go back to identifying as cis males or cis females when it's convenient for them.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>