<post>
  <author>aaronb50</author>
  <date>2021-05-10T22:55:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/n8xict/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_10_2021/gxnyx3r/</link>
  <title>Part 2</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Back to Politics</p>
      <p>This isn’t just bad in and of itself—it is also rhetorical fodder for minimum wage opponents, whether cynical Chamber of Commerce types or those genuinely concerned about its effects on unemployment for the poor. By comparison, no one can say that Biden’s recent COVID relief checks are secretly bad for the people getting them, since they’re directly getting the money!</p>
      <p>Ok, so why does the minimum wage get so much attention?</p>
      <p>I don’t really know, but my best guess is a combination of intuitive appeal, state capacity, and path dependence.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Intuitive appeal</li>
      </ol>
      <p>The notion that full-time workers should not be living in poverty and therefore that employers should not be permitted to pay meager wages is intuitively compelling. As I said up top, I agree that workers should not live in poverty, but wage mandates aren’t <em>necessarily</em> the best way of going about this.</p>
      <p>The obvious, immediate cause of low wage workers’ plight is that paychecks are too small, and forcing the employer to pay better just seems like the thing to do. I could imagine a world in which this wasn’t the case and cash assistance was the intuitive, salient solution, but (in America at least) that’s not the world we live in.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>State capacity</li>
      </ol>
      <p>The minimum wage doesn’t really require the government to do anything. The weakest, most incompetent government on earth could “have” a minimum wage, even though it would struggle to enforce it.</p>
      <p>The same isn’t true for many labor organization policies, worker training programs, or direct assistance programs, which require active, deliberate action by a competent bureaucracy. This can range from having the government mail everyone an annual check to directly hiring people to clean up national parks or something.</p>
      <p>This is directly related to…</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Path dependence</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Early progressives really started advocating for a minimum wage <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_wage_in_the_United_States#History">around 1890</a>, and the first state laws were passed in the early 20th century. Did the pre-WWI, very pre-New Deal U.S. have the state capacity to undertake more active welfare policies? I don’t know. Maybe we could have done UI, but wouldn’t have been able to do Medicaid. State governments probably had less capacity than the federal government, too.</p>
      <p>Anyway, the activists weren’t stupid. If you’re going to agitate for a new policy, you better make sure that the government can physically make that policy happen. Surely, these early activists knew that ‘general law enforcement’ was something in the government’s wheelhouse of competence.</p>
      <p>Once the minimum wage became an established part of the U.S. safety net, it probably settled in as one of the questions in American politics that everyone agrees to have an opinion on. This, to some extent, crowded out other types of pro-worker/safety net programs. In other words, raising the minimum wage has become something of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Focal_point_(game_theory">Schelling point</a>#:~:text=In%20game%20theory%2C%20a%20focal,Strategy%20of%20Conflict%20(1960).) for liberals and progressives: the default, consensus policy and rallying cry.</p>
      <p>Conclusion</p>
      <p>In his recent <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/04/30/podcasts/ezra-klein-podcast-chuck-schumer-transcript.html">interview</a> with Ezra Klein, Chuck Schumer said that the Democratic Party’s most fundamental strength is that “we believe government is there to help people, help them economically…”</p>
      <p>I agree. Thing is, there are a lot of ways we could do this: free college, free healthcare, child tax credits, UBI, minimum wage, food stamps, negative income tax, jobs guarantee, the list goes on (quite literally forever, as there are an infinite number of permutations and parameters to adjust).</p>
      <p>I am not arguing that the minimum wage is bad. I am arguing that it has received an undue amount of legislative attention. In 2020, <a href="https://minimumwage.com/2020/12/80-states-and-localities-will-see-minimum-wage-hikes-in-2021/">80 states and localities raised their minimum wage</a>.</p>
      <p>On its own terms, I think this is a good thing! But progressive activists only have so much time and money, politicians only have so much political capital, and voters only have so much attention. How many UBI, UI, or negative income tax ballot measures and bills has the minimum wage crowded out? We can’t know, but I’d guess a lot. I’m happy to see <a href="https://www.yangforny.com/policies/a-basic-income-for-new-york-city">Andrew Yang’s proposal</a> for a modest UBI in New York City, but I can imagine a world in which this kind of thing wasn’t such a novelty.</p>
      <p>So here is my call to action for those on my side of the political spectrum: let’s take policy prioritization seriously. I don’t mean demanding <em>more</em> when doing so isn’t politically feasible, like calling for a national ban on firearm ownership. No, I mean making sure that we’re asking for the best policy among many <em>given a particular level of political feasibility.</em></p>
      <p>If both options are politically comparable, should we prioritize a carbon tax or negative emissions technology research? Background checks or a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bump_stock">bump stock</a> ban? Public housing or zoning deregulation (you can guess where I stand on that one)? A negative income tax, or a higher minimum wage?</p>
      <p>Political capital is a scarce resource. To make the most of what we have, we need to choose priorities wisely. And, I believe, de-emphasizing the minimum wage in favor of more effective economic welfare policies is a good place to start.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>