<post>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2021-05-07T21:03:12Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/n3pe45/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_03_2021/gxbgksh/</link>
  <title>Constructs "Designed" To Filter for Cognitive and Empathic Capacity</title>
  <category>
    <li>civilization</li>
    <li>moloch</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>If you're unintelligent, have low social skills or mental health issues, things can seem like people are conspiring to keep you down.</p>
      <p>People don't always tell the truth. Intelligent, in-the-know people and people who can read and write between the lines do communicate in ways that's designed the fly over the head of those who aren't supposed to understand it (just not through time-reversed pop songs and hidden symbols printed on money etc). I mean this on low levels already, like office politics and small-town corruption. In both "benevolent" and "sinister" ways. Maybe they think it's just hard to explain to those outside the loop and they wouldn't get it anyway. Other times it's just cold hard calculation to step over the bodies of others, to elbow your way up.</p>
      <p>People do strategize. Not everything you read is honest on its absolute surface level. <em>Deception is as old as life.</em></p>
      <p>Do you think people will no try to use every socially manipulative tool at their disposal for their literally most important affairs, such as their career, social status, love life etc? Again, it's not pure psychopathy. Sometimes it just means you have to beat around the bush, use flowery language, "politician talk", fill an email with jargon to cover that you fucked up, etc. Or write a long and confusing email reply to make people go away and not bother you. Only those don't do it who are not self-reflective enough to catch themselves.</p>
      <p>There <em>are</em> multi-step plans, perhaps literally sketched out with flowcharts and potential Plan Bs to resort to. People don't just do that when plotting to rob a bank in the movies. People do it to plan out their career, to inflate some parts of their past, while downplaying others, crafting ultimately misleading narratives about themselves etc.</p>
      <p>This is all normal for the sufficiently intelligent and socially embedded person. It happens, everyone gets tangled up in these sometimes as the "victim" too, occasionally and often without ever knowing. But at other times you try to gain a 1 up over others.</p>
      <p>There <em>are</em> layers hidden below the surface. But probably not <em>sooo</em> wild. Not everything is a lie. Non-psychopathic people generally try to do "the right thing". But through tradition and "systemic" issues, you can also carry out these things unwittingly. Like writing obscurely formulated letters as cargo culting. You don't know why, it's just something your boss or teacher taught you, but it actually saves your and your colleagues' asses in some critical cases. Sometimes trivial bureaucratic inconveniences and barriers have specific functions, in planned ways. Lobbyists want stuff, politicians give it to them. Maybe it even gets forgotten after a decade, but it still performs its function.</p>
      <p>If you can't see through these because you are unintelligent or have low abilities to see situations from other points of view and understand social nuance and strategy fused into text and actions (like autists) all this may appear as a concerted effort to target you specifically. When it's more of a distributed effort of self-interested agents to help themselves at the end of the day.</p>
      <p>I can, for example, understand how incels may think there's a conspiracy by evil women going on and the femoids want to keep oppressing low-tier men.</p>
      <p>Just as advanced tech can be indistinguishable from magic to primitive civilizations, the web of small self-serving lies or and lies-by-omission or lies-by-obscurity-and-dancing-around-the-point can seem like a conspiracy that targets you especially.</p>
      <p>If you get detached from this reality early on, are never let in to an "inner circle" or any sort, you can likely get paranoid. It will just seem mysterious. Everything is confusing, you feel that stuff doesn't quite add up, because you can't read through the layers of bullshit that other well-functioning people routinely do everyday.</p>
      <p>And people won't necessarily sit down with you to explain how such things manifest in your current organization unless they can expect similar insight from you in reverse. E.g. watercooler discussions at offices that do go through something akin to "secret handshakes", except verbally. But girls won't sit down with you and tell you what makes you odd or how you should act instead. You're just left out, not even necessarily consciously to hurt you (but sometimes yes, but it's still just an individual, not a conspiracy) they just have better things to do, and it's risky to reveal or even think about their strategy/preferences too much.</p>
      <p>If you always take everything at face value that teachers, parents, movies and news tell you, reality <em>will</em> be mysterious.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Unintelligent and low-social-skills people are routinely stepped over and screwed over using constructs "designed" (or rather evolved) to filter for cognitive and empathic capacity.</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Does this mean there's some big conspiracy? In some sense yeah, it will feel like that when you are excluded. There is scheming and below-surface subtext and strategizing. But it's not a singular entity or a top-down thing, even though that will be how it feels if you can't interpret what's up. Certainly something <em>is</em> up with Wall Street, big corporations' influence etc. But you won't be able to articulate it yourself precisely.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>