<post>
  <author>d4shing</author>
  <date>2020-06-02T04:37:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fslqbit/</link>
  <title>Black People Did Not Misplay the Great Hand of Sympathetic Victimhood</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I know I said this in last week's thread, but to reiterate:</p>
      <p>This post (and many posts in this thread) contains factual claims about what hundreds of millions of people think with zero data.  No opinion polls, not even any related statistics about protest participation/crowd size compared to other protests, nada.</p>
      <p>It is amazing to me that, in this particular subreddit -- of all places, where people are generally aware that their opinions on a broad variety of topics are unconventional -- people nonetheless express an evidence-free belief that they are part of some silent majority.  I try to be humble about assuming that many people agree with my personal beliefs, especially in the political realm, or of framing my own beliefs as necessarily widespread.</p>
      <p>As a historical matter, the "you had my sympathy at first but now you've gone too far/crossed a line!" <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2020/05/white-backlash-nothing-new/611914/">rhetoric of backlash</a> has been applied to the Civil Rights Act of 1964, the Reconstruction, the environmental movement, womens rights, gay rights, etc.  Certainly, if the sympathy of these urban whites subject to curfew amid quarantine is so easily evaporated, one has to ask how sincere it was in the first place, or what legislation or policy could have been advanced with it in the months ahead.</p>
      <p>What happened with Eric Garner?  You may recall the NYPD choked him to death on suspicion of selling cigarettes without paying taxes.  It was all caught on video.  People were generally aghast.  There were some peaceful protests but no riots.  By the logic of this post, that should have turned out well for African-Americans, right?  The manifest injustice combined with peaceful protest should have changed the hearts and minds of these fence-sitting white folks, resulting in policy victories for African-Americans. But in fact, nothing changed (although the cop lost his job five years (!) later).</p>
      <p>Here are two alternative theories:</p>
      <p>1) White people who were previously indifferent to/skeptical of racism were briefly moved by the George Floyd video are like most people who watch a PETA movie about cows in a slaughterhouse.  Initially horrified, they swear off beef for a day or two, and then go back to burgers, citing various excuses.  They got upset because it's unpleasant, and they don't like to think about it or be confronted with the background violence that makes their lives comfortable, and so they'll go back to not thinking about it in a week or two whether or not a Target is torched.</p>
      <p>2) Police escalation of violence against white non-violent protestors and white members of the media (personally, I was shocked by the Minneapolis cop shooting the CNN reporter in the eye from about 40 feet away completely unprovoked), along with spectacles like the Cincinnati PD taking down the American flag to raise their blue line flag, makes white people think "that could be my daughter!" and people to finally say "enough" and pass <a href="https://twitter.com/samswey/status/1180655701271732224">meaningful police reform</a>.  </p>
      <p>While we're at it, let's say it also drives record turnout in minority communities in the 2020 election, despite an otherwise totally uninspiring Joe Biden at the helm.  Newly elected by a landslide, he prioritizes, as a policy matter, FBI investigation into all of these wrongful deaths (the statute of limitations is <em>long</em>) and related cover-ups (destruction of evidence, the inevitable lying-to-the-FBI charges), putting dozens of disgraced police officers in federal prison.  This is actually super popular, as people detest bullies and everyone loves a good come-uppance story, and results in his cryogenically suspended corpse being reelected in 2024. Congress ends qualified immunity and requires the return of all military surplus gear from police departments to which it had been previously given.  Everyone lives happily ever after, the end.</p>
      <p>Anyways, like I said, I don't claim to know what the American public thinks. But I can't see much historical support for the idea that black people misplayed their great hand of sympathetic victimhood by burning some police cars and a Target.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>