<post>
  <author>dnkndnts</author>
  <date>2020-06-02T23:06:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsory3u/</link>
  <title>Don't be a Pavlik Morozov, You Rat</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Create a culture of ratting people out to the state - as worked well in communist countries.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>lolwut. I was going to just link the wiki to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pavlik_Morozov">Pavlik Morozov</a> and leave it at that, but after glancing over the article, it was clearly written by westerners who haven't the first clue who this person is or why he's significant.</p>
      <p>Pavlik's relevance, like Trayvon Martin's or George Floyd's, is symbolic, with the actual details of what happened being of little importance. The gist of the narrative is innocent little Pavlik became aware of his father's shady dealings and reported him to the government. His father was then sentenced to die in some frozen hellscape like every other enemy of the state at that time, and the family, upon discovering what had transpired, murdered Pavlik. To the Soviet government, this looked like perfect PR material, and so they embarked upon their media crusade. What Pavlik had done was an act of heroism - yea, of martyrdom! - worthy of being featured on every magazine cover and taught in every classroom. Every good little soviet Pioneer should aspire to emulate the moral fortitude of Pavlik Morozov.</p>
      <p>And it backfired <em>horrendously</em>.</p>
      <p>To this day, the name Pavlik Morozov in Russian is synonymous with being a traitor - like Benedict Arnold, but worse. This little ratfucker sold out his family and village because he - get this - he actually thought the government were the good guys (ахахахахаха!). As such, it is now the duty of any upstanding Russian father figure is to regale his little prestupniki with this fable, much like Aesop, with the moral of the story being if you ever pull a stunt like little Pavlik, <em>we will bury you</em> (shoe may be removed and smacked upon the tabletop for emphasis).</p>
      <p>Anyway, to the broader point, no, the Soviet ideal of tattling did not in fact work (you don't see any USSR now, do you?). All that ended up happening was all the competent people got sent off to work camps and replaced with political opportunists who realized that the way to beat a competent person wasn't to be more competent than he was, but to simply tattle on him (everyone's guilty of <em>something</em>) and get him removed so you can have his position.</p>
      <p>The failure of the USSR is remarkable in that it simply collapsed on itself - nobody even did anything to defeat it - and unlike many countries, you can't even pass off the failure on HBD reasons. Russian IQ is no lower than that of the West, so it's not that they didn't have human capital, it's that they somehow constructed a system that systematically squandered it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>