<post>
  <author>Faceh</author>
  <date>2020-06-02T18:09:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsnqrtr/</link>
  <title>Taking Difficult Steps to Resolve Underlying Conditions that Lead to Crime</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>what's the most effective way to target improving the underlying conditions that lead to greater crime rates?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This very much depends on where you think the source of the issues arises from.</p>
      <p>If you go with the premise that it is at all/mostly tied to genetics, you've got some serious issues to grapple with, especially if you want to avoid the obvious-but-likely-wrong conclusion that eugenics will need to be used if any change is to be made.</p>
      <p>If you think it is all/mostly from socially constructed bias and systemic racism, then burning down the system does seem a viable way forward.</p>
      <p>I think conservatives focus in on the general 'culture' of black Americans and critique it whilst holding up examples of successfully African-Americans who embraced their ideal of 'American' culture and went on to massive success. Work hard, don't commit crimes, and be responsible in your personal life.</p>
      <p>And personally I think there's actually a decent argument present in the <a href="https://twitter.com/yaf/status/956323171988332546">boilerplate advice</a> you get from conservatives:</p>
      <p>Don't have children before you get married.</p>
      <p>Finish high school.</p>
      <p>Get a full-time job.</p>
      <p>And if you look into the stats for African-Americans, you cannot possibly ignore the huge rates of single parents, high-school dropouts, and unemployment/partial employment among them. </p>
      <p>If you could address <em>only</em> those three issues, I suspect we would see pretty rapid improvement in outcomes for black Americans among every other metric.</p>
      <p>And one of the ironies of the <em>liberal</em> approach to this problem is that they seem to either ignore these factors <em>or</em> they imply that the system should be designed such that black Americans should be able to succeed <em>even if</em> they're undereducated, with poor familial support and dead-end jobs. </p>
      <p>But the Conservative suggestions for fixing things seems pretty pointless and tone deaf. I hear constant assertions that if black folks would just "go to church/follow the bible, stop listening to rap music,  stop dressing like a hoodlum, save money, buy a house instead of renting... Oh, and vote Republican" then stuff would get better.</p>
      <p>Which I have to imagine comes across as "toss out most of your current cultural identity and act 'white' if you want to succeed! And certainly sounds like they're asking you to just pull yourself up by your bootstraps even when everything works against you.</p>
      <p>Is there any way to offer an effective but 'limited' intervention that would put Black Americans back on a track that will lead to their general status improving towards that of the average American? I say 'limited' in the sense that it doesn't require heavy-handed government presence in their communities and lives, and will actually terminate at a predictable point rather than becoming just another welfare program or never-ending effort, a la affirmative action, to make headway.</p>
      <p>Even if it cost a trillion dollars or thereabouts, it would likely pay for itself in short order.</p>
      <p>Me, I don't have any faith in government interventions to succeed regardless of how much money is thrown at the problem.</p>
      <p>But it also seems obvious to me that drastic shifts need to happen. And the people making the shifts need to have skin in the game and very, VERY direct accountability for their actions. Which suggests, to me, a 'localist' solution wherein each individual community is treated on its own basis, rather than just assuming there exists a panacea that will immediately lead to improvements for all communities at once. If a community thinks it needs to separate itself from white people to heal, they should be allowed to. If a community wants to invite and accept white people's assistance and presence they should be allowed to.</p>
      <p>It is likely (I haven't done extensive research) that there are <em>existing</em> communities that have seen serious success that can provide good models.</p>
      <p>I can think of at least one, but some people might dislike the fact that it required a millionaire to get real generous to make it happen:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/26/us/tangelo-park-orlando-florida.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/26/us/tangelo-park-orlando-florida.html</a>
      </p>
      <p>I don't even know, unfortunately, how you would best structure things so those 'running' the project are held to strict accountability for outcomes, but I also sincerely believe that ANY agency or branch of the Federal government will never be held accountable and thus is not who we should look to.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.cato.org/publications/commentary/americas-most-costly-educational-failure">The saga of one Federal Judge's</a> attempt to force a state to fix things via massive expenditures was strong evidence of this to me.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>But there's still the question of what happened to lead to this set of conditions in the first place. </p>
      <p>I'm willing to put tons of blame on the drug war and given how little time there was between the Civil Rights Act (1964) and the Controlled Substances Act (1970) and the creation of the Drug Enforcement Agency (1973) I can see how it could have supplanted Jim Crow and segregation as the primary legal attack on black American success. I have directly observed the effects of overzealous drug laws on (mostly poor) white Americans too, though, so believe me I don't see this as a pure racial matter, more one that managed to kneecap the American underclass, which was disproportionately African American due to the <em>prior</em> legal disadvantages.</p>
      <p>I likewise attribute a HUGE portion of the police brutality issue that is causing current strife to the drug war, so over the years there's been a compounding effect as police tactics get more aggressive to get us where we are now.</p>
      <p>If accurate, then an immediate actionable step would be loosening of drug laws and trying to undo damage done where possible.</p>
      <p>But most social issues are never monocausal, and I know there were tons of other factors, both within black communities and without them in place that might have led us to a similar point even without the drug war. </p>
      <hr />
      <p>And, finally, I have to conclude that this is going to be a multi-generational effort no matter how you approach it, I simply cannot believe there is any silver bullet available and while we may see improvements over the course of a couple decades, ANYONE who is demanding that parity must be achieved immediately or else the effort is failed and should be abandoned can likely be ignored.</p>
      <p>Likewise those who insist revolution is the only way and anything short of complete upheaval will never work.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>