<post>
  <author>georgioz</author>
  <date>2020-06-02T19:04:04Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsnxsnl/</link>
  <title>To the US: Gratitude and Reassurement from Slovakia</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Actually I probably encountered his blog in eary 2010s and I have to say that it clicked with me. I am 1980s child from Slovakia. So I saw the transformation from hardcore communist regime to "wild wild west" of 1990s in Slovakia. I was a child back then - and by all means the majority of population were law abiding citizens. Nothing like looting or overall unrest. But nevertheless this was a time where in some schools you could have come to school with new sneakers during birthday -  only to return with slippers to your home. And you were lucky not to be beaten. Hard times but we held together. Now to also say, the situation in Slovakia never escalated to what we now see in other parts of the world. There was this transition from communist society - where people had to use their social contacts to get basic needs - to capitalist society. But nevertheless there were losers. </p>
      <p>The times were hard when I was young teenager in Slovakia in 1990s and I as I previously said - my father is from family of 8 and my mother is from family of 3. All basically living in the same small Town of 50,000. Now my mother was divorced with some health problems but my luck wast that we could lean into these family relations. However my older brothers had to be rough in the street (no criminal activity involved just protecting family reputation) and I had huge protection from my larger family as the by far younger brother. I know what it feels like to come to home and open the empty fridge. For me - if it was summer - meant to go and pick up some plums and cherries from municipal trees possibly wandering to "enemy territory" of other small child groups. Now for anybody who wants to pitty me - don't. As a child I learned so much about human relatonship, betrayal and true friendship to last for a lifetime. To this day to my mid-30ies I cherish these memories as an incredible life lesson. Connecting to CW angle I recently met a very bright child from family from Sri-Lanka whose grandfathers fled civil conflict. And he was full if SJW rhetoric. And then he shared some of his child memories and then I shared some my child memories - like having nothing to eat and picking wild plumbs to sate myself. And we clicked then and talked for hours of day-to-day business an how to make it better. Despite me being now this "middle class white privileged programmer" - which was enabled by sacrifice on many levels of my family that protected me for which I am forever in gratitude. </p>
      <p>Anyway stop talking about me and how Eastern European whites from Serbia or Croatia or Ukraine are not even in consideration as immigrants in SJW purview. (Heck I could not help myself). The point is that Ferfal blog connected to me on some visceral level. I cannot tell why Slovakia in 1992 or 1993 did not disintegrate despite having 15% plus unemployment rate. Here I remember my grandfather who just invested all his savings toward Slovak national treasury fund. He was robbed BTW - but it did not shatter his resolve. To his death in 2000 he was true Patriot trying to make sure of Slovakia's future. I was child at the time but I can attest that for every criminal act there were 10 acts of neighborhood help. Ranging from small loans so that your unemployed neighbor has a bread today to larger movements that wanted to move Slovakia forward (despite opposition). And make no mistake - there were people opposing this every step of the way. And now I can say that I am proud of what Slovakia accomplished in last 30 years without any bad taste in my mouth. </p>
      <p>And this is my message to USA. Stay strong. Slovakia will be forever indebted for what you did for us in 1919 and 1989. For me the City on a Hill is still shining with bright light. You will get through this and stronger than ever. As an atheist I have to say God be with you and stay safe.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>