<post>
  <author>georgioz</author>
  <date>2020-06-02T07:43:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsm4pzo/</link>
  <title>The Immense Difficulty of Full Solar/Wind Electricity</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is a topic I sometimes delve in and I think you underestimate what it takes to have fully solar/wind electricity production. I will use Germany as an example. There is a nice paper on it for Germany <a href="https://www.hanswernersinn.de/dcs/2017%20Buffering%20Volatility%20EER%2099%202017.pdf">here</a>. Some key takeways</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>On average wind produces only 16.3% of installed power capacity. But of high availability output characterized as 99.5% availability the wind can produce only 0.4% of its installed capacity. Solar obviously provides 0% due to day/night cycle. The wind/solar are very volatile energy sources.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Much more problematic than day-night peak/volatility management is seasonal management. Even with combined ideal Wind/Solar if it was 100% of energy production in Germany it would require storage capacity of almost 9,243 pumped-storage power plants, or over 264 times the current pumped-storage capacity in Germany that is currently just 35 power plants. As a sidenote - the cost of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goldisthal_Pumped_Storage_Station">Goldisthal Pumped Storage power plant</a> was EUR 600 million - and also faced massive protest by environmental organizations for devastating local ecosystems BTW. So in order to even theoretically build the storage capacity we are talking trillions of EUR for Germany. Needless to say it is impossible to build that capacity for pump-storage due to geographical reasons. And pumped-storage is now by far the cheapest storage one can build. The energy storage problem is MASSIVE GIGAPROBLEM. All the articles about Tesla batteries and whatnot are useless. We are talking many orders of magnitudes of capacity - not to even talk about economic feasibility - away to solve it. So instead what is done now is building up backup fossil fuel plants covering intermittent nature of renewable sources of energy - which defeats the purpose of carbon-free electricity and incurs costs on its own - and also some countries just "cheat" by importing electricity from other countries with more solid and stable electricity production. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The seasonal problems of wind/solar also underscores the demand management issues. Many people who are into smart grids rely on factors such as smart homes smoothing electricity consumption over small periods of hours. But the true problem is seasonal volatility of renewable energy - not day/night cycle where smartgrid-friendly freezer or AC unit will use the electricity more efficiently within one day cycle. So if anybody says that "smart grids" utilizing "blockchain" and other buzzwords will magically solve the problem of renewable energy you can immediately discount what they are saying. But if you repost it on futurology subreddit it will earn you some reddit karma for sure. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>And finally the largest issue was not even tackled. So far we were only talking about current electric energy production. But in general electricity is around 15-20% of the energy consumption. In case we want to reach truly carbon free energy it means electric transportation, heating and other usages of energy. So you may as well add another order of magnitude to the overall problem. </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>As other example for instance today France gets 75% of electricity from nuclear reactors. The rest is mostly hydroelectricity and some gas power plants to cover peak demand. In order to do that France now uses 57 nuclear rectors with total capacity of 62 GWe. So we are roughly on the level of 1% of electricity production for 1GWe for France. Now let's see how this adds up economically. There is currently a lot of controversy about costs of nuclear reactors. So let's use the worst current situation  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olkiluoto_Nuclear_Power_Plant">Olkiluoto Nuclear reactor in Finland</a>. This power plant will launch in 2021 and cost are approxiamtely EUR 8.5 billion for reactor of 1.6 GW electric. Which gives us a cost of around EUR 5 billion per 1GWe. One additional note is that the costs are balooned by two main factors: first, nuclear power plants are simply not built nowadays. So lack of know-how and competition drives the cost up. Second, there is insane amount of regultion around it. For instance in the 1980s the cost per 1GWe of nuclear power was around EUR 1 billion. But let's use this high price estimate. The economy of France is EUR 2.7 trillion a year. With investment of 1.5% of GDP over next ten years France can comfortably replace its existing stock of nuclear power plants and achieve 100% green energy. </p>
      <p>Now let's look at USA. The France generates around 560 TWh of electricity a year. So going with nuclear this means that 1GWe costing $5 billion can produce around 5.6 TWh a year. And by the way this may be wrong calculation. According to wiki the Finnish nuclear power plant will generate 8.9 TWh per 1GWe. Anyway USA generates around 4,100 TWh a year. So to cover all the needs for USA they need to add 732 GWe of nuclear power to the grid for total cost of 3.66 trillion or 18% of US GDP. Again with 1% of GDP investment a year USA could be completely green in 18 years even when I stacked economical factors against it. By all accounts these costs can be 2-5 times lower. Jeez, imagine that this happened in 2005 after Kyoto agreement. By now USA would have completely green energy. No need for smart grids, rewiring of infrastructure and all that jazz. </p>
      <p>Now one can say again that these are huge costs. But costs for supporting green energy are high as well. For instance Germany produces around 650 TWh of electricity a year - so comparable to France. In the past Germany was leading country to transform its energy generation toward alternative sources in ambitious <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Energy_transition">Energiewende</a> plan. The costs are hard to calculate but according to <a href="https://energsustainsoc.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13705-017-0141-0">this article</a> in 2017 the costs were already EUR 500 billion and if carried in full they will be above EUR 1 trillion by 2030. Again if Germany used the same effort to improve nuclear power plant building and efficiency they could have already be 100% green for fraction of the cost of this "green" endevour - and maybe companies like Siemens could have been the pioneers of safe and efficient nuclear energy to build abroad.</p>
      <p>Now of course I see the objection - nuclear power is not politically feasible. But the whole alternative energy is mired in political problems as well. For instance in Germany the wind electricity is best built on the shores of North Sea. However the industrial heartland is in the south of the country. So we are talking about thousands of miles of wires and new grids to be built. But then the theory meets reality. Local municipalities in thousands villages, towns and cities <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s13705-016-0069-9">vehemently object</a> to high voltage cables crisscrossing their idylic landscape. So what follows is costly rerouting of the power lines often forcing government to dig them into earth which massively increases costs. </p>
      <p>Anyway I long ago saw that this is lost fight. I see this as huge paradox. Eco organizations blame inept governments and sluggish political process for their inability to tackle the existential risk of Climate Change. Can they not see that now is not the time for politicking and squabbles? We need to solve climate change NOW or our kids will die. But when somebody mentions perfectly feasible nuclear solution than suddenly there is the barrage of arguments. Nuclear power is not economically feasible. And even if it is feasible then it is not safe. And even if it is safe it is not politically feasible ... Where did I hear this rhetorical tactics? Oh, yes with climate change denialists. They use the same ideological defense in depth to dissipate any attack on their entrenched ideological position: Climate change is not real. And even if it is real it was not caused by humans. And even if it was caused by humans it is not politically feasible to do anything about that. Again, the paradox would be incredibly funny if it was not all that sad.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>