<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-06-03T08:57:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsq98vc/</link>
  <title>A Conscientious Autistic Zoomer Discovers Progressivism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This should've been an answer to <a href="/u/eldy50">/u/eldy50</a><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsppwkt/">post</a>, but halfway through I realized it's about a significantly different issue, and maybe one curious enough for top level. details changed.</p>
      <p>A few years ago, I was planning to enter a PhD program in a discipline different from one I studied in university, and didn't understand well. (In retrospect this was stupid, as I was already fed up with academia). To motivate myself for accelerated reeducation and procrastinate less, I... uhhh... I created something more than a study group but less than a cult; a miniature secular ideology that'd have been derided as Petersonian rip-off if it hadn't preceded his rise to fame. While researching the ingredients of successful cults, I remembered seeing that one site about good thinking or something, oh right, lesswrong; tore through the sequences, discovered SSC and gwern and neoreaction and...  </p>
      <p>Anyway, my plan paid off (or maybe I procrastinated all summer but the bar wasn't that high): in the last 10 days before entrance exams I finally began studying the subject matter and got full marks, after which I largely abandoned the created – unfinished – community with some dozens of active users from all across ex-USSR. But it didn't fizzle out right away, and I'm still in occasional contact with a bunch of people who remember its golden days fondly (God, creating communities is so much more fun than working on PhD). One of those was, then, an adorably conscientious, somewhat autistic Ukrainian school pupil who later made it into one of the highest-ranking colleges in Great Britain. My boy!   </p>
      <p>So he's enrolled in that college, he makes some friends, but is pretty much 24/7 focused on his education, and then George Floyd dies in Minneapolis. (Note: at that moment the guy's at home, due to Covid). And his social network <em>explodes</em> with BLM stuff, protest stuff, and of course the generic fuck white people stuff, and I don't mean the background noise, people send him these memes in messengers as very biting commentary, with "amirite?" attitude, expecting the reaction he doesn't give. Because the guy looks at the propaganda, cringes and begins to – as one late Russian comedian said in such cases, «Ready? Inhale!» – he begins to <em>rationally discuss</em> the issue of disparate impact of police brutality on Black community and how it might not warrant destructive protests, with his opportunistically woke Kenyan friends and his aristocratically woke British friends and his lazily woke Pakistani friends (but mainly the former). They shoo and boo but he's ackshuallyng them, he questions everything, he credulously cites things sifted from Wikipedia, on the level of 13-50 statistics, beseeching them to «work together towards discovering the root of the problem». He's puzzled at their reaction (look no further than Twitter, which he doesn't have cus «distracting garbage», if you wonder what he gets).   </p>
      <p>This is where he reaches out to me for help in proofreading his new, Damore-esque manifesto (all extremely polite and as far as I can tell expressing his genuine belief in human equality etc. etc.). I, being dumb, irresponsibly give him <a href="https://twitter.com/ZachG932/status/1266926255082999810?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Etweet">Zach's Goldberg's</a> Twitter and <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/11/25/race-and-justice-much-more-than-you-wanted-to-know/">Scott's</a> piece and a bunch of other stuff we all know around here, but  then beg him to stop engaging and lay low, because my boy, art thou daft, these people will destroy your hard-earned future, look at Damore, look at Kashuv! He agrees that "Aaliyah" has already got one guy expelled for racism via complaints to faculty, but blithely ignores my advice because his smart and nice friends will understand him if he just makes his point clearly and correctly; he thanks me and proceeds to work on his well-referenced, hopeless investigation. Two days later he receives feedback. Some of it is, I'm astonished to learn, positive. The other... the other makes him literally <em>proclaim himself racist</em> because Black people are «incapable of rational discussion». There are some harsher words. He means Oxford-tier Black people (who wrote some indignant articulate tribalist waffle rehashing the same «systemic racism» circularity), and (seeing riots) can't not think about the implication.  I explain that no, this doesn't make him a racist, and practically nobody is capable of rational discussion, that's the whole problem, people are invested in morally loaded narratives... Well, he's done with the topic, as many of his friends are done with him. I'm not sure what will happen to this guy. I've failed him.   </p>
      <p>Hoping I've changed enough details to not make it worse, I'll now say what's curious here. There are things about an academic field, indispensable in research, that you just can't find in textbooks (this surprised me, although the importance of practical know-how is obvious); similarly, there are things you can't learn about a foreign society if you take what it says at face value. This guy took all these declarations about British tradition of analytic rationalism, and science-based policies, and debate and civility and freedom of speech at face value. But his peers learn the real culture <em>as children</em>, when they absorb the silence and blank spaces and frowns and hushed scared «we don't do that here».  They internalize it so deeply, they have inbuilt memetic defenses that stop badthink from ever making it to their consciousness.  </p>
      <p>Scott, like many others, has <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/08/gay-rites-are-civil-rites/">described Progressivism as new religion</a>. A LessWrong post on <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/aHaqgTNnFzD7NGLMx/reason-as-memetic-immune-disorder">Reason as memetic immune disorder</a> is a good decade older. The latter mused about the ways mature religious memeplexes evolve towards creating cognitive blind spots that allow the faithful to not notice the contradictions and absurdities of their belief (perhaps even to <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/CqyJzDZWvGhhFJ7dY/belief-in-belief">believe in belief</a> they do not have in any strict sense) – because otherwise religion is irreconcilable with proper human life. It even hinted at how religiously Progressive people might also be this way: <em>«We have a powerful cultural norm in America that says that all people are equal (whatever that means); originally, this powerful and ambiguous belief was counterbalanced by a set of blind spots so large that this belief did not even impel us to free slaves or let women or non-property-owners vote.»</em></p>
      <p>Today the configuration of spots has changed, but that's about it. And it's only possible to fully understand how insidious and mind-killing and <em>retarded</em> this religion is when you get a conscientious autistic zoomer from another system to live by its declared rules.  </p>
      <hr />
      <p>Here's some of our last communication. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Ilforte: Is it okay if I tell of your experience on reddit? Like, won't it doxx you if I say that one acquaintance of mine, studying in one of the highest-ranking universities in [Country], tried to reason with progressives and became redpilled?  </p>
        <p>Boy: Red pill is what?  </p>
        <p>I: LMAO  </p>
        <p>B: Explain like a normal person  </p>
        <p>I: Did you watch Matrix?  </p>
        <p>B: Nah<br />
B: Googled, got it  </p>
        <p>B: Wait, you mean redpill has negative connotation?  </p>
      </blockquote>
      <hr />
      <p>This made me tear up a little.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, if you have zoomers you care about, don't discuss racism, better get them to watch Matrix. It won't help but at least they'll know a thing or two about good movies. Though it turns out I'm very bad at this whole giving advice thing, so disregard that.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>