<post>
  <author>TheSingularThey</author>
  <date>2020-06-03T16:12:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsrd9pb/</link>
  <title>Pain, Rage, and the Lion with the Infected Tooth</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Do they <em>need</em> a "reason", in a rational sense, that can be lucidly articulated?</p>
      <p>I remember watching some TV program as a kid, about some celebrities that owned a male lion as a pet. One day, while they were in public, the lion attacked someone. They later found it out was because it had an infected tooth that was causing it enormous pain.</p>
      <p>The pain made it angry and irritated, and the anger and irritation made it lash out at something unrelated.</p>
      <p>I don't think humans are all that much more sophisticated than this. All you need for a protest is enough angry irritated people in pain and then a widely-communicated coordination signal to get them all to gather at the same time. For example, cops killing unarmed black men has become a widely recognized trigger to start protests and riots. So when you see one happening, you realize that <em>everyone else realizes</em> that now is a good time to do that. So everyone spontaneously gathers to, well, do that.</p>
      <p>But do people really need a <em>reason</em> beyond being angry? Beyond having something inside them telling them that they need to do <em>something</em> about their anger, even if they can't reason out what exactly that should be?</p>
      <p>Probably, humans being more intelligent than lions, they're not all mad about toothaches. They're mad about society, or the government, or the people around them. But they're not exactly sure what needs to be done. They just know that <em>something</em> needs to be done, and they need to let everyone know that. And they're gonna keep expressing their dissatisfaction until it goes away, so you'd better figure out a way to make that happen.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>