<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-06-03T18:23:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsru5nw/</link>
  <title>Building a Structurally, not Ideologically, Diverse University</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It goes without saying that I'm wildly interested in a project in this vein.My main thought, and one that's been on my mind a lot lately:</p>
      <p>I no longer believe a truly ideologically diverse environment within the constraints of a single institution is possible. I'm also not certain it's desirable. By this, I don't mean that the individuals involved won't have a range of distinct viewpoints, but that an identifiable group <em>zeitgeist</em> will inevitably emerge. The free speech sphere you mention (to which I'll add UnHerd)? It's diverse along many axes, but the more it grows in influence the more a certain distinct culture emerges. One thing I like about UnHerd is the way they make that explicit:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>We are not aligned with any political party, and the writers and ideas we are interested in come from both left and right traditions. But we instinctively believe that the way forward will be found through a shift of emphasis: towards community not just individualism, towards responsibilities as well as Rights, and towards meaning and virtue over shallow materialism.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think these groups are worth allying with. But I think it's important to emphasize that they're probably not fundamentally more ideologically diverse than the current paradigm, just usefully distinct from it. Every institution, every group is inevitably going to be biased. That doesn't mean distorting truth, necessarily, only focusing on a specific portion of it. Notice that, plan for it, and go in with the goal to be biased in a useful direction rather than fundamentally unbiased.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="/r/themotte">/r/themotte</a> itself serves as another example of this. There's plenty of ideological diversity here, as the survey attested, but I'd be lying if I said I didn't see myself clearly in <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/g717ft/two_views_of_survey_data_the_modal_motte_user_a/">the summarized picture</a>. To paraphrase a philosopher of our day: dread it; run from it; culture still arrives. Another community experimenting with the "open culture, free exchange of ideas" model, <a href="/r/politicalcompassmemes">/r/politicalcompassmemes</a>, provides a fascinating example: While in its early days it was predominantly "libleft" flairs with a side of "libright", it's been drifting <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/PoliticalCompassMemes/comments/guhvrd/data_is_sad/">increasingly and inexorably rightward</a>. Cthulhu swims backwards at times and seasons, it seems. This isn't bad, to be clear, and in particular the act of making one's loyalties and biases clear plays an important role in its success and continued diversity, just a reminder that a common culture <em>will</em> emerge. (Emphasizing a lesson from that: in an ideologically diverse environment, it's useful to get people to fly explicit ideological flags.)</p>
      <p>Going back to universities, I don't know that the problem is exactly phrased as ideological diversity. There's room for a broad range of perspectives, particularly if someone is careful and thoughtful, and the range is visible when diving in. Rather, the problem is that there's a single, overarching culture shared and understood across most of them. Take the structure of grade school for an example. Isn't it <em>weird</em> that virtually every single grade school in the developed world has decided to separate their students primarily by age? That's an arbitrary line. It's not a measure of truth. It's not derived from first principles as the One True Way to educate. It was just stable enough, and effective enough, that it kicked around in America, then spread to everywhere America influences (that is to say: everywhere). I was struck to enter a Taiwanese elementary school classroom and realize it looked near-identical, structurally, to an American one. But of course it did. It follows principles derived from American academia. How else is it going to look?</p>
      <p>Side note: One place Moldbug gets silly, I think, is in his claim that he wants the Antiversity to focus on pure truth, then derive principles for governing, etc. from there. Respectfully to him, that comes off as absolute nonsense. He's not in pursuit of alternative facts. He's in pursuit of an alternate narrative around the same facts, a distinct structural/value system. The idea that you could focus on pure truth where the universities are systematically deluded is an impossibility. What you <em>can</em> do is focus explicitly on a different part of the ideascape. </p>
      <p>Part of what I'm getting at, I suppose, is that I think free speech and ideological diversity might be the wrong starting ideal for the task. The goal isn't as much diversity of ideas on an individual level as diversity of cultures on an institutional level. Structural diversity, not ideological diversity. Focus on doing something different, not thinking something different. Imagine, for example, a world with more <a href="https://www.deepsprings.edu/">Deep Springs Colleges</a> around, where all students receive a full scholarship and work 20 hours per week on a cattle ranch. One of my own pipe dreams is creating a more effective teacher's college, one that among other things focuses heavily on the practice of teaching as opposed to the theoretical frameworks people have built. Teachers would spend massively increased time on deliberate, coached practice, among other differences to the current standard. </p>
      <p>...hm. I have a lot more to say, but my train of thought has derailed a bit. I'll close by summarizing some of my gut responses: Starting with focused boot camps would be a useful part of structural diversity. Explicit ideological diversity among professors should be less of a goal than finding a group of people who are willing/able to create a distinct cultural structure. A focus on excellence and a willingness to ask students to make significant lifestyle changes to join the institution strike me as useful aspects—it should be more of a shaping than a self-discovery institution, not because self-discovery is bad but because shaping is underrepresented. If the structure and culture are distinct and effective, new and interesting ideas will follow.</p>
      <p>I always have more thoughts on this, but these are the ones I have right now.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>