<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T23:29:57Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fskumsf/</link>
  <title> How Tribal Narratives Evolve Around Evidence</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Out of the many stories unfolding in the riots, a developing situation in Omaha caught my eye. It makes a useful case study of how competing tribal narratives evolve over time as bits of evidence come forward. Soon (that is to say, tonight) it will also make a useful case study of riots and mayhem.</p>
      <p>The skeleton of the situation, using early known facts:</p>
      <p>A libertarian, ex-Marine, Trump-supporting bar owner shot and killed an unarmed 22-year-old black protestor outside his bar, which had had some windows broken. <a href="https://twitter.com/Only1Kross/status/1267010037890846720">One shaky video</a> shows him backing away from a group of men before a couple of shots ring out. Before the shooting, he <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EZVfcRnWAAAVIa0?format=jpg&amp;name=900x900">remarked on Facebook</a> that he didn't expect to "have to pull a 48-hour military-style firewatch."</p>
      <p>You can already see from that how the narrative would run. And run it did, across <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/politics/comments/gub9it/black_protester_shot_to_death_outside_omaha_bar/">political subreddits</a> (<a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/BlackPeopleTwitter/comments/gu2x0p/his_name_will_continue_to_be_james_scurlock/">many more, but I'm linking only one other</a>) and <a href="https://twitter.com/dimplehazza/status/1267276723504263170">Twitter</a>. The shooter's cousin chipped in calling him a <a href="https://twitter.com/juniperfitz/status/1267126764679159811">white supremacist</a>, people noticed he'd previously made some controversial comments on <a href="https://unothegateway.com/hive-owner-sparks-discussion-transgender-restrooms/">the trans restroom issue</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/JIngalis/status/1267017419576553472">protest attendees accused him of hurling slurs immediately prior to the incident</a>, and the internet joined together to condemn him. For a moment, news spread that the shooter was released immediately without charges, but that rumor died quickly.</p>
      <p>The other narrative was much quieter at this point online, but was essentially "He has a right to defend his property."</p>
      <p>And then—stop me if you've heard this one already—things got a bit more complex. While he wasn't released without charges immediately, an announcement of his release (yes, without charges) came through today. The county attorney <a href="https://www.ketv.com/article/officials-announce-no-charges-to-be-filed-at-this-time-in-the-death-of-22-year-old-james-scurlock/32733160">explained the reasoning</a>, and provided new footage alongside it.</p>
      <p>Here's the summary, with the new info:</p>
      <p>The shooter, Jake Gardner, was near the entrance of the bar with his father. He had a concealed gun and an expired concealed carry permit. His father initiated a confrontation with a group outside the bar, shoving one and telling them to leave. One of the group shoved him back. At that point, Gardner entered the confrontation—not hitting anyone, but walking forward to talk/argue with them. No slurs recorded or reported by witnesses. After the deceased (Spurlock) shoved another man away, the group attention turned towards Gardner, and three or four men started approaching him. He backed away slowly, exposing his gun. They continued after him; he continued to back away. A few seconds later, one of them tackled him to the ground. He fired a shot into the air, and the tackler left. Spurlock tackled him from behind. After saying, "Get off me, get off me, get off me," Gardner fired at Spurlock's clavicle, killing him. </p>
      <p>So what happened to the narratives?</p>
      <p>The property defense narrative shifted to a much more convincing self-defense one, and a lot more people flipped over to it (including a good number of less-political people, who had previously been focused more on the main narrative). To my eye, it's the obvious viewing of the footage. Then again, as an &lt;IDENTITY&gt;, I would think that. People stopped talking about property damage and started pointing out that he was on the ground with a man pinning him down. I'm not too interested in defending that narrative in detail. Even seeing it as self-defense, it's a bitter, tragic event for all involved. One man is dead. Another's reputation and business is ruined, probably for good. There's nothing to feel happy or vindicated about here—it's just dark. Instead, I want to examine how the other narrative shifted—that is to say, the reason Omaha will probably burn tonight.</p>
      <p>Aside from the previous details that hadn't been deconfirmed (Trump supporter, libertarian, ex-Marine, prior controversy, in a protest/riot zone with a gun and ready for a fight), the new footage and information contained a few tidbits that could be folded into the narrative. Per current footage, Gardner's father initiated the active physical confrontation. His concealed carry permit was expired. He fired gunshots before Spurlock tackled him. With the new information, the narrative has become, more or less, this:</p>
      <p>A transphobic, white supremacist Trump supporter with prior gun-related criminal charges (illegal carry and such—can't find articles atm) brought a gun to a non-violent protest, itching for a fight and carrying illegally. His side (his father) started trouble with a group of nonviolent protesters nearby, at which point he jumped into the fray, possibly throwing out racial slurs. He escalated the situation by showing a gun and firing a shot, at which point a young hero jumped in aiming to neutralize the active shooter and died for his troubles. The police department colluded with the state to let him go free without even letting a neutral grand jury decide whether there should be a trial. His parents want a fair trial and justice for their son. If the races were reversed, he would have been tried and found guilty in a heartbeat.</p>
      <p>It's hard to say how much this narrative will take hold among the general public. Again, to my eyes, the footage displays <em>really clear</em> self-defense, and browsing related comments sections <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/news/comments/guq79d/no_charges_in_scurlock_death/">that idea seems to be catching on among leftish but not-as-committed-partisan groups</a>. But the context of the situation is as perfectly partisan and toxoplasma-laden as it gets. A young black man is dead. A stereotypical Trump supporter killed him. The killer has now been released with no charges. All this in the middle of a series of race-related protests and riots nationwide.  </p>
      <p>In that tinderbox, even full, clear video footage is far from enough to set the narrative. That's what I find fascinating here, more than anything. When there isn't video of events, we talk a lot about how valuable it would be to see what actually happened, how that would clear questions up and bring the truth to light. Sometimes, that's true. Times like this? The video is just one more match on the pile, one more Rorschach test in which everyone can see their own desired image reflected. Even when you hand all the facts to everyone, even when you pin the events down and get widespread agreement on the specific events, the divergent narratives persist.</p>
      <p>As for the results? Well, check tomorrow to see if Omaha's still standing. It's likely to be an ugly night.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>