<post>
  <author>baj2235</author>
  <date>2020-10-14T01:15:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8r4l69/</link>
  <title>On Shepherding Communities: Thoughts and Criticism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <h1>(1/2)</h1>
      <p>I debated or not whether to post this (as I do with most things - hence my general lack of public activity), but for once I'll just go ahead and say it.</p>
      <p>I should have said this when you first mentioned it in the modmail, but I think you are making an enormous mistake. I think you are not just hurting this place, but have already failed at what you desire to accomplish before you have even begun. This not is because of any failing on your part, or even because you have allied with one of the top 3 worst<sup>1</sup> posters I have ever had to deal with as a moderator. </p>
      <p>You have failed what you seek to achieve cannot be achieved by "splitting a community" or "starting a forum from scratch." To rephrase for sake of clarity, no one who seeks to start an online community with some intention in mind is capable of bringing about that vision. Communities are built, develop, and grow organically . Communities are not "designed." To rephrase again, I am postulating that no one has ever achieved what you are trying to achieve by deliberately trying to do so, you will not achieve what you are trying to achieve by doing this, but don't feel bad because as long as humans can credibly be described as "human" the number of people setting out to create a space such as the one you are trying to create will equal exactly zero.</p>
      <p>This is the second community I have been in charge of shepherding in my life,<sup>2</sup> and despite being as different as I can imagine they are the same in many, many ways. The dirty secret that was true for absolutely both of them Absolutely no one has any clue why the successful ones turn out successful or adopt the characteristics that they do. Take this place: the subreddit was started because someone liked a then obscure blog. On this obscure blog, an extraordinarily talented  writer put out interesting content at a surprising rate, which was then discussed on the subreddit. Similar content related to topics the blogger discussed got posted there as well. The Culture War Thread was created because the said blogger, for a host of reasons, didn't mind people posting about Culture War Content but preferred the Front Page of the subreddit bearing his brand to not have so much Culture War content. However this thread was not "The Thread" that is aroused in your mind by saying its name, either how it was known in <a href="/r/SSC">/r/SSC</a> or <a href="/r/TheMotte">/r/TheMotte</a>. It was populated by many of the same people you believe to be great users, but it was explicitly not "The Thread" in any meaningful sense. For months, activity was low effort and uneventful, and to be honest it was mostly boring. My first comment was on the third CW thread on a post from <a href="http://maddox.xmission.com/">Maddox</a> of all people.  This, despite its ruleset being the famous VSBL light, which our and to extent your ruleset is based off of and despite the norms you wish to instill in your new community already being practiced. What kicked it off? Having a year or more ago combed through them all: setting sort order to new. Seriously, if I could point one definitive moment it is the decision to switch to "suggested sort new". Then the 2016 election happened and activity rose. Then people started hammering out long though out blog post quality essays, <em>after which</em> the AAQC Reports were started<sup>3.</sup> Then <a href="/u/gemmaem">/u/gemmaem</a> wrote our welcome message which we still use. Then the pressure got to Scott, and the moderators who thought the Culture War Thread was worth continuing created this subreddit. Then ZorbaTHut (with feedback from the then moderators) expanded the VSBL to the rule set we have today both the meet challenges both practical and of ideals. Through all of this? We have had literally hundreds of users that have repeatedly posted high effort content come and go, most without a single word. So many that I made a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/thethread/wiki/index">wiki</a> so I could keep track. The early ones aren't the more recent ones, and the ones now will not be the future ones.</p>
      <p>What is the point of all this? A mix of criticism (since I am really unhappy with you doing this) of you and advice (because I do respect you).</p>
      <p>1) None of the things that made this community, or any community, a success could be predicted. No one can with any, certainty (myself included), give you a complete list of the factors, tell you their relative contributions, or provide you any thing beyond basic correlates they noticed. This includes the role lofty goals like our sidebar, key features like the AAQC, or even banal things that appear to have outsized influence like setting the thread sort order to "new". This was true for this community, this was true to the previous one I helped run. I talked to 80 year men in the other one I ran that found the things that stuck around surprised them, as did the things that fell to the wayside.</p>
      <p>2) Whatever you intentions, your success or failure is beyond your hands. Reddit is filled with hundreds of empty subreddits with interesting premises. In the case of your goal, both <a href="/r/leftrationism">/r/leftrationism</a> and DataSecretslox.com are already spaces attempting to do exactly  what you are trying to do, split from the very same subculture you are proposing splitting from. One is a ghost town, the other reasonably active but only time will determine its success (the current activity of its 570 members will only dwindle without some method of attracting new users). No one can tell you why one failed, or whether one will continue to succeed, or why this one has been a "success". No one can tell you why the other organization I ran had lasted 7 decades, while a half dozen that are superficially the same didn't. People can make mouth noises, some of which may actually correspond to some bit of reality. You will not be able to differentiate them.</p>
      <p>3) "Success" will not look like what you think "success" is. This forum isn't perfect, but I am happy with it. This, despite looking nothing like <a href="/r/slatestarcodex">/r/slatestarcodex</a> was when I joined (at the time having with 800ish subscribers). It is significantly different from the Thread nearly 3 years ago when I became a moderator of <a href="/r/slatestarcodex">/r/slatestarcodex</a>. It will be different still next year. The norms you want to instill will run into issues of practicality and enforceability (what is a quality conversation?), differences of interpretation (what I say is quality is not what you think is crap), as well as people who are valuable but otherwise don't like the ideals behind the rules or how they are enforced. Even if you maintain a self-sustaining user base of any size, you will look back years from now wondering how you got there. Something isn't working and you will change it. Something will never work. Something will only work because of the small number of users that make up your founding population, and will strain and break IF you manage to grow. This IS a <strong>certainty</strong>, again not because of any failing on your part: <em>there has never been nor ever will be an organization formed where this hasn't happened .</em> This is doubly true for one built on discussion of contentious topics where people disagree. Your problems may not be the exact problems we have here, but only because the set of possible problems a forum (or really any organization) can run into and their relative severity is so complex that it cannot be described.</p>
      <p>4) No one actually goes to online forums for the moderation, the norms, or the rulesets. Period. They go there because there is content that they like. Moderation, good norms, or specific rules can drive people <em>away</em>. Lack of moderation, lack of a set of good norms, or a lack of good rules can also drive people away. But they are in no way something that could be described as a motivating factor of growth, despite all the ink spilled about them. If you actually want you forum to succeed it will need content (regularly posted and of sufficient quality, whatever that means). Everything else comes second, and should be either thought of as a luxury brought about by the existence of said content or put in place to encourage its creation. As of now, exactly zero people are in that habit. The only thing you can hope to do to encourage it is is create that content, see Scott Alexander. People who like the content you post will stay there, and hopefully share both your norms and post content of their own (practicing you norms). This may not be enough either way.</p>
      <p>5) You, as a moderator, are going to escape exactly zero of the problems you face as a moderator here. The average user may not be aware of it because you ban people faster or remove posts, but this is the internet. People are going wander in from everywhere. <strong>If nothing else, I encourage you to internalize just this bullet point.</strong></p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>