<post>
  <author>gattsuru</author>
  <date>2020-10-13T15:00:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8p4q4i/</link>
  <title>A Sharp Critique of Theschism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'll be blunt: this is an <em>awful</em> look.</p>
      <p>Your thoughtful left-leaning cofounder is not just a sneerclubber, but a particularly bad one who was repeatedly banned and eventually permabanned from SSC; you yourself note here that they spent a long campaign trolling the SSC subreddit, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/CultureWarRoundup/comments/e85i0r/offtopic_and_loweffort_cw_thread_for_the_week_of/fal1xdv/">by your own analysis</a> they went into other subreddits to troll them, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/CultureWarRoundup/comments/e4xddj/on_my_islamophobia/f9l6025/">poorly</a>.  I have no reason to suspect that their definition of bigotry is anywhere near <em>useful</em> rather than just a weapon to apply against <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/SneerClub/comments/achgor/rssc_user_posts_a_meme_gets_downvoted_and_banned/">"nazi nerds"</a>.  They've complained about one of your own <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/SneerClub/comments/ii2wuv/is_there_any_community_that_actually_is_what_the/g34kofx/">fellow moderators</a>, recently.</p>
      <p>Your example of overt hostility to your core values quickly swung into a call for your political enemies to retreat from the <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ifiyso/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_24_2020/g35sipn/">public streets when challenged</a>.  A position that has been openly endorsed by <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/c7ojkk/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_01_2019/esra48n/?context=3">modhatted</a> posters here.</p>
      <p>Your long concerns about the downvote brigade (which, to be fair, I'm not a huge fan of) and a right-leaning atmosphere are justified not by your own low-scored posts or a top-level post where you faced unreasonable criticism.  You're on the higher end in terms of AAQCs, upvotes, and even your left-most posts don't actually show this avalanche of resistance.  Nor in <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8n85ex/">our conversation yesterday</a> did you point to good heavily downvoted posts by left- or liberal-leaning people.  That might well exist, but instead we're circled around absolute garbage from posters like Darwin2500 or TheAncientGeek -- and, notably, these two posters <em>don't</em> receive such pushback even when making very Leftish posts when they bother engaging instead of preregistering strawmen of future conduct, submitting undisprovable hypotheticals while outright admitting no effort applied toward the facts, or accusing their enemies of inevitably turning to murder.</p>
      <p>...</p>
      <p>Which, fine.  I'd rather SneerClubbers have their space (though, uh, notably 89518's not the only one to go trolling).  I hope you have fun.</p>
      <p>But I'm hard-pressed to evaluate your judgement today as well as I would yesterday morning.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>