<post>
  <author>gattsuru</author>
  <date>2020-10-13T16:03:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8pbyhi/</link>
  <title>The Taxonomy of the Rationalsphere</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Yudkowsky and LessWrong were the origin point for the Rationalist Sphere (as separate from the philosophical tradition), starting in 2009 or so.  There were a few precursors, with Yudkowsky and Hanson writing on <em>Overcoming Bias</em> in '06, but '09 had <em>The Sword Of Good</em> and <em>Three Worlds Collide</em>, and the start of the main <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Sequences">Sequences</a>.  There's a lot of ties to epistemology, overcoming limitations to understanding, and truth-seeking, along with approaches to ethics like Effective Altruism, and (while not much recognizing in the Culture War World) a lot of the emphasis on AI goal consistency and meta-ethics came about; these date back to the Sequence era.  </p>
      <p>(Also weird stuff; we have a decent number of polyamorist BDSMers, and that got a lot of attention because it was an easy way to draw Yudkowsky as a cult leader, but we also have furries and bronies and lifestylers.  And, while not the same thing, a lot of trans women).</p>
      <p>The exact endpoint depends on who you ask, but Yudkowsky started spending more time on abstract quantum physics stuff, Harry Potter fanfic (yes, really), and Facebook around 2010, and while a few posters (Gwern, Yvain-who-became-Scott-Alexander, LukeProg, for example) tried to make up for it, I'd say 2012 or 2014 LessWrong's community had faded pretty badly and by 2016 it had turned into a bit of a ghost town.  Most people went to <a href="https://rationalist-masterlist.tumblr.com/post/130139930539/rationalist-masterlist">tumblr</a> or facebook, along with meatspace meetings and a small twitter presence.  Each of these ended up with a different focus.</p>
      <p>Scott Alexander wrote on LessWrong as Yvain and LiveJournal as squid###, but in 2013 he began the Slate Star Codex blog.  While he started out and eventually <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/07/03/to-the-great-city/">returned</a> to the Bay Area of California (which means roommates, most of which were tumblr-rationalists), for much of the 2013-2017 time period he was in Michigan.  This wasn't necessarily less Hard Rationalist, and more just moving away from the limitations of the LessWrong (and LiveJournal) format.  But it described politics-adjacent stuff, and got linked from a number of high-profile right-libertarians, culminating in an Instapundit link to <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/09/03/the-guardian-vs-induction/">a late 2014 post</a>.</p>
      <p>Slate Star Codex-the-blog originally had Open Threads beginning in the <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/06/04/open-thread/">middle of 2014</a>, and Link Threads sometimes acted on the same topic.  But the blog's comment software was (and remains) awful for threaded conversation, only going a couple layers deep.  So in 2014, Bakkot created a subreddit, and by the middle of 2015, some conversation moved toward it.</p>
      <p>Reddit's method of sorting posts had some awkward parts, though, and as a result, it wasn't uncommon for political stuff to end up frontpaged much longer than non-political stuff, even if the latter was better.  So in 2016, SSC-the-subreddit moved anything "related to the Culture War" into a single stickied thread.</p>
      <p>Which worked for a bit, but as a result of that Instalauche and some other factors, SSC-the-subreddit was right-leaning compared to the general internet.  Not compared to the general population, but enough that people <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/02/22/rip-culture-war-thread/">targeted Scott with enough harassment to cause a nervous breakdown</a> in 2019.  To reduce that, SSC-the-subreddit kicked out the culture war thread, and both SSC-the-subreddit and SSC-the-blog and prohibited any conversation on it (which minor exceptions for when Scott was posting the matter himself).</p>
      <p>SneerClub was technically a response to Yudkowsky (in fact, named <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/HPMOR/comments/2n3yh5/what_is_it_with_dark_lord_potter_and_hpmor/cmad6x3/?context=3">from a quote</a> in one of his rare 2016 posts outside of Facebook), but largely evolved into a generic Bash Anything LessWrongish group.  (Not the only one; a lot of the Tumblr Ratsphere are at least better anti-LessWrong posters, though while some are terrible like su3su2u1.)  With Slatestarcodex as one of the more active internet-visible portions, they tended to turn to it and its progeny, sometimes turning to direct trolling.</p>
      <p>CultureWarRoundup was formed by PM_ME_UR_OBSIDIAN in 2017, but is largely Zontargs' baby at this point.  Mostly intended as a response to what they perceived as overactive moderation, but since one of the moderation points was the attempt to ban anything related to human bio-diversity (charitably: Charles Murray advocates; uncharitably: psuedoscientific racists) in the SSC-subreddit, founder effect.</p>
      <p>There's also a LeftRationalism subreddit and a slatestarcodex_cw subreddit, though neither are terribly large.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>