<post>
  <author>jacobin93</author>
  <date>2020-10-13T18:17:03Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8ps09q/</link>
  <title>Hate AAA Games-As-A-Service? Follow Indie Gaming Instead</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Every time I see one of these complaints about AAA games-as-a-service and how much better things used to be in the old days, I always wonder- have you not been paying attention to the indie gaming sphere? I prefer the state of modern gaming compared to the 90s just for indie games.</p>
      <p>For one thing, there's <em>a lot</em> of them now, with a bewildering diversity of genre and implementation. The kinds of games that would have maybe one release every two years, like Bioware-style RPGs or metroidvanias or space-fighter sims, often have multiple titles a year. And they aren't usually identical, but vary wildly. Look at just metroidvanias - want insect-themed Victorian steampunk? <a href="https://www.gog.com/game/hollow_knight">Done.</a> Craving BDSM Catholicism instead? <a href="https://www.gog.com/game/blasphemous">Done.</a> How about Mexican Wrestling themed? <a href="https://www.gog.com/game/guacamelee_gold_edition">Done!</a> This massive amount of choice wasn't available 20 years ago. (Plus, you can still play a lot of the games that came out back then!)</p>
      <p>And while AAA games are pretty creatively sterile and derivative, there are some wonderfully imaginative and downright <em>weird</em> games that have come out this decade. Like one where you play as <a href="https://www.gog.com/game/heavens_vault">an archaeologist deciphering a forgotten language.</a> Or <a href="https://www.gog.com/game/pathologic_2">a surgeon in a Russian steppe using mysticism to cure a plague.</a> Or <a href="https://www.gog.com/game/transistor">the quasi-turn-based game where you use a talking sword to fight the Illuminati in a computer simulation.</a> If you're bored by the sameness of the big games, take a gander at the small ones. You never know what you might find. </p>
      <p>(If you just a <a href="https://www.gog.com/game/dusk">first-person shooter</a> or a <a href="https://www.gog.com/game/into_the_breach">decent puzzle game</a>, there's that too.)</p>
      <p>And many of these games (including every single one I linked to) are available on gog.com, DRM-free! No "games as a service" - you buy it, you own it. </p>
      <p>So, yeah, the big releases by the big companies are kinda shit and the practices they want to normalize are questionably moral. But I don't understand pining for the good old days and condemning the games industry as a whole when there's still a bunch of stuff going on unrelated to the mainstream AAA sphere.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>