<post>
  <author>NUMBERS2357</author>
  <date>2020-10-14T14:17:09Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8sq8uq/</link>
  <title>Critically Analyzing the Electoral College </title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I agree with the overall thrust of your skinny/fat example, but I don't agree that this is what the Constitution was meant to do, in the context of the Electoral College (which seems to be what you're focusing on), and I think the extent to which it is doing this now is overrated.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>First, when people talk about what effect the Electoral College has, they usually take the system as it works now</strong>, which has the following elements none of which are in the actual Constitution:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>states allocate their electors by a popular vote</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>states allocate their electors in a winner-take-all manner</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>electors, by law, by unwritten rule, or otherwise by design, vote for the candidate to whom they're pledged</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>there is a significant advantage of voting strength for small states compared to a national popular vote</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <strong>Second, when people talk about the effects of the Electoral College they implicitly compare it to the popular vote.  It wasn't the case that the founders were all thinking this.</strong>  A popular vote was one thing considered, but it wasn't the obvious choice to them as it is to us.  When the founders were thinking about the Electoral College, they were focused on:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>the electors themselves exercising discretion and acting as a mediating influence</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>the fact that electoral vote allocation was dependent on the number of people in a state (slaves only at a 3/5ths rate), not the number of voters.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>not the protection of small states.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>extremely definitely not protection of the interests of rural areas. This is a perfect example of people taking what they think is happening now and projecting it back onto the founders.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <strong>Third, the vaunted small state boost of the electoral college is overrated.</strong>  The winner-take-all nature of the electoral college (in 48 states, and partially in the other 2) is a larger effect.  In particular, in 2016:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>had electoral votes been apportioned among the states strictly in proportion to population, trump still would have won</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>had all states allocated their electoral votes proportionally, Clinton would have won.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>It's true that the voters of Wyoming get a massive boost with the electoral college, but they're so few in number that it barely matters.  And even so, there are small states on both sides so the effect isn't that big.  Among 3-vote states, in 2016 Republicans won 5, and Democrats won 3.  Among 4-vote states, it's 4-1 for the Democrats.</p>
      <p>If you want, go compare California's percent of the national popular vote vs California's percent of the electoral votes in 2016.  It's not the bulwark against domination by California that people claim.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Fourth, the real impact is the winner-take-all thing, and it doesn't help small states or rural states.  It helps swing states</strong>; and the swing states change over time and mostly introduce an element of randomness and unpredictability.  People seem to think the system will benefit Republicans forever but you can easily sketch out a future where the opposite happens - all you have to do is project future trends forward like 10 years.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Fifth, the Electoral College isn't a bulwark against NY and LA dominating the election</strong> (or "the cities" or "the coasts" or whatever):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>those places don't have the numbers to win a national popular vote.  Unless you expand the set of places you're talking about to the point that they would carry the electoral college anyway.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>if those places did have the numbers to win the national popular vote, that would probably affect the apportionment of the electoral college such that they'd win that too.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>the winner-take-all system doesn't let a city dominate the nationwide vote, but it does let cities dominate a statewide vote.  Like, Democrats' whole strategy in Pennsylvania is to run up the score in Philadelphia and Pittsburgh.  In Illinois, it's Cook county.  In Colorado it's Denver and Boulder.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>If enough states happen to have cities big enough that this strategy works, then the electoral college will amplify, not hurt, the urban based party.  This is in fact what's happening as the country gets more polarized along urban-rural lines.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>