<post>
  <author>RIP_Finnegan</author>
  <date>2020-10-14T18:37:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8tl16d/</link>
  <title>You Can't Drain the Swamp, but You Can Breed a Bigger, Badder Swamp Creature</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Perspective from a cynical beltway asshole: citizens massively underrate the sheer size of the apparatus you need to make effective policy in the modern era. As the government grows, the size of the policy apparatus you need to create an implementable agenda - think tanks, lobbyists, friendly journalists, lawyers (oh god so many fucking lawyers) - grows in tandem. The Democrats massively outclass the Republicans in this, not just because of progressive control of universities but also because of money. Except on issues where there are Republican megadonors or orgs like NRA (so, usually establishment agendas Trump's base doesn't care much about), the kind of grant money etc. you get from a liberal org is often more than an order of magnitude higher than a conservative one. </p>
      <p>Partly, this is Tea Party Republicans shooting themselves in the foot. The government will literally pay you to hire Congressional staff! But no, Tom Hardass (R-IA) wants to run ads showing how little government money his office is spending, and doesn't realize that means when Republicans get back into power he has no idea how to contribute to writing an Obamacare replacement.</p>
      <p>Note that this is all about getting things done. Most of these things which get done will be bad and in many respects worse than doing nothing at all, because of special interest influences. Obamacare was a spaghetti soup of a law, but it <em>got done</em> and Rs have no replacement plan beyond Trump pledging to protect pre-existing conditions. OK, how? At what stage in the healthcare process? Who pays? Someone needs to be paid to figure out what is a legal, politically acceptable way to do this, and how to get that solution into the corridors of power. And right now on many issues - including the most important ones like healthcare, infrastructure, tech, education - Rs are really bad at that.</p>
      <p>This is particularly bad for Trump because there is no Trumpist policy apparatus. It's just a couple of super-smart, independently minded dudes like Steven Miller, a lot of disorganized grifters like Steve Bannon, and a few in between like Rex Tillerson. If there was a Trumpist policy infrastructure, we'd have seen a lot more stuff like <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/01/18/watch-new-health-picks/">Balaji at the FDA</a> potentially kicking the shit out of corona in February, but there wasn't and there won't be for years (Robert Mercer give me money please). Note how effective Trump has been where he aligned with existing policy infrastructure like the Federalist Society on judges, and that he's been pretty effective on areas like trade where there was a nascent Trumpist policy infrastructure (Wilbur Ross is Thiel's guy - sworn in instantly and has worked quietly ever since. Robert Lighthizer, too, hugely experienced in the swamp).</p>
      <p>tl;dr you can't drain the Swamp. The Swamp <em>always</em> wins. The only thing you can do is breed yourself a bigger, badder swamp kraken than your opponent.</p>
      <p>EDIT: I suppose there is one possible policy solution which DC will never, ever want to implement. Nationalize think tanks. Not literally, but give members of Congress such colossal funds for research staff, legal support, etc. that the money a place like Brookings pays is chump change in comparison, then force Congressmen to spend 100% of it on legitimate staff. This would be a grain of sand in the Federal budget compared to the costs of bad policy which could be averted. Hell, pay for it by ending 501c status for "charitable foundations" that lobby the government. Unless some rationalist billionaire is reading this and wants to lobby for it, though, it's unfeasible - public pressure would need to force Congress to push this through. Instead, as the Federal government's body gets more bloated every year, the brain controlling that body atrophies. Draw your own metaphor to the rest of the country.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>