<post>
  <author>SaxifragetheGreen</author>
  <date>2020-10-14T18:07:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8thi71/</link>
  <title>A Schism, A Deathblow, A Coup</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Your actions speak so loud I cannot hear what you say.</p>
      <p>I was going to write a longer post, but every time I get to something, I end up here:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I'll stop mincing words: I've created a schism</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Yes, you did. You have created a scishm, because you wanted to, and in so doing you have irreparably harmed this space. That's what a schism is, after all, a break, a rupture. You've ruptured this subreddit and tried to cleave off half for yourself. What's worst is your insistence that you want to see both places succeed. Once again, your actions reveal your words as a lie. You <em>say</em> you want this place to succeed ("I'm excited for people to build both <a href="/r/theschism">/r/theschism</a> and <a href="/r/themotte">/r/themotte</a> towards their ideal forms"), but your <em>actions</em> show that you think the appropriate final form for <a href="/r/themotte">/r/themotte</a> is dead and in the ground. If you really want <a href="/r/themotte">/r/themotte</a> to succeed, you'd be acting like it, instead of deciding it's too far gone and jumping ship.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="/u/mcjunker">/u/mcjunker</a> spotted it right away, correctly calling what you did a deathblow to this subreddit. You can say whatever you want about your intentions, but the results will speak for themselves, and others are not so willing as you to hem and haw and hedge their bets. They call it as it is: you've launched a coup against this sub, trying to wrest the resources away from it and towards your own personal fiefdom. It seems you've bee somewhat successful so far, but what you're succeeding at isn't your stated goal, it's your implicit goal, revealed by your actions.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>