<post>
  <author>vogue_epiphany</author>
  <date>2020-10-13T23:48:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j8trco/the_bailey_podcast_e016_the_banality_of_catgirls/g8qv9g4/</link>
  <title>On Effective And Ineffective Precommitment</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The problem I always have with "commitment devices" is that you can always just lie your way out of it.  Like, I can say "I'm going to donate $500 to a cause I hate if I make the mistake of engaging in [unhealthy activity] this week," and I can even give that money to a friend, but I can always lie and say, "Oh yeah, I spent this entire week stone-cold sober! No need to donate that $500 to a cause that I hate!"</p>
      <p>In a way, doing a "fast" is just another form of pre-commitment that can also be easily violated: I can tell myself "I'm not going to surf the internet at all this week," but how do you actually enforce that on yourself if you're an addict?  I think the 'precommitment' strategy tends to work best if it's paired with something that actually increases the friction of accessing the superstimulus, so that way you can't engage in that activity impulsively.  For example, if you're trying to fast from World of Warcraft, uninstall the game.  This doesn't prevent you from reinstalling it, but at least it means the game is a 40-minute download away, rather than a click away, which means you won't find yourself looking at the game menu after just a moment of poor impulse control.  Or, if you're trying to quit it entirely, you can delete (or sell) your account.</p>
      <p>Really though, I think the problem that a lot of the strategies like "fasting" and commitment devices have is that they're all centered on abstention.  In a lot of cases, people turn to addictive behaviors or habits to fill a hole in their life, and if you just remove that addiction, you're still left with a hole.  You have to find some other way to fill it.  Some remarks from JBP that feel apropos (and are forever etched into my my mind thanks to a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VJ3v2oGm6Sk">catchy song</a>):</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>If you're trying to stop drinking, you need something better than alcohol. And alcohol is pretty good, so you'd better find something a lot better! Esteemable people do esteemable things, so you want to find something that you're doing with your life that's worth not getting drunk and screwing up. You might say, "Why do people drink too much?" If you like alcohol, that's a stupid question. "Why do people drink too much?" Well, 'cause it's great! So why stop? Well, you do stupid things when you're drunk, you hurt yourself, you compromise your health, it's really hard on the people around you, you tend to turn into a liar, and it screws up your life. But yeah, it's pretty fun! It is! You need something better than that. And what's better isn't "being straight" and "not making mistakes." That's all prohibition in some sense. So what's better is, you need an adventure. You need to get out there and have something to do. Something worth waking up for. That's the substitute for the addiction.  Actually, the addiction is the substitute for that, if truth be known.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think the "fasts" that work best are the ones that <em>replace</em> the addictive activity.  For example, instead of just having an "internet-free weekend," you can go on a trip or do some weekend-long activity without your cell phone.  Spend time doing activities you enjoy that <em>aren't</em> browsing the internet, instead of just sitting in your apartment several feet away from your desk, thinking to yourself "thou shalt not walk over to the computer and start browsing Reddit."</p>
      <p>Saying "I will donate $500 to [non-profit I hate] if I start surfing the internet" is a really negative framing: it's all stick, and no carrot. I do think there's real value in giving yourself a yourself a carrot, which actually helps to better frame the "addiction" as somehow subtracting from the parts of your life that you really like.  </p>
      <p>For example, the impulse to check the internet multiple times per day is significantly reduced if I'm in the middle of reading a good novel.  (And the great thing about print books is that they can physically occupy the space that you're spending time in, so that every time I sit down at my desk, there it is, right in my field of view.  Grabbing the book and picking right where I left off would actually require <em>less</em> effort than reaching into my pocket and opening the app for Reddit/Twitter/FB/whatever.)</p>
      <p>Likewise, I have multiple friends who kicked their addiction to spending money on gacha games by becoming really committed to the idea of "FI/RE" ("financial independence/retiring early," see <a href="/r/financialindependence">/r/financialindependence</a>, <a href="/r/leanfire">/r/leanfire</a>).  If your gacha purchase is framed as, "It isn't wise to spend $100 on a virtual slot machine," that just feels like a vague prohibition.  "Be smarter with your money" isn't directly actionable advice.  But if you frame it as, "<em>not</em> spending $100 on the gacha slot machine today means that you'll get to get to retire one day earlier, that's one less day of your life spent sitting at a desk and working for a boss, think of all of the things you could do with an extra day off," suddenly the idea of <em>not</em> spending money can become more attractive.</p>
      <p>Part of the appeal of these "free to play" video games is that they allow you to spend money to make progress in-game, and if the costs feel vague and the payoff feels tangible, it's tempting to buy that virtual item. You're spending hours of your labor to buy it, but it doesn't <em>feel</em> like you're spending something tangible.  It <em>feels</em> like "easy progress."  So, when I feel the desire to spend $20 on something to make progress toward a goal, I sign onto my student loan provider's website and make an extra $20 payment toward paying off my student loans.  Instead of paying money to a Chinese video game company to make the numbers in a video game go up faster, I pay money to a student loan provider to accelerate my progress there.  From a financial standpoint, this isn't the most prudent possible use of my money (it's a subsidized loan with a tiny interest rate, and my money would do more for me in basically any investment vehicle, which is why I still have student loan debt despite having the financial means to pay it off), but at least I've spent that $20 making progress toward something more productive than making the numbers in a video game go up faster.  And paying off $20 of student loan debt actually fills me with the same sort of giddy excitement I'd get from spending $20 on a random impulse purchase, so it lets me channel that energy of "I want to spend some money right now" into something that's at least a productive use of my money.</p>
      <p>The key is to find something <em>specific</em> that you are working toward.  "Spending 2 hours browsing reddit is a waste of time" is a vague statement that probably won't do too much to cure you of the habit.  But wasting 2 hours that you could have spent working toward a <em>specific goal</em> or engaging in some other <em>specific enjoyable activity</em> allows you to actually feel the real cost of having spent 2 hours on Reddit.  Like, "damn, that's 2 hours I could have spent making progress on my Japanese lessons."  Or "I could have hit the basketball court and worked on my jump shot."  Or "I could have watched a Martin Scorsese movie, which probably would have been a more enjoyable and edifying experience than looking at memes for 2 hours." (I'm actually a big fan of watching movies as a way of breaking bad habits, because I don't think people get addicted to watching movies the same way that they get addicted to watching TV shows, since movies are typically designed to have a satisfying conclusion after 2 hours.  And I think that forcing yourself to concentrate on a single thing for 2 hours, even if it's for a purely passive activity like watching a movie, can be good for taming the impulses to constantly be checking your phone or whatever.  When I got in the habit of spending one night every month or so in a movie theater where it was impossible for me to pause the movie and I was prohibited from looking at my phone, I think it improved my cognitive function in a lot of small and hard-to-detect ways.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>