<post>
  <author>WestphalianPeace</author>
  <date>2020-10-13T11:06:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8ok9my/</link>
  <title>An Ode To Penn's Woods</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I have avoided making a Reddit account like the plague for years now. I have made one specifically to let you know that, for myself and a few others at least, I love my state. I am absolutely a proud Pennsylvanian despite having a Canadian childhood and only coming to the US in early adolescence. </p>
      <p>I admit I don't know the state flower. But I sure as hell know the state gun, it's the Pennsylvania Long Rifle and it has a proud role to play in the history of firearms in the US.</p>
      <p>I mean it sincerely when I say that I've fallen in love with this country and I've fallen in love with this state. I'm proud of it's history, it's symbols, it's strange demographic composition, it's religious oddities, it's population centers, it's economy, it's education network, it's culture.</p>
      <p>I love it's geography. I love the Appalachians that run through it, I love the Piedmont, I love the valleys, the open plains of farmland, the Schuylkill and the Delaware. I love how whenever someone builds a cultural subdivision map for the United States that Pennsylvania straddles this midpoint boundary of neither fully north, fully south, or properly midwest. Because we are all of those things and none of them in a way that is just different.</p>
      <p>I love our strange history. There is long effect of the Quakers on our local culture thanks to William Penn. There are meeting Houses right next door to where I live, Quaker Wedding's are integrated into our law code in a way not found elsewhere, and Quakers are still getting together to create old folks homes that arn't hell on earth. I love our Amish  even as I complain about their buggies on the road. I love that Pennsylvania Dutch is still a thing. I love our Mummers parade. I love our unofficial state beer, Yuengling, and I love how PA has become an East Coast Belgium of creativity for beer that goes beyond just adding more and more hops. I love our University systems spread throughout the state giving each region something to be proud of. I love the Gordian Knot Cutting Job Integration system of Drexel, the racial uplifting history of Temple, the academic fortitude of University of Pennsylvania, the Engineering Prowess of Carnegie Melon, the humanistic Cathedral of Knowledge of Pittsburgh, and the sheer camaraderie and pride Penn State engenders in everyone it touches. I love how wacky Ben Franklin was and I love our history of being housing Congress Hall. I love how Pittsburgh has pulled itself up after the struggles of the rust belt and became this unsung achievement of revitalization. I love how they have america's ugliest accent and how they just don't care. I love how the city appears out of nowhere, just forested hills and highway and then something magnificent. Its bridge system makes me feel like i'm in an industrial Rivendell and when I leave at night I love watching the skyline of the city rise up to the top of the hills and merge with the night sky creating an unceasing blanket of lights. </p>
      <p>I love our political culture here. Philadelphia, Pittsburgh, and Alabama in between creates just the right tension between factions. We were Borderer's and Quakers mixed  together and that created something I believe to be uniquely Pennsylvanian by smoothing out the extremes of both. </p>
      <p>Having just two major cities stops either from becoming The One City That Overwhelms Everything the way I see in New York, Maryland, Massachusetts, Illinois, Oregon, Washington, and more. The cities combined stop the Red from making us too Right and the Red stops us from the worst impulses I fear from the left. </p>
      <p>This is a mid-argument interruption to remind the world that Wawa is better than Sheetz but that Sheetz is better than Wawa when you want food after midnight. </p>
      <p>I love how many liberal and left-leaning coworkers I have who sincerely believe in absolute gun rights and I love how many right-leaning and republican coworkers i have who take arguments over trans issues with sincere ear. And speaking of guns I love just how PA phrases it's gun rights. </p>
      <p>Article 1, section 21 "The right of the citizens to bear arms in defense of themselves and the State shall not be questioned."</p>
      <p>'I just can't help but smile at how excessively American "SHALL NOT BE QUESTIONED" feels. Not that that has stopped my state from having it's own complicated history of gun laws but that style of assertion genuinely warms my heart in a way that other constitutions simply do not. </p>
      <p>I don't feel at ease in other states anymore. Not even after living there for extended periods of time. They have their charms and I don't mean to be rude but each adjacent state just feels wrong to me now. Delaware makes me long for my forests and New Jersey is just too much surburban sprawl. The demographics of the South, both racial and religious, create enough of a separate culture to push me away although it's nice to visit. New York does it's own thing. New England is nice but genuinely does come off as too "there is only one correct path" for me. Maryland is the March between PA and the South and i'm thankful for it's presence but I still don't want to live in the March. </p>
      <p>I hope the above is not too uncharitable to those states. If you live there please understand that I am not saying those states are inherently worse then Pennsylvania. Only that, as a Pennsylvanian, I get the same effect there as I do when traveling abroad. Visiting them reminds me of everything that makes home home.</p>
      <p>I could go on about this state. There is so much left unsaid but I'll try to drive home one last point. When Pennsylvania fails it hurts me because I expect us to do better. Our gerrymandering was legendary until just over a year ago. A large percent of the state is registered Independent but we have a closed primary system. Our court system has a serious problem with corruption. We are still coming to terms with what de-industrialization has done to our state and all the cultural fallout that comes with it. The opioid epidemic is an absolute nightmare. Philadelphia genuinely feels like a city that could be so much more than it currently is. Our regional rail has such a reputation that the website "Is SEPTA Fucked" is needed. Even our flag is a pathetic seal on a bedsheet. And admitting all that hurts because I love this state and I want what's best for it. That pain would not be there if we all felt such weak attachment to our home state. </p>
      <p>There is something special in this state that has captured me and I hope I have gotten that across without sounding weird or excessive.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>