<post>
  <author>XantosCell</author>
  <date>2020-10-15T00:29:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8uoqxw/</link>
  <title>A Personal Experience of the Motte's Influence</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>With the recent creation of theschism and subsequent extensive meta discussion of 'radicalization' and the like I wanted to sum up my personal experience with that kind of thing on TheMotte. I have read 95%+ of comments in the culture war thread since basically the founding of the sub. I came here from HPMOR-&gt;LessWrong-&gt;SSC-&gt;TheMotte. I never read the culture war thread on SSC before it was moved here. </p>
      <p>A brief note on "labels”: I don't think that many labels (progressive, alt-right, evangelical, libertarian, etc.) are particularly helpful for understanding someone/something, but can be helpful for comparing. As my goal with this post is to compare my past and current selves as well as the effect of TheMotte on them, I will hesitantly use labels to approximate.</p>
      <p>When I started that journey I was fairly progressive and very much on board with social justice. I come from a Red state and social group, but my family were always liberal democrats. I can't for the life of me pinpoint an exact moment that I really started to change my views explicitly, but over a period of about two years I became a ""conservative."" (Double air quotes intentional) To pull language from<a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/09/30/i-can-tolerate-anything-except-the-outgroup/"> this SSC post</a>, I don't think that I really fully fit into any of the tribes. I'm too politically right for the blue tribe, too cosmopolitan and uncaring about ‘Murica for the red tribe, and aside from drinking Soylent fairly often I don't have much in common with the grey tribe either. It is worth noting that the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/g717ft/two_views_of_survey_data_the_modal_motte_user_a/">Modal Motte User</a> post from a while back described me scarily accurately, although how much of that is due to the sub selecting for certain kinds of people and driving others away vs. people who read similar ideological works becoming more similar I have no idea.</p>
      <p>I used to be a HARDCORE <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/24/conflict-vs-mistake/">mistake theorist</a>, but this sub has opened my eyes to conflict theory in a profound way. Not at all in the sense of "violence is a solution to political problems," but more in a "there is sometimes no amount of conversation that will resolve differences." My tact now tends to be "I'll vote for mine and you for yours, lets go do/talk about something more interesting." </p>
      <p>The other major way that my thoughts have been changed by my time here is via fear. I now live in fear of a movement that is often called ‘social justice’. I hold beliefs that are unsanctioned in today's politics, but live in a leftist sphere. I don't say things that I believe anymore. Basically ever. It is absolutely not worth it. The fear is that there are others similarly self-silencing, and that because of that silence there will be no resistance to further censorship/cancelling/what have you. <a href="https://medium.com/@adamwinfield/under-toronto-6d457338408d">This</a> is what my nightmare looks like, and I fear the future to some extent because I can see clearly the pathway that leads reality towards that nightmare.</p>
      <p>I am very grateful to have found this space, mostly for the chance to read (free of charge!!!) the work/thoughts of people who are clearly much, much wiser than I. Overall, I've changed a lot as a result of reading TheMotte daily for a couple of years, probably for better and for worse. Does this sub "radicalize" people? Not really in my experience, but it does serve as a space where discourse outside the overton window happens, and I think that that can seem like radicalization from inside the window.</p>
      <p>The biggest thing I took away from this subreddit, is funnily enough, a dedication to working out and eating healthy. Deep in some long forgotten thread a user was asking what steps they could take to improve their lives and someone commented that lifting and eating right were going to be ten thousand times more beneficial than any essay you could read on the internet. Approximately 1.5 years of lifting later and I unreservedly agree. Broccoli is the key to human happiness. (To conform to the requirement to proactively provide evidence for inflammatory claims: <a href="https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/benefits-of-broccoli#TOC_TITLE_HDR_9">link</a>. I’m not sure how deeply broccoli haters have penetrated into the mod team here, but better safe than sorry.)</p>
      <p>Tldr: Eat vegetables and exercise.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>