<post>
  <author>Appropriate-Report</author>
  <date>2020-02-05T17:34:26Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fgmghok/</link>
  <title>Supplies for Border Crossers being an Attractive Nuisance</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I imagine the government's deterrence theory is that leaving out food and water encourages people to cross, and encouraging people to cross is wrong, as the journey is dangerous, and people die.  Suppose coyotes cross several times and find this food and water stash.  The next time they cross they will expect the stash to be there, and thus not carry enough water for the entire crossing, dooming some people to die.  There is a trade-off between the additional people who are encouraged to cross because of this help, and who die in the attempt, and the set of people who are helped by leaving out water. </p>
      <p>In law there is a notion of an attractive  nuisance:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>a landowner may be held liable for injuries to children trespassing on the land if the injury is caused by an object on the land that is likely to attract children.[1] The doctrine is designed to protect children who are unable to appreciate the risk posed by the object, by imposing a liability on the landowner.[1] The doctrine has been applied to hold landowners liable for injuries caused by abandoned cars, piles of lumber or sand, trampolines, and swimming pools.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think leaving out water is similar.  Tracking through the desert is dangerous, and leaving out water and food encourages people to do this. </p>
      <p>It is hard to come up with an exact analogy, but I think this is close:  Suppose there is a rave in the desert, something like Burning Man, but without permits, where the partiers are trespassing.  Some people worry, (for deeply/vaguely religious reasons) that the participants will be dehydrated, so they provide food, water, and tents.  Some people will see this as just something good and helpful. 
 Other people would agree that this would encourage people to attend, increase the numbers, and is generally wrong, as it is a policy of promoting illegal acts.  Still other people can believe this is wrong because it will bring more people to the desert, who will injure themselves in the dangerous environment. The government is presumably who gets to decide who is correct.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>