<post>
  <author>CPlusPlusDeveloper</author>
  <date>2020-02-06T06:45:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fgoitsx/</link>
  <title>Why We Should Hold Primaries Two Years Early</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think the biggest winner out of this clusterfuck is Trump. On the betting markets his implied probability of winning re-election has risen from 50% to 60% over the past week. </p>
      <p>The thing is, even when the primary process goes smoothly, the nominee rarely comes out of it smelling nice. I think it's a big reason why the incumbent has such an advantage. The slow-burning chaos, public airing of dirty laundry, and petty squabbles all guarantees that at least one faction of the party comes away pissed off with memories still fresh on election day.</p>
      <p>If I was the DNC, I'd take the opportunity to redesign the system from scratch. Here's how I think you could do a lot better. Run the nationwide primary, two years before the presidential election. In fact hold it on the same election as the Congressional midterms. This has the ancillary bonus of raising turnout for the midterms. Always a boon for the Democrats. </p>
      <p>Two years is a long time to wait. So in that time period the nominee will serve as the "opposition leader". It won't be an official federal office, but the party will essentially treat it that way. This provides a central point of leadership for the party when they don't control the White House. Having a clear leader, like POTUS is to his party, is always better from a strategy and coordination standpoint. </p>
      <p>This also shores up the resume of the nominee before he runs for president. By serving as the opposition leader, a role which also involves oversight of the executive branch, he/she's getting executive experience on the national stage. That makes the candidate look like he's ready to take office on election day.</p>
      <p>And then of course, there's the obvious benefit that it gives the DNC two years to focus messaging, fundraising, and electioneering for the singular purpose of winning back the White House. That's guaranteed to produce better results than bitter in-fighting for a year and a half, with only six months to unify the party.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>