<post>
  <author>CriticalDuty</author>
  <date>2020-02-05T20:35:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fgmzo4w/</link>
  <title>Identity Politics not Winding Down</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A lot of people who subscribe to this pendulum theory of idpol seem to implicitly believe that idpol is just an ideological aberration caused by malign actors hoodwinking the population into identity-based hostilities. This is misguided and couldn't be further from the truth; it seems clearer to me that idpol is the product of a society composed of mutually alien tribes coming to terms with the fact that they no longer have anything in common, that their interests are often directly opposed, and that there is a Pareto efficiency of social, cultural and economic resources in this society that makes opting for open identitarian struggle a matter of simple self-interest. If people are simply responding to their rational incentives to engage in idpol, there is nothing particularly "wrong" about it. As for impeding its progress, that ship sailed with Hart-Celler in 1965.</p>
      <p>Barack Obama was an ostensibly moderate progressive who governed as President for eight years. Was the social justice movement more subdued during this period? In tone, perhaps. But this was the period when <em>Rolling Stone</em> was fabricating stories of white frat boys gangraping co-eds, the Department of Education was sending Dear Colleague letters threatening to yank funding from institutions that didn't appropriately crack down on a largely non-existent rape epidemic on campuses, the Department of Justice was dragging the Little Sisters of the Poor to the Supreme Court for holding standard Catholic views on birth control, etc etc. What does the moderation that we are supposedly going to return to look like, exactly?</p>
      <p>In right-wing legal circles, a major event that swayed a lot of Trump-skeptical guys I knew to vote for the Donald in 2016 was a highly talked about <a href="https://balkin.blogspot.com/2016/05/abandoning-defensive-crouch-liberal.html">blog post</a> by Mark Tushnet, a professor of constitutional law at Harvard and a commonly-cited legal figure in Blue Tribe media and politics (the Democratic Party has invited him to testify in Congressional hearings several times, for example). Tushnet is a Jewish socialist who proposed that once Hillary Clinton won the election and secured the judiciary, the left should exercise the muscle of the courts to treat Christian conservatives as vanquished Nazis and crush them entirely. It ultimately didn't work out that way because Trump won, but I think Tushnet's mindset is going to be more typical of the hypothetical post-2020 progressive approach to politics in the event of a Trump loss. In public you will have the usual guff about "healing a divided nation" etc etc., but the private view is going to be more like "We won, bayonet the survivors." </p>
      <p>Tushnet was probably not wrong about crushing your enemies being the best way to bring about whatever your personal standard of public sanity is, though. I think few events in the blogosphere were more impactful on the Culture War than Peter Thiel killing Gawker. Sites like <em>Jezebel</em> used to run interference for bad actors like Sabrina Erdely, but today nobody talks about <em>Jezebel</em> anymore. Total ruin has been more effective than engaging your enemies in reasoned debate, and certainly more effective than giving them the power to destroy you and trusting them to make mistakes.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>