<post>
  <author>dedicating_ruckus</author>
  <date>2020-02-03T21:31:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fggnfec/</link>
  <title>Social Conservatism, Survival, and Scalability</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Accounting social conservatism as imposing costs, and forgoing it as a viable means of avoiding those costs, is presupposing a great deal about the nature of your society.</p>
      <p>Fundamentally, social conservatism is a system for maximizing survival. The whole point of "family values" is that a family is an institution that can scale all the way down to just two people in a howling wilderness. If everything else fails you, if the state collapses and the economy is wrecked and bandits roam the streets, you can still go to your family and get support in return for support. (In theory at least.)</p>
      <p>The "costs" social conservatism imposes are effectively the necessary accommodations to make human life consistent with family. (As filtered through messy heuristics and reduction to simplicity, of course.) By living in a socially conservative way, you build in slack to your lifestyle such that you can cope with negative external shocks, even quite severe ones. This method of accounting for downside risk is, again, very downward scalable; this system still works even when no other system can be counted on.</p>
      <p>In modern societies, we've built all sorts of structures that can in some conditions seem to obviate the need for family. We have social safety nets and public-school-as-daycare and mass-media-as-socialization and all that stuff. Under some circumstances, and for some people, these systems work as designed, allowing a decent life (and a shock-tolerant one) even to those without family to fall back on. And, indeed, the original motivation for building many of these was to handle people who had, for one reason or another, fallen through the cracks of the older family-based system. The older system is not perfect (just as the new system isn't), and in some cases the new one covers cases the old one didn't.</p>
      <p>The new system, though, is very distinctively <em>not</em> resilient to larger-scale negative shocks. It depends on society as a whole having a massive surplus of resources that can easily be tapped to flow off into distant, unaccountable institutions without putting too much strain on the local. It works through a small number of giant singletons that are a (civilization-scale) novel human endeavor, without much in the way of contingency options if they become unreliable (other than just falling back on the old family system). Most fundamentally, it is <em>large-scale</em>; it doesn't easily decompose downward, and it doesn't easily split if large-scale problems occur. Its failure modes in all these cases are likely to be catastrophic.</p>
      <p>It's true that some people are, by choice or inherent inclination, less well-suited to social conservatism -- that is, the family system -- than the majority of humans for which it's a good fit. In a society like ours, these people may perceive the necessary accommodations to fit into the family system as costs, and they may be able to avoid these costs on a personal basis by falling into full dependency on the structures of the new system, cutting the ties that they could otherwise use to fall back on the support of family. It's important to recognize that, in making this choice, these people are not getting any kind of free lunch. They trade the necessity of fitting themselves into the family system for utter dependency on the large-scale systems of our society; a moderate gain in the present time is traded for a ruinous tail risk. Whether this trade is worth it for you is a matter of risk tolerance, but the phrase "picking up pennies in front of a steamroller" comes to mind.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>