<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-02-07T01:07:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fgr40dd/</link>
  <title>Hamilton</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I try to make a point of being out-of-date wherever possible, but I think enough time has now elapsed that I can safely discuss the musical <em>Hamilton</em> without being accused of being in tune with popular culture.</p>
      <p>Let me say at the outset that I'm not much a musical theater buff, unless we're counting opera. I've also never seen <em>Hamilton</em> live. However, I've listened to the soundtrack an embarrassing number of times, and it pains me to admit that I now know most of the lyrics off-by-heart. In addition to being musically superb, I think it's a fascinating cultural artefact. Let me single out three CW-relevant things that I think it does brilliantly.</p>
      <p>First, astonishingly, I find it genuinely <strong>patriotically inspiring</strong>. It makes me feel exhilarated at the the American project and the unique ideological foundation of the United States. And this is in spite of the fact that - some transatlantic affiliations notwithstanding - <em>I'm British</em>. I think it helps that King George has <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eKFN-aqPJH8">some great songs</a> and isn't a figure of hatred or ridicule, but I'm amazed that any work of art - let alone a Broadway musical - has me cheering for the Yanks at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SWZy3zRbBHI">the Battle of Yorktown</a>. Listening to <em>Hamilton,</em> I walk away with the conviction that the Revolutionary War (or as we call it, the War of American Aggression) was a profound moment for the Enlightenment project and humanity as a whole. And that's fucking insane. How good is your propaganda that it can have this effect on one of her Majesty's loyal subjects? I can't realistically picture a British dramatic production ever hitting the same clear notes of patriotism in this day and age, nor can I imagine many other European countries pulling a similar trick - themes of national pride would at best be framed in terms of vernacular virtues like good humour, toleration, or common sense, rather than our glorious destiny, and even then, they'd likely be balanced by minor key motifs about our morally vexed colonial history. So I'm jealous that the US has produced such a ridiculously powerful patriotic work - what I wouldn't give to consider myself to be - "just like my country" - <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ic7NqP_YGlg">young, scrappy and hungry</a>; instead I usually feel (again, just like my country) old, tired, and vaguely drunk.</p>
      <p>Second, despite being a core Blue Tribe creation that exemplifies liberal values, <strong>it's not politically obnoxious or cheap</strong>. It doesn't take easy potshots at Trump or Republicans or contemporary politics. And while race, gender, and slavery are key themes, it doesn't descend into polarising cultural messages. George Washington, for example, is portrayed as an incredibly heroic and positive figure, and the musical entirely avoids exploring his relationship with slavery. Again, I can't imagine a British production doing the same with, say, Churchill - you'd <em>have</em> to address his 'problematic' beliefs in any popular treatment of the man, yet somehow <em>Hamilton</em> gets away with it. Granted, Jefferson might be carrying some of the flak here - he's a treated with a bit more ambivalence, but <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9014vq1lqXM">he still has some utterly brilliant moments</a>, and isn't a wholly unsympathetic figure by any means. Likewise, it paints an incredibly positive portrayal of white anti-slavery campaigners like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Laurens">John Laurens</a>. The treatment of gender is similarly - well, ecumenical and appealing. There are brilliantly <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cnVBzu1Jrbk">smart</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a0k0FJrY4a8">compelling</a> female characters, but there's no anachronistic aria complaining about the oppression of women in 18th century America. And even the musical's most famous political line ("<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6_35a7sn6ds">immigrants, we get the job done</a>") isn't explicitly racial - the actors may be black and Hispanics, but the characters are a white Frenchman and a (probably) white American born in the Caribbean.</p>
      <p>Finally, the whole musical is <strong>gloriously wonkish</strong>. I find it hard to imagine the meeting where Lin Manuel Miranda pitched lengthy scenes about the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dSYW61XQZeo">formation of the Federal Reserve</a> or <a href="http://ruccs.rutgers.edu/faculty/pylyshyn.html">the debate about where to locate the American capital</a> to a bunch of Broadway investors, but somehow, the musical manages to brilliantly dramatise complex political and economic events. Sure, it may gloss over some details; but name another musical that delves into monetary and fiscal policy. (As an aside: sometimes I feel that wonkishness supersedes all my other political identities - I'd rather get into a detailed conversation with a Neoreactionary about 19th century crime rates or a radical progressive about the relationship between pornography and sexual assault than deal with emotionally charged platitudes from someone who agrees with me about everything). So, the fact that Hamilton managed to incorporate some quite complex and technical bits of history - this alone makes me fall in love with it.</p>
      <p>I'd love to hear others' reflections on the musical, especially from red-tribe identified folk. And if you haven't already given it a listen, then regardless of your political persuasions, I can't recommend it enough.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>