<post>
  <author>GoldPlatedDalek</author>
  <date>2020-02-04T14:44:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fgiosbg/</link>
  <title>Reflections on Covington, News, and Memory Holes</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Over the weekend I was cleaning out my inbox and I found a draft email that had been languishing for almost a year.   The email’s content contained partially finished assessment of the whole Covington Catholic situation with links to the associated stories for various news outlets.  The short version of why said draft email exists is that, at the time, a friend and I decided that the Covington Situation could be a good opportunity for us to update our priors on various news organizations’ partiality, so we planned to track the Covington story though it’s media journey across different organizations and try to come up with an assessment of how each organization handled the story.  </p>
      <p>We didn’t finish our project, but looking at the email reignited my curiosity.  I started clicking though the links we had gathered and found, somewhat to my surprise, that the stories weren’t actually that inflammatory.  There was still some biased presentation in some cases, but the accounts were largely factual based on the time that they were written and didn’t contain much IDPol at all.  At this point I’m saying to myself, “Is that it”?  I remembered there being outrage on both sides, first from the left about a bunch of smug white kids MAGA hats mobbing a native American protestor, then from the right reminding everyone that celebrities said insensitive things, pundits crossed the line, and here is an itemized list of every person that totally missed the mark.  I remember a dog fight.  Did I make it all up?</p>
      <p>So, I decided to dig in a little more.  What I found may not be surprising to some people, but it definitely brings up an interesting topic with respect to news organizations behave now that a large portion of content is posted online.  To what extent are media organizations subtly memory-holing things and is anyone tracking what’s going on?  Most of what I found aren’t huge changes, they are subtle, but in my opinion, take the edge off some of the vitriol I remember.  </p>
      <p>For example, the first Covington story from the NY Times about Covington is currently  headlined ”Viral Video Shows Boys in Make America Great Again Hats Surrounding Native Elder”.  <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/19/us/covington-catholic-high-school-nathan-phillips.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/19/us/covington-catholic-high-school-nathan-phillips.html</a>.  The original title for the story was “Boys in Make America Great Again Hats Mob Native Elder at Indigenous Peoples March”.  Not a huge modification, but headlines set the tone for articles and this change frames the story in a less combative way.  The follow-up story <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/20/us/nathan-phillips-covington.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/20/us/nathan-phillips-covington.html</a> and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20190121003654/https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/20/us/nathan-phillips-covington.html">https://web.archive.org/web/20190121003654/https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/20/us/nathan-phillips-covington.html</a><del>have</del> has some actual textual changes.  The new version, along with general article organization changes, removes some things such as comments from the March for Life president condemning the situation, and a statement from a Cincinnati paper saying that the boys were cheering to pass time.  In my opinion, these statements subtly soften the narrative.  The original March for Life president quote conveys “Look! Even the leader of the anti-abortion event that they were attending condemned them!” and the Cincinnati quote conveys “We were just being disruptive to pass time.”.  The new version of the article adds content as well, such as Nick Sandmann’s statement regarding the incident.  Adding Sandmann’s statement, again, softens the narrative as it indicates that the article writer was careful enough to include the “other” side’s rationale to the incident.  </p>
      <p>Again, these are not big changes individually, but together I think they make a difference; they are the difference between the vitriol I remember and projecting largely factual information through a biased perspective.  The current version of the NY Times article still calls out that most of the Covington students were white and wearing MAGA hats, that Trump does racist things, and that some people around the students heard a chant of build that wall.  These are all things that I would expect a blue tribe leaning publication to emphasize.  For me though, the changes were enough that when I looked back at the NY Times reporting this weekend my thought was “Oh wow, the Times actually did a pretty good job with this and didn’t let themselves get pulled into the culture war.”  Now, I not only feel that my original thought isn’t the case, but that I can’t trust the Times because they are ninja editing their content.  As you can imagine, the NY Times is not the only example.  Vox was a tire fire when I looked back at their stories and it seems like their MO is to continually update the same story as new information was presented.  So, wholesale reimaging of the story as time progressed and as new evidence came to light.  Note that, to my knowledge, there was no indication in any of these articles that edits or revisions were made. </p>
      <p>Anyway, I say all this because I thought it was interesting, but also for selfish reasons.  After my “investigation” I’m interested in other stories where subtle or blatant memory holing has happened and I was hoping to not have to do all of my own legwork to find out.  Has anyone else here looked for things like this?  If so, what did you find?  Feel free to provide examples if you come across them.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>