<post>
  <author>JustAWellwisher</author>
  <date>2020-02-03T14:16:04Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fgfi3y2/</link>
  <title>The Slow Transformation of reddit</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>At the start of your post I thought you were talking about going back to ancient reddit history like &lt;2008. Oh well.</p>
      <p>In any case, what you need to know is that around about the end of 2015 Reddit began seriously tampering with their front page with one primary goal.</p>
      <p>Diversify content.</p>
      <p>What was happening was one subreddit could dominate the front page if they were popular enough. Sometimes this was the donald, sometimes this was rPolitics.</p>
      <p>First, they made it harder for extremely trending new posts to appear on the front page. This was what was catapulting rTheDonald posts. Whether it was bots or just an influx of 4chan users upvoting memes, the algorithm was promoting them because they amassed a critical amount of upvotes within the first few minutes of posting.</p>
      <p>Can you tell what was meant to be the purpose of that function in the algorithm originally?</p>
      <p>That's right, news. Stuff that was so relevant, so pertinent, so social media immediate that everyone would want to know about it. That's what the upvote function is for after all - if you want more people to see a post, you upvote it. That's never been how redditors use it, but redditors rarely see upvotes from the systematic angle of the back end.</p>
      <p>So now you've got the problem that people are mass upvoting memes from TheDonald and launching them to the front page, pushing basically all non-political content down.</p>
      <p>Most people use reddit the same way most people use tinder the same way most people use facebook.</p>
      <p>They scroll down the feed of general content from the front page until something interests them, they check it out, then keep scrolling.</p>
      <p>I'm gonna make a bet that while reddit was going through its phase of being dominated by politics and especially TheDonald that the average user retention rate was going down. The average person reads politics memes for one whole page, two whole pages, they leave the website.</p>
      <p>Now if you read the front page, and especially as you scroll down, what you'll find is that now more than ever there is more space on the front page given to one or two extremely popular posts from a larger sample of less popular subreddits.</p>
      <p>Reddit has <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/announcements/comments/4oedco/lets_all_have_a_town_hall_about_rall/">been open about this by the way</a>. This post was made after the Orlando shooting when the only subreddits that left news about the shooting up were right-wing subreddits and thus conversation on right wing subreddits dominated rAll.</p>
      <p>I believe Spez that these changes had been in the pipeline for a while. The last time they fiddled with the front page was when they got rid of the concept of Default subreddits. Since you seem new, default subreddits were originally just a group of subreddits that you were automatically subscribed to when you created an account on reddit. Naturally, all of these subreddits dominated the front page. As Reddit grew it was clear they weren't happy with the system of their site failing to show people new subreddits, new memes, you know... it was all the same subreddits, the same content, hell the same powerusers. And that was a problem.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Now if you take a look at your All feed what you'll find is a lot of different subreddits. For me right now the top 20 posts go like this - blursedimages, pics, upliftingnews, clevercomebacks, funny, gifs, insanepeoplefacebook, comedyhomicide, pcmasterrace, politics, gifsthatkeepongiving, dankmemes, memes, science, nextfuckinglevel, wtf, me_irl, showerthoughts, aww, choosingbeggars, assholedesign.</p>
      <p>In fact the first double up is a second dankmemes post at number 77.</p>
      <p>This. This is what has changed. The subreddits of your favourite streamer or youtuber are more accessible because the algorithm is taking the top post of your subreddit and elevating it above the more popular second, third and fourth top posts from rFunny or rGifs. (I don't know the specific algorithm, just the gist)</p>
      <p>There have been a couple of unforeseen consequences of this system though.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>It's been much harder for news to reach the front page. It used to be that if something around the world happened, you'd find out first on reddit. That doesn't happen anymore. At the very least the algorithm is more complicated in the way it prioritizes a post that is rapidly trending.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The resulting system has benefited content that can be crossposted across multiple subreddits. For a while there were 10, 20, 30 political left leaning comedy subreddits that were frequently drowning out the front page in addition to the few right leaning subreddits.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>It's made undesirable communities far more visible and with this, reddit needed to take far stronger action to remove their presence from rAll. This is why quarantining subreddits got more frequent in the last four years. A post from a small community like rKillAll[InsertGroupYouHateHere] is at greater risk of actually making it to rAll now.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Smaller communities are slower communities. Look at TheMotte's front page. Our hottest post is yesterday's Small Questions Thread. If rAll was taking our top post at some point (whether it's 100 or 200 pages down) then that post would have stayed the same for nearly two days. rAll has gotten less dynamic because it's pulling from communities that are less dynamic. Fortunately, this is only a problem for reddit's <em>heavy</em> users. The addicts who put their phone away and open reddit on a new tab on their browser will find the same posts more often now for longer periods than they used to.</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>More people nowadays are aware that the best way to use reddit is to curate your experience - find subreddits you like, find content you like, find people who share the same interests as you, look for unique places and go to the front page when you want to see what everyone else is seeing.</p>
      <p>But that is still not how most visitors to reddit use the website. Most don't have accounts. Most that do don't even vote. Even more don't comment. Reddit over the past hmm six-ish years has been trying to change that. They've tried to introduce more social-media type elements to the site. That was a big part of the reason for the UI overhaul a while back. Reddit was trying to slightly shift it's priorities away from being a content feed towards being a community center. Now you can post to your own userpage, you can follow other users, you have a banner and a profile. They haven't really caught on.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>