<post>
  <author>ScienceMcGee</author>
  <date>2020-02-08T01:13:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fgumegk/</link>
  <title>All You Ever Wanted to Know about Adolescent Transition</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Full bias disclosure: Transsexual here. Wrote some papers on this in college. Transitioned as an adult. Generally take the stance that transsexuality is an overall negative phenomenon for the individual transsexual and that we should not unnecessarily create more of us.</p>
      <p>A substantial number of "gender-dysphoric" kids (&lt;10-13) do desist, but some evidence indicates these kids were being referred for gender therapy mostly for cross-gender <em>behavior</em>, not <em>identification</em>. That is, natal boys playing with Barbies or wearing dresses often grow up to be gay men; natal boys insisting repeatedly and spontaneously that they're girls are relatively likely to grow up to be trans women.  Going forward, I'm going to use the term dysphoria to refer to a constellation of traits, loosely paraphrasing the DSM-5: the desire to be the non-natal gender; the desire for the primary and secondary physical traits of the non-natal gender; the conviction that one is or should have been the other gender.</p>
      <p>Caveat: most of these studies were done before the explosion of transgender issues into pop culture around ~2014. I wouldn't be <em>surprised</em> if well-meaning parents are now more likely to read gender-nonconforming behavior as evidence of incipient transsexuality. I was unable to find literature on this, although I found a fair few CW-heavy but non-peer reviewed (and mostly anecdotal) claims that it's happening. Without an actual study, I'm skeptical that it's hugely common. Anecdotally, I'm not around enough parents to say either way.</p>
      <p>I have not seen convincing evidence that parenting can <em>alter</em> gender identity. That is, I've never seen evidence that parenting can induce big-D Dysphoria (as opposed to gender-atypical behavior) in a neurologically-typical child. My completely off-the-cuff speculation is that it might be <em>possible</em> for a kid whose brain wasn't strongly sexed to begin with, given very intense cross-sex socialization, but I've never seen any kind of hard evidence that this would happen. (Given how incredibly charged this issue is, and that teenagers are often pretty good at hiding dysphoria from unaccepting parents, I'm disinclined to trust anecdotes from either side about this. A lot of them feel like motivated reasoning at best.) Conversely, real-world attempts to raise kids as the opposite of their natal gender <em>have</em> consistently failed (e.g., David Reimer, who was raised as a girl after a botched circumcision but transitioned back after puberty).</p>
      <p>The obvious correlate of this argument is that we <em>might</em> be able to reverse or prevent transsexuality in some borderline cases with the right therapy. My general feeling on this one is "good luck"--although some sexologists, e.g., Kenneth Zucker, did report successes in individual cases, they also saw a whole hell of a lot of failures, who typically came out pretty unhappy. (Note also that most transsexuals were not raised in accepting, pro-trans homes!) For the best chance of success, you'd probably want to choose a kid with a very borderline brain structure and somewhat uncertain cross-sex identification. I don't know how you would do this reliably and I don't think it would be particularly ethical to try given the state of the science.</p>
      <p>We don't know enough about brain sexual dimorphism to say what transsexuality looks like in adolescents. I was only able to find one fMRI study of gender-dysphoric adolescents, with pretty standard fMRI issues (small sample size, "trendwise" significance) (Soleman <a href="https://et.al">et.al</a>, 2013). fMRI is so prone to weird, buggy results due to things like different amounts of head motion between sample groups--hell, I barely trust my own results half the time--that I'm not inclined to read very much into one study.</p>
      <p>In other words, somewhere between 0% and 100% of gender dysphoric children desist. The best evidence (from the 2000s and early 2010s, but still) suggests that we can tell desisters and persisters apart, but not perfectly. Statistics here are wildly skewed because they're typically taken from gender identity clinics. Now suppose we have a 10-year-old who <em>looks</em> likely to persist.</p>
      <p>A lot of what I would have said about Lupron has been said, although I will note that it has been used for years to slow precocious puberty (its effects aren't completely unknown). The chance of a long-term IQ drop is genuinely scary to me, although a handful of case studies aren't great evidence. Additionally, long-term Lupron can produce weird growth patterns that don't look quite right for either sex. I would not recommend long-term Lupron by itself for anyone. </p>
      <p>That said, low-dose Lupron paired with low-dose hormones (gradually ramping up the hormones and decreasing the Lupron) may be less likely to produce these bad effects, and this is a treatment some centers are moving toward. The problem here is obvious: if this kid was going to desist, we've just started them on the wrong puberty. If they desist early, they may still have some sex-atypical traits. If we've prevented desistance, we've created a transsexual (albeit an unusually normal-looking one) from what could've been a cissexual. See above for why I don't think this is a good outcome.</p>
      <p>
        <em>That said</em>. Waiting until adulthood to start transition can, anecdotally, screw up social development and <em>absolutely mangle your body</em>. I'm relatively lucky--I was getting thrown out of women's toilets even before starting testosterone, and I had zero trouble integrating as a man--and yet there are quite a few unchangeable aspects of my skeleton that I find highly distressing/disfiguring. It's difficult to convey to people who don't experience it how <em>extremely</em> unpleasant sex dysphoria can be: if you're cis male, imagine growing breasts, losing your facial hair, putting on most of your weight in a female distribution, having your voice drift up to a Minnie Mouse pitch, and losing your penis. Completely apart from the social ramifications of gender incongruence, sex dysphoria is <em>in and of itself</em> a highly unpleasant thing to have. </p>
      <p>If your natal puberty left you unable to pass as your identified gender, you also have to go through life looking extremely strange in a highly-stigmatized and highly-politicized way. You may be treated as a sex pervert or assumed to be a prostitute. You may have trouble getting hired outside Blue Tribe meccas. You may be treated badly by strangers. Given the opportunity to avert this bad outcome, <em>in someone who would have developed dysphoria no matter what</em>, I would move heaven and earth.</p>
      <p>In a perfect world, I'd recommend treating hormonally if gender dysphoria is still persistent <em>once</em> natal puberty begins--e.g., once breast buds appear or testicular enlargement begins. If present at this point, gender dysphoria rarely resolves itself, according to the studies we have (admittedly a few years old at this point, with a relatively small sample size (e.g., Steensma, Biemond, de Boer, &amp; Cohen-Kettenis, 2011)). The first six months of natal puberty do not make anyone [citation needed] completely unable to pass. The changes are subtle at first, albeit not reversible. If the kid is incredibly distressed about breast buds or bigger testicles, expresses clear cross-sex identification (and has done so for an extended period of time), and seems to be getting worse, not better, yeah, give low-dose hormones under close supervision. If the new hormones make the situation worse, not better--not an unheard-of outcome, even in adults--discontinue and go back to natal puberty. (I'd be more cautious with this in putative FTMs. Voice drop can be fast and hard to reverse. Mine happened within a few weeks.)</p>
      <p>(continued in next comment)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>