<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-02-07T22:54:03Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fguac31/</link>
  <title>The Democratic Primary Candidates</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Right now, a major strategic mistake I see the Democratic coalition making is framing the political spectrum largely in economic terms, and dismissing the social/cultural axis as essentially non-negotiable moral truths. My impression is that Coville gets this, while almost all other commentators miss it.</p>
      <p>What I mean by this is that if you look at the way candidates are described, you see people framing Sanders as a leftist, Warren as a progressive/leftist, and Buttigieg and Biden as centrists. But if you break down their social views, every single one has committed to the idea that the US should have essentially <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abortion_law#Europe">the least restrictive abortion laws in the world</a>, with federal funding provided and no restrictions up until birth. Every one of them is on board with the idea that trans rights are the civil rights battle of our time. They all agree that white nationalism and structural racism are critical present-day issues in the United States. So on, so forth. While a economic policy disagreement is allowed, social/cultural disagreement is mostly seen as a closed question.</p>
      <p>You see this if you dive into the various political subs. <a href="/r/neoliberal">/r/neoliberal</a> is the most visible subreddit cheering for the "centrists," and their tagline is "Woke Capitalism." They're serious about it, too. My impression is that they'd agree with <a href="/r/chapotraphouse">/r/chapotraphouse</a> on the vast majority of social issues, but one becomes leftist and the other centrist based on questions like Medicare For All, wealth tax, free college, trade deals, or issues like rent control. Which still leaves room for a <em>massive</em> amount of animosity between the two coalitions, as seen with the mutual hatred of each others' preferred candidates. Online Sanders supporters draw heavily from the idpol crowd, but because he focuses almost everything into the language of class struggle, it leaves room for anti-idpol Marxist places like <a href="/r/stupidpol">/r/stupidpol</a> to support him because he's the candidate most in line with Marxism.</p>
      <p>Here's where things get interesting for me, returning to the question of abortion--again, <a href="https://www.politico.com/2020-election/candidates-views-on-the-issues/health-care/abortion-contraception/">a settled question among the Democratic candidates</a>--as a test case. <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/246278/abortion-trends-party.aspx">30 percent of Democrats and 44 percent of independents identify as pro-life</a>. Only 40% of Democrats think abortion should be legal under every circumstance, and only 24% of independents think the same. That's a massive amount of disagreement for an issue that's not even on the table for a single candidate, an issue that will get you downvoted out of any online left space. Or take the reaction to Joe Rogan's endorsement of Bernie Sanders: in both liberal and leftist spaces online, most of them condemned Rogan as transphobic, with the anti-Sanders crowd using it as an indicator of his unfitness while the pro-Sanders crowd largely focused on the idea that while he's bigoted, you need to build a broad coalition.</p>
      <p>That may be where the centrist's dilemma comes in. If someone is further right socially than the Democratic Party and they prioritize social issues, they're simply not going to be represented by any current candidate. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/30/opinion/sunday/bernie-sanders.html">Ross Douthat agrees with you</a> in making a conservative case for Sanders on those grounds:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>This is why, despite technically preferring a moderate like Biden or Amy Klobuchar, I keep coming back to the conservative’s case for Bernie — which rests on the perhaps-wrong but still attractive supposition that he’s the liberal most likely to spend all his time trying to tax the rich and leave cultural conservatives alone.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It's the closest I've come to being comfortable with the idea of a Sanders presidency. I'm still deeply uncomfortable with it since he's made it clear that anything resembling compromise or bipartisanship is anathema to him, I feel like he'll only accelerate mutual antagonism and polarization in the country, and his campaign strikes me as more willing to lie for political advantage than most others in the race, but I can see the case. </p>
      <p>In my own case, it's pretty clear to me at this point that my relationship with leftism will largely be an antagonistic one, even though I share many of their goals, because their cultural approach clashes so completely with my own. The example of Buttigieg actually exemplifies this: I started listening to him early on and got really excited because he was framing progressive policy in a moderate, thoughtful way, and highlighting issues I cared a lot about that other candidates were skimming over. This was before the online progressive movement turned against him, so I was excited to have an area of crossover appeal. Then many of the same things that drew me to him--his moderate rhetoric, his wariness towards unproven large changes, his push to find and make progress on issues with broad consensus among Americans--ended up turning online progressives almost entirely against him (including, in a fascinating twist, every online LGBT community I've seen). When I resigned myself to a candidate rather further culturally left than I am, in other words, leftists broadly turned against him and I was left no more in line with them than I originally was.</p>
      <p>Returning to the original point: no candidate is an obvious choice for people misaligned with the social/cultural left, because every candidate embraces the social/cultural left and seeks to distinguish themselves on other grounds. This means that people in that boat who intend to vote Democrat end up needing to decide largely along other axes. Carville seems rather conscious of this dynamic, and the way it threatens even the "centrists" in the race, in a way that most commentators have ignored.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>