<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-02-08T13:36:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f0omax/on_pseudointellectualism_in_this_community/fgx4m0l/</link>
  <title>Reinventing the Wheel</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>In the spirit of engaging with the literature on topics, I'll bring in a couple of quotes that have been kicking around my mind.</p>
      <p>The first is from the book of Ecclesiastes, written some 2500 years ago:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>All the rivers run into the sea; yet the sea is not full; unto the place from whence the rivers come, thither they return again. ...</p>
        <p>The thing that hath been, it is that which shall be; and that which is done is that which shall be done: and there is no new thing under the sun.</p>
        <p>Is there any thing whereof it may be said, See, this is new? it hath been already of old time, which was before us.</p>
        <p>There is no remembrance of former things; neither shall there be any remembrance of things that are to come with those that shall come after.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The second, briefer quote is from C. S. Lewis:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Even in literature and art, no man who bothers about originality will ever be original: whereas if you simply try to tell the truth (without caring twopence how often it has been told before) you will, nine times out of ten, become original without ever having noticed it.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I bring these up to underscore that the history of human thinking is much longer than the history of academic literature, and because I believe that the same issues pop up again and again in parallel scenarios, under slightly different names. In other words, engaging with the literature is worthwhile, but the literature you refer to didn't invent these ideas, only express them in a form specific to their time. To give a tangible example to hang this on, take this summary of liberal arts versus practical education a friend pointed me towards:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"I believe that the teachers who are skilled in disputation and those who are occupied with astronomy and geometry and studies of that sort do not injure but, on the contrary, benefit their pupils, not so much as they profess, but more than others give them credit for. Most men see in such studies nothing but empty talk and hair-splitting; for none of these disciplines has any useful application either to private or to public affairs; nay, they are not even remembered for any length of time after they are learned because they do not attend us through life nor do they lend aid in what we do, but are wholly divorced from our necessities. But I am neither of this opinion nor am I far removed from it; rather <strong>it seems to me both that those who hold that this training is of no use in practical life are right and that those who speak in praise of it have truth on their side</strong>. </p>
        <p>If there is a contradiction in this statement, it is because these disciplines are different in their nature from the other studies which make up our education; for the other branches avail us only after we have gained a knowledge of them, whereas these studies can be of no benefit to us after we have mastered them unless we have elected to make our living from this source, and only help us while we are in the process of learning. For while we are occupied with the subtlety and exactness of astronomy and geometry and are forced to apply our minds to difficult problems, and are, in addition, being habituated to speak and apply ourselves to what is said and shown to us, and not to let our wits go wool-gathering, <strong>we gain the power, after being exercised and sharpened on these disciplines, of grasping and learning more easily and more quickly those subjects which are of more importance and of greater value</strong>."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I bring this up because there is a <em>massive</em> amount of literature on the question of liberal arts versus vocational training and a web of related topics (<a href="http://rapidintellect.com/AEQweb/5192NEW.pdf">eg</a>), but the conversation returns, time and again, to this point. That was from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isocrates">Isocrates</a>, in the fifth century B.C. We've been going in circles since then.</p>
      <p>Returning to your specific examples--say, critiques of capitalism. Anywhere with a market becomes a test case for that. As a kid, I played a lot on the virtual pet website Neopets, a place with an unusually robust economy. You got to see all sorts of patterns of scarcity, wealth concentration, inflation, status goods, monopolization, on and on and on. It's hardly unique in this regard. You can hop in anywhere with a market and start seeing a lot of what plays out in various scenarios, and many of the same patterns will repeat themselves time and again. Marx was uniquely influential in framing the terms of the conversation, but he didn't have insight unattainable elsewhere, and his critiques didn't manage to attain a perfection or clarity impossible to achieve without reference to him.</p>
      <p>And with toxic masculinity: queer and feminist theory didn't invent the topic, and they don't have a monopoly on it. People have been talking about and experiencing those topics for thousands of years, with plenty of thinkers throughout world history approaching the issue in their own ways. More, they don't have control over how the idea is used in practice out in the world, and people who have never engaged with that slice of literature still get plenty of opportunities to see how the ideas are expressed in the wild.</p>
      <p>There are some academic topics where it's vital to engage with the academic work done. In math, for example, you're wasting your time if you try to derive everything from scratch. It's a system worked out rigorously from first principles, and if you try to barge in ignorant of what's been done, you end up looking like <a href="https://dacemirror.sci-hub.tw/journal-article/dc7eb749153c71af843eb2c9b800cbf5/boston1995.pdf">Marilyn vos Savant trying to refute a proof of Fermat's Last Theorem</a>. </p>
      <p>Systems built to analyze human behavior, in contrast, are full of black boxes and observational research. Ideas are reproduced in slightly different form from one field to another all the time. A dozen different models are built to explain the same phenomenon, all of them addressing similar issues in parallel, and if you get too in the weeds with one specific model and reify it in a way similar to what's been done in math, you'll end up missing the important ways people have engaged with the topic outside that model and maintaining dangerous blind spots in the areas that model is weak.</p>
      <p>I raise all this not to say that people shouldn't engage with the academic literature on these topics, but to say that people shouldn't be required to absorb one specific subset of human thought (modern Western academia) to engage on these topics, nor should they be limited to discussing these topics only after accepting the premises inherent in that subset. Human issues have been analyzed and discussed as long as there have been humans, and we've been saying more or less the same things that whole time, just emphasizing different bits and providing different window dressing. The risk of engaging only in the way you suggest is that you'll end up privileging and reifying the perspectives of a specific subset of theorizers, talking yourself in circles around those perspectives.</p>
      <p>To give a tangible example of <em>that</em>, see my comment on <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/e4u7a6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_02/f9ndx88/">Drunk Mormon Hypotheses</a>, where people end up so convinced by one particular framework of the world that they end up coming to wildly wrong conclusions even when the accurate data is in front of their faces. Maintaining a wide variety of discussion <em>outside</em> any specific framework, even as you discuss ideas that have percolated out into common thought from that framework, is a good check against that.</p>
      <p>There's also the reality that ideas that win societal influence aren't the most inherently truthful ideas, they're the most durable and persuasive ideas. You only have to look at the history of religion to see that. While a few people are in a corner crafting theory, some snake oil–selling charlatan can spring to the top of the bestseller list and <a href="https://medium.com/@Soccermatics/how-swedes-were-fooled-by-one-of-the-biggest-scientific-bluffs-of-our-time-de47c82601ad">influence popular thought for decades</a> (or millennia) to come. Worse, those can themselves change the direction of academia. See <a href="https://www.psychologicalscience.org/news/releases/learning-styles-debunked-there-is-no-evidence-supporting-auditory-and-visual-learning-psychologists-say.html">the sordid history of learning styles</a> for that. There's no substitute for engagement with great thinkers, but engaging with one specific framework is neither necessary nor sufficient to allow someone to take part meaningfully in conversations about the underlying ideas.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>