<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-06-09T11:41:02Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/nu5kvj/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_07_2021/h153k9m/</link>
  <title>Culture of a Grander, Greater, More Beautiful Future</title>
  <category>
    <li>flux</li>
    <li>media</li>
  </category>
  <context>
    <p>Maybe this is proper. But Sci-fi is about creating new visions. At least trying to.</p>
    <p>What makes it so hard to come up with one celebrating humanity?</p>
    <p>What prevents someone like Thiel or Andreessen from funding a <a href="https://a16z.com/2020/04/18/its-time-to-build/">«Cultures that build»</a> Sci-fi contest?</p>
  </context>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Great post.</p>
      <p>I find Thiel and Andreesen, and really all of Silicon Valley <strong>utterly vulgar</strong>. To be a culture that builds you need to be a culture, and being a culture requires its own conception of beauty.</p>
      <p>You said when I lamented the pitiful state of Charedi art and architecture that they find the beauty in liturgy, tradition, music, conformity and so on, and are probably correct! Meanwhile, the progressive left appear to find some kind of beauty in diversity, sanctimoniousness in general, <em>Disney's Marvel's Black Panther</em> and pride parades (or whatever, I'm not really sure). But this libertarian/liberal centrist faction, who want desperately to build spaceships and ignite a startup revolution, what's their beauty? I don't think it's technology, in the sense of those Toyota engineers who 'worshipped' fast machines in the JCPA piece you link. Musk and even Zuckerberg have their supporters, but nobody is writing essays on the beauty of the Instagram 'discover' page algorithm, and if they are nobody's reading them. Sure, cars can be beautiful, but people who say this are usually referring to <a href="https://cdn.thegentlemansjournal.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/car-TGJ.06.jpg">this</a> (sorry car fans, I googled 'most beautiful car ever' and picked one), not <a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/b0/2020_Tesla_Model_Y%2C_front_8.1.20.jpg/1200px-2020_Tesla_Model_Y%2C_front_8.1.20.jpg">this</a>.</p>
      <p>Once again the lack of any interest in working or living in beautiful places shines though. This <a href="https://www.trustnodes.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/andreessen-horowitz-offices.jpg">dishevelled little shithole</a>, which looks like a dilapidated Swiss holiday home in a third-tier resort frequented by middle-class Germans, is apparently the headquarters of Andreessen Horowitz, that engine of technological modernity and people 'who build', currently managing $17bn. The <a href="https://vancebrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/Vance_Brown_AdreessenHorowitz_Office_8.jpg">inside</a> looks like the lobby of a budget cruise ship last refurbished in 1998. Back in the early 20th century when newspapers were among the most profitable businesses in San Francisco (and indeed anywhere), they built grand (perhaps a little kitschy, but it was the style) buildings like <a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/ba/Detroit_Photographic_Company_%280041%29.jpg/220px-Detroit_Photographic_Company_%280041%29.jpg">this</a>. In the late 1920s, at the zenith of Wall Street's biggest boom, banks built palatial art deco headquarters that are <a href="https://dmdlnu87i51n1.cloudfront.net/v1/uk/cjy8utkrx4ihk0195og8xarkg/0x0:2500x2328/960x960/onewallstreet4.jpg">still beautiful today.</a>. Today, venture capital is the most profitable industry in San Francisco, and yet its most successful businesses, which preach about "cultures that build" are reduced to environments of abject mediocrity. </p>
      <p>Science fiction is about aesthetics. Those grand Soviet (and, once upon a time, even American) visions of the future were aesthetically epic, aesthetic indeed above all else. The majesty of <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/ENEAwVVXsAIsAHh.jpg">this</a>, or <a href="https://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/soviet-futurism-03.jpg?w=1920&amp;ssl=1">this</a> is (from Tekhikia, apparently), is what captures idealism about the future. You won't have a culture that builds unless you convince them of a grander, greater, more beautiful future - and that starts with people like Andreesen and Thiel building beautiful things of their own.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>