<post>
  <author>CPlusPlusDeveloper</author>
  <date>2020-02-11T07:00:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f1lmga/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_10/fhacfyg/</link>
  <title>Education Policy Budgeting</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>In other developed economies, child care, early education, and higher education</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You don't have to turn to European examples. Florida, which has had a Republican governor and legislature for a quarter of a century is one of only three states with free universal free pre-K. It also has the lowest in-state college tuition (average $6300) in the union. UF (the seventh highest ranked public university) has a nearly identical average tuition. 39% of Florida university students (based on GPA+SAT merit) have free tuition.</p>
      <p>The point is that cheap comprehensive education is achievable without Bernie-style mass Federal programs. Even without any state income tax, Florida still manages to land closer to the author's European ideal than deep blue states like California or Illinois.</p>
      <p>So where does this supposedly free lunch come from? The answer is budget discipline with regards to public sector employees. Florida compensates public sector employees, in particular educators, much less than blue state equivalents. Salary differences are significant, but the real chasm is benefits and pensions. Blue states are politically dominated by powerful public sector unions. The unions manage to suck up nearly all excess fiscal resources. Nor do blue states appear to get better educators for all that spending. Adjusted for demographics, <a href="https://www.vox.com/2015/10/26/9617514/test-scores-naep-2013">Florida and Texas</a> outrank the NAEP scores of all but two blue states.</p>
      <p>We can have Finnish style education and childcare. The first step is to adopt Finnish salaries for teachers. That's going to mean American teachers take <a href="https://data.oecd.org/teachers/teachers-salaries.htm">an average 33% pay cut</a>. Blue state teachers even more so. And that's not even taking benefits into account.</p>
      <p>The reason the push for this is on the federal, not state, level is because blue states want to have their cake and eat it too. They want these programs funded by federal revenues so they don't have to make politically difficult budget reforms. Instead red states are expected to pick up the tab.</p>
      <p>It also reveals that most people advocating for this don't really care so much about actually achieving these policy goals. If they did it'd be much easier to make the reforms at the state level. Instead these types of opinions serve as intellectual fashion. The typical Elizabeth Warren voter in Santa Barbara gets much more social mileage from bemoaning that "America needs to be more like Scandinavia". If they changed their tune to "California needs to be more like Florida", they'd probably find themselves not invited back to book club.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>