<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-02-11T05:13:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f1lmga/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_10/fha5t1z/</link>
  <title>Estimated Effect Of The Coronavirus</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Essentially the “hard” orders of magnitude have already been crossed by the Corona virus. 10s if not 100s of thousands have been infected (the long asymptomatic incubation period means you can pretty-much multiply the official number by 3-5) and a thousand people have already died. </p>
      <p>That may sound a far way off from the prediction, but when you think of an exponential process 1 to 1000 death  or 1 to 10,000 infected is actually the same distance as 1000 to 1,000,000 dead or 10,000 to 100,000,000 infected.</p>
      <p>If corona virus was going to flair out or slow down before it got huge that would have to be apparent by now. It takes the same amount of time to go from 3k to 30k to 300k to 3mil. So we’re going to see at-least a few more orders of magnitude (especially with the 2-4 week incubation delay) before we can even see in the data if the quarantines are having an effect.</p>
      <p>Thunderfoot had a good video on just how finicky minor variables can be that would swing a exponential viral spread from nothing that flairs out to reaches 80% plus of all humans. Its just that crazy variable.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Also base-rate we average a super plague every 50ish years. Spanish Flu in 1918, AIDS in the 80s, ect. Now That one in 50 years plague will unavoidably be one of the every 5 year panic diseases we have (SARs, Swine Flu, Ebola, ect.) because those panics are false alarms for the 50 year plague (which you can’t miss if its happening).</p>
      <p>So just base rate every 5 year Scare should have a 10% chance of being comparably deadly to AIDS.</p>
      <p>But Coronavirus is a uniquely likely candidate since its already blasted through the bench marks set by those other panics. Coronavirus has already, in its first 2 months, killed more people than SARS ever did in its entire 6 month plus run (and remember the later months are the deadliest) and really only Ebola has had comparable casualty figures amongst the panics. But Ebola was a known quantity, we knew Ebola couldn’t really spread with any significance within the first world due to its transmission vector (blood and bodies, ect.), the fear was it would still manage to wipe out significant numbers of third worlders, which limited it even more since thirdworlders can’t really transmit between each others populations without a 2nd or 1st worlder transplanting it (very few poor Liberian villagers vacation in south america).</p>
      <p>Coronavirus by contrast can spread via simple coughs and surfaces, might be “airborn” for some non-technical value of the phrase, and has already blown past the metrics of most all the other panics since AIDS.</p>
      <p>If we assume the base rate will continue with one highly deadly plague every 50 years, then there might be 2 or 3 viruses/infections in that entire span that are as likely a candidate as Coronavirus, thus a 33-50 percent chance its Coronavirus.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>As for PRC. collapse, i clarified that i think “simply” losing Hong Kong or one or two provinces in more likely, but collapse is really probable. Modern Empires have lifespans that are measured in decades. A few like America or the British Empire manage to stretch a few centuries but notably those were the ones with really slow takeoffs (arguably America wasn’t a major empire til 1916, and didn’t reach its stable extent til 1945ish).</p>
      <p>The closest possible comparison to China: the Soviet Union, lasted 70ish years. For a base-rate to collapse of slightly more than 1.5% per year.</p>
      <p>However not every year is born equal, looking back the most likely times for the soviet empire to collapse were the initial civil war years to the the death of Lenin 1918-1924, the embarrassment of the winter war and Hitlers invasion 1940-43, the death of Stalin 1953-54, The Cuban Missile crisis to the Prague Spring 64-69(this actually sank Kruschev), and Chernobyl to its collapse 1986-91. So there were about 20ish individual years when it was vastly more likely, due to events ect. When a collapse was very plausible! And if we assume long term trend-lines also play a large predictive factor we could probably rule out the death of Stalin(theyd just won a war), thepost civil war early years (same), and maybe even the 60s (the soviet citizens were the least likely to die in a purge they’d ever been) so that would leave 10ish years were a collapse was shocking likely: the civil war, early WW2, and when it did. </p>
      <p>All three times when the government explicitly declared their war footing both literally or metaphorically or both (Chernobyl and Afghanistan were contemporaries)</p>
      <p>If we model instability as following a power law (which I do: multifactorial, unpredictable, finicky, ect.) then those 10 years might have been as likely to end in soviet collapse as All the other years combined which again civil war, ww2, when it did, ya! Sounds right. So odds of about 5+% per year in those 10 dangerous years.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>The CCP has already explicitly stated Coronavirus is “war conditions”, Hong Kong was already revolting when it struck, it could go catastrophically bad just from the virology, the quarantines have already wiped out this years growth in 1 month, Chinese citizens are comparing it to Chernobyl, they were in the midst of a trade war already, and all that on top of China’s notorious shadow banking/economic stability issues, long term demographic issues coming to ahead this decade,  and legitimacy issues resulting from increasing failures to deliver either liberties or the meteoric growth Chinese citizens have become used to.</p>
      <p>This would certainly place it within the PRC’s top 20 dangerous years over its 70 year, it very likely places it within its top 10 dangerous years.</p>
      <p>So that would get us to 15-25% over the next 3-5 years, and the extra percentage is my bias, i see Chinese people increasingly resistant and a Communist regime that looks increasingly spent and removed from the Revolutionary madness that could keep it going. They’re still brutal psychopaths, but i think most of the middle party members are looking for the exits and would be happy to let it go if they could guarantee a safe transition for themselves. It really looks like the soviet union during Chernobyl to me.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>