<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2020-02-10T06:49:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f1lmga/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_10/fh76uqb/</link>
  <title>The USCT at Petersburg</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I just realized that it’s Black History Month. Ordinarily I would not care, per se, but it <em>does</em> mean that I finally have an excuse to share one of my favorite Civil War stories! I’m excited. If you aren’t excited, get excited. It’s historical anecdote time!</p>
      <p>
        <strong>
          <em>PART ONE</em>
        </strong>
      </p>
      <p>So. Let’s set the stage. It’s 1864 and the tide has finally turned in the favor of the Union. After a frankly embarrassing run of flopped invasions of Virginia, the North finally got their shit together. Lee was finally on the back foot after all this time, after his failed counterinvasion led to the disaster at Gettysburg. The Union conquest of Vicksburg just days after that battle had also cut the Confederacy two.</p>
      <p>When Grant took his Army of the Potomac down south for yet another push onto Richmond, Lee did his trademark bold counterattack to stymie the Union advance. He picked a fight in the Wilderness, where the Northern advantage in cannon and numbers would be blunted. The fight was a bloody draw, but unlike every other commander who tangled with Lee, Grant didn’t get unnerved and skedaddle home. Grant was something new in the Eastern theater- a force of nature that could not be intimidated or psyched out or outfought. Grant intended to end the war this very year in one massive climactic battle. He was positive that the Army of the Potomac- superior now in training, in numbers, in supplies- could beat the Army of Northern Virginia in a straight fight.</p>
      <p>Lee could read Grant like a book. He could read every enemy general like a book, that’s how he has gotten so far on so little. The problem here is that he could see the hammer blow coming and knew he couldn’t block it. So he denied Grant his big apocalyptic battle. He delayed, skirmished, retreated, dugs into defensive trench lines... the old way of gallant charges into prepared positions have long since been proven pointless. Early in the war, the Richmond papers mocked Lee for entrenching Richmond like a coward; with Grant coming south like a juggernaut, no one was mocking him now. Grant never flung his soldiers against Lee’s trench lines because he knows it’d be a meat grinder, so the campaign bogged down into a slow paced chess game as Grant tried to maneuver around Lee’s defenses to force him into an open field, and Lee repositioned to avoid being trapped.</p>
      <p>It’s frustrating, galling, maddening. The bleak war of attrition wrecked morale on both sides. That is Lee’s only hope- maybe the Northern will to fight will finally be sapped as the casualties rack up in yet another bloody year. Maybe they’ll come to the negotiating table, and <em>de facto</em> independence might end up <em>de jure</em> independence. It’s a dicey proposition, because Southern will to fight is possibly even shakier than their opponents’ is.</p>
      <p>Our grand narrative starts in Petersburg, Virginia. Petersburg has a ton of trains and railways and can keep Richmond supplied during the siege. No army on the planet could hold a city like Richmond if their back door supply route was taken. Grant pushes to take the city and Lee matches him almost man for man, and the two armies hunker down into opposing trench lines that anticipat the static lines of WW1 by about 50 years.</p>
      <p>A Union engineer named Henry Pleasants takes one look at a Confederate strongpoint along the line, takes another look at the local dirt composition, and develops a plan so cunning you could brush your teeth with it. He had been a demolition man for a railroad company before the war; he knew explosives and digging inside and out. He figured he could plow right through the dirt under the Confederate feet and stack up a bomb to blow a hole in the line.</p>
      <p>Pleasants pitches his idea to his immediate boss, General Burnside (his facial hair is exactly as amazing as you are imagining it). He got approved and immediately starts digging away. Now, the the emplacement of the mine would take a couple of weeks. The tunnel’s construction alone was a minor miracle- only Pleasants’ mastery of the laws of physics allowed him to conquer issue after issue as they arose. But that’s background stuff.</p>
      <p>The focus here (being, if you’ll recall, Black History Month) is the small division of USCT soldiers that was selected to pour through the gap once the bomb went off. The United States Colored Troops were fresh fish, barely been in the war so far because it took awhile for the North to overcome its anti-black-people-carrying-guns gag reflex and allow ex slaves to fight. They’d been used for camp labor, of course, but never as front line infantry. This fight would be their crucible.</p>
      <p>Their division is two brigades strong- one brigade goes left around the coming crater, the other goes right. They train for the fight, memorizing which company takes what position, prepping their ladders to get out of the trenches fast. Every soldier drills himself so that on the day of everything will move like clockwork.</p>
      <p>But there are two problems in play here. The first problem is named General John Pegram. The second problem is named General Ambrose Burnside.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>