<post>
  <author>regan-regan</author>
  <date>2020-02-08T20:07:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fgzanx0/</link>
  <title>Lower-class Perceptions of Social Programms</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think you're misunderstanding Carville's point which is a value-coded frustration, so you think I'm on some tangent-- like I'm answering your math question with a poem....</p>
      <p>Well, yes, sort of.</p>
      <p>I am trying to use words to explain something that's embodied and super visceral,'you know it when you feel it" to readers who are not picking up this wavelength.</p>
      <p>It's not wonky results-oriented thinking ---it's automatic unconscious value coding that makes Carville facepalm as the Dems fail the most simple value-loaded questions which sound super bloody obvious to "normal people"...</p>
      <p>Carville and I and every one who had blue-collar experiences imprinted in them at a formative time is automatically hyper-vigilant to anything that reminds them of experiences with Bottom/underclass.</p>
      <p>It's like some social-wisdom-traumatic-residue that's with you for life.</p>
      <p>I wrote a big description of the underclass im talking about but it honestly started sounding evil lol-- contempt is hard to reason with even within oneself.</p>
      <p>Everyone who has ever lived in a city has had their issues and close calls and just total paradigm shifting conversations from contact with all sorts of human trash, real and perceived-- the gutter chaos we can't seem to fully quarantine away from the 'useful and normal' folks who follow the rules.</p>
      <p>Associations with this underclass are SO vivid for lots of blue-collar people (because the gross, criminal, crazy and lazy all compete for the same affordable neighborhoods, same public spaces like parks and libraries and streets you have to walk on way back from nightshift, same fill-out-this-form govt waitrooms that you take your grandma or disabled uncle to. Everyone looks around and mentally decides 'who should be here' and who's scamming/mooching/reason we can't have nice things)</p>
      <p>Govt programs that help the underclass are coded with scorn, pity, or total revulsion. These MUST be under a different umbrella or they will be seen as a cancer invited to destroy the good things the middle class built.</p>
      <p>Look at another example that set Carville off, 'so should the boston bomber be able to vote from prison?'</p>
      <p>As he said, saying anything but a clear and unwavering version of 'fuck that scumbag' is viscerally UNACCEPTABLE to a normal person.</p>
      <p>like WTF, are you for real? Do you even human? That's why Carville is fuming.</p>
      <p>Do they not realize how THATS the visual now imprinted whenever a dem says 'prison reform,' and thats the preposterous hypothetical your cousin will bring up at dinner...</p>
      <p>Trump AlWAYS has the correct emotional response to underclass questions like that... He just expresses scorn for the correct types of people at the right times, that's all. That is why he makes sense to the working class, no matter how rich he is.</p>
      <p>If you despise the right things, your head must be screwed on straight, and all the rest is noise.</p>
      <p>A few emotionally charged hypotheticals like that re-code practically everything the Dems say in the election....</p>
      <p>------------------</p>
      <p>Last night I heard Bernie and Warren list coverage for Mental Health and Addiction, every college student liberal nodded along in approval because of course that sounds good, and are very important timely issues!</p>
      <p>The 80% of me that is identifies 'college student liberalism' totally agrees!</p>
      <p>BUT the other part of me cringed knowing election time, every blue collar person watching tv will not hear those word and think of their depressive 20-something kid home from community college with no insurance, or their brother in law with pill problems after knee surgery.  They thought of the psychotic dirtbags claiming disability in the same line and all the homeless scary junkies that every bone-tired healthcare worker has seen waste Emergency Room resources, reeking of piss and scaring the female nurses they outweigh and tower over.</p>
      <p>This tired voter person is Everyone who takes public transportation to work that has to have their brain tuned to automatically "gauge stranger's worth and status and mental state" at all times for safety.</p>
      <p>Maybe for hardcore Republicans the underclass looks like Mexican immigrants, I don't know I'm not in Texas lol. For most everyone I know in real life that's vaguely democrat or not really political / "can't-be-bothered but my friends and kids all say I should vote"... it's variations on urban detritus, crime, corruption, mooching narratives, resentment for the daily that-was-almost-an-incident perpetual stress.</p>
      <p>If these normals are always hearing the Dems rhetorically welcome the underclass into more and more of their spaces to share services and get to feel themselves of equal worth... well, that value equivalency is absolutely repulsive to lots of normal people. "X thing for all!" to a normal person just means you are forcibly including even more parasitic lowlifes to water down very strained resources, inviting more corruption, less quality for everyone that counts.</p>
      <p>To many it will seem utterly illogical-- under the new medicare, EVERYONE can get the help they need! Or education, college for ALL! etc</p>
      <p>
        <strong>This "I love Everyone" compassion is what makes Carville spaz, this rhetoric is what he KNOWS does not compute with the experience of people out in the world who all feel different from each other and are comparing/contrasting their shares of social value at all moments.</strong>
      </p>
      <p>A working class person does not EXISTENTIALLY believe in an uncompartmentalized "ALL Welcome" thing for even one second-- everything has a cost and <strong>somehow they're always the ones who have to share</strong> space and resources and continue to stay exhaustively situationally aware at all times.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>