<post>
  <author>Shakesneer</author>
  <date>2020-02-10T20:04:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f1lmga/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_10/fh8q4hd/</link>
  <title>Multigenerational Projects</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It took hundreds of years to build the Notre Dame Cathedral. I would be ok with it taking hundreds of years, again, as long as the building remained a holy sanctuary with an aesthetic beauty meant as devotion to God. In secular terms -- I don't want the church to end up looking like an ugly sore of Brutalism or a bent nail of modern architecture stabbing at the heart of an icon. If that's what billionaires want, I'm glad not to use their money.</p>
      <p>I often dwell, actually, on the idea that these beautiful cathedrals took decades and centuries to build. Do we have that commitment in modern life? Imagine the shared sacrifice and vision it takes to construct a building over the course of generations, knowing that it won't be complete in your lifetime but may be richer for it. We supposedly have so much money and prosperity and happiness today, but I don't see this kind of purpose. The closest analogue I can think of are scientific projects -- we mostly accept that sequencing genomes or satellite programs are achieving only intermediary steps we may not fully realize. That's what the moon landing was for Kennedy. And I do wonder what this mindset would look like in other fields, a century-old computer program, a nutrition study of one hundred generations. But most of all I wonder what we could do for the arts. Imagine what beautiful spaces we could build if we spent fifty years lavishly constructing and decorating. Some of our cities have this quality, though very few have any consistent long-term vision, and living in the city can be an ugly experience anyways. Still Manhattan is rightly classed as one of the wonders of the world for sheer density of building, and Charleston has managed to preserve a real color on its streets. I wish we had more of this vision in our public affairs -- it would be a better monument to posterity. When so much modern construction is rightly swept aside as trash no one will remember who paid for it. But the will and determination of a people to see the project through many generations can never be forgotten in the same way.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>