<post>
  <author>Vortex_God</author>
  <date>2020-02-10T03:18:03Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f144vl/smallscale_question_sunday_for_the_week_of/fh6s0qo/</link>
  <title>The Innovations Of The XFL</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This second iteration of the XFL is quite different from the failed original. This is now intended as a league for NFL fans who want even more exciting games rather than a sideshow attraction for viewers who weren’t football fans already. Gone are all the Pro Wrestling trappings, no more manufactured storylines or provocative seediness. Vince McMahon’s company may own the league but he hired real football professionals to administer and shape the product on the field. The XFL took two years from its announcement to put a product on the field, compared to the recently failed AAF which begin roughly 9 months after its own founding and folded before the season even finished due to financial issues.</p>
      <p>The primary selling points of XFL 2.0 are speed of play, fewer meaningless plays, officiating transparency, and innovative rules. Much of what I’m about to discuss is succinctly presented here: <a href="https://youtu.be/UCRwd0WdC74">https://youtu.be/UCRwd0WdC74</a> and here <a href="https://ftw.usatoday.com/2020/02/xfl-rule-differences-explained">https://ftw.usatoday.com/2020/02/xfl-rule-differences-explained</a></p>
      <p>One fan gripe with the NFL is that the games can drag on for too long. In the NFL the Offense has a 40 second countdown to begin a play or face a penalty. Teams usually take full advantage of the countdown to communicate plays and observe the opposing team, or strategically run down the game clock to deny their opponent playtime. In the XFL this has been reduced to 25 seconds to keep the game moving. This may also have the effect of keeping the XFL teams on their toes as they have less time to set up and shift players. Or it could tire players more quickly and lead to play breakdowns that the other team could take advantage of. Halftime is 10 minutes rather than 30 minutes in the NFL, and teams get two timeouts each half rather than three each half. Other small tweaks such as a designated ball spotter have been implemented to keep the game moving quickly.</p>
      <p>Another NFL issue is plays that always end up with a similar result, resulting in little excitement for spectators. After a touchdown in the NFL a kicker can get 1 extra point by kicking a field goal from the 15 yard line, or the team’s offense can attempt another touchdown from the 2 yard line to get 2 extra points. Because the 1-point kick conversion is currently at a 93.9% success rate few teams “go for 2” unless absolutely necessary to catch up to an opponent. Even fans watching live in their stadium rarely muster the cheering energy to disrupt an opposing team’s kicker on 1-point conversions since missing is so rare. In the XFL after a touchdown a 1-point try will be run from the 2-yard line, a 2-point try will start at the 5-yard line, and a 3-point try will start at the 10-yard line. So there’s more risk/reward and uncertainty after a touchdown as coaches choose how many points they want to attempt. There certainly won’t be a 94% success rate, even on the 1 point try.</p>
      <p>Without going into too complicated of an explanation: in the NFL the kickoffs after points and the punts on 4th down have become rather routine in their results. The NFL kickoff allows the kicking team too much running momentum for the receiving team to gain many yards, the league average is about 22.5 yards. Which is barely better than intentionally taking a “touchback” where the ball is placed at the 20 yard line if it had fallen dead in the end zone during the kicking play. And most teams are certain to punt on 4th down since receiving teams rarely regain significant yards on the punt return compared to getting the ball at the spot of a failed 4th down running/passing play. Receiving players are also often at risk of being completely clobbered by an opposing player sprinting at them and so call a “fair catch” to stop the play at the spot where they catch the ball and disallow the kicking team to touch them. Boring. The XFL has redone the rules of when the teams can begin running and where the ball is spotted after a touchback in order to encourage more exciting yet safer kick returns and make punts less useful.</p>
      <p>In the NFL there has been an ongoing controversy of bad and inconsistent officiating, sometimes with implications that have reshaped entire playoff scenarios. Different referee crews will take different interpretations of what exactly constitutes a certain penalty. Some referees will simply miss an egregious penalty or give a phantom call on something that didn’t actually happen. And this is often as clear as day on the broadcast replay. Infuriating! Coaches can ransom a timeout to challenge a call and have the referees review, but coaches lose the timeout if they are overruled. And nobody is given an explanation of the referee crew’s thought process, sometimes not even after the game. In the XFL the referee crew’s discussion of a penalty review is broadcasted live, as well as their slow-motion replay machine. Fans see and hear the referee crew's entire thought process. Hopefully this leads to more transparency, and less sore feelings from fans that feel robbed. XFL coaches cannot challenge penalties, which again should keep the game moving.</p>
      <p>Finally, despite the strategic efficiency of running the ball in the NFL it is the passing play that truly excites fans. Especially long and daring throws that pick up a big number of yards. And so the XFL game ball is allegedly thinner to allow easier throwing accuracy. The rules on what constitutes an in-bounds catch have been relaxed to allow receivers to make more daring reaches. And a unique double forward pass rule allows some misdirection and trickery to happen during plays. It’s possible we might see a certain type of double quarterback play emerge where defenses don’t know who will end up throwing the ball downfield.</p>
      <p>As an NFL fan myself I tuned in this weekend to check out the XFL product. I watched one game based on one of the teams being closest to me geographically (though it's still quite far away), and I might watch some highlights of the other games. Ultimately it’s… okay as a product. Certainly a higher level of play than you get on average from college football, but not nearly as polished and explosive as the world-class players on the NFL. I’d say the primary issue is there are only so many great quarterbacks in the world and almost all of them are playing in the NFL. The XFL quarterbacks and receivers I watched in today’s game missed a fair bit of passes that would be almost automatic in the NFL. Ironically it was not a very high scoring game compared to an average NFL game due to player error stalling out drives. So if the XFL wants to be an exciting pass-heavy league it will need to figure out how to elevate the quarterback quality as soon as possible. Until the XFL can reach a stature to rival the NFL (if ever) it will always have to make do with lower tier players. If anything, I’d argue that the XFL should have gotten even wackier with the rule changes to create more unique plays but perhaps that type of gimmickry is what sunk XFL 1.0 in the first place. Time will tell if the XFL product catches on. Americans don’t even bother to tune in to Canadian Football so the XFL is in a weird place. I guess the XFL offers new football teams to certain USA cities and regions that don’t have a nearby NFL franchise? At very least the XFL <a href="https://xflnews.com/dc-defenders/xfl-has-already-sold-more-tickets-than-aaf-did-for-their-entire-season/">has sold more tickets its opening weekend than the AAF in its entire season</a>. But compared to many NFL teams selling out stadiums for every game, there is still a mountain to climb for the XFL to approach the throne.</p>
      <p>And one final thought: What's to stop the NFL from simply observing how these drastic rule changes play out in a full XFL season and then steal the good ideas for themselves? This would undoubtably be good for NFL fans to get an improved product, but potentially disastrous for the XFL's differentiation of their own product. Why watch mediocre football once the innovative rules become standard elsewhere?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>