<post>
  <author>wlxd</author>
  <date>2020-02-09T22:35:16Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fh5d3vv/</link>
  <title>Why People Are Against Obesity</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <em>The biggest arguments against obesity are "I don't like it" and "it causes health problems".</em>
      </p>
      <p>I think you meant the loudest. The biggest argument is not really socially acceptable to express, but it's really quite obvious to everyone, and is really driving the whole discussion, from both sides.</p>
      <p>Here goes: being overweight makes you unattractive, and being obese makes you actually ugly. Everybody knows this, and that's the reason most people don't want to become overweight, not some vague health problems in the far future. Being attractive is extremely important in our society, despite it being very gauche to say it outright. </p>
      <p>On one side, people pushing for "destigmatization" of obesity are doing so precisely to make it less unattractive. The other side doesn't like this, as they see it as blatant gaslighting. However, what you cannot do is to complain about this by saying that this will make people become ugly, or stop them from working on becoming not ugly. This is unacceptable for two reasons: first, since overweight people are everywhere, you can't say that being overweight is unattractive in a polite company, because it will hurt the feelings of overweight people hearing that, and we can't have that. On the other hand, pointing to it's health drawbacks is okay, because it means you care about their well-being. The other is that in a liberal individualist culture of the west, you're not supposed to have anything against other people preferences if they do not affect you -- if they prefer to be fat, or have terrible taste for interior design, it's none of your business. </p>
      <p>Thus, people hang on to bullshit arguments about health. I mean, come on: nobody cares about health that much. People took up smoking mostly because it was fashionable and made you look attractive, and they quit mostly because it was expensive and made you look unattractive once it went out of fashion. Most people who go to the gym don't care about health benefits (and, in my experience, gym people are much more likely to have joint and muscle injuries than couch potatoes). They want to look attractive. Health is just an excuse, and the core issue is people not liking to pretend that things which are ugly and harmful to your well-being are actually fine.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>