<post>
  <author>ZorbaTHut</author>
  <date>2020-02-11T00:42:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f1lmga/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_10/fh9hyk9/</link>
  <title>The Long Tail Of Trying Yourself</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Here's another few takes on this whole thing.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Part 1: A Weird Guy Who Believed In Hidden Messages In The Bible</strong>
      </p>
      <p>There's this guy who was kind of a nutcase and thought he could crack the secrets of the universe. He spent <em>years</em> mucking about with alchemy, trying to unlock the secrets of the Philosopher's Stone and transmute lead into gold. He did not succeed.</p>
      <p>A while after this, he decided that Deep Truths were encoded cryptographically in the Bible. He spent <em>years</em> searching for hidden text in the Bible using all sorts of crazy techniques. He did not succeed in this either.</p>
      <p>Between these futile pursuits, he - I'll quote Wikipedia here - "formulated the laws of motion and universal gravitation that formed the dominant scientific viewpoint until it was superseded by the theory of relativity".</p>
      <p>Isaac Newton was a bit of a nutcase. Most of the big projects he undertook didn't work. The one that worked provided a foundation for physics that lasted centuries.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Part 2: A Small Game Studio Making Totally Irrelevant Games</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Here is the first roughly-half of a specific game studio's released games. Read it in order; tell me at what point you figured out which game studio I'm talking about.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Mole War</li>
        <li>Paid to Kill</li>
        <li>Darkest Fear</li>
        <li>Formula GP Racing</li>
        <li>Playman Winter Games</li>
        <li>War Diary: Burma</li>
        <li>War Diary: Crusader</li>
        <li>War Diary: Torpedo</li>
        <li>Cyber Blood</li>
        <li>Darkest Fear 2: Grim Oak</li>
        <li>Darkest Fear 3: Nightmare</li>
        <li>Desert Sniper</li>
        <li>Need for Speed: Carbon</li>
        <li>US Marine Corps Scout Sniper</li>
        <li>Wolf Moon</li>
        <li>Burnout</li>
        <li>Dragon &amp; Jade</li>
        <li>Marine Sniper</li>
        <li>Patron Angel</li>
        <li>Shopping Madness</li>
        <li>Star Marine</li>
        <li>Sumea Ski Jump</li>
        <li>Bounce Boing Voyage</li>
        <li>Bounce Tales</li>
        <li>Bounce Touch</li>
        <li>Burger Rush</li>
        <li>Collapse Chaos</li>
        <li>Gem Drop Deluxe</li>
        <li>Paper Planes</li>
        <li>SWAT Elite Troops</li>
        <li>Totomi</li>
        <li>X Factor 2008</li>
        <li>Bounce Evolution</li>
        <li>Space Impact: Meteor Shield</li>
        <li>Angry Birds</li>
      </ul>
      <p>It was "Angry Birds", wasn't it? You'd probably never heard of any game before that, except for the games that were spinoffs of more popular games. And I bet what you said was "oh, it's the Angry Birds studio", not "oh, it's Rovio". Rovio is currently worth around 400 million dollars and it's almost entirely thanks to <em>their 51st game</em>. The previous 50 were all pretty crummy.</p>
      <p>You might be saying "that doesn't look like 51 games", and you're right, I couldn't even find a conclusive list of their games before Angry Birds. That's how irrelevant they were. Nobody cared about Rovio, then everyone cared about Rovio.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Part 3: A Guy Who Made Terrible Software</strong>
      </p>
      <p>One day this high-school kid made a startup with the intent of providing reports for traffic engineers. He never got it working well and the company went under. His next project was Microsoft and now Bill Gates is stupidly rich.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>The point I'm making here is that virtually everyone who's massively succeeded at something has also massively failed at something. In fact, I would say that you can roughly divide humanity into three groups:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>People who have neither failed nor succeeded</li>
        <li>People have have both failed and succeeded</li>
        <li>People who have failed, but not succeeded</li>
      </ul>
      <p>But the tough part is that you can actually divide humanity into <em>four</em> groups:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>People who have neither failed nor succeeded</li>
        <li>People have have both failed and succeeded</li>
        <li>People who have failed, but not succeeded</li>
        <li>People who have failed, but not succeeded, but <em>will</em> succeed</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The tough part is that it's impossible to distinguish those latter two groups. But you don't want to discourage people from being in those groups, because almost everyone in the Succeeded group has, at some point, been in the fourth group.</p>
      <p>And that's why I'm a big fan of people throwing away common knowledge and doing their own thing. Because <em>that's how we get phenomenal successes</em>. That's how we get stuff like SpaceX and Amazon and Microsoft and Unix and just a phenomenal number of successful businesses and technologies; someone saying "hrm, I wonder if I can make this better!", and someone else saying "no, you idiot, that's the best way to do it", and the first person saying ". . . nah, I'm gonna try to make this better anyway".</p>
      <p>And most of the time they fail, and most of the people who fail will never actually succeed.</p>
      <p>But some will.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>