<post>
  <author>bsbbtnh</author>
  <date>2019-12-09T19:47:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/fabbxhf/</link>
  <title>How not to engage a suspect</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>So for those people who are harshly condemning the police, I would like to hear how they think this scenario should have played out (realistically) so we can start recommending better training for these sorts of situations.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Standard training and applying it to the situation. I guarantee that the majority of those 19 police officers shooting did not have eyes on the suspects (or the hostage). They disregarded their backdrop. They didn't give any chance for the suspects to breathe, or open up any path for a different outcome.</p>
      <p>Better command on the scene. 19 officers shouldn't even have their guns out in this situation. 19 officers don't need to be focused on shooting 1 UPS van with 2 doors and 2 suspects. I see absolutely no officers making any attempt to protect, direct, or otherwise control the civilians in the area. Poor use of the police vehicles in this situation, as well.</p>
      <p>19 fucking cops shooting. That means nobody there had any role in their mind other than engaging the suspect. You need 1 who oversees the scene, working in the background. 1-2 guys who try to make verbal contact. Should have 1 guy in each positioned team who is tasked with firing lethal (only defensively or if giving the command), a support officer with non-lethal, and another with back-up lethal, who communicates with the senior officer on scene. </p>
      <p>And I know someone will say "how could they do that in so little time." They had ample time in their vehicles to plan out what they were going to do, assign roles, etc. Training is crucial for this. But that largely breaks down if you've got multiple agencies working together, unless they also train together.</p>
      <p>They also should have never used a civilian vehicle as a shield, whether they are actively engaging the suspects or not, because they are drawing fire towards civilians. </p>
      <p>Also, it isn't like that stalled traffic appeared out of nowhere. The helicopter saw it coming, most of the police should have seen it coming. Allowing that UPS van to reach that point was a failure. Police crowding in on that van, pushing it deeper into traffic (by staying right on their ass), and putting immense pressure on the suspects instead of letting them get clear from the traffic, was another failure. If blocking it with their own vehicles and engaging wasn't something they were willing to risk during the <em>many</em> opportunities leading up to that final moment, than they shouldn't do that when civilians are the ones <em>involuntarily</em> blocking it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>