<post>
  <author>cincilator</author>
  <date>2019-12-10T22:33:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/faf93pf/</link>
  <title>Nuances Regarding Indvidualism and Conformity</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I would like to meditate a bit on the nature of conformity versus rebelliousness here.</p>
      <p>At the heart of Liberalism is a gritty origin story in which liberalism started out as an underdog. A rebel. In that story, it was new class of merchants and enlightened intellectuals that shattered old and stagnant order that consisted of priests and lords. Lords ruled due to machinations and deceptions of the clergy until brave enlightened-era thinkers debunked their lies. For that reason, liberals like to see themselves as free-thinking rebels, and any challenge to liberalism as fundamentally conservative. Sexy, liberated rebels against evil conformist empire. </p>
      <p>But now there is a baffling role-reversal in that alt-right types see themselves as freewheeling thinkers and derisively call mainstream liberals "NPCs." And what is even stranger that the insult appears to be working in the sense of agitating its targets -- hence twitter banning it.</p>
      <p>So, what's going on?</p>
      <p>The image of Nazism -- and before that, of Prussian militarism -- is that of total conformists, the endless lines of soldiers marching as one. And that is certainly the image those systems wanted to present to the world. The antidote to such schemes, we believe, is to be a nonconformist and to think critically about what authority figures tell you. But reality was never so simple. </p>
      <p>One feature of Prussian militarism was that it often gave even relatively low-ranking officers lots of degrees of freedom to interpret orders -- as long as they got results. You could surprisingly often decide to disobey an order in the field as long as whatever you did instead accomplished original objective. Because of that Prussian officer didn't feel like unthinking automation, he felt empowered to conduct the assault in the way he thought had the best chance for success. War could therefore feel in some ways more liberating than the doldrums of civilian life where you often had to do <em>exactly</em> as told.</p>
      <p>Our image of Nazism is colored by Nuremberg trials when pretty much everyone tried to justify themselves as "just following orders," as unthinking robots doing der Führer's will. A lot of people are quick to point out that this "Nuremberg Defense" isn't morally valid. But what people miss is that it was not even true. In reality, Hitler never gave his underlings detailed instructions on what to do and being a successful Nazi required a great deal of initiative and out-of-the-box thinking.</p>
      <p>For example, it was clear that Hitler wanted Jews gone, but he never really explained how. So, many <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/01/30/book-review-eichmann-in-jerusalem/">different Solutions</a> were proposed and tried and after they settled on Final Solution (i.e. extermination) they were still trying out different methods. Shootings were tried first, but that was expensive with all the ammunition shortages. Later on, explosives were tried but that was too messy. There were even mobile gas chambers that utilized exhaust gases from the engine to kill prisoners in transit. It took lots of iteration to settle on big stationary gas chambers as the most economical method. This was not the result of top-down planning. It was the result of the Nazis cultivating multiple Jew-killing (and Slav-killing, Roma-killing etc) startups. </p>
      <p>(None of it was meant to absolve Hitler nor his followers. Everyone committing atrocities did so knowing that Hitler was okay with the holocaust. My point is that his subordinates were as complicit as him and not only as unthinking executors)</p>
      <p>In many ways Nazism represented rebellion against authority -- starting with the autority of the Treaty of Versailles to impose penalties against Germany. It was also rebellion against Weimar democracy. People who joined the Nazi party weren't looking to just follow orders. They intended to escape doldrums imposed on them by decaying social order... and by liberalism. Nazis were edgelords of the '30s, complete with dark uniforms. Part of the secret for their tactical success was meth -- or Panzerschokolade as they called it. France was conquered by nihilistic loons high on drugs! Not exactly mythical ubermensch. (Fortunately for the rest of us, their overall strategy sucked as they attacked Russia with fuel only to reach Smolensk.)</p>
      <p>Authoritarianism doesn't attract you by telling you to "follow orders," it often creates spaces where free play is allowed (as long as you are of "correct" race, not ideological enemy etc.). On the other hand, supposedly free societies can feel incredibly conformist and suffocating. Hippie communes often degenerate into little fiefdoms with a whole bunch of ad-hoc rules that are nevertheless binding and if you complain "that's how it is, man!"</p>
      <p>This is a <a href="https://americanaffairsjournal.org/2019/11/the-cubicle-archipelago/">very interesting article</a> on paradoxes of liberalism. It quotes Isaac Kramnick, "Though [liberal] radicals preached independence, freedom, and autonomy in polity and mar­ket, they preached order, routine, and subordination in factory, school, poorhouse, and prison." The article explains that, back when Adam Smith wrote <em>Wealth Of Nations</em> most of capitalist class consisted of small business -- butchers, bakers, shoemakers etc. These people could maintain great sense of agency and independence. But soon afterwards the big industrialists came to the scene and demanded total obedience out of disempowered proles. Granted, efficiency skyrocketed due to such methods. But that's not how people imagined great shinning age with no priests nor kings would be like. (This is what I meant by Nazis trying to escape doldrums of liberalism)</p>
      <p>In addition, it must be said that the liberalism's gritty origin story I mentioned before is also partially based on bad history -- horrors of pre-modern societies were often exaggerated by enlightenment-era thinkers. They looked at the Church and aristocracy in their period and found them stagnant, decrepit, and opposed to progress. So they projected their situation back to the past and constructed the story where the Church and the aristocracy were always united against Progress, always keeping The People down.</p>
      <p>There are many problems with that story. Beginning with the fact that medieval Church itself started out as an underdog in the hostile post-Roman world. It often had to fight for independence from aristocracy (local warlords, really). It took centuries to abolish layman investiture (a practice where King could handpick the bishops). Some noble-priest synergy where they team up to destroy Progress never really happened. </p>
      <p>What is also not often told is a story of <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/9kdkzo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_01/e73i3vk/">technological and scientific progress in medieval period</a>. Some parts of scientific method are of medieval origin. And people behind those advances weren't some enlightened free thinkers. They were crazy religious fanatics who nevertheless believed that the world simply <em>must</em> have some kind of order because it was created by a rational God (which wasn't really their idea, they got it from Plato). People like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Bacon">Roger Bacon</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_of_Cusa">Nicholas of Cusa</a>.</p>
      <p>The real reason why liberalism triumphed is that economic growth and skyrocketing standards of living made trad frugality absurd. Old ways simply weren't needed any more and they couldn't satisfy growing appetites of the rising middle class. This had nothing to do with some increase in "free thinking" or moderns being more rebellious. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/dunpwo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_11/f7fkh18/">Which also implies that any reduction in affluence threatens to unravel liberalism.</a></p>
      <p>There is a really poignant moment in Metal Gear Solid II. Raiden (protagonist) confronts evil Patriot AI created to monitor and control world's information. The protagonist makes a really passionate speech on the indomitable 
 human spirit and the need for freedom and self-determination. And the reply by the evil AI is pitch perfect. "Is that even your idea or are just repeating what Snake (another protagonist) told you?" </p>
      <p>In essence, AI called Raiden a "NPC." You think that you are free because the others told you so. You only "rebel" to ask for <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2013/03/03/reactionary-philosophy-in-an-enormous-planet-sized-nutshell/">fifty Stalins</a>. </p>
      <p>On twitter you have a neverending conflict between the two groups: the "Bluechecks" (i.e. often highly credentialed users who write under their real names) and nihilists often with pepe frog avatars. With the former using their clout to ban the latter.</p>
      <p>The Bluecheck is dissatisfied because all his life he has followed the (increasingly absurd) rules of "professional managerial class." Despite championing the ostensibly free society, he doesn't know what would he do without the constant fear of punishment. He is irritated because pepe posters aren't kowtowing to his credentials. Pepes don't jump when told to, unlike his interns. That's why being called "NPC" stings.</p>
      <p>The pepe poster actually has a better claim to a title of "free thinker" because his opinions on race, gender and society are actually taboo. He actually thinks critically about what authority figures tell him (which is not to say he is necessarily right; "free thinker" is not the same as "correct thinker"). But he is unhappy for a different reason. Namely because he probably still lives in his mother's basement and thus also doesn't have the independence he wants. Either because his version of anti-liberalism isn't very functional or because he isn't.</p>
      <p>So we have two groups, neither of which is capable of living up to their self-image.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>