<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2019-12-08T21:14:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e4u7a6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_02/fa7zrs2/</link>
  <title>Disscussing The Rise of Victimhood Culture</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This question is pretty well-answered in Bradley Campbell and Jason Manning's <em>The Rise of Victimhood Culture</em>.  <a href="https://www.skeptic.com/reading_room/honor-dignity-victim-cultures/">Here's a brief summary</a>.  Notably, they contrast "victimhood culture" with "honor culture" and "dignity culture."</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <em>Honor cultures</em> emerge when a centralized state authority is not present or not legitimate and when people are extremely materially vulnerable. Under these conditions, people will take offense very easily, grow quickly fearful, and engage in higher rates of defensive, pre-emptive aggression as well as vigilante justice in order to settle their disputes. In the worst-case scenario, this pre-emptive aggression can develop into bloody feuds enveloping whole families, gangs or lineages. Physical bravery, deferential respect to the powerful and an unwillingness to appear weak and vulnerable consequently become paramount values.</p>
        <p>...</p>
        <p>In a <em>dignity culture</em>, people in this more modern form of society may resort to legal authority when disputes and wrongdoings are sufficiently severe, but otherwise they will make efforts to privately resolve disputes in a non-violent manner. In such a society, all citizens are assumed to have a sense of dignity and self-restraint, and everyone is expected to, at least at first, give the benefit of the doubt to a disputant to see if a conflict can be resolved peacefully. However, Campbell and Manning contend that when state authority begins to exert monopolizing control over a population of increasingly diverse, legally “equal” people, a victim culture may emerge.</p>
        <p>
          <em>Victim cultures</em> share in common with honor cultures the sensitivity to slights or insults, but whereas those in an honor culture might try to retaliate (physically or otherwise), people in a victim culture will instead appeal to a powerful, omnipresent state/legal authority. Classic examples are Mao’s China and Stalin’s Russia. In contrast to honor cultures that expect victims to be strong and stern enough to defend themselves, and dignity cultures that expect victims to be calm and charitable when in a dispute or disagreement, victim cultures emphasize how complainants are emotionally or physically fragile, vulnerable, and weak. In order to have high status in a victim culture, one must perfect and dramatize a personal “narrative of suffering.”2 Confidently espousing one’s own weakness, frailty, and suffering might seem, perhaps, dishonorable or shameful from an honor culture perspective, or gratuitous and self-absorbed from a dignity culture perspective.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In short: honor culture expects people to defend themselves, so people take offense easily to any perceived slight. (Anyone who insults me might be testing me to see if I'm weak enough for them to extort my resources, which means I need to treat any insult as an attempt to take my resources, and respond to it with all due violence.)   Dignity culture allows people to expect state or institutional authority to protect them, so they can give people the benefit of the doubt over any perceived slight.  Victimhood culture combines the "take offense easily to any perceived slight" from honor culture with the "rely on state or institutional authority to protect me" of dignity culture.</p>
      <p>In an honor society, you're disincentivized from picking fights, because if you pick fights then you have to back them up with your own fists.  In dignity culture, you're disincentivized from taking offense because the state/instutitional authorities are seen as the arbiters of last resort (you don't want to take your neighbor to court just because he was playing loud music at 11 PM on a weeknight, so rather than escalate the conflict it's better to ask politely for them to turn it down).  Victimhood culture emerges when the incentive structure is aligned such that you are rewarded for taking offense, and pay no cost for picking fights.</p>
      <p>If you accuse a professor of committing microaggressions and triggering you during a college lecture, you pay no costs (you don't  have to duel him/you don't have to pay to hire a lawyer), you can easily escalate the conflict to "you have wronged me and I deserve an apology," and you are rewarded for doing so (you highlight your own wokeness and demonstrate that other people should serve your interests).  When that incentive structure is in place, the results should be fairly predictable.  Similar paradigms exist when you can complain to HR, use your clout to call someone out on the internet, etc. </p>
      <p>What separates martyrdom from victimhood culture is that martyrs actually had to pay a cost for their martyrdom, which meant that there was a significant suffering cost associated with being a martyr to serve as a disincentive.  (You were probably venerated to roughly the extent that you personally suffered.) In contrast, in modern society the costs associated with saying "I'm offended" are fairly low: unlike a martyr, you don't have to actually suffer yourself, since you can just appropriate the suffering of your ancestors or people who are part of your same demographic group.</p>
      <p>I'd like to draw another important distinction between being offended in honor culture vs being offended in victimhood culture.</p>
      <p>In honor culture, the paradigm is something like this:  "If someone gets away with insulting my mother, I am seen as weak.  If I am seen as weak, other strong people will see me as a target that they can extort resources from.  Therefore, if he insults my mother in an attempt to prove that I am weak, I must attack him to prove that I am strong and that anyone trying to transgress against me will be met with violence.  <em>However,</em> an equally acceptable outcome would be for him to withdraw his insult.  He can retreat verbally, which is just as good as him retreating physically, because it shows that he's afraid of the physical conflict that would result from me escalating our conflict, which he would only fear if he thought that I was strong enough to defeat him in physical combat."  So, when someone insults your mother, you stand up to him, puff out your chest, and say, "I'm sorry, pal.  I don't think I heard you right.  It <em>sounded</em> like you said something about my mother.  But you didn't <em>really</em> say that, did you?  I must have misheard you.  Because if you really said what I thought I heard you say, then I'd have to kick your ass."  At that point, you have given him an out to say, "No, of course not, I would never insult your mother.  My sincerest apologies if I said anything that made it sound like I was. You know what, let me buy you a drink to show how sorry I am about this unfortunate misunderstanding."  And of course, you accept his apology, because doing so serves your interests: you have effectively won the fight without having to throw a single punch.  Being aggrieved means you have to pick a fight, but you can avoid the fight by being "un-aggrieved" when your foe withdraws his insult and apologizes.  And if someone says something that <em>accidentally</em> insults you, then you have substantial incentive to let them withdraw the offending remark: after all, if they meant no harm, why bother picking a fight with them?  (Sometimes, community norms might still demand that you fight them even if the offense was accidental, as you don't want <em>other</em> people to see you as weak for not responding to an insult with violence, but there are incentives to forgive offense.)</p>
      <p>However, in victimhood culture, your incentive to take offense is that you <em>want</em> to be seen as aggrieved.  So there's no incentive for you to accept an apology, even if they offense was unintentional.  In fact, when your foe admits weakness by apologizing, that means they've admitted their wrongdoing and you'll be rewarded if you double down and go on the offense (with state/institutional power bearing down on your enemy, no need to throw your own punches).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>