<post>
  <author>Faceh</author>
  <date>2019-12-08T06:09:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e4u7a6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_02/fa2qihm/</link>
  <title>The Slippery Differences in Genetics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Seems a lot of the debate is muddied by failing to truly reach a fair definition of 'race.' Its a slippery concept, and I'm willing to bet the concept actually differ from person to person, let alone between various tribes, and most are certainly different from any 'scientific' definition.</p>
      <p>For many it does seem to roughly seem to correlate with skin tone. Some might bother to break it down by country of origin too. And some throw in a few other 'markers' that may or may not have scientific basis.</p>
      <p>And I think if we go by those definitions then yeah, the concept is not all that useful and it would be unwise to think of 'racial differences' as an important classification for judging <em>individuals</em> or otherwise making important social decisions.</p>
      <p>But if we're talking purely about genetics, and we have enough data to actually detect and identify the differences and similarities between individuals, then there's... going to be a way to define populations in terms of their differences and similarities. Even if they're .999999 the same, that last .000001 can be really frickin' salient.</p>
      <p>Going it a bit further, though, I think that the 'proof' that such designations are useful would be if they can capture what already seems to be meaningful differences between populations. So I want to, specifically, see the genetic differences that explain why <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2012/04/why-kenyans-make-such-great-runners-a-story-of-genes-and-cultures/256015/">a particular population tends to be good at long-distance running</a>, why <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/news/2018/04/bajau-sea-nomads-free-diving-spleen-science/">another group has advantages in swimming</a>, and maybe most importantly why <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Race_and_health#Single-gene_disorders">some groups have different responses to particular diseases or medical treatments.</a> once the genes that contribute to these outcomes are identified, you should be able to draw a clear distinction between groups that have the trait and those that do not, and group those that are most similar together apart from those that are most different, and call that 'race.'</p>
      <p>And in all likelihood you'll end up drawing up groups that also correlate/correspond with people's geographical origin and culture and language and, of course, other physical characteristics they share in common.</p>
      <p>And then you can get into the weeds when you do this for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ashkenazi_Jewish_intelligence">groups that are notable for intellectual achievement</a>.</p>
      <p>And yet even these racial categories wouldn't do well for judging <em>individual members</em> of those categories, since not every Kenyan (or whatever we call the genetically-defined group that captures Kenyans) will be a good distance runner, even if they will tend to have traits that make them better than average at distance running. It might turn out that <em>most</em> members of the group don't actually have the meaningful trait we originally identified, it just happens to be expressed more often if you take the population as a whole. Is it still a meaningful trait if that true? Seems like we should have <em>multiple</em> such traits at work to get better at predicting individual outcomes.</p>
      <p>Buuuut now it feels like I'm basically examining something that is even less salient than, say, dog breeds, where <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greyhound">some are more optimized for running</a>, whilst <a href="https://www.akc.org/expert-advice/lifestyle/breeds-that-are-born-to-swim/">others are optimized for swimming</a>, and all the individuals within an particular breed will almost assuredly exhibit the traits that define that breed, which is probably less true for the traits that define a race. So I can be far more confident that a randomly chosen greyhound will beat a randomly chosen Labrador in a footrace than I would be that a randomly chosen Kenyan would beat a randomly chosen Native American (or, again, whatever genetic definitions capture the Native Americans) in a long-distance race.</p>
      <p>So basically, genetically-defined racial categories seem like they would be meaningful and useful, but probably less meaningful and useful than we'd really like them to be in most contexts (medicine being a big exception), and certainly less meaningful than the people who are obsessed with 'race' (the slippery, unclear definition) would make it out to be, and how they would use it.</p>
      <p>And you can't expect that this definition of race will be successfully transmitted to the population at large and can fully expect them to just generalize to the obvious characteristics ("all kenyans are great at running, and Jews are just smarter!") and import none of the nuance or meaning but will still assume their beliefs are 'scientific', which may lead them to have the confidence to suggest the type of policies that lead to serious oppression and possible genocide.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>So I don't know where that leaves us. I think articles like this one from the NYT really just muddy the water and <em>intentionally</em> obfuscates the need for a rigorous definition of race by assuming that just because the definition of race is slippery and 'socially constructed' that there is no  way  to create a definition that is sufficiently precise to use in civil discussion.</p>
      <p>NYT doesn't want to admit that many people talking about racial differences are actually hitting on a meaningful phenomena, so they focus on those who use the most superficial and ill-intentioned definitions as an excuse to not have the conversation at all.</p>
      <p>But as I said, its possible that the concept of 'race' is just so poisoned that we aren't going to get everyone on the same page no matter how hard we try, so the culture war will currently be raging around any attempt to nail down the definition or craft a new term without all the baggage.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>