<post>
  <author>funobtainium</author>
  <date>2019-12-08T01:44:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e79pzs/2_arms_1_head_not_nsfw/fa1g9uh/</link>
  <title>A first hand account of paralysis</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Some who suffer spinal cord injuries soon get better.  They experience swelling, or something else, that puts pressure on their spinal cords, and then in one way or another the problem is solved.  Then they say the most shameless things to flatter themselves.   “I was determined to walk again.”  That is, they think it was their own personal strength or determination that made them get better.  The problem with this is that when these sorts of things are publicized, many get the idea that all that is needed for us to get better is hard work and unflagging willpower. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>When I was paralyzed (it's a bit of a long story, but I had a spinal cord injury that resulted in complete paraplegia from the waist down, had surgery immediately, and after a week I could move a toe, then eventually and gradually, I was able to gain more sensation and movement. I was in inpatient rehab for a month and was able to use a walker for short periods when I left, but was mostly using a wheelchair. Now, I'm mostly recovered...as good as it's going to get. I can walk but not run, though my balance isn't great, and I have sexual sensation and can use the bathroom normally. Those things took several months to resolve, and yes, that sucked very much and were the worst things about paralysis. Walking is indeed overrated in comparison.</p>
      <p>He's right about people who recover. It's luck. I was just lucky to draw an excellent random neurosurgeon (who used the word "miracle" when I could flex my ankle later) and have good insurance for world-class rehab. I did what I was supposed to there, but people who get knee replacements or have a torn ACL also mostly do what they're supposed to do in rehab; it doesn't take some form of preternatural pluckiness/courage/prayer protocol to do what physical therapists tell you to.</p>
      <p>That said, I'm the kind of person who doesn't really stay discouraged for long over things I can't change, either. I wouldn't want to exist like Terri Schiavo, but when it comes to most other states, things could always be <em>worse</em>.  Being a middle-aged person with a mobility disability isn't that bad, compared to having terminal cancer when you're a child. My hobbies aren't athletic, and my job was done on a computer. My life didn't really change except for the time and inconvenience aspects he mentioned, and I have a spouse who helped me.</p>
      <p>Before I knew that I'd be able to walk again, and a while after, because I never knew for sure where my recovery would <em>stop</em>, I spent a lot of time reading posts on forums about spinal cord injury and paralysis. This was useful for the practical tips and commiseration/support, but in places like this, you also see various levels of function and of the capacity to accept and cope with disability. </p>
      <p>I didn't take a poll, but it did seem that the people with the most difficulty coping with paralysis were, unsurprisingly, young and very physically active. If you derive a lot of joy and fulfillment from rock climbing or riding a motorcycle like Clayton, no matter how many other abilities or hobbies you have, it seems much more devastating to cope with that loss. You can drive a car ably with hand controls, but you can't have the exact same motorcycle experience as an able-bodied person. Some things will never be the same.</p>
      <p>The <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1980-01001-001">famous study</a> that compares happiness levels after winning the lottery or being paralyzed did demonstrate that people mostly return to their usual emotional state after adapting to a new reality; lottery winners aren't all ecstatically happy forever, and paralyzed people aren't all full of existential gloom. I will tell you that doctors do automatically push antidepressants on people with these sorts of injuries. I took my Wellbutrin dutifully for a month or two, but I wasn't depressed before the injury and I wasn't depressed afterward. I often see people on Reddit say things like, "If I was paralyzed I would kill myself," but you can't know how you'd cope unless it happens to you, and you can't judge someone else for how they cope.</p>
      <p>I feel great sorrow for the author, mostly because he suffered so deeply and was so lonely in the midst of his despair.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>