<post>
  <author>JTarrou</author>
  <date>2019-12-11T12:09:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/fagoxgv/</link>
  <title>Race, Culture, and Faith Healing</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>In which I relate a history of religious extremism, and how it informs my views on race in modern society. </p>
      <p>For those who have been around long enough, you may have read some of this before, so bear with me a bit. Or skip entirely.  </p>
      <p>A long, long time ago in a millennium far away, I grew up in a <a href="https://culteducation.com/group/1289-general-information/28442-faith-assembly-film-to-document-faith-healing-church-and-those-who-died-because-of-its-beliefs.html">faith-healing</a> cult in Indiana, lead by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hobart_Freeman">this guy</a>. In that context, I received an unconventional but first-class education in theology, argumentation, ancient languages, etc. Modern biology, not so much, but hey, you can't have everything. This church had formed in the mid to late seventies, and was made up of a lot of converts, heavily influenced by the hippie generation in aesthetics and lifestyle. So, faith healing religious zealots who gardened a lot and played guitar rather than organ. The other bit they imported was the racial egalitarianism of the day, and that was helped by the religious zealotry. When the only thing that matters is the Kingdom of God, human race isn't even a blip on the radar of importance. </p>
      <p>It may or may not be believed, but growing up, race was just something never remarked upon. Yes, people looked different, and I was told about past, historical racism. But never to my young mind was race ever pointed out as linked in any way to relevant differences between people. While the church was heavily white, it was a lot less white than the rest of northern Indiana, mixed race couples were common, and there were several nonwhite members of church leadership. At least in earshot of us children, the adults never made a distinction at all, and kids hear everything. I thought, up until about the age of sixteen, that all of society was more or less in line with us on that front, so even while I was disengaging from the church and the faith in my early teens, I didn't think there would be a difference. </p>
      <p>It was surprising, shocking even, to find that racial stereotypes were still a thing in the wider world. Not that there was a ton of racism, but when the baseline is zero, one notices a lot. And my time in other countries had given me a much higher baseline for other types of racism and ethnocentrism. If a white person in the US talked about black people the way Russians talk about Georgians or Ukrainians, they'd be cancelled, fired, assaulted, and convicted of bruising their assailant's fists before breakfast. Even so, I had found that racial attitudes had not reached the egalitarian ideal of my childhood. </p>
      <p>Worst of all, I found the source of at least some of those attitudes, and it was not entirely unsympathetic.  I moved to a majority-minority rust belt town that was top-5 most violent mid-sized cities in the country for two decades running.  My new home was deeply racially divided. The blue collar whites who had formed and dominated the town in its heydey had been pushed out by a burgeoning black underclass. Violence was endemic, local politics hilariously corrupt and race-based, the economy bad and not getting better, drugs rife. Lots of racial resentment on both sides. On the black side, they saw whites as strip mining the good years, and then escaping to the township when things got bad, taking the tax base and all the good public services with them. On the white side, they saw blacks coming in when times were good, then turning feral and driving them out of their homes just as the economy collapsed. Elements of truth flavored with ingroup/outgroup bias on both sides. </p>
      <p>So where does that leave us today? We find identity politics coming up fast on both extremes. Is a return to the racial attitudes of my crazy cult feasible or even desirable? The lessons I've drawn are that race is a lot less important than culture, but race and culture can overlap a lot, so it may be hard to tell at times. And, if we want to move to a post-racial society, that is possible. But, it requires a pathological devotion to a shared higher purpose, and the only two current candidates (religion and nationalism) are both hugely dangerous when raised to that level of importance. Personally, I think we could reduce current internal tensions somewhat by increasing nationalism somewhat, but there is a trade-off at the margins. In some sense, this only shifts the consequences of ingroup/outgroup bias beyond national borders. This may be pessimism speaking, but I think there is a conservation of bigotry at work in humanity. Our decision may come down to who to hate, rather than whether to hate, at least on a societal scale. Is it better to hate our neighbor than to hate our national neighbor, or worse?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>