<post>
  <author>JTarrou</author>
  <date>2019-12-11T16:52:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/fahbus3/</link>
  <title>Speaking of Faith Healing</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Hard to say what it was like, it just seemed normal to me growing up in it, although I knew most other kids didn't have the same sort of life. It still seems normal to me, a sort of theocratic home I don't believe in anymore, but feels comfortable.</p>
      <p>No christmas (pagan holiday), no TV, no movies, no music other than worship songs, no radio, no newspapers, no magazines. Lots of books. Not believing in medical care extended to birth control, I'm the oldest of seven. I didn't get my own room until I was sixteen, and I had to build it, in our unfinished basement.</p>
      <p>The religious doctrines were pretty much in line with a lot of modern evangelical christianity, with the Charismatic flair. Lots of prophecy, speaking in tongues etc. in addition to the faith healing. Broadly, the ideal was of a semi-communistic imitation of the early christian church. Nationalism was hated, and there was a virulent strain of anti-catholicism. The government was distrusted, and cooperation with the authorities was discouraged on many fronts, even voting was considered to be participating in an unrighteous system. As one might expect, the faith healing shit resulted in a lot of needless deaths, and many people in the church were prosecuted, mostly for child neglect or similar crimes. Interestingly, among the doctrines was one that barred church members from defending themselves in court. Almost all those prosecuted plead "no contest" and refused legal help, which resulted in rather long prison sentences. The church was radically pacifist. No violence of any sort was tolerated, something I violated a lot as a kid. It didn't matter if six other boys assaulted you with baseball bats, you were not to fight back, ever. That was the first crack in my adherence to the faith, because that was bullshit to me even at the age of five.</p>
      <p>Culture shock was there, but limited. My parents did a couple stints as missionaries, so by the time I was exposed to a lot of the wider world, I'd done the culture shock thing a few times. It's still  there a bit though. I have none of the shared cultural markers of kids who grew up in the eighties, cartoons, TV shows, movies etc. My pop culture knowledge starts at about 1996.</p>
      <p>I do have fond memories, and I've kept a few friends from those days. The church was good at a lot of things, and it improved the lives of a lot of the members, I have no doubt. The theological debating and training, combined with the lack of entertainment to make most of the kids I grew up with distinctly better educated than what I saw in public schools, even counting the miseducation about evolution and the like. Then again, it engendered massive guilt, a lunatic ideology, and lead directly to the deaths of between 130 and 250 people, depending on the estimates. I spent a lot of years hating my parents, the church, and everyone who enabled all that shit, but with time and hopefully wisdom has come acceptance. It was a really bad idea that a lot of people thought was a really good idea. They did what they sincerely thought was best, and (not) all of us have to live with the consequences.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>