<post>
  <author>kellykebab</author>
  <date>2019-12-10T08:23:47Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/faddtbl/</link>
  <title>Struggling with the Death of God</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think humanity is still recovering from the "death of God." I suspect that our spiritual instinct evolved simultaneously or even prior to our modern consciousness and that we are simply programmed to inject a deeper meaning and intentionality into the world than actually exists. And I think despite the philosophical repudiation of God during the late 19th and early 20th century, humans have not developed the mental ability to move through the world effectively while self-aware but absent some kind of binding power.</p>
      <p>And I think the 20th century is evidence of our immaturity in the face of this new, very stark kind of reality. We've discovered that creating secular doctrines that provide safety, security, meaning, and coherence to life is a much more difficult (and dangerous) program than it first seemed. Meanwhile, we have become ever more aware of the effects of our actions, simply because there is more information about literally everything available to us.</p>
      <p>So in the world of aesthetics, many of our traditional values (order, harmony, beauty, strict sexual dimorphism, etc.) were tied to hierarchies inspired by or associated with a spiritual order. When the core of that order has been dismissed, the hierarchies too appear less compelling. But there isn't a new core yet. Maybe there will be one in the future. But for now, I think we're still floundering to create one and I think we're finding that we aren't very good at it.</p>
      <p>What we seem to be trying is some kind of general humanism where the human subject is conceived as both self-sufficiently authoritative and equal across human groups. But a) we don't have long-standing traditions and cultural rituals around this belief, and b) we find that it isn't a very empirical belief based largely on how shoddy we have been in implementing this idea. Meanwhile, we're probably <em>more</em> conscious, <em>more</em> self-aware than we ever have been. So our ideological impotence is all the more obvious to us on a daily level.</p>
      <p>I'm not sure what the solution is. Perhaps humanity will build up a proper secular conceptual structure of value in the future, but as of now, I think we're aware that we've propped up very limp substitutes for the structure of meaning that we used to have. And one very human way of dealing with that is irony and sarcasm and nihilism. And our art reflects that. Unfortunately, I think our art will continue to reflect that until we decide that materialism is completely insufferable for humanity with or without a supernatural deity and that there is more to existence than acquiring resources and "commenting" on that banal phenomenon.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>