<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2019-12-11T15:55:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/fah5prn/</link>
  <title>Where Race and Ethnicity Come Apart</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I grew up in one of the most diverse cities in America. Something like white 30%, hispanic 30%, Cambodian 10%, black 10%, and the other 20% was literally every other ethnicity on the planet.</p>
      <p>Multiethnicity was never weird to me, ever. It was my baseline, as with you. I went on a road trip through the Midwest when I was twelve and it creeped me out, seeing town after town after town with nothing but white people and maybe one or two Mexicans, no black people at all except one biker heading to Sturgis.</p>
      <p>Then I joined the Army, where all colors bleed into shitty greyish camo by design- East LA cholos, white trash from the trailer parks of North Texas, Berkeley hippie Asians, and recent immigrants from Uganda taking the shortcut to citizenship with an army contract all came together in a shared set of speaking tics, dress sense, values, and rituals. In short, we all joined a brand new ethnic group.</p>
      <p>I learned bigotry in Afghanistan- there was in fact an Other out there who was unbearable different, inferior in morals, a present danger to <em>real</em> humans like you and me. Still though, my bigotry was based on ideology, not ethnicity- I had no problem with the locals who embraced American style civilization, only the ones who rejected it.</p>
      <p>But then I got home, and <em>holy shit</em>, now that I knew what to look for, bigotry was everywhere. Communities bound by a common flag were not bound by common culture or values. The catalyst for this realization was a gentlemen in South Central Los Angeles who fulfilled every single negative stereotype of blacks I had ever heard. He was in and out of prison for petty crimes, blamed whitey for his problems, former gang member before getting old and losing status, on welfare, had had a kid out of wedlock at age fifteen, was constantly drunk and high, spoke in an almost incomprehensible patois. I was in awe- it was like finding out Bigfoot really does exist. All respectable persons had assured me he was a myth, but here he was talking to me in the flesh, complaining that the security guard at the grocery store was a prick to him just because he had caught him stealing from the beer aisle.</p>
      <p>It had never really occurred to me that an American man, speaking my language and dressed in blue jeans, living mere miles away from where I slept every night, might be as alien as any Pashtun. It was thought provoking, to be sure.</p>
      <p>I realized, belatedly, I had never actually met somebody of a different ethnicity while growing up. I had only ever interacted with fellow lower middle class Californians as a kid, and within the tribe the fact that my grandfathers had come from Germany and hers from the Philippines, or my dad’s great grandfather was French Canadian and his was Cuban, was about meaningful as what brand of soda you prefer- plenty of different answers, and they all signify nothing of importance.</p>
      <p>In short, the black dudes I grew up with would have been equally as repulsed by the walking stereotype from South Central, and for the same reasons. Shared skin tone would have counted for nothing.</p>
      <p>To sum up- people are a problem.</p>
      <p>The only way I’ve been able to parse all this is by asserting that ethnic differences are extremely real, real in a way that doesn’t go away just because you proclaim yourself tolerant of all people. Real in a manner that results in permanent grievance and resentment when resource allocation becomes a zero sum game. But the data of my lived experience also leads me to assert that ethnicity and “race” at best correlate at times, being something of a Venn diagram instead of being synonyms. My follow on conclusion is that there are bazillions more ethnicities out there then anybody accounts for, and they are almost all tiny, being bound to a specific location and a specific class and a specific subculture in a specific time period- they mutate, emerge as a distinct clot of group identity, and either establish themselves in the long term or dissolve. Their severe limitations do not stop them from mattering.</p>
      <p>A thoughtless bigot who claims that all black people have the following list of bad traits isn’t wrong by listing the traits. He’s wrong when he first says “all black people”, because already he’s fighting an unwinnable war against reality- what connection has a ghetto kid with a black guy born and raised in a gated community? What shared experiences does the Ugandan immigrant recruit have with a black career DMV employee from Detroit? What common cultural touchstones has an Oakland Black Panther with a Hutu farmer who turned genocidaire?</p>
      <p>And of course, one needs only crack open a history book to find that the terms “white” and “Asian” are not monolithic blocs of identity either.</p>
      <p>I don’t really know how to cap this off. Mostly, I guess, I just want people to acknowledge that you can’t just declare ethnic tension solved, that tolerance for the Other may be Good but it is not natural, and that the ancient custom of respect, courtesy, and hospitality towards strangers matters more than you might expect.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>