<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-03-17T12:42:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/m5eawi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_15_2021/gr8bqfn/</link>
  <title>The rejection of (at least some of) the sexual revolution</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A return to Victorian sexual morality (middle class insistence upon chastity, endless fears of fallen women, whores of modern babylon and so on) is unlikely - <em>aesthetically</em> the shift will not look like previously conservative morality for obvious reasons. </p>
      <p>But if you look at changing attitudes to sex among young people, and particularly the growing idea in the wealthy classes that things like divorce and <em>even infidelity</em> (a remarkable shift some of my fellow UMC commenters may have noticed) are seen as trashy, nouveau or otherwise undesirable, it’s clear <strong>something</strong> is happening. Young people are having less sex - the result of porn and video games more than title ix or tinder, which like all heterosexual hookup apps struggles to reach its early growth targets precisely because most people do not participate in hookup culture no matter how easy it may be. </p>
      <p>
        <strong>It is more helpful to see what is happening as a rejection of the sexual revolution</strong>. I am convinced more than ever that the sexual revolution was an aberration <em>even</em> given general acceptance of liberalism’s long march/cthulhu swims left. Note by sexual revolution I don’t mean homosexual rights movements (which, though they benefited from some similar wider social changes, largely has separate origins) but rather purely broad social acceptance and promotion of promiscuity - particularly to women. This was the unique confluence of postwar American capitalism, a booming publishing industry catering to the middle class, Hugh Hefner and co (everyone from professional athletes to ad men to politicians) and the bet that the declining centrality of religion and traditional morality in western life would <em>allow</em> it to be pushed. The walls of traditional sexuality suddenly appeared uniquely fragile in the turmoil of three decades of immense social change, and so they walked in and smashed them - to their sexual and often financial profit. </p>
      <p>I’ve discussed this here before, but the sexual revolution was motivated largely separately from women’s desires by the ambition of men - particularly wealthier or more educated men - to sleep with more (young) women. The earliest protests in Paris in 1968 were not about revolution, or overthrowing De Gaulle, or getting the American military out of France or getting France out of Algeria or taking from the rich or any of those things - they were by socialist male university students (and some faculty) who gathered to protest the ban on male students being allowed into female dorms at night. Other data points are near infinite. </p>
      <p>The sexual revolution was about increasing (some) male access to sex. Incels and TRP aficionados will counter that many, perhaps most, men have <em>lost</em> from the sexual revolution, and indeed that may be the case. It is entirely compatible with this theory, in fact. Publishing industry execs who want to be able to fuck all their secretaries with impunity, rock stars who want to sleep with their teenage fans without their parents being able to hurt them (being ‘cancelled’ we might call it today) etc etc, they are the people in question. </p>
      <p>It was inevitable that eventually women would catch on, and realize what a poor deal this was. And the men (or rather, their successors several generations later) would get their comeuppance.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>