<post>
  <author>cantbeproductive</author>
  <date>2020-02-16T14:06:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f1lmga/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_10/fhskg6l/</link>
  <title>Validation and Presentation</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>When I was a teen I was really concerned with how I looked. Because I was really concerned with how people perceived me. I spent a decent amount of time on fashion/menswear forums trying to figure out the best manner in which to present my “true self”. I learned about all the different wears, not just menswear and femswear, but preppy, gothninja, business casual, minimalist, pale wave, and all the rest. I would assume a style and make it my true presentation, In the hopes that by finally presenting my true self to others, I will finally feel comfortable in who I am and bask in my newfound social glory.</p>
      <p>Turned out that in the real world, nobody really gives a shit how you dress, as long as it’s above a bare minimum of decorum. My problem wasn’t in how I was presenting myself or labeling myself, but in my need for validation through external signifiers (part of this, of course, is just being a teen). I thought my big social problem, my big validation problem, was that I dressed poorly, when really I just wasn’t an approachable guy and had a male restingbitchface. I was looking at the wrong thing to solve my problem. It wasn’t in appearance but in my internal disposition and outlook of the (social) world. I was looking for the answer in a totally wrong domain.</p>
      <p>Anyway, my conservative, backwards, simplistic <strong>opinion</strong> on all this gender stuffs is that they are repeating the same mistake I made. They are looking for some way to present their true self that will answer to all of their emotional, social, existential doubts and anxieties. And they are looking in the wrong domain. People shouldn’t have to go searching for a decade in who they are really attracted to, just as they shouldn’t go looking for how to <em>truly</em> present their <em>true</em> self. My obsession with right presentation did not solve my problems of anxiety and invalidation, but only amplified it. When I started appreciating others for who they are, and appreciated myself for who I am, and allowed my inner feelings to roam freely, I realize all that obsessing was totally errant. </p>
      <p>I do not think that obsessing over gender is something that a healthy-minded person does. Whenever you obsess about something it runs the risk of becoming the lens with which you view all things. If you obsess about sexuality long enough, you will see all your problems through that lens, including problems that really belong to the domain of spirituality/ethics/human-condition. And by seeing your problems through that lens you’ll assume that the answer is also through that lens. </p>
      <p>Normal people do not have to obsess over their gender or why they’re into. It’s self-evident. It’s plain. It doesn’t take decades of rumination. I fear that Contrapoints is neurotically fixated on gender and sexuality and that this is preventing Contrapoints from actually examining not only gender questions but existential questions. “Coming out” should be a term reserved for existential breakthroughs: Someone comes out as a loving parent, a monk, a Christian, an artist, a nature-lover. The whole genital shit is microscopically insignificant compared to the existential questions we ought to be concerned with. Transgender people, from what I’ve found, are invariably obsessed with gender shit and it has subsumed the cognitive space that in ordinary people is concerned with how they ought to live and what God they ought to worship. The puzzles of life become the puzzles of the flesh, which lowers their entire appreciation for the grandeur of life.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>