<post>
  <author>GrapeGrater</author>
  <date>2020-02-14T02:06:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f1lmga/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_10/fhjgyzb/</link>
  <title>A Story Of Two Elites</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Over time I've gradually moved towards a more Peter Turchin-like theory that the working class finds itself basically mute and useless. Rather, the working class tends to be too political inept, disorganized and otherwise content to really get too involved. Rather, the working class plays kingmaker between members of the elite class that compete to out-elite each other.</p>
      <p>With this in mind, I alter it slightly to point out there are at least two kinds of elites: the information elite and the mercantile elite. The information elite is divided among the academies, media, Hollywood and discussion-altering parts of the tech companies. The mercantile elite ate the wealthy CEOs. Traditionally, the Democrats are the information elite and the Republicans are the mercantile elite.</p>
      <p>What is often missed is that management has to at least pretend to identify and protect their worker's interests or the workers will simply flee or not follow orders. The information elites, on the other hand, have to relate through entertainment; they think they relate via taking money from the mercantile elite but they tip their hands with things like Free college for all (which won't help people who don't have a high school diploma and decided school is a rigid hellscape which they'd rather avoid). This is why "the left" often wrings their hands about "the working class voting against their interests."</p>
      <p>Related, the left have been discriminating against much of the right for decades and the mercantile elite started moving left socially. This created a kind of elite-in-exile that is able to provide support for Trump. Except, because this part of the elite was kicked out of the elite bubble, it's forced to draw support from a fraction of the population-at-large that renders it's bubble somewhat closer to the old working class.</p>
      <p>The <em>actual</em> working class is voting for Johhnson and Trump, but no member of the elite can come out and defend the positions of the working class or else they get destroyed by the dominant elites in cultural and economic power. The solution is for the elites to release the strangleholds on power, but they seem completely unable and instead purity spiral harder and faster.</p>
      <p>And the culture war intensifies.</p>
      <p>----</p>
      <p>If you look at the data, the <em>real</em> divides aren't what people are saying they are. The Narrative is that Trump is a closet white supremacist trying to kick out the nonwhites. In truth, his approval ratings are higher than previous Republican administrations with various minority communities.</p>
      <p>The <em>real</em> divides are among the educated (most clear in the non-educated/educated whites broken out in most surveys--conspicuously missing from many surveys for non-white populations) and male and female (but only when looking at the young and primarily among women). The press is lying, again, because it doesn't want to admit that as members of the information elite, they've failed to connect to the working classes. Instead they want to live in a fantasy where they'll vote to dis-empower and destroy the mercantile elites to seize more power and the working class will automatically side with them. Instead: "I'm voting for Bernie because MSNBC hates him"</p>
      <p>Edit: This doesn't imply the mercantile elite wins either. By breaking with their old allies on the right they open themselves up to have basically no popular support and by joining in the information elite in playing social politics games with issues like transgender-ism (which has been adopted far too rapidly to be as complete as normal). They could very well find themselves as the absolute losers in the culture war.</p>
      <p>The populist political right will almost certainly lose. Their issue is far simpler: they don't have any way (and seem dead set on avoiding) to make a long term infrastructure to support themselves. Without institutionalization, their moment will probably not last past then end of the decade. But, they could play kingmaker in the near future. Will it be Tucker Carlson? Or Sean Hannity? The new populist or the old Reaganite? Without a home, they will be looking to pick sides, will the mercantile elites be loath to forgive tariffs? Or will the information elites be forever tied to Social Justice and be unwilling to make amends?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>