<post>
  <author>HuskyCriminologist</author>
  <date>2020-02-20T19:56:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f53qhm/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_17/fi7utf3/</link>
  <title>A History Of Gun Control In The United States</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <h2>1986-2004</h2>
      <p>Unfortunately, some things never changed. The ATF still mostly prosecuted gun crimes. In fact, the ATF loves prosecuting gun crimes to this day. And they're not particular about how they get those convictions. We just finished up 1986 and the seeds of dissent that are still around today. Now we're actually reversing a little bit, to 1971. Have you ever heard of Ruby Ridge? You might've, it's relatively famous. But the specifics are often lost in the discussion, so I'll start with undisputed facts.</p>
      <p>Randy Weaver received an honorable discharge from the United States Army in 1971, after serving for three years some of which was spent as a Green Beret, Army Special Forces. After his discharge, he got married, had some kids, and got more into some fringe fundamentalist beliefs. So he and his family moved up in the mountains to a place called Ruby Ridge. In 1984 Randy Weaver got into a dispute with a neighbor, Terry Kinnison, over a land deal. Kinnison lost in court and had to pay the Weavers $3000 for the land deal, and $2,100 in damages and fees. Kinnison then wrote letters to the FBI, Secret Service, and county sheriff alleging that Randy had threatened to kill the Pope, the President, and the governor of Idaho. In 1985 the Weavers were interviewed by FBI and Secret Service agents, who had been told Weaver was a member of the Aryan Nations, a white supremacist group. Later that year they file an affidavit at the courthouse saying enemies of the family are plotting to get the FBI to kill them.</p>
      <p>What the heck does this have to do with the 2020 stagnation of gun rights? Well hold on, it's coming I promise.</p>
      <p>The ATF gets involved at this point after Randy Weaver is introduced to an undercover ATF agent while at a white supremacist gathering in 1986. Randy is not a sympathetic character here, he really isn't. But what happens to him is important. In 1989 the ATF alleges that Randy Weaver sold that undercover ATF agent shotguns that were shorter than the legal minimum. In June 1990, the ATF attempts to get Randy to become an informant in the Aryan Nations, using the shotgun charges as leverage. He refuses, and the charges are filed. The ATF tells the court that Randy Weaver was also a convicted bank robber. Charitably, they were misinformed. Uncharitably, they lied to the court. In December of that year, a grand jury indicts Randy Weaver for making and possessing (but not selling) illegal weapons. The ATF decides it would be too dangerous to arrest Randy Weaver on his property so in January 1991 two ATF agents posing as broken down motorists arrest Randy when he pulls over to help, and inform him of the charges against him. Randy is released on bail.</p>
      <p>There was then a comedy of errors in the court system. Randy's court-appointed attorney couldn't get ahold of him. His probation officer didn't give him any contact information. The date of the trial is changed from February 19th to February 20th. Randy gets a letter from his probation officer saying the trial was set for March 20th. When Randy didn't show up to the February 20th court date, a bench warrant is issued for his arrest. A few days later the court is informed by a reporter about the letter from the probation officer but refuses to withdraw the warrant. A grand jury is assembled on March 14th, is not informed about the probation officer's error, and indicts Randy Weaver for failure to appear.</p>
      <p>The Marshals are given Randy's case. They are not informed that the ATF attempted to recruit Weaver as an informant. Weaver is at some point informed (wrongly) that if he loses this case he will lose his property, leaving his wife and children homeless. Randy Weaver decides to simply stay in his home, and resist any efforts to take him. The Marshals start surveilling the Weaver residence. On April 18, 1992, a helicopter flies over Ruby Ridge. Someone reports that the helicopter was shot at. The USMS surveillance team says they saw a helicopter but heard no shots. Weaver gives an interview saying nobody fired at the helicopter. The helicopter pilot gives an FBI interview that nobody shot at his helicopter.</p>
      <p>The Marshals and FBI use the justification that Randy Weaver shot at the helicopter while drafting the rules of engagement, and the allegation would make its way into the prosecution of Randy Weaver.</p>
      <p>The situation really goes south on August 21st, 1992. The Marshals are still surveilling the Weavers. At some point, they throw rocks at the dogs to "test their reaction". A family friend Kevin Harris and Randy Weaver's 14-year-old son Sammy, believing the dogs had sighted game animals, come out of the cabin with rifles. The Marshals retreat through the woods briefly and are followed by the dogs. The dogs are followed by Kevin and Sammy. Accounts of what happens next are confused. The Marshals say they identified themselves as law enforcement. Kevin Harris says the did not. A gunfight breaks out. One of the Weavers' dogs is killed, at which point Sammy returns fire, before turning to flee. While running away, he is shot in the back. Kevin Harris then shoots and kills Deputy US Marshal Bill Degan.</p>
      <p>Things deteriorate further from there. FBI Sniper Lon Horiuchi sees Randy Weaver opening the shed where his dead son's body is stored. He shoots, wounding Weaver. Weaver, his 16-year-old daughter, and Harris run for the cabin. Horiuchi fires a second time, wounding Harris and killing Vicki Weaver, who at the time was standing in the doorway, holding her 10-month-old baby in her arms.</p>
      <p>Randy Weaver is eventually convinced to surrender to government agents. He and Kevin Harris are indicted on a variety of charges. Both are found not guilty on all counts, except Randy Weaver's charges of missing his initial court date and violating his bail provisions.</p>
      <p>But what does any of that have to do with gun control? Well, let me (very briefly I promise) retell the Ruby Ridge saga from a less charitable point of view. The ATF (which already has bad blood with gun owners) tries to get a guy to become an informant over two shotguns, based on a law that gun owners largely disagree with. He refuses. So the ATF sets up an operation using the US Marshals and the FBI to force him to comply. In doing so they kill Weaver's dog, son, and wife under unconstitutional rules of engagement. After all of that, a jury of his peers finds him not guilty of the charges they were trying to use to force him to become an informant on a violent white supremacist organization. Not a single person in the (Democrat-controlled) government suffers for this egregious act. Oh, and don't forget the ATF and Marshals services lied to everyone, including the courts, throughout this entire process.</p>
      <p>Doesn't exactly engender warm feelings, does it?</p>
      <p>Two years after Ruby Ridge, Congress passes, and Bill Clinton signs into law, the 1994 Assault Weapons Ban. The guns it targets are fairly niche and are only used in about 2% of homicides. In fact, they were really only owned by gun enthusiasts or members of the competitive shooting sports. If you were a gun owner in 1994, you might feel a little personally targeted, and the NRA wasn't much help. All they managed to accomplish was putting a 10-year sunset clause on it. The law says that guns that accept detachable magazines and have certain features are "assault weapons" and cannot be sold anymore. These features include adjustable stocks, pistol grips, bayonet mounts, flash hiders or threaded barrels, and grenade launchers.</p>
      <p>The Federal Assault Weapons Ban expired in 2004. <a href="https://www.factcheck.org/2013/02/did-the-1994-assault-weapons-ban-work/">Subsequent analyses</a> of the ban have shown it did not impact homicide rates. Analyses of its effect on mass shootings have been mixed, in large part due to differences in defining a mass shooting.</p>
      <h2>2004-Present</h2>
      <p>I may do a section on this later, which would largely focus on state-level politics.</p>
      <h2>Post</h2>
      <p>I have excluded quite a bit from this in order to stay within 30,000 characters. I did not, for example, discuss the Waco Siege, which has also engendered extremely poor feelings between gun owners and the ATF. I have not discussed the ATF's ongoing misconduct, which includes things like <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/national/archive/2013/12/allegations-against-the-atf-using-the-mentally-disabled-as-pawns/282226/">using the mentally ill</a> to create gun crime rings which the ATF would then bust. Or giving children weed and alcohol and convincing them to steal guns so they could arrest them on harsher charges (ibid). Or putting a felon in charge of a pawn shop, and arresting people who pawned firearms (ibid).</p>
      <hr />
      <p>3 of 3</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>