<post>
  <author>Lykurg480</author>
  <date>2020-02-20T23:53:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f53qhm/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_17/fi8ld5y/</link>
  <title>Steelmanning Folk Transscepticism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It certainly does a good job presenting your opinion, but I wouldnt hand this out to be convincing. The argument here is basically "Assume that Im 90% correct. Then it seems pretty reasonable that Im 100% correct.". This is a natural mistake to make if you dont understand your opponents, and as usual conservatives havent been very good at explaining themselves. So Ill try to give a semi-steelmanned example of what a trans-sceptical opinion might look like:</p>
      <p>Our everyday experience is a lot more complicated than we usually give it credit for. Theres thousands of things we see and hear and feel that we will never think about or remember. Youve propably heard of how you will start to see the car you think about buying everywhere on the streets. It has of course not become more common, you just didnt notice how much you saw it before, and now that your brain decided its important you do. I started seeing the ambulance cars everywhere after sitting in one for a month, even when I was in the back seat and not looking at the street. Sensitivity to these unreferenced experiences varies by person and topic: Sometimes they will pop up in your head as soon as youre in a situation where theyre vaguely relevant. Sometimes they pop up with a more direct prompt, like seeing a photo and noticing that you saw that guy today, even though you didnt pay any attention at the time. Often you just notice things you wouldnt have otherwise after something was brought to your attention. And sometimes you need to be pointed at something while its happening. This isnt all that controversial so far, where it gets interesting is applying this to emotional experience rather than perception. For example, imagine that for some reason I worry that I might be suicidal. My brain decides that signs that Im suicidal are extra important. So I might start to notice for example how Im looking forward to closing my eyes and the disappearence of my thoughts (it sure is getting late. 5 more minutes). Or how when Im near a high drop-off, I intrusively imagine jumping. Well, these are some decent signs. So my brain adjusts the worry up, and maybe then Ill notice even more signs. Now, I have some good reasons to think Im not suicidal. Pretty much everyone has experienced being tired, and its well communicated what its like. The thing about jumping I noticed because I read an article about it somewhere that also said its actually associated with lower suicide risks. But I also have a very good meta-reason, that being that theres a bajillion things I experience and I can find evidence for anything in there if my brain decides to look for it hard enough. This is why I havent actually worried about being suicidal, and can just give you these two measly examples of things I might find if I did. Now, imagine that for some reason you worry about being the wrong gender. Gender is far bigger part of our life than suicide. Theres so much for you to notice! Like how you sometimes spin and make vaguely ballet-like movements with your arms when youre happy. Or some dress you thought about trying on. Or one of thousands of other things you can read on any "Am I transgender?"-forum. And then you can think that yes, that seems like there might be something to that, and pay even more attention to it. Rinse and repeat. And once youre convinced, you have a whole belt full of "typical signs of being transgender". And then when you do scientific research on those, you will find for any given one, most trans people report having it and some cis people also do. But looking at all of them, trans people report far more of them than cis people. Just like the "clear scientific proof" that transgender is a "separate cluster in thingspace". Obviously this cant happen to just anyone. You have to start worrying about it for some reason - propably some trusted source telling you that hey, you might be. Also some signs youre initially aware of to make it credible - maybe hard to miss ones like gender nonconformity or autogenderphilia. And then you have to be someone who does notice the relevant experiences easily on prompting, and relatively quick to update your view of yourself, to keep the cycle going. So there is a certain predisposition to it, but most of that isnt about gender per se. If history had gone slightly differently, they could have been pretty normal or become obsessed with something else instead. As indeed they have! People have gotten crazy over all sorts of things, its no surprise that [salient topic] would be among them. This would also explain the high incidence of mental illnesses other than gender dysphoria.</p>
      <p>Point being, at "when I discovered my gender identity", youve already lost most of your potential readership.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>