<post>
  <author>Mexatt</author>
  <date>2020-02-21T18:15:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f53qhm/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_17/fiav1yd/</link>
  <title>Comparing Bernie's Platform to Scandinavia</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Part of the trick the Bernie crowd is playing on people is making them think universal healthcare == Medicare For All and all other countries have programs just like Medicare for All and they work fine.</p>
      <p>In truth, full single payer is relatively rare among OECD countries and, in those where it actually exists, none are quite as extreme as that proposed by Bernie. Canada gets closest and even then a <em>lot</em> of the details are administered at the provincial level, not the Federal level, so it's difficult to generalize.</p>
      <p>Norway, in particular, has a national health service similar to the one in the UK. There is a OOP fee with an annual max, however, something that Sanders has said his program wouldn't include.</p>
      <p>The other Nordic countries follow different models.</p>
      <p>Sweden is single payer but, again, has copays. It's also got some measure of multi-payer to it, with some Swedes choosing private health insurance. Sanders' plan bans private health insurance.</p>
      <p>Denmark is a bit weird. It's like Canada but on a much smaller scale. Health expenditures are 90% public, but they are spent by regional authorities, not the central government. They also have copays and there is private insurance to cover this cost. Once more, Medicare for All bans private insurance and claims it will not have copays.</p>
      <p>Finland is a mix of all three. There are a lot of municipally owned health institutions, there is a national insurance plan, there are private institutions making up a small portion of the market, and it all ties together into an interestingly complicated mess. I'm sure it makes more sense from the inside.</p>
      <p>The lesson to take away is that Sanders &amp; crew don't seem to have a detailed understanding of what Scandinavia actually looks like. They just want to use it as a selling point. His offering is more totalizing, more intrusive, more generous, and more expensive than what any Nordic country offers and really more so than anywhere else in the OECD. But they'd have you belief his plan is common, every day stuff elsewhere.</p>
      <p>Minimum wages in Northern Europe don't exist as a statutory thing and the minimum wages negotiated between the national labor federations and national employer organizations are <em>much</em> more flexible than a flat, $15 national minimum wage would be.</p>
      <p>Norway has precisely zero intention of 'transitioning to renewable energy sources with plans to get fossil fuel workers jobs in the new industry'. The country itself runs on rather green energy sources but the entire apparatus is utterly dependent on the export oil industry. The country would collapse without it. A Bernie or an AOC suggesting closing the oil industry down wouldn't get 10% of the vote in Norway.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>