<post>
  <author>pointsandcorsi</author>
  <date>2020-02-18T17:18:55Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f53qhm/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_17/fi0wrwh/</link>
  <title>Jobs Aren't Rewards</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Anyone else think that the concept of a job is handled backwards in popular culture? That is, a job is portrayed purely as a reward that carries a level of prestige proportional to the pay. Because jobs are "rewards," strange memes like "Jim doesn't deserve the job" or "Dave and Tom should get fired for those <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/newfoundland-labrador/racism-apology-labrador-1.5393719">comments</a>" are front and centre. The idea that someone is relied upon to provide a service of greater value than their salary seems to go unacknowledged.</p>
      <p>Further to that last example, not only did Dave and Tom get fired, their <em>employer</em> had their <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/newfoundland-labrador/nalcor-bans-men-churchill-falls-1.5392181">contract terminated</a>. I understand that the reason for these firings is meant to avoid a PR nightmare, but reporting angle makes no sense. The real story is that a general contractor had to pay a bunch of money to find new people to paint equipment for them, because two employees of the subcontractor were overheard saying inappropriate things on a plane. To the CBC, getting fired is akin to having your trophy taken away, which they obviously think is totally deserved. And maybe it is. But in reality, a firing in this circumstance means someone has to pay extra money to find someone else to do the job. This cost is completely ignored by the popular framing.</p>
      <p>While painting equipment might not have obvious "societal benefit" in the sense that an oncologist might, it clearly has economic value, and therefore... value. Imagine the same scenario with an oncologist in the middle of handling a patient at risk of dying. The oncologist says something rude on a plane. Would the CBC gleefully report that person's firing, if the replacement oncologist who has to pick up an unfamiliar case has a much lower likelihood of saving the patient? </p>
      <p>My conception of a job is an arrangement where an employee provides a service and the employer pays them. It's very difficult to measure exactly how much each employee "makes" for a company, but ideally every employee is a net economic benefit to the company. It's critically important to a company that it's employees are competent. I picture employees more like suppliers. If I'm an employer, I'm purchasing a service from Jim for $70k/year and selling it at a profit. If you tell me that someone other than Jim should have that job for a reason besides the profitability of the service, why would I listen for more than 10 seconds? </p>
      <p>This first principles approach gets harder to see in larger organizations. Employees are much farther removed from revenue generation, promotions can take the role of employee rewards, removing a bad employee can be more expensive than keeping him, and so on. Large companies can't afford to rely on individuals, so roles are meant to be as replaceable as possible. People's roles are less legible to bosses multiple levels above them. PR liability is much greater. If the organization is government, efficiency isn't actually worth anything because there are no stakeholders. There's also no threat of going out of business. While that's mostly to say that it's impossible to run an organization of 10,000 as tight as an organization of 10, but the first principles are exactly the same. In the narrative I see though, these principles are completely lost.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>