<post>
  <author>professorgerm</author>
  <date>2020-02-20T14:39:05Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f53qhm/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_17/fi6x563/</link>
  <title>Racial Categories</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <em>what does it mean for traditional racial categories to be "valid?"</em>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I disagree this is the question that needs answered. The better question is, are they <em>useful</em>? In what ways are they useful? What do they actually tell us that we <em>need to know</em>? I don't think they're that useful as more than a historical interest point.</p>
      <p>I think this is where the progressive side trips on its face; it tries to have its race-cake and eat it too: "oh they don't really exist but also they're super important and we're going to create legislation to protect people and give them stuff based on this thing that totally doesn't exist." </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>10% of self-IDed African-Americans can trace most of their ancestry to Europe.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Well... this would be one failure point, but isn't really a death knell for the definition. African-Americans (and really, not even AA, but specifically Black people) are one of the more admixed groups for the obvious historical reasons, but they still comprise a quite small percent of the world population. Biology is messy, and that it works for 95% but not 5% is kind of a stupid reason to throw something out <em>if there's not a better replacement</em> (hint: we don't have one yet) (see also gender being not quite binary but HIGHLY bimodal). </p>
      <p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_genetic_clustering">wiki page on human genetic clusters</a> is pretty good. K is the number of groupings, and k=5 (Africa, Eurasia (Europe, Middle East, and Central/South Asia), East Asia, Oceania, and the Americas ) might be the most common because it's the most useful. Take note there: oceans and mountains. Beyond this the split-offs get smaller and smaller, and less informative. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalash_people#Genetic_origins">Kalash people</a> might be most well-known for splitting off at K=7 for a population that's hardly a few tens of thousands, and they're more interesting than the K=6 tribes for political reasons. K=6 actually splits off an even smaller group, as it separates the Americas into "two Brazilian tribes of less than 2,000 people total" and "every other indigenous American."</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <strong>Racial identities match up with genetic ancestry.</strong>
        </p>
        <p>
          <strong>Racial identities correspond to clusters of human genetic variation</strong>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't think there's as much daylight here as you seem to think. You can only determine ancestry <em>by</em> variation. If there was no variation, we'd all be clones. Racial identities (except for 10% of Black people, or less than 1/10 of 1% of the world population) line up quite close to the ancestry genetic clustering. Race is different than ethnicity, though, and both are distinct from culture (well... sort of).</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>If this is true, then can't we split humans into hundreds, if not thousands, of races? </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It also depends on what genetic information you're looking at. Autosomal ancestry markers: K=5 reigns king. Y-haplogroups, however, are much more varied. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Y-DNA_haplogroups_by_ethnic_group">wiki pages are considerably less informative</a> (or rather, considerably more broken-up because it is finer-grained) and will break up much smaller groups. </p>
      <p>If you wanted to make a genetic "race versus ethnicity" distinction, this would be the way to do it. Autosomal info can get you "Eurasian" but Y haplogroups will get you "Kosovo Albanian" or distinguishing almost 20 kinds of Arab.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Why use "race," a term with heavy historical baggage and a widely-recognized popular meaning, to refer to genetic clusters when you could use "population" or "group" instead? </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Because most people are uneducated, and they stick with the term that's been used for decades if not centuries. Academics will use "populations" for this reason; good luck getting it into the popular discourse especially as long as people continue to use race for other reasons (terms like racist, employment quotas, scholarships, etc).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>