<post>
  <author>QWERT123321Z</author>
  <date>2020-02-13T07:07:58Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f1lmga/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_10/fhgstf4/</link>
  <title>Medical School Not Being Very Useful</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Medical school possibly more than any other form of schooling today is struggling to justify its own existence. </p>
      <p>For those that don't attend, you spend two years taking school exams and then a standardized exam. There's nothing wrong with that, until it becomes apparent that the school grades are essentially meaningless while the standardized exam score determines your <em>entire</em> future. This has led to lectures at my institution with less than <em>ten</em> out of two hundred people showing up and maybe half at best watching the lectures from home. Many schools have made their classes pass fail ostensibly because the grades cause stress but realistically because nobody cares about those grades anyway.</p>
      <p>Due to the standardized nature of the material, the professors are having to compete with third party instructors who actually know how to teach, and care about teaching material that matters. And frankly the professors are getting absolutely annihilated. The students opinion of them ranges from disinterest to well-earned avid hatred.</p>
      <p>At some point during medical school I began to wonder why the hell I was spending $100k a year to sit on the couch and watch youtube in order to run circles around people who studied the old way. I couldn't have done this from my couch back home on the other side of the country for literally less than 5% of the cost?</p>
      <p>Instead of fixing this in a productive manner the <em>ludicrously</em> out of touch medical school administrators instead opted for the option that made then look the best. This is unsurprising as medical school professors are some of the the most egotistical, self-congratulatory people I've had the displeasure of knowing. (We once had a lecture where a professor told us to study her classes over boards. The dean cut her off and said study for your boards. The <em>entire room</em> of 200 people went wild and started screaming like apes in favor. I wouldn't believe it if I wasn't there, it was a real-life movie experience).</p>
      <p>"Diversity" here is just tacked on. It's meaningless and boilerplate and we all know it.</p>
      <p>But to return to medical schools failing to justify their own existence:</p>
      <p>This is at least a partial admission from the bigwigs that, well, the stuff you learn for half of med school (at <em>least</em> half) is completely goddamned irrelevant to actual practice. I will never encounter a lysosomal storage disease nor be asked the inheritance of Tuberous Sclerosis. Of the past 24 months I've spent in school I've learned virtually nothing that has <em>any</em> utility in the real world. There have been exceptions, but the <em>vast</em> majority of medical school is facts learned for signalling rather than actual medical use.</p>
      <p>As a medical student, the only real differences between PAs and us are the expectations, human capital and postgraduate training offered. Yes, I sat through lectures on Organic Chemistry and Biochemistry while the PA didn't... but I don't remember any of it. I haven't retained 99% of the anatomy, either. <strong>Nobody does</strong>. The idea that doctors have X number of years of training while the PA has Y ignores the fact that <em>at least half</em> - I'd say even 75% + - of the medical students years are largely pointless signalling exercises. God help you if you take a research year which is <em>pure</em> signalling for the intended purpose of signalling.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>