<post>
  <author>Stefferi</author>
  <date>2020-02-20T09:22:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f53qhm/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_17/fi6e8cg/</link>
  <title>The Tactics of Sander's Socialist Branding</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm going to take a stab on why it was a smart thing for Bernie to campaign using the word 'socialist' from the get-go. I mean, many people have wondered why didn't just call himself a "New Deal Democrat" or something if much of what he proposes is closer to the New Deal than the Soviet Union, since that would be less abrasive.</p>
      <p>Basically, Bernie saw that there was a great deal of anti-party anger - aimed at DNC as well as RNC - that he could tap into. By specifically taking an abrasive but ideologically somewhat undefined term - like 'socialist' - he could turn it into a label for, basically, people who want to vote for the Democrats - but <em>not these lizards</em>. People who feel angry and dismissive about slick, focus-group-tested, jargon-spouting career-track Democrats, exemplified by the Hillary 2016 presidential campaign.</p>
      <p>If you were against all that, you could now vote for Bernie, and a part of Bernie's appeal was that he would basically go "yeah, I'm a socialist, so what?" after decades of Republicans slurring capitalist Democrats as socialists and Democrats weakly countering that no, we're not socialists, we love freedom! It sounds different, it sounds strange, there's a "did-he-just-do-that?" reaction - that's why it's appealing to Bernie voters, it wouldn't pass focus groups!  That's also why, when you look into Bernie voters, you find a surprising amount of more conservative Democrats, or at least that applied in 2016; those types have also felt angry about DNC's variant of urban city-slicker liberalism, and Bernie offered them a way to go against them.</p>
      <p>Of course, the main matching pattern on the Republican side is obvious - the current President - but I think that what's happened with the word 'socialist' is the same as with the word 'libertarian' on the GOP side, for some time - similarly, it's obvious to me that 'libertarian' had less a connotation of the strict doctrinaire libertarianism that you find in ideological libertarian circles and more of "Republican, but <em>not these lizards</em>", often specifically aimed at the equally fake and artificial Evangelical GOP subculture that had a lot of strength in the party. </p>
      <p>Of course, that didn't necessary mean that people calling themselves libertarians would be very libertarian, as Libertarian Party has had to find out a number of times, and it's no surprise that many of Ron Paul supporters, for example, would go over to Trump as soon as there was a better way to indicate that you are Republican, but <em>not these lizards</em>.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>