<post>
  <author>TexasJefferson</author>
  <date>2019-12-03T09:09:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e4u7a6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_02/f9jalda/</link>
  <title>X/Harm when evaluating claims</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>In that case, having stepped over or near the line, is 0.2% really that punitive or scary?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>There is a habit by which folks dismiss harms by picking out a sufficiently large denominator as to make the harm look small by means of division. It would be an even tinier number, if you were to compare to American GDP over the last 240 years. It would also be about as relevant.</p>
      <p>Fines Uber acquires as they 'extra-legally' enter a new city are fair game to evaluate as a cost of doing business. On the other hand, this is, in some ways, akin to a fine paid for having decorated an office wrong (indeed, it is possible that literally that could be among the issues). If your corporate bureaucracy realizes that a given office design costs an extra $10,000,000 compared to what management sees as roughly the same workhouse, well, it's not a negligible disincentive on its own. We can observe the results across every large company in the US to see exactly how effective—which is to say for its detractors, scary—the current enforcement of legally-mandated professional decorum is. (Most companies can never hope to be as wildly profitable as a run-away, international gaming success but penalties/settlements/judgements/etc. for workplace harassment claims aren't, AFAIK, scaled for profitability-per-employee.)</p>
      <p>But, ofc., we're not looking at the settlement as an isolated payment—it's just a small manifestation of the larger disciplinary apparatus. If Riot chose the other path, to value it's apparently terrible frat culture, own it, say that's just who they were and if you didn't like it, go elsewhere, what happens then? The state would begin dismantling them until they relent. If current management refused, they would be replaced by the board; if the board refused, a judge could let minority shareholders ditch them (less clear how likely that'd actually be); if the board's power were maintained or the shareholders were united, their assets would be taken piecemeal by plaintiffs and the government until there was nothing left.</p>
      <p>The state's power is always terrifying, even when only a little bit of it is on display.</p>
      <p>To avoid further aggravation, Riot will do the opposite: it will empower a bureaucracy to protect it (notably, this may not actually help the people suffering in the current culture that much). Folks whose performance does not justify the legal risk they impose will be dropped. The culture will be dissolved into yet another indifferent inoffensive corporate soup. Employees will waste a few extra hours each year in insulting trainings, and everyone involved from the interns to the CEO will hang their own greengrocer's sign.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Elide that discussion for a second, or just assume that there is some place on that continuum that we've chosen.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Every law which is to be enforced requires an inhuman willingness to break any entity that rejects its demands. It is a blunt instrument, wielded bluntly. For this reason, we should be very careful when deciding how to encode morality and cultural expectations into it.</p>
      <p>Talking about drawing a line, as if, <em>a priori</em> it were known that it was appropriate to draw one at all and we just need to hill-climb to a local optimum is already begging most of the harm.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>