<post>
  <author>4bpp</author>
  <date>2020-03-29T05:24:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fneib4/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_23_2020/flt515f/</link>
  <title>The Prevalence of Conversion Narratives</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This isn't the first time I have seen some variation of this post, and every time they seem to follow a pattern that registers as "I was genuinely deluded into believing a, b and c with my whole heart... and then it fell like scales from my eyes... I started seeing the fnords... and finally I came around to a realisation that I surely would have made sooner if only I had listened to my heart: not abc, but e, f and in particular g (!!!) are actually true".</p>
      <p>Considered in a vacuum, every single one of these conversion stories looks compelling, genuine, and only a complete cynic without a shred of charity or assumption of good faith could assume that the poster is not telling a personal tale of their internal dialogue with universal reason and morality, which should give us all pause and invite us to reinvestigate our assumptions as well. Only, it turns out that a, b and c are exactly standard beliefs of one prominent tribe in the country/cultural landscape they hail from, and e, f ang g are standard beliefs of another tribe, and moreover the particularly alarming point g is a particularly prominent wedge issue between those tribes.</p>
      <p>Could this just be what "falling in with a different tribe/friend group" feels like from the inside, as your brain engages in parallel construction to generate a narrative where the shift in beliefs was due to reasoning as opposed to a deep-seated drive to agree with the beliefs of your peers and allies? I certainly feel that something in <em>me</em> is pulling in that direction ever since I have started spending an inordinate amount of time on post-awokening internet culture wars. Whatever my positions on other left/right topics may be, as an early emigrant child into a higher-prestige country where the common people absolutely despised my ethnicity (Eastern Europe-&gt;Germany), I almost naturally grew up to be (and still am, on an intellectual level) the staunchest internationalist, and a younger me would have unblinkingly, or even with some extent of sadistic glee, cheered on the full gamut of right-wing bogeyman fantasies like "population replacement", "flag-desecration ceremonies" or what-not. (I think I've outgrown the sadism, but still believe in measures against ethnic consciousness and nationalism.) Yet, after years of finding myself on the "deplorable" side of  academic SJ, feminism and American-style diversity celebration arguments, I find that on an <em>emotional</em> level, my instinct has turned to want to <em>defend</em> the nationalists (who just happened to usually be on my side in the unrelated SJ topics), and take the <em>globalists</em> down a peg, wherever they clash. As far as I know, nothing of note happened to cause me to update against my anti-nationalist views (unless you want to count some rare instance of "okay, the EU probably does empower paper-pushers who are criminally incompetent at their job, cf. the electric kettle power limitation rules"), which I certainly had told myself (and am still telling myself!) are based on data - but I do get these feeling that, if condensed into words, amount to "wouldn't it be <em>nice</em> if you could find some evidence to shift your beliefs against the globalist camp? Look, Dominic Cummings wants to explosively increase university funding! Isn't that a good reason?".</p>
      <p>(I do have to say, though, that nothing about what is apparently now my tribe has so far pushed me to desire reasons to be against abortion, as the inferential distance to considering fetuses human is just insurmountably high (making it easier to rationalise the opposition as "tribal markers"+"actually wanting to impose control on sexual activity through the backdoor"). To me even newborns register as something closer to insect larvae, deserving of protection only insofar as they are insect larvae that some small number of humans have an extreme degree of emotional investment in, and because birth is a better Schelling point than having to agree on some definition of the end of the bug-thing stage.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>