<post>
  <author>crushedoranges</author>
  <date>2020-03-30T10:48:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/frkulx/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_30_2020/flwu6np/</link>
  <title>Anime Tiddies Are the Salvation of Western Civilization</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>As an alt-right big anime tiddie supporter, I'd like to say my piece. </p>
      <p>Tautologically, that which is pleasing to the eye is beautiful. You don't have to be a tradcon to appreciate the beauty of a young girl, the lewdness of a mature woman, or the cuteness of a feminine boy. People are, in short, attracted to the ideal, and our artwork reflects both our worship and pursuit of it. </p>
      <p>What is inherently wrong with the social justice perspective is that they seek to change this. Because what is considered attractive is not evenly distributed throughout society, by wiping the slate clean of biology and culture they can enforce new standards of aesthetic perfection. That is why you see short-haired women of vibrant hair color in your fiction in the West of avante-garde fashion. Some Hollywood casting magnate is trying to manipulate your opinion on what is beautiful for the high ideal of representation. Which is why they all look like metropolitan victims of a maniac barber from Hot Topic.</p>
      <p>It will never work. No matter how much they contrive to remove every feminine quality from the cultural milieu, men will still be attracted to <em>feminine</em> women, and vis versa. If there's going to be a genderqueer bisexual paradise it won't be gotten by poking sticks into the eyes of a heterosexual audience. Western media has been wholly consumed by this... </p>
      <p>...which is why anime is a good thing. No matter how much moeshit and harem isekais come out of the commercial mill, at least it has a <em>audience</em> for such things. They exist to make money, which is infinitely more tolerable than being made for a progressive <em>message</em>. The only asylum you'll find from the all-consuming culture war is in foreign media. When you watch Konosuba, you're not worried that you'll get an immersion-breaking lecture on feminism from the main heroines. When you watch Vinland Saga, you're not expecting to suddenly see a host of diverse people in an ostensibly historical work. </p>
      <p>In anime, it's still in a halycon age, where men are men, women are women, and I can enjoy the work based on its merits rather than be skeptical at a potential propaganda piece. </p>
      <p>TL:DR Anime tiddies are the salvation of western civilization, fite me</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>