<post>
  <author>cvdailyupdates</author>
  <date>2020-03-29T01:11:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fo3q5e/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_three/flskkly/</link>
  <title>How Twitter and Reddit Outperformed Institutions on COVID-19</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>My claim is not "Twitter and reddit, writ large, outperformed official institutions." </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'll make this claim.</p>
      <p>Almost every piece of content on my site is sourced from Reddit.</p>
      <p>Aside from there, the only other data sources I've used really are news articles and medical papers being linked around on Discord and 4chan.</p>
      <p>The 'weaponized autism' of all these internet people has dramatically outperformed our official institutions. It has done this, mostly, by just massively signal boosting relevant signals. </p>
      <p>It's not even <em>really</em> a failure of our institutions, it's just, like, (to use an analogy) we're here using the newfangled telegraph to communicate things in real time, and our institutions were built during an era of courier'd mail. It's not that they're even doing anything badly, it's just that we are moving faster than them because of fundamental differences in our toolsets. </p>
      <p>I agree with darwin above when he says</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I'm pretty sure you would have been monumentally worse off following the advice of a random sampling of people on Twitter/reddit than following the WHO.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>But I don't think it's relevant. Of course there's a million idiots on twitter and reddit. But that's why we ignore them. I know this is kind of a special pleading argument, and it basically reduces down to "if you only pay attention to the good sources, the sources are good", but it really is like that. There's a sort of background evolutionary pressure going on where there's enough smart people looking at these things, from enough different perspectives, that relevant information gets surfaced pretty quickly, and bullshit either gets suppressed, or we all recognize it as BS and mock it. </p>
      <hr />
      <p>Of course, I also am generally aligned with TW here regarding the WHO and China. I think that the WHO has been criminally incompetent in this, if not outright corrupt. I've talked about it elsewhere, but I agree that they have been pushing China's preferred narratives for a while now. One thing that was instructive was watching their actions during the mission to Wuhan. Right up to when they dispatched doctors to Wuhan (which China forced them to wait several weeks before allowing), the WHO was pushing "just the flu". Within days of their mission ending, they got quite a bit more somber and serious. I read this as "they foolishly believed China's downplaying, and then when they had a first-hand view of what it was like at ground zero, they realized how bad it was". </p>
      <p>The blatant flip flopping is also bad. It's not just eg the flip from "it's just the flu" to "it's worse than the flu". That alone could be forgiven if they updated in response to better data. But they didn't just update. They 1) updated; 2) pretended that all the previous guidance they said regarding "it's just the flu" never happened; and 3) started aggressively shaming everyone who would listen to them for not preparing sooner. Of course they didn't prepare, you kept telling them they didn't have to! They have just seamlessly disavowed all responsibility for all the downplaying they've done, and it sneaks under the radar by blaming other governments.</p>
      <p>Now, I think I also agree that "now is not the time". It is clear that China is playing geopolitical games. They are quite good at soft power. The middle of a crisis is not the time for the WHO to take a politically controversial stand. Yes, the cost of this is that the data from Taiwan gets ignored. I don't think this is the Right Thing, but I think is the Least Wrong Thing <em>Possible</em> Right Now. </p>
      <hr />
      <p>Re: other institutions, I still agree. I still don't understand exactly what happened with the CDC and FDA but it seems pretty inexcusable to me. Even more inexcusable is the fact that, at least as far as I know, no leaders or politicians or bureaucrats have even come out and explained "yep, we fucked up, sorry, we fixed it". I guess that's an unrealistic expectation. </p>
      <hr />
      <blockquote>
        <p>EG, it would be bad for someone to take away the message 'The WHO has proven themselves untrustworthy, therefore if they recommend ashing my hands 5 times a day I should ignore them. I would more or less trust the medical advice they give and their general efforts to help people, while still wishing for reforms or a better alternative in the future.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I disagree with this on three grounds.</p>
      <p>First, there is the game-theory-spite perspective. When a person or organization abuses your trust, you <em>have to</em> reduce your trust in them, across the board, as a strategic incentive for them to not lie, about anything. Even if the WHO's China-related lies have no bearing on medical anything (I don't agree with this, but granting it), part of the function of degrading the trust I put in them <em>in general</em> is to punish them for lying. The idea is "your core mission is public health. You engaged in actions I consider to be immoral. Consequently, I am in retaliation sabotaging your public health initiative, by refusing to believe it. Now you have to make a decision on if the temporary benefit of lying for China is worth sacrificing your public health mission for".</p>
      <p>Another possible silly analogy is that if my friend steals money from me, I'm not going to invite him over for dinner anymore. One might say "come on, whether or not he steals is orthogonal to whether or not he's a good dinner guest", and one might be correct! But I have as a terminal value "don't steal from me", and revoking dinner invitations are not done because I think the theft makes dinner taste bad, but as a retaliatory measure intended to punish him for stealing. </p>
      <p>Secondly: Character flaws and instances of immorality <em>tend to</em> be correlated. Sure, there is no logical deduction that proves that lying about China has anything to do with trustworthiness with public health. But <em>in practice</em>, <em>heuristically</em>, an entity that is happy to lie about one thing will tend to be happy to lie about other things. Consequently, downgrading your trust in them <em>in general</em> in response to a specific violation of trust makes sense, even if you can't prove it, because heuristically it will be correct more often than it's not</p>
      <p>But thirdly: I disagree that there is no public health implication to their lies. One of the effects of China's downplaying everything so hard is that the west didn't properly prepare (note: the west is plenty guilty of incompetence on their own, and none of this should be taken to absolve them of responsibility). The WHO knew-or-should-have-known that these were lies (these = "no h2h transmission", "the flu is worse", "screening and quarantining is unnecessary and pointless", "masks don't work", etc), but by repeating them, they impeded the response in the west. </p>
      <p>I am not a doctor. I am not properly equipped to judge whether any individual thing that the WHO says is reliable. I am also not a geopolitical strategist. I am not properly equipped to judge whether China would plausibly lie about, or stand to benefit from, any particular public health claim. But now I have an existence proof that a) the WHO is more than willing to signal-boost CCP lies; and b) they are not concerned about the potential impact to public health from doing so. <em><strong>Because I am fundamentally ill-equipped to judge where this is likely to be relevant</strong></em>, it <em><strong>could</strong></em> be relevant <em><strong>anywhere</strong></em>. Consequently I have a serious trust bootstrapping problem, where the only consistent position is to assume that <em>anything</em> they say is potentially contaminated with lies pending better, <em>trustworthy</em> data</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>