<post>
  <author>FCfromSSC</author>
  <date>2020-03-27T17:46:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fneib4/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_23_2020/flo412r/</link>
  <title>Media Bias and the Biden Sexual Assault Allegation</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>One of the frequent topics of conversation here is whether or not "the media" is "biased". We've been over it so many times that most of the regulars here can probably do both sides of the conversation on autopilot. The last several iterations, I've seen an argument that I and others have disagreed strongly with, but for which it seemed like a more substantive response was needed.</p>
      <p>The argument as I understand it goes something like this:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"This thing Red Tribers refer to as 'The Media' doesn't actually exist. Sure, there are partisan blue tribe outlets, but there are also partisan Red Tribe outlets, and that balances things out. Sure, ~90% of journalists vote Democrat, but the vast majority of talk radio is Red Tribe to the core. The two sides might not be symmetrical in every respect, but that doesn't justify a narrative of Blue Tribe media locking down the national conversation or brainwashing people. It certainly doesn't justify Red Tribe's growing attitude that the Press is the enemy of the people. "</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't buy this argument, because I think it ignores how the Media actually works, how the national conversation actually works, and the glaring vulnerabilities in the way our society frames and engages with news and current events. My counterargument would be something like this:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The thing Red Tribe refers to as "The Media" absolutely exists. We can point to the corporations, organizations and individuals involved. We can observe their behavior in detail via social media. We can see that they coordinate stories, takes and talking points. We can see that their relative prestige is self-reinforcing, as high-status institutions ignore, excuse and cover for each others' misdeeds and mistakes. We can see how their closed-cycle-human-centipede ecosystem creates the illusion of consensus, and how it uses that illusion to drown out competing perspectives and narratives, turning the national conversation into a monoculture.  </p>
        <p>Further, all these advantages are greatly amplified by Blue Tribe dominance in other high-status institutions like education, Academia, the Federal Beauracracy, and so on. When the people taking action, the people assessing that action and the people writing about both the action and the assessment are all unified by partisan political interest,  </p>
        <p>Red Tribe media might have a large and loyal audiance, but that is not enough to counteract the self-reinforcing and self-amplifying effects of Blue Tribe social dominance. Red Tribe media can occasionally force *a* story into the national conversation to the point that Blue Tribe media has to respond to it. Blue Tribe media IS the national conversation by default, and everything they decide to push Red Tribe media has to respond to or be left behind. Further, the sheer disparity in numbers on each side is telling; blue tribe can try an order of magnitude more takes in more outlets than Red Tribe can, which gives them far more chances to strike on something viral. They also have a far greater ability to force virility by sheer volume of output; it's easier to establish that "everyone is talking about it" when 90% of the people talking are working together to coordinate a message.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Of course, I would think that. I'm a mindkilled Red Tribe culture warrior. So probably if I want to make these sorts of inflammatory claims, I should bring evidence. Fortunately, it seems like there's a pretty good piece of evidence at hand.</p>
      <p>At some point wednesday, online outlets started reporting that Joe Biden <a href="https://twitter.com/kthalps/status/1242691746561167360">has been accused of sexual assault</a>. A former staffer claims that on a certain day in 1993 Biden began kissing her, pushed her up against a wall, and penetrated her with his fingers. Apparently, the staffer claims she told a few close friends about the assault at the time, and those friends have confirmed that she did indeed tell them.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://theintercept.com/2020/03/24/joe-biden-metoo-times-up/">Reade had previously come forward</a> to join other women in accusing Biden of sexual harassment via inappropriate touching. She claims to have made a formal complaint at the time of the touching, and also claims that others witnessed it. When she came forward, however, she suffered severe online harassment and accusations that she was a Russian agent. Reade reached out to Time's Up, a legal organization established in the wake of the #MeToo movement to help survivors tell their stories. Time's Up declined to assist her, claiming that since her accusation was against a candidate for federal office, assisting her might threaten the organization's non-profit status.</p>
      <p>It's been two days since I saw the initial report on a filthy Red Tribe ghetto blog. CNN still has no story about the allegations. Neither does MSNBC. Neither does CBS. Neither does Fox News. One might argue that the pandemic is swamping out all other issues, but all three outlets have in fact posted stories about Joe Biden since the allegations were made public. Meawhile, the story is slowly pushing its way up through the news ecosystem, with reports gradually accumulating from <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/lifestyle/joe-biden-former-staffer-alleges-152313133.html">smaller</a> and <a href="https://thefederalist.com/2020/03/27/read-biden-accusers-account-of-his-alleged-sexual-assault/">more</a><a href="https://reason.com/2020/03/26/joe-biden-tara-reade-sexual-assault-me-too-believe-women/">partisan</a><a href="https://www.washingtonexaminer.com/opinion/biden-supporters-face-metoo-reckoning-after-tara-reade-accuses-him-of-sexual-assault">outlets</a>,  but nothing from the major outlets.</p>
      <p>We've had a variety of examples from the recent past of how "the media" handles scandalous allegations when they pertain to Red Tribe. Covington, Smollett, Kavanaugh, and Trump spring immediately to mind, and none of them involved sitting on a juicy story for 48 hours. Presumably the story will continue to grow, and the major outlets will be forced to address it once it hits critical mass on its own, probably sometime this weekend or early next week. It's going to be an interesting example of how media bias impacts our political process and our society as a whole.</p>
      <p>The main thing I'd like to point out, though, is how powerful media bias is in a space like this one. We have a community here that is supposed to be about high effort and high standards, but we're only human after all. For the most part, we talk about what the media talks about, <em>whether we agree with that media or not</em>.</p>
      <p>Synthesizing other people's arguments is orders of magnitude easier than generating novel arguments yourself, and the media, and especially the prestige media, are by far the biggest argument generator in existence. This gives them an unparalleled ability to steer conversations society-wide, simply by picking which issues or events to spotlight, and how to contextualize them. Over time, this dynamic becomes instinctual for consumers such as ourselves, and we converge on a point where things are real to the extent that the prestige media talk about them.</p>
      <p>I saw the story about Biden two days ago, and I didn't post about it here because I saw it in the Red Tribe ghetto, and so I didn't know if it was real or not. I'm posting about it now because it's starting to get picked up by enough outlets that I'm now sufficiently confident. But my own behavior is granting de facto control to a system that I know for a fact hates me and wishes me harm. I don't think I'm the only one doing this, and I don't think our usual conversations about the media account for this behavior.</p>
      <p>Red or Blue, we talk about what the media talks about, and we talk about it <em>the way the media talks about it</em>. Above, I've laid out a narrative about sexual assault allegations, and a compare and contrast to the handling of similar allegations against Red Tribe targets, and so anyone reading this is probably thinking about the story in those terms. What they're probably not thinking about is the online harassment angle. Why not? Online harassment against women speaking out has been a serious issue in the national news before. Why not this time?</p>
      <p>...Maybe because the media isn't making it the issue, and so it isn't real?</p>
      <p>[EDIT] - Stories are now up on Fox, Vox, huffpost,  and other mainstream sources.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>