<post>
  <author>JTarrou</author>
  <date>2020-03-28T10:33:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fq2uow/its_time_to_abolish_the_enlistedofficer_divide/flqepvm/</link>
  <title>Some Notes on the US Officer Corps</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>How so? It would take ten-ish years to reach "officer" status, but that makes your low-level officers actually in tactical command twenty-eight to thirty. By thirty-five to forty they'd be moving on to staff positions, and by forty-five ready for higher command, with the general-level guys shaking out from that.   Which frankly, sounds like the management system of most large organizations. Nobody else is complaining that their managers can't possibly have enough time to rise through the ranks unless they get a head start for their college degree.</p>
      <p>Our generals are already old, historically speaking. Alexander started in his teens (but had a lifetime of training for the job). Even in the US, the youngest general in Army history (the wonderfully named Uriah Galusha Pennypacker) was twenty when promoted to general.</p>
      <p>But as a side note, when the military was downsized in the early '90s, the officer corps all tried (mostly successfully) to keep their rank and commissions by creating vast numbers of new, do nothing jobs for officers to do that had previously not been done, or been done by the enlisted. Our officer to enlisted ratio rose to one in five. Even the war on terror has not slowed the trend, the officer to enlisted ratio has <a href="https://mtntactical.com/knowledge/officers-less-enlisted-changing-force-structure-u-s-military/">increased</a> 21% since 2000. A decent write-up about the bloat in the officer corps <a href="https://www.chicagotribune.com/news/ct-xpm-1988-03-25-8803030455-story.html">here</a>. Only problem is that it's from 1988, and the problem has worsened considerably since then. If we slashed the officer corps back to a reasonable size, there would be plenty of advancement potential for the ones that remain. It's hard to get ahead as an officer right now, because there are far more officers than units to command.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>