<post>
  <author>OPSIA_0966</author>
  <date>2020-03-25T10:16:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fo3q5e/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_three/flg5esi/</link>
  <title>The Overwhelming Leftward Bias of Reddit</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>We can see from sites like 8chan/4chan (both examples of noticeable online sites with a distinctly rightist bent, and also coincidentally enough two of the least censorious) that young people can absolutely lean right too though. And "leaning left" doesn't necessarily mean practicing reddit's particular brand of absolute feelings-safe, almost entirely self-unaware censorship either (which is a hallmark of the mainstream, censorious left, not necessary every left-wing group), as groups like the Cum Town podcast's fanbase or /leftypol/ prove (though I'd say it's still justifiable to say that the left is overall more censorious and increased censorship and left-wing takeovers tend to go hand-in-hand).</p>
      <p>I just don't think you can explain the left-wing bent of reddit purely demographically. <a href="https://www.pewforum.org/fact-sheet/public-opinion-on-abortion/">For example, this public opinion poll suggests that 30% of Americans 18-29 are still more anti-abortion than not (and I don't think you can attack this with the usual objections about how polls phrase questions as, due to the issue's longevity and intensity, people's opinions on abortion are fairly crystallized and consistent I'd imagine).</a></p>
      <p>And yet on almost all reddit subs (including all of the ones that are most representative of "mainstream reddit culture"), in any thread about abortion, you'd be lucky to see maybe 1 out of 100 comments (being highly generous) expressing an anti-abortion viewpoint, and of course they'd all be heavily downvoted. I remember reading an AskReddit thread, one marked with a serious tag, around 13 hours after it was posted that asked pro-lifers to explain their position... which failed because not a single pro-lifer showed up in the thread. reddit isn't just mildly biased; it's basically a one-sided affair (with a few people from the other side who stick around purely because they like going against the vast, rabid majority) in most cases.</p>
      <p>The case for reddit gets even worse still when you adjust a youth-based explanation for its leaky abstractions, for example that other age groups do use reddit still too, maybe not as much, but definitely still a decent amount (and also still almost always overwhelmingly lean as left as reddit's younger users despite their age group's more conservative views in general).</p>
      <p>We know that it wasn't always this way either. With its early free speech absolutist rhetoric and willingness to host every kind of community from racists advocating genocide to pedophiles posting (legal, technically, or at least supposedly) pictures of preteens in thongs to users engaging in questionable transactions involving drugs and firearms, reddit quite obviously attracted a distinctly libertarian-leaning userbase at first, a userbase with the type of broad tolerance for a diversity of opinion, content, and expression that's basically antithetical to the modern left as embodied by mainstream reddit now.</p>
      <p>So we know reddit started out more libertarian than anything else. We know that it took a drastic turn toward the hard censorious left (in a way that sometimes even marginalizes even left-wingers that are less censorious, though still not as much as their right-wing counterparts) around a half a decade ago and is now far more left-wing than any natural demography can explain. And we have countless examples of blatantly left-favoring censorship on reddit and basically not a single example of right-favoring censorship (outside of deliberately marginalized right-wing subs like <a href="/r/The_Donald">/r/The_Donald</a>, which by the way has been effectively shut down by the admins, turning themselves into right-wing circlejerks in protest of reddit's greater left-wing circlejerk), certainly not on the admin or powermod levels. How much more evidence do we need that reddit leans left and that, while demographic factors may explain some of it, the absolute nature of its bias (that transformed the entire site and its usebase from what it used to be) is definitely the result of top down edicts coming from its operators in San Francisco?</p>
      <p>To deny that reddit is heavily and deliberately biased toward the left is like living in London, having someone pour a bucket of water on you every day, and dismissing it with "Well yes it's rainy in England." Sure, it is, but not to the point of soaking you every day unless something else is going on.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>