<post>
  <author>ruhend</author>
  <date>2020-03-30T00:02:47Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fneib4/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_23_2020/flvloq0/</link>
  <title>The Weakness of Meta-Awareness</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>That it is not inherently good to value higher levels of meta-awareness.  In so far as I think I am similar to the people on this subreddit, this may also apply to you.  But the fact that this post is in response to a meta-comment on a meta-thread in a meta-subreddit tells me that you all are indeed similar to me.</p>
      <p>Self-awareness is a fundamental part of the human condition in a social and evolutionary sense.  It yields information that is inaccessible to those who are not self-aware.  Self-awareness is expanded by moving up the levels of meta-awareness.  It is easy to forget that the impulse to move up the ladder is not a good in itself, it must be justified by something else.  </p>
      <p>In a social sense it is interesting.  Using this post as an example: <a href="/u/BurdensomeCount">/u/BurdensomeCount</a> gave us a question that put those of us who reply in a position to show off how skillfully aware and intelligent we are but also a position to look like pompous assholes and complete dunces.  We are to offer something that is to be adequately insightful at the next-highest meta level of analysis about the most meta-subreddit on this meta(content-aggregator)-site.  In doing so, we will have displayed how unaware all the other members of this subreddit are, a subreddit filled with people who value meta-awareness.  I have replied with a meta-comment, which amplifies the stakes.</p>
      <p>Moving down the levels can also be evolutionarily good:  A man lost in thought runs into a pole.  This pole serves as a reminder that he needs to place more value on his direct perception, rather than on higher meta-levels.  </p>
      <p>But, for the more mundane parts of our lives when we are sitting about searching for some glimpse of an interesting thing to engage in, we generally considered meta to be a good in itself.</p>
      <p>The bubble popped when I realized that most of the real vigor I get in my day-to-day life come from lower levels of meta-awareness.  I had not repaid this vigor with the adequate attention that these lower meta-states have deserved.  I also realized that many of the people who seem most engaged with life are those who don't like to think about meta-narratives, they just enjoy participating in their narratives.  And their narratives mean life or death, because they have no meta-narratives to escape to.</p>
      <p>In order to enjoy a movie, I have to temporarily abandon meta-awareness in order to fully engage with what is happening.  I can't think about things I will do later, the cinematography, who the actors are, etc. because then I won't experience the movie as it is intended to be experienced: as though all of the scenes are actually happening before my eyes and the plot meant life or death.</p>
      <p>I have found that my pursuit of meta-awareness was not based on some principle, but rather my own interest in the meta-levels.  The bubble popped when my own interests had shifted but my value system remained with 'the pursuit of higher meta-levels' inscribed at the top.</p>
      <p>Meta is not good unto itself.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>