<post>
  <author>Winter_Shaker</author>
  <date>2020-03-31T10:27:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/frkulx/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_30_2020/fm09wad/</link>
  <title>The Multicultural Attraction of the Major Scale</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diatonic_scale">major scale as we know it</a> is originally based on simple frequency ratios between notes (the octave is a ratio of 1:2, the fifth is based on 2:3, the major third is based on 4:5, etc), as discovered, or at least as first talked about, by the Ancient Greeks.</p>
      <p>After taking that process as far as they felt worthwhile, figuring out a series of increasingly complex ratios, music theorists noticed that there were twelve very-approximately-equal divisions you could split the octave into, of which you only wanted a limited set based on the simpler ratios in any given melody (or, if you were to throw in the other ones, there would still be only a limited set that constituted the main ones that your melody was at home in, with the others being sort of spicy filler notes). In Europe, people decided that they liked the set of seven that we now call the diatonic scale ("major", if you like, but the same set of seven notes also gets you the natural minor and all the old church modes).</p>
      <p>The Middle East took this process further than most - they carried on subdividing the frequency ratios until they had a scale that included quarter-tones, but they weren't fundamentally doing anything different. The modern <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arabic_maqam">maqam</a> system common to Arabic, Turkish, Persian etc music (with presumably some variations too subtle for me to be aware of) <em>contains</em> the Western diatonic scale as a subset of all of its possible scales.</p>
      <p>The important thing to note is that vibrating strings naturally contain a blend of these intervals, as do most column-of-air type instruments such as flutes (cylinders which are closed at one end, like clarinets, trombones etc, add some weird complications that I won't go into). That is, the note you hear is made up of the nominal frequency plus all the whole-number multiples of that frequency, so when you play two simple-ratio notes together, most of their overtones are actually the same. Music based on these intervals will sound 'in tune with itself' as long as you take as your home key the frequency that you are basing your ratios on. If you build a keyboard tuned to that scale, you can't venture too far from the home key before your chords start to sound out of tune.</p>
      <p>As far as I understand it, this set of simple frequency ratios was discovered independently in China and Europe and also I think India, though I'm less sure ... but in China they decided they only needed the five simplest ratios, to produce the pentatonic scale (one of the things that gives traditional Chinese music its distinctive sound is that it avoids semitones). Presumably something similar happened in Africa as well, since the pentatonic scale is widespread there, but I know little about African traditional music.</p>
      <p>At a later stage, European music theorists noticed that if you squeezed the tuning of the twelve notes just a little, you could make them twelve exactly equal divisions of the octave - 'equal temperament' - and although none of your intervals are perfect simple whole-number ratios any more apart from the octave, all of them are still about close enough that the human ear isn't bothered by it, unless you are playing on an instrument with very powerful overtones. That allows you to play in any key, which is what made it possible for European classical music to venture off and explore the wild world of harmony to a greater extent than any other independly-evolved tradition.</p>
      <p>India, meanwhile, nominally recognises a basic scale of seven notes (in the sense that it has separate names for seven notes, sa, re, ga, ma, pa, da, ni, analogous to do, re, mi etc.) but is happy to incorporate both the flat version and the sharp version (there are low and high versions of all but Sa and Pa, for the same twelve total that European music has) in the same raga (if you tune your 'sa' to what we would call C, your raga could well include both B natural and B flat, though it might do something like using one of them only when going up the scale and the other only when coming down),,, but it also recognises 'shrutis' - tiny microtonal intervals such that each of the twelve notes, again with the exception of Sa and Pa have a barely-perceptible distinction between a high and a low form. I think you need to be really <em>really</em> paying attention during the slow meditative 'alap' section of a recital to be able to make out this distinction at all, since the shrutis are roughly within the same tiny narrow space of tuning that distinguished European equal temperament from the old 'just intonation' based on the simple ratios.</p>
      <p>Interestingly, the cultural region that most conspicuously rejected this system Indonesia (and to a lesser extent pasrts of mainland South East Asia), has a classical music tradition heavily based on tuned percussion, and in particular, metal tuned percussion: gongs, bells and metallophones (i.e. like a xylophone except with metal bars), and those instruments do <em>not</em> tend to produce overtones in harmonic ratios in the way that strings or woodwind instruments do. If, because of the physical properties of your instruments, the notes of your scale sound no more consonant with each other in the diatonic scale than in some other scale, there's no reason to expect your culture to develop the diatonic scale.</p>
      <p>Anyway, tl;dr: the major scale that we recognise is not the only tuning system that cultures may adopt, but it, or something fundamentally very similar, is a strong attractor in musical-scale-space, based on the laws of physics, and not entirely arbitrary.</p>
      <p>Just don't ask me what the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PU3WwRtan8M">Georgians</a> are up to :-)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>