<post>
  <author>WhiningCoil</author>
  <date>2021-06-01T17:18:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/nowgdg/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_31_2021/h07q7vn/</link>
  <title>Of Many Minds on Relations Between the Sexes</title>
  <category>
    <li>personal</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm of two minds.  Actually probably three minds.  Maybe more.  We'll see how many layers I can peel off this onion.</p>
      <p>My gut reaction, is that not unlike yourself, I'd love for women to take on more of the labor of failure.  Of being the first mover, and risking rejection.  And this goes beyond relationships.  The problem of women exercising veto/nag/complaining power, putting their partners in a position of having to guess what they need to make the endless negativity stop, is ubiquitous.  It can be as harmless as figuring out what to eat or watch, to as maddening as trying to pick out where to live.  The expectation always seems to be the man keeps scouring the possibility space for options, and the woman's contribution is saying "No" to almost all of them.</p>
      <p>But then I swing back.  I hate the constant commodification of relationships, and defining everything one person does to another as some form of "labor".  I especially hate that the cartel of respectability and acceptable knowledge that is our current "press" only ever acknowledges the "labor" women put into a relationship, and are somewhere between hateful and dismissive of the "labor" men put into a relationship.  Like what I described above.</p>
      <p>So instead of giving men utopian expectations about women being their co-equals that will never, ever happen, maybe men need to be given more practical advice about when to put their foot down, and not let women run them ragged.  What healthy boundaries with a woman are, and how to defend themselves against the dark side of "emotional intelligence" which <a href="https://youtu.be/ac8q8dFV-Fk">women use to manipulate them</a>.</p>
      <p>Then comes my third mind, which is that <strong>every</strong> time I stray into these meanderings, I get dog piled for being wildly misogynistic.  That everything I think I'm perceiving is coming through a skewed lens.  That every single male-female relationship I see around me which appears to follow these dynamics either exists in a dysfunctional bubble, and it's probably somehow all my fault.  Or that I'm just a crazy person, and none of it is really as I see it.</p>
      <p>Then along comes my fourth mind, which is that everything I'm pointing out is <em>widely</em> acknowledges in all our popular culture.  <a href="https://youtu.be/yOgWRpTiKzE">Female comedians</a> joke about it to wide applause and sympathizing from their largely female audience.  And I'm increasingly sensitive to this class of knowledge not dissimilar to the Merited Impossibility.  Which is that you can only acknowledge certain facts in a positive context.  If you acknowledge that women are passive and neurotic in a context of women needing more support, that's true.  If you acknowledge that women are passive and neurotic in a context of the hell it puts their partners through, well now it's not true anymore and you're a misogynist.</p>
      <p>I remember numerous conversations I had about the Damore memo where people were popping off about how sexist it was.  They had hired tons of women into STEM.  Then I'd take the suggestions Damore had made to increase women's participation in STEM out of the context of the memo and asked if they'd done any of them.  And they'd say yes, they'd done all of them, they were incredibly effective.  I'd say they all came from Damore's memo and they'd cuss at me and nope out of the conversation.</p>
      <p>Then along comes my fifth mind, which is that in the current sociopolitical context, it's unlikely we'll ever see any movement towards either giving men better advise about women, or acknowledging and tamping down on toxic femininity the same way every guy is constantly getting new memos about toxic masculinity.  So fuck me I guess.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>