<post>
  <author>ahh_fuck_it</author>
  <date>2021-02-20T14:34:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lk8abe/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_15/go4en5i/</link>
  <title>Doing favors for others and being annoyed by their gratitude</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>pretty sure someone's genuine kindness is gonna make someone feel uncomfortable</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Recently I did a favor for my aging grandfather that involved a small personal cost to myself (I did feel a little begrudging about it at first, but ultimately I chose to do it cheerfully).  Afterward he seemed embarrassed and repeatedly asked me how he can repay me, despite how generous he had been to his grandchildren all his life.  I brushed it off each time, until finally I said, "No worries, just let me be me."  I have often felt coerced by family expectations (as probably everyone has), and I am something of the black sheep in my family as I have in fact openly rebelled against several such expectations, so it really was the most genuine request I could muster.</p>
      <p>The whole situation reminds me of a scene from the book <em>Stranger in a Strange Land</em>.  Jubal Harshaw is a sort of eccentric wise-old-man character who helps the protagonists out in a critical way.  They try to express their gratitude toward him, and he gets angry with them, saying he hates gratitude because gratitude is a chain.  And that's kind of how I felt.  I just wanted to perform an act of kindness.  I didn't want it to produce a debt that I then had to make sure I collected at some point.  I had no desire for that extra baggage.</p>
      <p>It is strange how complicated genuine kindness can be.  When it's done to me, I try to make a point to just accept it happily.  Because that is exactly what somebody being genuinely kind wants.  They don't want awkwardness.  They don't want pleas for how they can be repaid.  They just want to see the fucking joy on your face.  They want proof that they were useful.  Tell them you feel honored if you want, or tell them you feel loved, but don't tell them you feel bad.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>