<post>
  <author>iprayiam3</author>
  <date>2021-02-24T21:57:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/goms4rq/</link>
  <title>Inclusivity As a Social Practice and the 99%</title>
  <category>
    <li>coteries</li>
    <li>personal</li>
  </category>
  <context>
    <p>I'm in favor of replacing "men" (or "women") with more specific and inclusive language where sensible though.</p>
  </context>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>In situations like 'people with prostates' or 'chestfeeding' or 'pregnant people' or whatever,  I absolutely am not in favor of this. And in fact, see organized pushes to do so as overtly hostile.</p>
      <p>This is the stalking horse behind 'Transwomen are women'. Its not enough to expand the class to include them, But now you have to reorganize further what women means because they clearly aren't in medically necessary terms. It's asking both to expand the umbrella, and reduce it in places to accommodate the expansion. I find the latter far more outright hostile than the former.</p>
      <p>
        <em>"I have an elephant."</em> Fine, if it makes you happy.</p>
      <p>
        <em>"I want to take around with me"</em> Wherever it will fit, I guess.</p>
      <p>
        <em>"More places ought to be accommodating of my elephant"</em> That's a reasonable perspective from your point of view. I am not sure I agree to the extent of your need for change.</p>
      <p>
        <em>"You must let me bring my elephant into your party"</em> Well hold, on. You don't get to tell me what I can and can't---</p>
      <p>
        <em>"Since my elephant is taking up so much room at your party, you need to kick other people out to fit us"</em>
      </p>
      <p>I see this last point the most hostile escalation. Trans gets forced into the context of 'women' but the also kicks out other accepted and frankly essential contexts. For example it forces 'pregnancy and birth' out of the context of womanhood and by extension motherdom. They're just pregnant 'people' now.</p>
      <p>I can see this as an interesting taxonomical solution from a dispassionate perspective, but it comes off as abhorrent to me.</p>
      <p>Why is it that the definition of woman <em>must</em> privilege including trans over pregnancy in a context where they both don't fit? If <em>man</em> is confusing in a medical context that involves a prostate or a natural penis, why is it the one that must be redefined and not the other? In the medical context it is more important that the transperson gets to keep their label that all other sexual dimorphism must be castrated. Framing this as "inclusive" is misleading. it is wildly, radically exclusive language that deligitmatizes the essential components of one's biological sex for 99% of humans</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>