<post>
  <author>Njordsier</author>
  <date>2021-02-22T19:06:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/goddrm3/</link>
  <title>Steelmanning four quadrants on Amazon worker relations and gay wedding cakes</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Seems to me one's position on Amazon and transgender cakes need not be correlated. I can steelman all four quadrants:</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Neither Amazon nor cake bakers should have been able to refuse service</strong>: corporations have a responsibility to not discriminate based on point of view, in the <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2013/12/29/the-spirit-of-the-first-amendment/">spirit of the First Amendment</a>. In both cases, the company uses its discretion to silence speech it doesn't like, which goes against the values of a free society. It would be better for all companies providing a platform for speech, whether through icing on a cake or hosting a website, to be blind to the content of the speech it hosts to avoid distorting free expression (the companies are also free to express their position by other means than by denying service to customers).</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Amazon should have been able to deplatform Parler, but the cake baker should not have been able to refuse service</strong>: Parler was being used to plan and coordinate violence, both a violation of the TOS and a threat to peaceful democratic society. A cake poses no such threat, even if you believe the transition surgery that it celebrates is child abuse: Parler wasn't banned because it celebrated violence, but because it coordinated violence, and deplatforming it could be reasonably expected to prevent that violence, whereas no child abuse would be prevented by denying a cake. This is the same as above, but granting a narrow exception against violent speech.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Amazon should not have been able to deplatform Parler, but the cake baker had the right to refuse service</strong>: Amazon controls a huge share of the cloud, meaning there's no alternative that the victims of deplatforming can fall back to. A cake baker does not hold the same leverage and the customers they deny service to can reasonably expect to find a competitor willing to serve them. There's some trade-off between the rights of an individual to free speech and a company's right to refuse compelled speech, but the latter becomes disproportionately adverse to the former the more powerful and monopolistic the company is.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Both Amazon and Parler should have been able to refuse service</strong>: either there is no trade-off as described above, or the threshold of monopoly power that merits compulsion of speech is higher than what Amazon has attained. After all, Parler is migrating its backend, showing that Amazon isn't able to completely lock them out of the marketplace of ideas. You can also argue from a contractualist standpoint that neither case is really about speech, but about the freedom to mutually enter into or unilaterally refuse agreements of commerce. Amazon was up front in its TOS about its requirements and was simply enforcing those terms that Parler had signed onto, and the cake baker was exercising the right to not enter into an agreement to make a cake they didn't want to make.</p>
      <p>Usually when people juxtapose two events like this, they're trying to insinuate some kind of hypocrisy, but there seem to be enough confounders in these cases that I can see a non-hypocritical, principled case for any combination of support for or opposition to the companies' deplatforming actions.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>