<post>
  <author>Rov_Scam</author>
  <date>2021-02-24T21:40:55Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/gomq3dx/</link>
  <title>Housing Politics--this Time, in Pittsburgh!</title>
  <category>
    <li>economics</li>
    <li>civilization</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Part of the problem is that opposition to new housing construction extends beyond the issue of zoning. I live in the Pittsburgh area, where zoning isn't much of an issue outside of suburbs that no one is concerned about anyway due to lack of transit access. Yet it seems like every major housing project meets opposition, only for housing advocates rather than opponents. </p>
      <p>As a case in point we can look at the troubled history of the former Civic Arena site. The Hill District is Pittsburgh's best-known traditionally black neighborhood (this is where the movie Fences is set). It occupies, as the name would suggest, a hill directly west of downtown whose summit runs parallel to the Monongahela and Allegheny rivers. Its slopes are extremely steep in places and the area is rather isolated from the surrounding neighborhoods even though you'd think it was a good location just from a map. </p>
      <p>The Lower Hill was the part of the neighborhood closest to downtown, roughly located where the hill slopes gently downward from Crawford Ave. to I-576. Wylie Ave., the main drag in the Hill ran directly through the Lower Hill and into downtown. By the late 1950s, the Lower Hill was in decline, and in the spirit of the age it became the target of urban renewal. Pretty much the entire neighborhood was bulldozed to make way for the Civic (later Mellon) Arena, best-known as the former home of the Pittsburgh Penguins. For the next 50 years the project would become the symbol of and scapegoat for the decline of the Hill. The rest of the neighborhood was now completely isolated, especially since the part of Wylie Ave. that connected it to downtown was disbanded as part of the development. It was now a sitting duck for the civil unrest of the 60s, rising crime of the 70s, crack epidemic of the 80s, gang warfare of the 90s, and all the other woes that befell black communities during this time period. (It's worth noting that the <em>real</em> decline of the Hill didn't start until after the 1968 riots; the business district moved from Wylie Ave. to Center Ave. after the arena project but increasing civil unrest drove out the neighborhood's substantial Jewish population and made whites who previously had no problem patronizing local establishments reluctant to venture into what was now perceived as an urban ghetto. This isn't particularly important to the story but should nonetheless be mentioned.)</p>
      <p>By the mid-2000s the Penguins were unhappy with their arena and wanted a new one. There was much speculation about what would become of the site, and excitement that developing the area for normal commercial and residential use would help spur development in the Hill. Pennsylvania had recently legalized casino gambling and Mario Lemieux felt that obtaining a license was the only way to procure funding which had thus far been lacking. The Penguins entered a deal with Isle of Capri Casinos, who agreed to build an arena and use the existing site for their casino as well as additional commercial and residential development. That deal fell through, though, when the gaming commission awarded Pittsburgh's sole license to different company. The team then threatened to move to Kansas City and Governor Rendell stepped in to try to procure funding for a new arena (leading to the joke that the Penguins didn't get their arena for free because Ed Rendell wanted to pay for one). Part of the eventual arena deal gave the Penguins "development rights" to the 28-acre site of the old arena. I use scare quotes because ownership and rights to the land in question is so complicated I'm not even going to try to parse it. The land is technically owned by the Allegheny County Sports and Exhibition Authority but the Pittsburgh Urban Redevelopment Authority has to approve anything that has to do with it and community groups in the Hill seem to have a say as well and it's not even clear what rights the Penguins have but they must be worth something. The deal was reached in 2007 and the Civic Arena was demolished after the new arena opened in 2010. </p>
      <p>The site is currently a parking lot for the new arena. The old street grid has been at least partially restored, but any serious development has gotten lost in a no man's land of proposals, meetings, protests, etc. This is a project the public was excited about; when the 2007 deal was reached the assumption was that they'd plan it for the next three years and when the new building was ready they'd demolish the Civic Arena and get to work on the new development. Instead, the community groups who are involved, and have significant clout with the URA, keep making demand after demand, and backing out of proposals that meet terms they said they'd agreed to in principle. They spend time arguing over what percentage of apartments would be "affordable". They want veto power over what retail establishments will be allowed to lease space. They want a minority jobs guarantee. They want a local jobs guarantee. Meanwhile the site sits empty, as much a barrier now as it ever was.</p>
      <p>In May of last year, the Penguins put forth a $600 million proposal that would allow for the construction of a skyscraper for a bank headquarters, an indoor/outdoor music venue, and a bunch of retail and apartments. The URA initially denied the proposal and came back with more demands, but granted an emergency approval after the Penguins threatened to back out of the deal entirely. The community leaders were furious. The latest concern is that public grants the Penguins intend on using for financing will cannibalize the funds so that no money is available for other projects. For their part, the Penguins didn't comply with their end of the bargain to purchase additional land needed to complete the project by the October 22 deadline, so the URA retaliated by refusing to grant an extension. </p>
      <p>This is only one of the various projects in the city that has been hamstrung by issues totally unrelated to zoning. I could write a post of similar length about the redevelopment of a former public housing site in the city's East Liberty neighborhood. For that matter, the whole controversy surrounding the gentrification of East Liberty is fascinating in and of itself. And then there's the up-and-coming controversy surrounding the AlMonO project on the site of the old LTV mill in Hazelwood. But zoning was never an issue in any of these places. People will always find something to bitch about.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>