<post>
  <author>self_made_human</author>
  <date>2021-02-20T06:37:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lk8abe/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_15/go3hg9d/</link>
  <title>Quality of Life (Poor) in the "Third World"</title>
  <category>
    <li>economics</li>
    <li>personal</li>
  </category>
  <context>
    <p>Currently I live in the UK. While the standard economic indicators such as GDP per capita may not be as good as in the US, it is still a pretty cushy and nice life where as a skilled worker I get paid very good money. Even for not so skilled workers the strong social security net means they get to enjoy a decent lifestyle (perhaps one thing we actually do do better than the US).</p>
    <p>Hence it would be pretty surprising for me to wish that I was born in a less developed country, but the more I think about it the more convinced I am it would personally have been a good thing for me. Of course there is a certain amount of "grass is always greener on the other side" going on here but I think there are actual tangible benefits.</p>
  </context>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>As someone in a 3rd World Country (India), studiously planning to emigrate to the UK, your post made me want to beat my head against a wall and scream haha. </p>
      <p>(I don't mean that as an insult to you, simply that there's such a gulf in experience between you and someone raised here that I would feel the same way about an alien from a post-scarcity civilization like the Culture moving to a backwater)</p>
      <p>Now, I'll point out several caveats in the claims I'm about to express:</p>
      <p>1) QOL varies massively even within the 3rd World. You have reasonably middle-income nations, poor nations on a steep upper line trajectory, and countries that seemed poised to approach middle- income like India but failed along the way. And then are the massive outliers like Singapore, Hong Kong and Taiwan, where you could move and expect an <em>increase</em> in standard of living. Unless otherwise specified, assume I'm speaking about the Indian subcontinent.</p>
      <p>2) Your QOL also depends greatly on your personal preferences. If cheap healthcare and housing are your desires, you could probably do fine, but things like electronics, automobiles etc are proportionately more expensive, and you need to keep in mind purchasing power parity.</p>
      <p>3) As others have pointed out, you can experience all of the positives and avoid most of the negatives by simply emigrating to a 3rd World nation of your choice, without the constraints of being born here.</p>
      <p>Here are the things that I feel you've been misinformed about or simply lack the context to appreciate about life here-</p>
      <p>1) You're in the UK. You've got effectively free public healthcare, which can probably only be beaten if you're rich enough to afford private care in the US, and since the NHS is more focused on explicit cost-benefit calculations, that's not even a knock against it. Assuming you're modal middle class, it's not really a contest which system is superior for you. Indian Healthcare is free and serviceable, I'd know as a doctor here, but there's a reason the middle class and above avoid it unless they're desperate, and if you're curious, look at my recent posts to see a ground-level overview of the situation. </p>
      <p>2) The difference in culture is <em>tremendous</em>. Being gay or an atheist is illegal in much of the Global South, religious freedoms are suppressed or the government throws its weight behind a favored religion, PDA is often enough to get you arrested or beaten publicly, and social-mores have more in common with the 50s as opposed to what's the norm in the West.</p>
      <p>3) Just being born here is enough to curtail or restrict your potential opportunities. Getting a work permit or H1B is such a pain in the ass that the waiting times are <strong>50</strong> years on average for an Indian, and I don't think most of South Asia is that much better off. Your passport is shit, and you probably won't be able to afford to travel much in the first place.</p>
      <p>4) You are correct about middle-class Indians being able to afford privileges that seem insane to most of the West, but given that a lot of people are accustomed to that kind of luxury and <em>still</em> want to leave should be a knock against it. Once again, this is down to your personal preferences. It's not a <em>bad</em> thing per se, </p>
      <p>5) Taxes are terrible in India. Only 2% of the country pays income tax, and we're milked like an ass to carry the rest. That alone sucks, but what's worse is noticing the rampant corruption and waste, to the point that you'd get more return by pouring a lot of your money into a ditch and setting it on fire to get high off the fumes. </p>
      <p>6) Most of the place is dirty, poor and polluted, you don't appreciate how great it is to have clean parks and sidewalks, quality public transport and so on.</p>
      <p>7) Corruption is a massive drag, commensurate with the relatively greater opportunities to find untapped markets, you've got the headache that is <em>bribery</em>, and we're not talking relatively genteel kickbacks, but blatant money under the table or 'gifts'.</p>
      <p>In the US, there's quite a heavy emphasis on learning a second language, namely Spanish, but once again, the reason that most people are happy enough with just English is because they don't <em>need</em> anything else. On the contrary, to function in the upper middle class, you need to be fluent in English to avoid disdain, and you need a local language to manage more mundane affairs, but the utility of said language is very limited geographically. The proposed benefits of bilingualism don't seem to be massive enough to be worth the time expenditure in people who won't otherwise use it in my eyes, but YMMW.</p>
      <p>Everything I've said is, once again, personal experience in a constrained section of the 3rd World. But given that India and the rest of South Asia makes up about 1.6 billion people, give or take the population of France, and you'll see that this is quite close to the modal state of affairs. If you really wanted to pick and choose, there probably are countries where you can avoid some of these drawbacks, but they're vanishingly rare, and should be singled out in context.</p>
      <p>The cost of immigration is exorbitant, which stops the majority of the 1% from leaving, but as a recent survey of the most academically talented Indians showed, the best of the best leave as soon as they can and do <em>much</em> better abroad.</p>
      <p>By all means, come visit, vacation, even plan your retirement here. But I'd wager the grass really is greener up there, leaving aside the relative absence of drought.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>