<post>
  <note>Not happy with the categories on this one.</note>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2021-02-24T18:13:57Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/golxv9s/</link>
  <title>A Case-by-case Examination of Fatal Shootings in Minneapolis</title>
  <category>
    <li>civilization</li>
    <li>media</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I must say, your comments egregiously misrepresent the content of the linked article. It is not a random investigation into 100 testimonies that found 25 cases of perjury for a 25% rate of dishonest testimony; rather, it is an investigation into 100 <strong>settlements</strong> that were paid out by the city over 20 years - representing the worst police oversteps over those decades - and in ~25 of those cases an officer was <strong>accused</strong> of a misrepresentation of force by the litigant. Your own article immediately clarifies that this commonly only means that every aspect of the altercation was not immediately perfectly documented and that it was actually <strong>only 6 cases</strong> where the officer stuck to contentious versions of events that were contradicted either by video evidence <strong>or</strong> expert testimony <strong>or</strong> a judge's ruling</p>
      <p>The George Floyd case is illustrative in this regard. Floyd died with his system coursing with <a href="https://www.kare11.com/article/news/local/george-floyd/new-court-docs-say-george-floyd-had-fatal-level-of-fentanyl-in-his-system/89-ed69d09d-a9ec-481c-90fe-7acd4ead3d04">a fatal level of fentanyl under normal circumstances</a> and is known to have previously <a href="https://thenewamerican.com/floyd-judge-jury-can-t-hear-evidence-of-floyd-s-drug-addiction-violent-crime/">swallowed a large amount of drugs when facing arrest, necessitating immediate hospitalization</a> only a year prior. <a href="https://www.fox9.com/news/transcript-of-officers-body-camera-shows-george-floyd-told-officers-i-cant-breathe-before-being-restrained">Floyd was yelling that he "couldn't breathe" well before any officers put him in a restraint hold</a> - when he was still standing up in fact - and the restraint hold that the officers put him in to get him to stop violently flailing while awaiting the impending ambulance they had called allowed him ample air to shout and holler until he passed. A Bayesian analysis would regard this as a fentanyl overdose - an extremely common variant of OD even outside of circumstances where someone has swallowed a large amount to destroy evidence - but this would go into your pool of "lies" by virtue of being contradicted by expert testimony</p>
      <p>Now, you use this misrepresentation of the article to imply that the actual # of unarmed black men killed by police is notably higher than is reported. Let's look at the deaths of <strong><em>all</em></strong> other black men by police in Minneapolis over the last 6+ years and see if any have been mischaracterized as 'armed':</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Killing_of_Dolal_Idd">Dolal Idd</a> - Bodycam video of weapons dealer shooting at officers from his car before they returned fire</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://minnesota.cbslocal.com/2020/03/02/minneapolis-police-officer-cleared-in-shooting-death-of-mario-benjamin-last-august/">Mario Benjamin</a> - Bodycam video of Mario refusing repeated calls to drop his drawn firearm as he stood, high on meth, over the paralyzed body of his girlfriend who he had just shot in front of their kids on a public street</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.hennepinattorney.org/news/news/2019/January/Jordan-OIS-Finalreport">Travis Jordan</a> - Bodycam video of Travis approaching officers with 13.5" knife, screaming "Let's do this" as the officers plead for him to drop the weapon, saying verbatim "I don't want to do this, drop the knife!" before firing as he continued to approach them brandishing the weapon, screaming all the while</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.hennepinattorney.org/news/news/2018/July/blevins-no-charge">Thurman Blevins</a> - Bodycam video of officers approaching a drunk man who had instigated 9-1-1 calls by firing his handgun into the air on a public street, he flees gun in hand, refuses to drop the weapon or desist, and is shot after repeated "Put your hands up! I will shoot you!" by the pursuing officers</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Jamar_Clark">Jamar Clark</a> - The sole incident of a black decedent in Minneapolis in WaPo's 6+ year database predating bodycam footage. He was engaged by officers after interfering with paramedics following a fight at a party. Police and paramedics claim he grabbed an officer's firearm; some onlookers say he was restrained and cooperating. Forensic evidence supported the police narrative and an investigation cleared them, though after mass unrest Clark's family was given a $200K settlement. Already categorized as "Unarmed"</p>
      <p>So what we see is 5 fatal shootings of black criminals in 6 years, 5 of which were clearly armed and shot justifiably after refusing lawful orders to desist and drop their weapons. The only questionable instance is already categorized as 'Unarmed', despite credible evidence that he had gripped an officer's service weapon, and the city already made a gesture of compensating the victim's family despite investigations clearing the officers of any wrongdoing</p>
      <p>All of this reinforces that the BLM narrative of police wantonly and maliciously killing blacks en masse without accountability is completely untethered from reality. Your apologetics for such a destructive and dishonest campaign are unbecoming; the facts are indeed trustworthy when actually investigated, rather than relying on distortions and inflations of tangential issues (general use of force reporting) to muddy the waters</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>