<post>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2021-02-23T19:51:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/gohyme8/</link>
  <title>Political self-identification and quantitative knowledge of fatal police shootings</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Last week, we had a top-level post where a commenter expressed interest in a survey that broke down knowledge by political affiliation on a range of topics that covered basic civics and compositional questions about our country (i.e. population size, number of representatives, ethnic demographic make-up) as well as "politically-charged or controversial but nonetheless still empirically verifiable questions" which the commenter, by way of example, focused on  racial differences in crime and police shootings. Conveniently, I happened to come across this Twitter thread this morning where the consistently insightful <a href="https://www.tabletmag.com/contributors/zach-goldberg">Great Awokening researcher Zach Goldberg</a> promoted data on just this issue: <a href="https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1364024711592738817.html">Thread</a></p>
      <p>As Goldberg notes, there was a steep divide in answers by self-identified Conservatives and Liberals when asked "How many unarmed Black [sic] men were killed by police in 2019?". The correct answer was between 13, per WaPo's Fatal Force database which documents fatal police shootings, and 27, per Mapping Police Violence's database which documents deaths by any means at the hands of police - including off-duty officers and other security agencies, e.g. ICE - and includes toy / replica weapons in the 'Unarmed' designation, leading to clear cases of <a href="https://www.fox4news.com/news/arlington-police-release-video-of-deadly-officer-involved-shooting">suicide by cop</a> being classified as such. Yet <strong>44%</strong> of self-identified Liberals (Liberal + Very Liberal) estimated that there were <strong>About 1,000 or higher</strong> such killings - <strong>~40x</strong> the actual count! Moreover, <strong>15%</strong> of (Liberal + Very Liberals) believed that there were <strong>About 10,000</strong> or higher such killings - an overshoot by a factor of <strong>~400x</strong>! Meanwhile, ~80% of (Conservative + Very Conservative) respondents estimated the number at About 100 or less</p>
      <p>This seems important because it demonstrates that the differing partisan stances on BLM adjacent issues don't just come down to different values or priorities - rather, they come down to the fact that, while both sides overestimate police killings, one side truly has a radically misinformed view of the scope of the issue. It is not hard to imagine that the Very Liberal respondents who perceived the scope of the problem to be the largest disproportionately comprise the loudest voices on this issue - the people blocking freeways, screaming in cops faces, plastering social media with outrage, mobbing congressmen, demanding radical change. Meanwhile, they, frankly, have no idea what they're talking about and are multiple orders of magnitude off-base in terms of how their propagandized perceptions deviate wildly from reality</p>
      <p>While I'm not able to find corresponding data, it seems very plausible to me that there is also a corresponding misconception about how these cases play out. Every time there's a viral incidence, we have a discussion about it based on the initially released info which seems spun for maximum outrage (e.g. Jacob Blake was breaking up a fight and shot 7 times in the back while unarmed for his trouble) and then there is more context released later that seems to provide far more clarity that is quietly disclosed after people have moved on (Jacob Blake had active warrants for rape, police were called as he was harassing the victim, he fought aggressively with officers, pulled a knife, and was attempting to drive off in the victims car w/ her children in it before being shot 4x by an officer who had already expended his taser in the scuffle). This is the pattern for Michael Brown, George Floyd, Ahmaud Arbery, Rayshard Brooks, Breonna Taylor, and countless others, and stems not only from media sources deliberately misrepresenting facts but also activists spinning them online and lobbying to remove exculpatory details (e.g. Blake's knife) from Wikipedia. I have a post from last summer <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0c7hcm?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3">breaking down some of the 2019 'unarmed' police shootings</a>, and nearly half seem to be conclusively fully justifiable, with others more ambiguous but decidedly more tragic than malicious. Meanwhile, BLM, whose members still use the <a href="https://thehill.com/opinion/civil-rights/457049-time-to-retire-ferguson-narrative">Michael Brown hoax</a> as a rallying cry, decidedly frame the issue as one of 'white supremacy' and racial animus</p>
      <p>An open question is whether simply disseminating the truth would be sufficient to alleve much of the passion behind such issues. It seems readily apparent that our media is fully dedicated to actively misrepresenting the issue as much as possible for clicks and ideological gains, but what if at, say, a Presidential debate or during a Super Bowl commercial someone directly communicated to the bulk of the American public that i) there are, maximally, around 2 dozen unarmed black men killed by police per year; ii) those killed are largely violent criminals who actively created dangerous situations; iii) the black share of Americans killed by police is <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EZEbtpgWkAE15MJ?format=jpg&amp;name=large">markedly lower</a> than the black share of homicide perpetrators, violent criminals, individuals who kill or shoot at police, etc; and iv) black rates of violent crime are significantly higher than that of other demographics <a href="https://sci-hub.st/10.1016/j.intell.2011.08.001">even when controlling for poverty</a>? Could the issue of race and policing that led to so much unrest and division and violence and destruction and, ultimately, <a href="https://reason.com/volokh/2021/02/01/explaining-the-great-2020-homicide-spike/">4,000 excess homicides</a> last year, actually be defused with 60 seconds of candor? Or would the passions remain even after the underlying radical misconceptions were corrected?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>