<post>
  <author>themadrevelation</author>
  <date>2021-02-24T12:59:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/gokszfq/</link>
  <title>Nature versus nurture in trans-Atlantic crime demographics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I recently found this sub and there is a burning issue in my country that might be of interest to all of you. Apologies in advance if I make any grammatical mistakes as English is not my first language.</p>
      <p>There is a traditionally nomadic minority ethnic group spread across most of Europe known as the Romani people (colloquially Gypsies) that happen to live in my country. They have a... <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskReddit/comments/1f3bok/what_makes_europeans_hate_gypsies_so_much_are/">well, let's say</a><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskEurope/comments/7hgnjj/what_is_the_general_opinion_on_the_roma_people/">less-than-positive</a><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskEurope/comments/90ry7t/why_do_some_europeans_hate_gypsiesroma/">reputation</a> among most Europeans, regardless of race. In Finland, where the Romani make up less than 0.2% of the population, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finnish_Kale">Romani people still manage to commit over 18% of all street robbery crimes</a>. This is not an isolated case, either: in Czechia, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romani_people_in_the_Czech_Republic#Crime">20-30% of Romani make their living off of crime</a>. Slovakian Romani have a staggering <a href="https://www.aljazeera.com/features/2017/5/10/life-in-slovakias-roma-slums-poverty-and-segregation">97% unemployment rate</a> and a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antiziganism#Public_opinion">83% unfavorability rating</a> among Italians, the lowest rate of any ethnic group polled. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antiziganism#Czech_Republic">45% of Czechs</a> want to expel all Romani people from their country. Several <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roma_wall">Roma walls</a> have been built across Europe with the explicit purpose of isolating Romani ghettos, which are infamous for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lun%C3%ADk_IX">having no toilets and no running water</a>. <a href="http://www.errc.org/cikk.php?cikk=2743">Romani students</a> are still segregated from other children in European schools. The Romani people have <a href="https://emilkirkegaard.dk/en/2020/06/roma-gypsy-iq-meta-analysis-74/">an average IQ of 74</a>, which makes about half of them literally mentally retarded under most standard definitions. Most Eastern European countries have had their own vicious <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1993_H%C4%83d%C4%83reni_riots">anti-Romani pogroms</a> well into the modern era. Millions of Roma were killed in a <a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiYqNzsvYLvAhWoHjQIHWcdC44QFjAAegQIChAD&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fen.wikipedia.org%2Fwiki%2FRomani_genocide&amp;usg=AOvVaw2mhBUOAd7R7osoIXJPHT6e">largely-forgotten purge</a> during the Holocaust. I could go on, but suffice to say that Romani people likely have the worst reputation out of any ethnic group in the first world. Most of the time, the Romani are simply ignored, even though their social rot is an extremely widespread unspoken truth, but there is growing right-wing chatter over whether or not they should be forcibly re-educated, and while that's not the main topic of discussion I want to bring up I'd be interested to hear this sub's thoughts on that.</p>
      <p>Although what really interested me about this discussion was the HBD element. Romani people <a href="https://bmcgenomdata.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12863-017-0547-x">descend</a> from a group of wandering tribes from India that were expelled in the fifth century, and as a consequence they share much of their DNA with modern-day Indians and Indian-Americans, with a <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/article?id=10.1371/journal.pgen.1008417">significant amount of Persian and European ancestry</a>. It is <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Romania/comments/7irtu5/i_was_born_in_romania_but_was_adopted_by/dr14nxt/?utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3">common knowledge</a> in Europe that adopted Romani who are isolated from the culture tend to act like "normal" people for the most part. <a href="https://emilkirkegaard.dk/en/2020/06/roma-gypsy-iq-meta-analysis-74/">The average IQ of an integrated urban Romani youth is 98</a>. The kicker is that the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romani_society_and_culture#Moral_values">Romani culture is so insular, so strict,</a> after <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slavery_in_Romania">hundreds of years of discrimination and slavery</a>, that Romani people almost always choose to self-segregate and refuse employment and education regardless of the opportunities presented to them. There is a significant lack of <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/16626330/">genetic cohesion</a> among Romani people, aside from a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/ejhg2015201">few similarities that originate from group bottlenecks</a>, that would normally lend to genetic explanations of their behavior. There is even one tribe of the Romani people, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_Travellers">Irish Travellers</a>, who display nearly all of the traits that the Romani possess while still maintaining over <a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiKk_7tvoLvAhW8FzQIHbXlDpgQFjABegQIFhAD&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.ed.ac.uk%2Fusher%2Fnews-events%2Fnews-2017%2Fgene-study-reveals-irish-travellers-ancestry&amp;usg=AOvVaw1VMbgUd7SVFHKO8rMfQGpS">99% European DNA</a>. It seems quite clear to me that the lower IQ, the higher aggression, and the lack of education among Romani stems from their culture and environment, rather than their genetics. At least in my eyes, this obfuscates American arguments that racial differences in behavior can be explained by supposed genetic differences between European and African Americans, because African Americans have a <a href="https://www.mun.ca/biology/scarr/Black_vs_White_IQ_scores.html">higher IQ</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Race_and_crime_in_the_United_States">a lower crime rate</a>, and a <a href="https://www.census.gov/library/stories/2020/09/poverty-rates-for-blacks-and-hispanics-reached-historic-lows-in-2019.html">lower poverty rate</a> than Romani people despite going through a similar history of dehumanization and slavery. Is there anything I'm missing here? If social inequities are primarily the result of genetic differences between races, and not culture, as some here may claim, what genes make African Americans closer to Europeans than the Romani, who are often very genetically similar to their European neighbors?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>