<post>
  <author>ThirteenValleys</author>
  <date>2021-02-22T21:10:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/godujvo/</link>
  <title>How the World Looks, Where Jobs Are Rewards, Not Responsibilities</title>
  <category>
    <li>coteries</li>
    <li>civilization</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>One post on here from a while back that really put a lot of pieces together for me (can't remember who; please speak up if it was you) said something like "progressives see high-status, high-paying jobs as <em>rewards given to the deserving,</em> not <em>responsibilities entrusted to the capable.</em>" When you tease out the implications, it amounts to everything from racial quotas to cancel culture being morally justified, if not essential, because (in this framework) society is actually losing nothing by firing all the skilled, knowledgeable workers who also say objectionable things. Jobs are rewards, not responsibilities, so if one software engineer is as good as another, why not cut all the creepy white dudes? If it won't affect the quality of work, why not make everyone jump through SJ-culture hoops to prove they belong? </p>
      <p>Now, I imagine most of you disagree with this strenuously, but I propose that that attitude comes from an understandable place, and perhaps can be mitigated. </p>
      <p>
        <strong>The Menial Group</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Let's start with the young menial workers, the ones who make up the X% in all those "X% of people younger than 25 approve of communism" polls. All those things that don't/shouldn't apply to high-skill jobs like engineer and surgeon <em>do</em> apply to menial labor jobs like retail and customer service--probably the only jobs some of those people have ever had. You <em>are</em> replaceable, and it will not affect the quality of the company as a whole. Companies <em>can</em> fire you at a whim for saying the wrong thing or pissing off the wrong person. Your job is being a people-pleaser to some degree, certainly more than an engineer's is. You have never rated your job satisfaction higher than a 5/10, and it occasionally plummets to a zero, so the idea of ruining someone's life's work by getting them canceled likewise may not register. </p>
      <p>Should someone with no experience in high-skill industries still be able to grok that the goals, methods, and motives of a surgeon should be different from a Target cashier? Yes, probably. But cognition is hard. The point here is, the framework of "jobs are mostly bullshit and have nothing to do with skill or competency" matches the experience of many people out there. That's the fuse, and the bomb is "So let's just rid every industry of people who don't think like us, because it's all upside and no downside". </p>
      <p>
        <strong>The Idea Group</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The second group is the liberal-arts people; journalists, PR people, artists, consultants, etc. Their jobs are not menial or rote, and may not even be public facing, but they don't have to answer to the laws of nature, the "either the patient lives or he dies; either the bridge stays up or it collapses" demands of more technical fields. I hesitate to write this as someone of a liberal arts background, because we come in for enough abuse here as it is. As others have said, what does it even mean to be "the best" literary critic? Clearly your ideas should challenge, not grovel to, the reader's preconceptions, but when does challenging become needlessly contrarian? If the average person can't even decipher your writing, is that elitist, or just the sign of a deep thinker? Is 'quantity has a quality all its own' true or false when it comes to written output? And these are all formal questions, having nothing to do with content!</p>
      <p>So the gaps in those questions will be filled with the prevailing political biases of the day. But more than that, all these fields are chained to novelty. Every "idea-based" field from fashion to movies to journalism is going to have to deal with the fact that people, deprived of an objective scale to rate your work, will eventually get bored with it and try something else. This would be true even if we <em>did</em> have an objective scale for quality of thought, and even if the political winds were the opposite and the journalists were all trying to one-up each other on how everything in our culture should support the white suburban heterosexual nuclear family. It would not surprise me a whit if propagandists in 20th-century fascist states found ever-weirder and wronger ways to blame their regime's misfortunes on liberals and leftists, even as the regime's self-inflicted failure was staring everyone else in the face. </p>
      <p>So that's two large groups, many of them left-wing, who have every reason and incentive to believe that losing a job for your political beliefs is fine, because jobs aren't real and any random shmuck could do it just as well, so why not pick someone with the right demographics? </p>
      <p>
        <strong>The Skill Group</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The third group are the high-skilled workers who have seen with their own eyes that jobs are not just "rewards" that society "gives" you, that the bridge <em>does</em> collapse, the patient <em>does</em> die, the software <em>does</em> crash, based on the competency of the people involved, but still seem to be onboard with mass firings and replacements of the unwoke by the woke. The worst-possible-world explanation is the one I'll deal with first, because if it's true we're all fucked: they see dead surgery patients, crashing software, and collapsing bridges as an <em>acceptable price to pay</em> if it means more minority surgeons, coders, and engineers, because the latter is an <em>end in itself</em> in their worldview. There are probably some of those people; domain intelligence and general common sense can be quite divorced at times. I think more likely is that they play tricks on themselves mentally: "Meritocracy is racist and we need more black female surgeons...but of course you don't hire <em>unqualified</em> people." Cognitive dissonance is easy for most people. Maybe they convince themselves that all the people who get fired also all happen to be terrible at their jobs, down to the last, so there's no loss to the company or the public. Maybe they think that minorities who are genuinely <em>more skilled</em> are being deliberately, consciously held back to keep <em>less skilled</em> white people in positions of power, i.e. the modal kind of racism. Those explanations all have problems of their own, but any of them would be a <em>far</em> better starting point than "Yes, hiring a black female anesthesiologist <em>is</em> more important than keeping your grandma alive, stop being racist." (For the record I am not saying you <em>can't</em> satisfy both conditions; I'm saying, were a conflict between them to arise, this sort of person would default to the first and question the moral judgement of people who didn't.)</p>
      <p>
        <strong>How to Fix It</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Now I'm probably unqualified to write this next bit because, in addition to my education background, I just really don't like work. I don't derive much personal value of self-esteem from it and I don't really understand people who do. I am very invested in the idea of a society where most people don't have to work for a living unless they want to. But that's all separate from the fact that jobs-as-reward superseding jobs-as-responsibility as the dominant economic folk wisdom has some nasty consequences. </p>
      <p>The goal, the finish line is a situation where people realize that jobs have value beyond social status-jockeying because they see it in their own lives, which the Menial Group and the Idea Group currently don't. For the Menial Group it's a non-starter: they are replaceable because the laws of supply and demand say so, not because asshole managers and corporations and governments say so. I can think of no real way to convince people not to fire unwoke cashiers and waiters on account of their competency level, not one without a shitload of collateral damage. </p>
      <p>For the Idea Group, though, I have the germ of an idea, one that may work because it aligns with the group's values, rather than one that's imposed upon them, and to put it simply, it's: <strong>Incentivize Unorthodox Perspectives.</strong></p>
      <p>"Impossible," you say, "They all walk in lockstep already." Well, maybe they do. The impression I get (and when dealing with 'underground' dissent, impressions are sometimes all there is) is the opposite, based on all the out-and-proud dissidents like Weiss and DeBoer talking about all the anonymous "I can't reveal my name, but keep fighting the good fight" support they get about their work. What causes common-but-taboo knowledge to suddenly, spontaneously spill into common knowledge? I don't know. Maybe some conservatives can weigh in here; the buzz is that many average-Joe conservatives feel that the whole nexus of the American state is corrupt and worthless, whereas ten years ago they limited themselves to bitching about Obama and Pelosi. That's a big jump to make mentally! But many people have made it. Widespread underground dissent, which we have, is a necessary but not sufficient condition for an overturn of an oppressive social order. </p>
      <p>One thing I have more or less adopted from libertarianism is that money can do what social power can't. So, what if universities were to set aside some dough and some space on campus for a Department of Unorthodox Conclusions? Basically, a deliberate attempt to reward and nurture people whose perspectives are sufficiently different from their peers. Their legal protections would be reinforced to the utmost, the increasingly vicious and uncompromising student population may not even be aware of their existence. 99% of the university's resources would be still be free to woke it up, but this 1% would be allowed free rein in their little corner. It wouldn't be much at first, but you can't run until you walk. </p>
      <p>And in the spirit of deliberately favoring unorthodox beliefs: Doomers, if you think I'm hopelessly naive and this will never happen, at least try to explain it in a more practical, actionable way than "The Cult is all-powerful and everything is doomed". I am <em>deeply</em> familiar with that argument and am hoping for something more innovative.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>