<post>
  <author>WestphalianPeace</author>
  <date>2021-02-19T14:47:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ln1sv9/maginot_syndrome_bullish_for_han_hegemony/go0dwn0/</link>
  <title>China's lack of incentives to drink from the Ohio river</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Even if all of this is true the conclusion that the US must respond does not follow because China does not have a cause to threaten the US's core national interest. The US has very few actual vital national interests and China is not ideologically deluded enough to cross them. Your comparison between France and the USA is actually a fantastic illustration of the important differences in national interest in pre-WW2 great power politics for everyone else except America and the modern day.</p>
      <p>Namely that when France lost it was conquered and subjected to Nazi soldiers enforcing their will on Paris and the expulsions of ethnic French from vast swaths of their homeland. Should the US lose a carrier group in the South China Sea and call for terms of peace are we seriously to believe that China would continue until it has the equivalence of marching through Paris?</p>
      <p>In other words, where is China's incentive to try and "drink from the Ohio river" as Lincoln would put it? Where is the Chinese self-interest in hurting the US to the point where it actually affects an American? Not American prestige, or the ability of the US to project power on the other side of the globe without interference. But when does Chinese aggression actually result in someone from Nebraska having a worse day?</p>
      <p>Realpolitik is incredibly useful and all states need to understand it. It is value that must come before all others values, since without survival the implementation of all of values becomes moot. I'm personally a Defensive Neorealist before I am any liberal, conservative, or libertarian. But the fears of conquest, territorial control, and ethnic expulsion that have to be considered when one thinks of Europe (Ukraine-Russia), Africa (Collapse in the Sahel, or Africa's 'Not Prussia' aka Rwanda winning again), or the Middle East (Saudi Arabia's eastern Shia vs Iranian Arabic Khuzestani's) do not have the same weight when applied to America.</p>
      <p>The year is 2030, after a humiliating loss of an entire Carrier battle group in a 7 day naval engagement China has complete control of the South China Sea and US retreated with its tail behind its legs. In a humiliating armistice the US-Japan mutual self-defense pact is torn up. Troops are ordered to return home from South Korea and Okinawa. The Philippines signs an agreement to 100 years of neutrality ensuring no US troops on it's soil. China has a String of Pearls guaranteeing it access through Malacca to the Indian Ocean. Vietnam is building so many bunkers that it makes Communist Albania looks like a pacifist nation. It's the nightmare scenario.</p>
      <p>And my life here in Pennsylvania is affected literally not one bit. Neither is the life of anyone in California. No American's life is worse off except that they feel shame and anger over not being to win a fight against a nation 4 times their size halfway across the world for a wargoal that means nothing to any American but which means everything to every Han. This shame and anger exists because Americans have been told all their lives to think it normal that the US can do whatever it wants anywhere it likes. Meanwhile the US's industrial capacity is literally untouched, the Midwest provides more food than we can ever consume, trade with Europe, North &amp; South America continue unabated, and the as a result of the worst military defeat in 300 years the result is what?</p>
      <p>The possible surrender of Guam?</p>
      <p>I genuinely sympathize for the Chamorro/Guamians. I've argued to those who will listen that it's a real shame that they can't vote, how the Jones Act damages their economy, and that they should probably just be either outright incorporated into Hawaii or given a few billions as'sorry for the imperialism and good luck with independence' gift. But this is not Nazi Germany carving up France and making up plans for german resettlement of French-Comte. It's not even like Germany taking Corsica. This is Germany winning the Battle of France, taking St. Pierre &amp; Miquelon, and then returning back across the Rhine.</p>
      <p>In short, all of this is to reinforce the central point that US has very few actual core national interests that can be hurt by anyone, China included. This is genuinely comparable to Russia being terrified of it's future, perhaps even discussing moving the capitol from Moscow to Omsk, because it's no longer 100% certain it could stop the US from taking Havanna. The US conquest of Cuba doesn't threaten Russia. It never has and it never will. Neither does Chinese control of Taiwan threaten the US. Because Taiwan, the Phillipines, South Korea, Japan, and greater SEA are not core US national interests. They are convenient. They are fiddling around the edges.</p>
      <p>None of this is  to dispute your assertions that American is in decline and that China's rise is real and must be taken seriously.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>