<post>
  <author>ChevalMalFet</author>
  <date>2020-06-22T07:45:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gyvay9/george_floyd_protest_megathread/fvm8fnv/</link>
  <title>Ulysses S. Grant as an Abolitionist Hero</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm so incensed about this I can hardly see straight. Let me rant even though this iwll be buried in the thread and never seen. </p>
      <p>Please know where I'm coming from: I used to work at the Ulysses S. Grant Historic Site in St. Louis, which is the former plantation of said "slave owning family." Though most of the historic buildings have been preserved, there are no slave quarters - Grant was so disgusted with them that as soon as his father-in-law passed and he (that is, his wife, Julia Dent) inherited the property he had them all torn down (this was after emancipation, there were no abruptly homeless slaves). I am a hopeless pro-Grant partisan, but I also know what I'm talking about.</p>
      <p>Anyway. Let's leave aside the idiocy of "married a slave owning family" as a criticism and talk about Grant's owning a slave. Here's what these ahistorical cretins don't get: Grant <em>loathed</em> slavery, and he demonstrated that loathing at deep personal cost with no hope or expectation of reward (indeed, he wasn't rewarded!). </p>
      <p>Grant was born in Ohio to a couple that was - well, if they weren't outright abolitionists they were the next best thing. The thing to understand about abolitionism is that while it wasn't unheard of, particularly in the 1820s and 1830s it was a deeply <em>weird</em> political belief. Lots of people wished slavery were more humane, thought the trade should be banned, that slavery shouldn't be allowed to expand further, but outright <em>ending</em> it throughout the country was a very fringe opinion through most of the antebellum years. Abolitionists evangelized and wrote and argued and held speeches, but they were never especially influential. Lincoln was not an abolitionist, for example. The best way to think of them, I think, is like vegans today - people wish animals were raised more humanely, want to ban testing, etc., but only a few fringe folk are saying we should stop eating them altogether. Anyway, if Grant's family weren't vegans, they were probably at least vegetarians. </p>
      <p>So it was a source of tension when Hiram Ulysses married Julia Dent. Julia was the pampered daughter of Augustus Dent, a wealthy landowner in St. Louis. Grant met her while stationed at Jefferson Barracks in the city, and the two were deeply in love all their lives. Grant married her, but moved her off her father's plantation. </p>
      <p>Now, here's the context for Grant owning a slave "for about a year." Grant left the army in the early '50s for various reasons, and tried to make it as a farmer. He built a house for him and Julia (a shitty one, Grant was a terrible carpenter), he tried to make the farm wrok, but he failed. Grant was poorly suited for life in peacetime. He tried to make it as a rent collector, but the damn softy bought every sob story the people he was meant to evict sold him and he failed at that, too. He worked for his asshole father-in-law on the plantation, in the fields alongside the slaves (he was, reportedly, hopeless at getting them to work). Eventually he was reduced to selling firewood on the streets of St. Louis to try and make ends meet for his wife (who expected fine things*) and his three young children. He was almost dirt poor, broke, and struggling.</p>
      <p>Now, it is in this context that his slave should be placed. Grant was gifted a man, William Jones, by his father-in-law, in 1858. Now, do you know how much wealth that represented? A good slave went for nearly $800 in 1860 - which is an incredible sum. To put that in perspective, Union privates the next year were paid a princely $13 a month. Confederate privates made $11. So, a poor soldier - about the social level Grant had sunk to by 1858 - could save his money and not spend a single dime of it for <em>five years</em> and he <em>still</em> would not have enough to afford a slave at average prices. That's without eating, without paying for his uniform or other incidentals, that's 100% of every paycheck into his "future slave" fund.** </p>
      <p>So here's the reality for Grant: If he can't stand having a slave, he could sell William Jones. He'd make enough money - even if he only gets $400-500 for him - to have his family fed and clothed for months or possibly even years depending on how frugal he could be. He'd begged his father for a loan at this time - but he had the solution to his troubles right there! What would you sell, for five years' salary? </p>
      <p>But he didn't. Instead, after less than a year of owning him, Grant signed Jones' manumission papers in March, 1859. He took that store of wealth and basically watched it evaporate into thin air, even in the midst of desperate poverty - because it was the right thing to do. Then he swallowed his pride, moved to Galena, and took a job working for his kid brother as a clerk in the store his brother owned. He was there a year later when the war broke out and the mayor asked the little shop clerk with military experience if he'd be willing to help raise a volunteer regiment...</p>
      <p>SO yeah. Grant <em>hated</em> slavery and he demonstrated it in the firmest way possible - he never expected his manumission of William Jones to be remembered, he never received any recognition or reward for it, he just <em>ate</em> the huge financial loss at a time when he was desperate for any sort of money. Then he saved the Union and was the best civil rights President we've ever had. Fuck these people. </p>
      <p>*To her credit, Julia stuck loyally with Grant all through this time. Theirs is one of the better American romances.</p>
      <p>** Grant, as a captain, would make $115 a month, minus allowances for horse, mess, uniform, etc, had he stayed in the army.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>