<post>
  <author>egoitis</author>
  <date>2020-06-22T21:46:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvoht2p/</link>
  <title>Analyzing "Strange Statisitcs"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I've seen the /pol/ meme "Despite making up only 13% of the population, black people account for over 50% of murders/violent crimes/crimes" shared uncritically on this subreddit, and I'd like to push back on that. The source of this meme, so far as I can tell, is <a href="https://ucr.fbi.gov/crime-in-the-u.s/2018/crime-in-the-u.s.-2018/tables/expanded-homicide-data-table-3.xls">FBI crime statistics</a>, which are based entirely on cleared murders (which for this level of analysis can be considered basically equivalent to convictions). The FBI itself estimates the murder clearance rate at <a href="https://ucr.fbi.gov/crime-in-the-u.s/2018/crime-in-the-u.s.-2018/topic-pages/clearances">62%</a>, so there's quite a lot of room for disparate enforcement to create a disparity there, even presuming all convictions are correct. Furthermore, about 30% of the FBI's listed murders have an offender of unknown race. This can push the vaunted 52% number below 30% in the worst-case scenario.</p>
      <p>Based on this alone, using 13/52 as evidence against police racism is circular logic. ("We know law enforcement isn't racist, so when 52% of people convicted of murder are black, that means 52% of murderers are black. Therefore it is appropriate and not racist to focus law enforcement resources on black communities.") Were it not for the fact that I have seen this exact argument made unchallenged, I would not have made this post, as I agree that the disparity presented in FBI crime statistics are a lot of smoke for there to be no fire whatsoever. However, treating this statistic as fundamentally reliable in a discussion of law enforcement policy and tactics is assuming your conclusion.</p>
      <p>So what other evidence do we have? Well, I've been covering murder so far due to the FBI keeping better numbers on it, but we can look at the <a href="https://www.bjs.gov/content/pub/pdf/cv18.pdf">National Crime Victimization Survey</a>, which directly asks victims about their victimization, and is thus less manipulable by law enforcement. Sadly, we cannot poll murder victims, but the NCVS says that 22% of violent offenders were perceived as black (page 13). That's pretty disproportionate, at 1.8 times the prevalence of black people in the population, but the ratio of cleared murders to reported incidents of violence is even more so! I wish the FBI had racial statistics on aggregated violent crimes, but evidently they only consider murder important enough to gather racial information on.</p>
      <p>And lastly, we cannot forget the prevalence of false convictions. <a href="https://www.law.umich.edu/special/exoneration/Documents/Race_and_Wrongful_Convictions.pdf">The National Registry for Exonerations</a> reports that despite making up only 13% of the population, black people constitute over 50% of those convicted for crimes and later exonerated. (How's that for a meme to uncritically repeat on social media?) In particular, they are <strong>seven times</strong> as likely to be convicted of murder and later exonerated. That's an enormous disparity, comparable to the 13/52 that prompted this discussion! Full numbers on false convictions are almost by definition not available, but I think there is a strong case to be made that they are racially biased given the data on exoneration. Given that, the reliability of FBI crime statistics as a guide to actual rates of criminality must be considered somewhat dubious. It's a data point, to be sure, but it ought to be the beginning of a discussion, and is not on its own the knockdown argument /pol/acks think it is.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>