<post>
  <author>is_not_strained</author>
  <date>2020-06-20T23:29:37Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fvhjs6h/</link>
  <title>On Straining to Build Things</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Build and maintain civilization.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't know whether you have ever built something, but I have, and some small number of billions of people use some of the things I have built regularly.  (I must admit, other people helped at times. I did not do it all by myself, though it sometimes felt like that.)  </p>
      <p>Very few people get to build something that matters.  I was in the Smithsonian museum with my father in law, and when we came to the capsule that returned from the moon, he pointed out a piece of it, which he worked on.  It was maybe five inches long, but it was his responsibility, and it worked (I suppose, they did survive).  He was there animatedly pointing out which bits were his to his grandchildren when some Asian tourists came by and misunderstood what he was saying, and presumed he was an astronaut and demanded to take pictures.  This was fine, as all old white guys look the same anyway.  </p>
      <p>If you read Charles Murray's <a href="https://www.gwern.net/docs/sociology/2003-murray-humanaccomplishment.pdf">Human Accomplishment</a> the most striking things is how few people are listed, and how far down the ranks of achievements this goes.  Just looking at science, mathematics, and technology lists I think most people will realize that they don't know what most people on the list contributed and more importantly, only 1400 people are listed (I am ignoring the literature, art, and music pieces, as while important, they muddy the water).  Almost no-one contributed to the civilization that got us to the moon.  These 1400 people (or the people who actually did the work if these people falsely got the credit) did the majority of the work in developing modern science and technology.  Of course, huge numbers of other people helped, but the architects, to use a building metaphor, were a tiny set.</p>
      <p>Ask an example, which of the following people from his list (selected at random) can you associate with their achievement?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Thomson, James. Thomson, William. Trevithick, Richard. Tsiolkovsky,Konstantin. Cai Lun. Tull, Jethro.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>To help, they invented modern agriculture, paper, rocket propulsion, the high-pressure steam engine, everything named Kelvin, and torque. (in reverse order)</p>
      <p>To give an example of someone not on that list consider the fact that wheat was domesticated once.  That means someone decided to collect proto-wheat seeds, and select the best for planting next season, and did this all their life, and convinced their children and grandchildren this was a good idea to continue.  This person is responsible for the bread you eat.  It was all their work, their idea, and their drive, and their ability to get their family on board with the concept.  I suppose the same is true of whoever did rice, and the handful of other crops.  Society exists because of the huge efforts of this tiny number of people.  </p>
      <p>To build something requires opportunity, a completely self-destructive drive, a mildly supportive environment, and most importantly, an absence of enemies.  The one thing that will ensure that nothing gets done are people working to stop progress.  It is far easier to destroy than to create, and easier still to prevent creation.  </p>
      <p>I tried quite hard for six months to get a statue of Maryam Mirzakhani put up at Stanford where she worked.  Raising the money was trivial, it was oversubscribed instantly,  everything else was impossible.  From every possible direction, there were people who objected on the most bizarre grounds. No statue is going to be erected anytime soon, despite most people being completely supportive, because the same people who want to pull down statue are against other people building statues.  No Iranians can get a statue unless a Hispanic and Black mathematician also get one. No names of appropriate black and Hispanic mathematicians are forthcoming, of course.  No statue of a Muslim woman can show hair.  Actually, no statue of Muslims at all, etc. </p>
      <p>The enemy of progress is the enemies of progress, the people who care more about splitting the current pie than creating more.  Call these people what you like, NIMBYs, socialists, bureaucracy, or whatever, but it is this drive to demand short term equity that prevents long term growth.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>a few serious people to start an effective movement,</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>To build things, you don't start a movement.  Movements are what prevent things from being built.  To build things you start building and hope against hope that the people with movements don't notice you.</p>
      <p>The most important environmental precursor for invention is the absence of people who will work against it.  Silicon Valley was far enough away from the centers of power so people could create. As the Internet makes the world smaller, fewer places are available where people have the space to build before their enemies emerge.  </p>
      <p>The next time you see a social phenomenon, ask yourself this:  "Is this a necessary step on the path to fully-automated luxury gay space communism"? Almost every political act I see fails this test.  To get to the stars, we need to create, but everywhere I see people mobilizing to stop others, or even to destroy the institutions that would allow creation.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>