<post>
  <author>LawOfTheGrokodus</author>
  <date>2020-06-22T19:10:04Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvnz0zs/</link>
  <title>The Need to Get This Election Right</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Getting the general election right ought to be the top task for every state in the country right now, particularly ones that were close in 2016. Collapse in trust in electoral results has the potential to be vastly more damaging than the coronavirus, and I'm worried that a lot of states are sleepwalking towards disaster.</p>
      <p>I don't think coronavirus will be gone by November, and I suspect a lot of voters, particularly elderly ones, will be reluctant to go to an in-person polling place and stand in line indoors for an hour. In many places, it may not be legal for polling places to require voters wear masks, making the voting process even more dangerous. But that's just half the problem. Pollworkers are predominantly older, and so state and county election boards will have a nightmare of a time recruiting enough people, given that they're normally understaffed. <a href="/u/GeriatricZergling">u/GeriatricZergling</a>'s suggestion regarding making it an election week instead of Election Day is sort of already in place with early voting, which usually runs about a week. Expanding early voting might be a good idea for protecting voters, but it puts higher burden on the pollworkers.</p>
      <p>Vote by mail is probably the way to go to ensure the franchise. It can work — some states, like Washington State, have had near-exclusively vote by mail for a long time now without obvious hiccups. Limited vote by mail is already pretty universal in the form of absentee ballots. To be clear, there are certain disadvantages to vote by mail that are intrinsic, most notably the lesser privacy as compared to polling booths. Certain forms of vote manipulation are also more feasible, though on the bright side the security nightmare of electronic voting machines is eliminated.</p>
      <p>The Washington State Director of Elections sent out a <a href="https://coaltionforgoodgovernance.sharefile.com/share/view/s7ea18c433a34152a">memo</a> to her fellow election administrators around the country cheekily titled "Suddenly You All Love Vote By Mail!" that broke down the challenges of implementing it. The physical design of the ballot and associated envelopes isn't trivial (heck, you even need specialty paper!) and the Post Office has a number of regulations that the state needs to comply with to send out its ballots without breaking the bank. Verifying signatures is not a trivial task, and making the whole process auditable is vital for security but challenging at scale.</p>
      <p>In my state, the primary was held primarily by mail-in voting. I've been listening to some meetings of the state and county board of elections, and the level of competence is... varied. One lady with a sinecure and a ton of power misinformed a state senator about ballot privacy, saying that his individual ballot could be tied back to him, but don't worry, they wouldn't do that to deanonymize his vote, just to help him get a new ballot if he requested one. In fact, the identifier was on the envelope, not the ballot, and only indicated which ballot he got (precinct and party), not who exactly he was.</p>
      <p>Once the ballots are received though, there's the process of actually counting them, called the canvass. This is much, much more labor-intensive for vote by mail than for physical polling places. Consequently, the challenge of finding enough pollworkers still applies even in full vote by mail! Thanks to the limited resources allocated to election boards, many don't even have enough space for a larger-scale canvass and have to rent out warehouses or the like. To address personnel shortages, my state decided that it would waive the usual requirement that ballot review be conducted by two pollworkers of different parties, removing an important integrity measure.</p>
      <p>Members of the public can view the canvass through livestreams, but it's not the highest quality video, and of course the angles are limited. If a pollworker were spoiling ballots they didn't like, us viewers wouldn't be able to tell. Still, it's interesting to watch. To discard a ballot as invalid requires unanimous consensus from among a panel of five or so pollworkers, and they are generally disinclined to do so. Still, rules are rules, and when for instance two accidentally swap ballots and fill out the ballot addressed to the other person, both get discarded. There's also some weirder cases, like the person who voted for Trump in every election, including local school board Democratic primary, and signed their ballot "Nancy Pelosi". </p>
      <p>I am quite worried by Trump attacking vote by mail as inherently fraudulent. There's absolutely difficulties to getting it working, and many election boards aren't bastions of competence, but it's our best chance this year for having an election where people can vote safely. Over here on the left, our nightmare is Republican governors or state legislatures using the pretense of fraud to not implement vote by mail, and then shuttering virtually all polling places in Democratic-leaning areas thanks to the shortage of pollworkers. I'd like to be wrong about this, but it seems worrisomely possible.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>