<post>
  <author>marinuso</author>
  <date>2020-06-20T18:21:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fvgn0r7/</link>
  <title>BLM Protests, Answering What Changed</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>There's been BLM agitation before, and it never worked this well. What suddenly changed? Was the death of Floyd really that impactful? That picturesque?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>No doubt the lockdown boredom helped, but mostly I think it's the media (both old and new) regaining control and flexing their muscle.</p>
      <p>In the pre-Internet days, the mass media basically set the Overton window. In an otherwise functioning democracy, that grants you something quite near to total power. A small group of people (and you do not even need a conspiracy for that; TV is simply hard and expensive to make, and to a lesser extent this even applies to newspapers too, meaning a small oligopoly is close to the natural outcome even before power is consolidated afterwards) decided what people thought the issues were, and what people thought the sides were. </p>
      <p>When the powers that were wanted something done, they'd amplify some tiny movement (there are always plenty of crazies in all directions) or astroturf one if there really were no useful crazies. Wall to wall news coverage means everyone at least starts caring, and most people will even take the stance presented as right. If they didn't want something, then they'd simply not put that message out, and discussion of it would not proceed beyond the local bars. This also alienated dissenters from each other - if the whole world (as presented by the media) are in agreement, and only you and your drinking buddies disagree, then surely the problem is with you, right? </p>
      <p>In this way there was a system that was on the one hand a completely functioning democracy, with free and fair elections in every observable way. But in practice, no politician could run without the media's consent (you'd simply not get your message out), and people would vote according to the issues they were told by those same media were important, and the elected politicians were there simply to work out the details. The media were our informal version of Iran's Guardian Council. All of this has long been known and written about, e.g. "Manufacturing Consent", though it never hit the mainstream (weird, huh?). The whole West had variations on this system (the European version includes a state broadcaster, but in practice that doesn't change all that much). </p>
      <p>The Internet changed this, with many-to-many communication. No longer could the media hide things by simply not reporting on them. It became obvious. Someone would complain, and then everyone else would join in and go "hey, it's the same here!". The dissenters in the pubs all found one another, and turned out to be a significant chunk of the population. The traditional media's Internet presence even used to have comment sections themselves, which would be filled with "this is a bald-faced lie and here is the proof" whenever they tried something. The result was a wave of "populism", as democracy suddenly worked as advertised. </p>
      <p>The media reacted poorly and doubled down. In particular I remember the New Year's Eve mass sexual assaults at the start of 2016, and the subsequent attempted coverup, as a watershed moment, when the whole idea of manufacturing consent became clearly and undeniably visible, at least here in Europe. This was also the age of Brexit and Trump. This is when you got chants about the lying press, the enemy of the people, and "Tell the truth! Tell the truth!" at Trump rallies.</p>
      <p>It is also, at least here in the Netherlands, the only time I've ever seen the government truly worried about protests. No longer just the stage-managed quasi-Orwellian "spontaneous demonstrations" for lefty or proto-Woke causes that you'd see from time to time, there were bottom-up protests about real dissatisfaction - this was also the height of the migrant crisis. There were even counter-demonstrations against the "spontaneous demonstrations". And man, did they not like it. This is when the police started harassing people over Tweets without even having any legal basis for it. People called it repression, which it was, but more than that, to me it looked like the sheer panic of a cornered animal. </p>
      <p>But this is also the moment when the centralization of social media had proceeded far enough that Twitter and Facebook now held the power to set the Overton window. I don't think they fully realized this until they had inadvertently 'allowed' the populist wave to happen. Furthermore, the undercurrent of quasi-anarchist libertarianism that has been in the IT world since the beginning, had not yet fully been conquered. People were not all that comfortable with censorship even if they were all lefties. But the light in the heads of the Zuckerbergs went on. </p>
      <p>The remaining libertarians were either 'canceled' out of the tech sphere, or shut themselves up out of fear. Censorship was ramped up, and pacts with the old media made. Twitter now censors Trump. <a href="https://reclaimthenet.org/youtube-remove-politicians-statements-but-allow-media/">YouTube has recently outright stated that they will delete videos by politicians that they don't like in favour of MSM reporting on it, so they can add the necessary - ahem - context</a>. Even we, as small and fringe and non-threatening as we are, look to be the unfortunate recipients of NYT attention soon, and the hatchet will likely follow soon after. </p>
      <p>The old hegemony has been all but reestablished, the only difference being that Facebook, YouTube and Twitter get a seat at the big boy's table of CNN, MSNBC and Fox.</p>
      <p>So what is now left to do, for our old new masters? The George Floyd protests, entirely media-orchestrated, have been a show of renewed force and a mop-up operation in one. Floyd himself - perhaps ironically - doesn't matter in the slightest. 200 black people are killed each year by police. They could've pushed this button at any time. And yet, he has been basically sainted. He's been paraded through the streets in a golden coffin. This is not about Floyd per se, it is about getting people into the streets. It's as spontaneous a demonstration as Orwell could've dreamt up, and it's spread throughout the Western world, as far afield as Lithuania, which maybe has two black people. Media coverage has, of course, been entirely one-sided. The only hint of dissent even existing that we've seen is some cheerful, congratulatory reports on people getting fired for not cheering loudly enough. Meanwhile, every progressive drum is beaten as loudly as possible. The real message is: we are back and the thaw is over.</p>
      <p>This is the message that the people who are saying "it's over" are receiving. What is over? Unrestricted many-to-many communication, and the hopes that it brought. Who won? The media did. It will be like the 1990s again, with everyone on the same page, except you and your drinking buddies in the pub.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>