<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-06-22T13:41:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdpa15/mormons_and_voluntary_organization_much_more_than/fvmwu8k/</link>
  <title>Gold and Silver Souls in Mormon Voluntary Organizations</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Have you read Jim Faulconer's lengthily-titled <em><a href="http://jamesfaulconer.byu.edu/papers/coke_not_coffee.pdf">Why a Mormon Won’t Drink Coffee but Might Have a Coke: The Atheological Character of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints</a></em>?  Faulconer is a formidable philosopher (or so my Continental friends assure me--my specialties do not overlap much with his) as well as someone who converted to Mormonism in adulthood, if memory serves.  (And as a bonus for you, he talks a little about narratives, too.)</p>
      <p>The essay might not seem to have a lot to do with what you're talking about--voluntary organization--but bear with me.  Because I wonder if this is the most important sentence in your essay:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Everyone has an assignment (sorry, 'calling')</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The inside view on "callings" is that God is inspiring some people to tell other people to do the work.  The outside view is that a bunch of crusty old patriarchs are bossing around their congregants with the carrot of eternal life and the stick of eternal damnation.  But take the pragmatic view instead.  Suppose you are a moderately reflective person in a leadership role, i.e., your assignment is in part to give assignments.  You are going to seek "inspiration" on the matter, which in the Mormon canon includes study and reflection.  Being moderately reflective, you're going to consider at least a couple of questions:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Who has abilities relevant to this assignment?</li>
        <li>Who would personally benefit from having or doing this assignment?</li>
        <li>Who will actually accept this assignment?</li>
        <li>Who will actually perform the relevant work <em>after</em> accepting this assignment?</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Of these considerations, 1, 3, and 4 are actually identical to some considerations you might expect to see if you were <em>hiring</em> someone for a position in a business organization--except the carrot you have is a much more pragmatic "small pile of money."  In every congregation you will have some True Believers who will always accept the assignment you give them, and do it to the best of their ability, so when they have useful abilities, it's easy to find a good calling for them. Let's mangle Plato and call these congregants Gold Souls. Gold Souls will often be the first name that comes to mind in answering all four questions.</p>
      <p>When they do <em>not</em> have useful abilities, you're still expected to find them a calling, however.  Call these Silver Souls.  If they seem likely to commit themselves to 3 and 4, then if the answer to 2 can inform your "inspiration."  Will they grow and learn as a result of the assignment?  This is a question I think many businesses fail to ask, or ask but fail to appropriately emphasize (though probably some of the more successful ones do).  A church that claims to "make bad men good and good men better," as at least one Mormon leader has said, must present <em>opportunities for growth</em>.  This means taking people outside their "comfort zone" (or do we now call it "safe space?") from time to time, and providing adequate support for them to eventually grow comfortable there.</p>
      <p>If you can fill all relevant positions with Gold and Silver Souls, then you're pretty well set, organizationally.  But probably this isn't possible in many congregations.  Some people will refuse some assignments.  Some people will refuse <em>all</em> assignments, though presumably this would reduce their standing in the congregation.  Some people will accept assignments for reasons of standing and simply never do the work, or half-ass it.  The latter may actually be worse than the former, though in some cases half-assing is still preferable to contributing nothing at all, I suppose.  So lump these together as Bronze Souls.  With Bronze Souls it's not going to matter much what assignments you give them, they won't do them.  So your job as a leader is to go hunting for a spark of interest.  Obviously if they didn't want to be a part of the Church at all, they would just quit.  But whatever pressure keeps them showing up--family, friends, a lifetime of guilt, whatever--the leader's job is to find a way to "upgrade" it into personal motivation and a willingness to do the work.  Again--in the corporate world, they just can your ass.  </p>
      <p>But to return to Faulconer: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>There is little consistency among LDS practices regarding caffeinated drinks and no more consistency regarding the explanations of those practices. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Replace "caffeinated drinks" here with "callings."  The clearest thing about LDS community structure is its <em>structure</em>.  Everything else is wildly <em>ad hoc</em>.  This post I'm writing, all by itself, gives more guidance on the practice of <em>actually making assignments</em> than LDS congregational leaders ever get (unless, I suppose, their superiors decide to hand them a Covey book!).  The internal expectation is that "revelation" will handle things: God is the boss, and God calls the shots.  Oh and P.S. God wants you to study things out in your own mind before you ask any questions.  He gave you a brain and expects you to use it.  From a practical perspective, then, it makes sense that so many Mormon leaders are selected from the ranks of people who spend time in business management: they have abilities relevant to a leadership assignment, or would benefit personally from the added management practice.  So long as they will accept the assignment and do the work!</p>
      <p>Well I don't think my Platonic cribbing here shows me to be any great genius on the matter. I'm shooting almost entirely from the hip; I have a little experience with hiring in the business world and in academia, so I'm not speaking from total inexperience, but I assume someone who had actually been a Mormon Bishop or Stake President could expand on my account dramatically.  Rather, what I'm trying to illustrate is that what is interesting about Mormon hierarchy is its bold commitment to <em>the hierarchy</em>.  Where other faiths tend to be a set of commitments to certain metaphysical propositions, Mormonism as it exists today is more like a set of commitments to the success of a certain organization.  It is the ultimate Organized Religion.  In the absence of an organized theology, to be a Mormon is to <em>do the work of Mormonism</em>, whatever that happens to be right now.</p>
      <p>Which is kind of a long way of drawing conclusions that appear to parallel yours: such problems as the Mormon Church has come down to the perils of overstructuring and over-organizing.  A lot of people really hate hierarchies!  But the tradeoffs are clear.  The booming growth exhibited by churches in the 20th century appears to have flattened and in many cases reversed.  In the U.S., at least, hatred of hierarchy appears to be waxing, though I think we are not yet back to the 1960s levels of anti-establishment sentiment.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>