<post>
  <author>Omegaile</author>
  <date>2020-06-20T22:30:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fvhdnvz/</link>
  <title>Models of Disability</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is an answer to <a href="/u/Ilforte">u/Ilforte</a>, on his previous comments on the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/hadcew/comment/fv2uvmg">main sub</a> and here.</p>
      <p>More precisely, I believe I understand more the view of Kevin Bird, and can shed some light here. I don't agree with him, I just think his position is more complex than simple identitarianism. His position is the social model of disability.</p>
      <p>The social model of disability.</p>
      <p>First we start with a philosophical question, what is disability? The standard definition, which is referred by the proponents of the social model as the medical model of disability is basically this: a disability is not having the ability to do something that the majority of people do. For the social model, a disability is a social construct, something like: not having the ability to do something that is socially expected. I will atempt to steelman this position.</p>
      <p>Let's start with the easiest case: dyslexia. Most people would consider dyslexia a disability, but notice that it is only a problem within literate sociaties. In a pre-literate society, dyslexia is simply not a problem. Clearly, what makes dyslexia a problem is the social condition of the society around you. That is not to say that there weren't neurological differences that today we call dyslexia, only that those differences weren't and shouldn't be considered disabilities.</p>
      <p>Conversely, maybe in the future they will invent some new technology, and society will reestructure itself around this technology. And maybe someone with your neurology will be utterly incapable to use this technology, and people like you will be considered disabled. So, are you disabled now? Given that every person has some weak point, imagine a possible society such that this weak point is utterly essential for day to day functioning. Would that mean that everyone is disabled?</p>
      <p>In a different direction, observe something like severe myopia. Before glasses, that would be considered a disability. Now myopic people can function basically the same as perfectly sighted people. Maybe you would still consider myopia a disability, but it is certainly a small one, whereas before glasses it might even be life threatening.</p>
      <p>Now let's consider a more complicated case: autism. Most people would consider autism a disability. Except maybe aspies, or high functioning autists.  Wait is the fact that they can function well in society the reason for not being considered disabled? That seems a lot like the social model. Or perhaps it's because despite lack of social ability, there are advantages associated with autism, such as: abstraction, memory, higher IQ, ability to hyperfocus, capacity to detect small nuances in sound, sight and texture. (Note: I am not claiming that autistic people are better at all those things, but as far as I know, they are positively correlated with autism.) But these compensatory abilities go all the way down, with people who cannot do basic arithmetic, but can reproduce with fidelity a music only heard once. Most autistic people are not savants, but there is a high correlation between the two.</p>
      <p>The point is there are pros and cons, and they are intrinsicly connected. It's not like with Stephen Hawking, that was a genius and also had Lou Gehrig disease, completely unrelated. And if there are pros and cons, how do you determine objectively where to draw the line? It seems like every line you draw would be a social convention.</p>
      <p>But looking further, it seems like these pros and cons go way beyond autism. People who have lost one sense tend to overdevelop the other senses, blind people have better hearing and deaf people have better sight. In a imaginary society that puts too much emphasis on sight and very little on hearing, perhaps being deaf would be considered desirable.</p>
      <p>In a chimpanzee society, humans would be considered disabled. These big hairless monkeys, cannot even properly climb a tree. They don't have fur to protect from the elements, and they are weak despite their size. Useless big hairless monkeys. Being intelligent would be pretty useless in a chimp society.</p>
      <p>Coming back to humans, in a pre modern pastoral society that had most of its calories from milk and cheese, maybe someone who is lactose intolerant could be considered disabled. And in a hunter-gatherer society that had no access to wheat, celiac disease would be a non issue.</p>
      <p>Lastly, let's consider a more provoking case: homosexuality. But wait, homosexuality is not a disability, I hear you saying. Well it's not considered now, but it used to be considered a disorder. (Note: I don't think the model distinguishes between disability and disorder. I myself don't see much difference, except that disorder seems to be a disability of the mind). But, I still hear you saying, that's only because people were bigoted back then, or perhaps religiously motivated, or had the Aristotelean view that the purpose of sex is reproduction and therefore non reproductive sex is unnatural, and therefore wrong. Well, these were certainly true, and may very well have biased psychologists. But the issue was deeper, as there were a lot of independent, clearly undesirable measures that didn't favor homosexuals. Such as higher anxiety and depression, unemployment and subemployment, criminality (with things such as prostitution and drug use) and suicidal tendencies. Psychologists were not simply "I hate gays let's consider it a disorder", they had all these correlated issues to make a case. Now, a modern explanation would be something like:  Of course they had all these problems, they suffered discrimination, violence, were often disinherited by their parents. Of course that would cause all sorts of psychological traumas and life issues. But this explanation only favors the social model, as one could easily imagine that the problems associated with some disorder/disability are purely caused by discrimination, and not by biology itself.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>So anyway, this is where Kevin Bird is coming from. He doesn't consider disabilities to be intrinsicly bad, only the interaction of what he considers to be normal differences with society. And that the solution to the problem is always to change society and not the person. As a matter of fact, he doesn't even consider technological solutions to be bad, as he stated that inhalers are good for asthmatics, just as glasses are a solution to myopia in my example, and ramps are a solution to people on wheelchair.</p>
      <p>He does seem to make a logical error, which is that he sees society considering disorders undesirable as the problem and abortion for these disorders as evidence, as consequence of the problem, and therefore wrong. But false implies truth all the time, and bad cab imply good as well. No neo atheist would say: theists believe God commands them to do charity, but God is a bad belief, therefore charity in the name of God is bad as well. Or at least my interpretation of his position seems to contain this logical mistake. But nonetheless this is a small mistake and not the main source of my disagreement.</p>
      <p>In my impression, the social model seems to be very popular among the deaf and the blind communities, and somewhat popular within the autistic community.</p>
      <p>Now that my steelman ended, I can say that the social model of disability has its merits, but should be seen in light of that maxim, all models are wrong, some models are useful. Whenever we see someone with a problem, we should always ask ourselves whether it's easier to change society or to change the person. Kevin Bird is pretty radical, in that he sees the answer to this question as always change society. Moreover even if you think that the social model is always true, and disability is always the fault of society, it's not clear that the necessary changes in society are feasible, either politically, culturally, or technologically. In the end, everybody needs to find a balance between changing society and conforming to society even with impairments. It's not like society is like it is purely for arbritary reasons. Some thingsay be completely arbritary, such as discrimination against homosexuals, and should be completely abolished. Some things are not arbritary, but are low cost enough that we should change, such as installing ramps for wheelchairs. And some things are prohibitive, such as abolishing literacy in order to accommodate dyslexics, even if that was true in the past. But changing education requirements for dyslexics is very feasible, and we do that in order to reduce its disability, while not completely eliminating it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>