<post>
  <author>Shakesneer</author>
  <date>2020-06-22T15:24:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvn7u0e/</link>
  <title>The Irregularaties of American Elections</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The root problem is that American elections are a Gordian Knot patchwork of municipal, local, federal, state, and private regulations. No two elections in America are ever really the same election. Every state is hamstrung by different laws, based in different local circumstances, with different party machines that operate in different ways. The old saw about the Electoral College doesn't go far enough: The Presidential Election is not 50 elections (one per state) but tens of thousands, each governed by different rules. The final result looks less like an actual modern democracy and more like the byzantine systems which elected a Holy Roman Emperor or a Doge of Venice.</p>
      <p>This patchwork is a direct consequence of how American democracy evolved. America never was a democracy. It was always a federalist system, which meant that as our democracy developed it was specific to different times and places. And so we have different rules everywhere: elections run differently from primaries; primaries run differently between Democrats and Republicans; primaries within the same party run differently between different states; residency requirements different everywhere; ballots counted by different rules; completely inconsistent standards for creating ballot initiatives or initiating recalls; dozens of rulesets for what happens if a Senator or Congressman needs to be replaced; wildly specific rules on who where qualifies for mail-in ballots when.</p>
      <p>What America has now is indeed a Democracy. But in my opinion this Democracy is so different from the image evoked by that word that we do great injustice to our self-conception. Every state has a governor, every town has a mayor, broadly speaking every place has the same positions to vote for competed between by the same two parties, and so everything looks the same. But it isn't the same.</p>
      <p>This constant irregularity is especially noticeable in contested elections. Consider all the court challenges of Franken-Cole in 2008, 
 or the byzantine challenging requirements in Arizona's contested 2018 election to replace Flake. One would think that after the infamous "hanging chads" episode of 2000 Florida that there would be national support for some kind of new system. But there isn't, because the federal government does not have the power to inflict such a system on all the states, and there will never be popular support for the Constitutional overhaul this would require as long as Republicans and Democrats are totally suspicious of the legitimacy of any attempts at reform.</p>
      <p>It's worth comparing our system here to other modern democracies. Ours evolved organically over hundreds of years, acquiring all the crust and mold of a long-fermenting system. This is highly unusual. Most modern democracies are centralized systems imposed all at once from above, often after war or revolution. This is the state of Japan, Germany, Italy, France, Austria, Spain, Turkey, Korea... Even Iraq has a more-consistent electoral system than we do. No one will say that these democracies are perfect, but they are national systems that came into being, more or less, all at once. The local systems are run as extensions of the national system. When the system is reformed, those reforms are national in scope and apply everywhere at once. The major exception to this pattern would be Britain. British Democracy has evolved over an even longer period than American Democracy and at times acquired truly musty crusted-over local complexities. But, again, Britain does not have a federal system the same way America does, and so simplifying reforms have often been applied to the entire country all at once.</p>
      <p>I do not suppose American democracy will be easily reformed any time soon. It takes great effort to revoke privileges from local governments -- the history of the modern state is written on the conflicts of centralized courts navigating complex medieval rights. No one wants to give those rights up. Just as few Americans like Congress but many Americans like their individual Congressmen, few Americans like our electoral system but enjoy their local subsystem.</p>
      <p>This all comes before any discussion of mail-in ballots specifically and the concerns both sides have about rigging the election. And while it would be easy to dismiss those concerns as empty conspiricizing, I think American history offers plenty enough examples to give both parties fits of suspicion. It isn't just a matter of suspicious theories about Miami-Dade and Debbie Wasserman Schultz or urban myths about Kennedy stealing Chicago in '62. American elections can and have been stolen, more often than we like to admit. Plenty of the great political machines of the 19th and 20th Centuries stole elections all the time, or else managed elections so as to accomplish the same thing. Tammany Hall is the famous example, but such machines operated all over the country so that even President Truman was suspected of benefitting when he was elected to the Senate. Or, on the subject of Senate elections... Maybe the best-documented example of a stolen election ever is the 2nd book of Robert Caro's biography of Lyndon Johnson, "The Means of Ascent". Caro documents, thoroughly, how Johnson bribed judges, foremen, slumlords, and plenty of assorted officials to steal tens of thousands if not hundreds of thousands of votes, culminating in the "Box 13" scandal where 202 votes were discovered, in alphabetical order, in the same handwriting, 6 days after the election in a locked box. This was just enough votes to swing the election to Johnson, for the first time. The case went all the way to the Supreme Court before Hugo Black ruled that... the federal government could not get involved in election matters contained to the states.</p>
      <p>I suppose that elections don't function quite like that anymore, but I can't suppose they can't. I'm sure there are plenty of irregularities that are kept hidden from the public, more than just Tim Kaine being picked as Hillary's VP years in advance or Donna Brazille passing along a few debate questions or Republicans bragging about voter suppression. And even if there aren't any more irregularities than those -- our suspicious will be dark enough that neither side will ever want to concede to the other enough power to reform the system as it stands today.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>