<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-06-20T22:01:03Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fvhaic0/</link>
  <title></title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>[5/5]</strong>
      </p>
      <h3>Filling A Market Inefficiency</h3>
      <p>With that all out of the way, we come to the meat of this all. I'm very fond of <a href="/r/themotte">/r/themotte</a>. I think it's vital to have a meeting point for different ideological structures, aimed at candid, open discussion. But I don't think it's the only group structure that can be valuable. I expect quite a few will disagree with me on one or both of the communities I've cite as positive, sane groups, but from my angle, both have raised the local sanity waterlines around them. If you disagree with that assessment, note instead their success as rivals and reminders that contrarian movement-building is possible. In both cases, I wound up noticing them because one or another representative of their group said enough sensible things elsewhere that I was able to follow the breadcrumbs back. Narratives will inevitably form and aren't strictly bad. Given that, there is a real use in creating communities unapologetically centered around specific narratives.</p>
      <p>The particular narrative I would hope to see a community spring up around shouldn't be much of a surprise to anyone here. Marc Andreesen recently wrote a viral article titled <a href="https://a16z.com/2020/04/18/its-time-to-build/">It's Time To Build</a>, arguing this:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Every Western institution was unprepared for the coronavirus pandemic, despite many prior warnings. This monumental failure of institutional effectiveness will reverberate for the rest of the decade, but it’s not too early to ask why, and what we need to do about it.... Part of the problem is clearly foresight, a failure of imagination. But the other part of the problem is what we didn’t <em>do</em> in advance, and what we’re failing to do now. And that is a failure of action, and specifically our widespread inability to <em>build</em>.... You don’t just see this smug complacency, this satisfaction with the status quo and the unwillingness to build, in the pandemic, or in healthcare generally. You see it throughout Western life, and specifically throughout American life.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Recently, Tanner Greer followed it up with another insightful commentary: <a href="https://scholars-stage.blogspot.com/2020/06/on-cultures-that-build.html">On Cultures That Build</a>. I'll quote his tl;dr and one other useful bit:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In the 21st century, the main question in American social life is not "how do we make that happen?" but "how do we get management to take our side?" This is a learned response, and a culture which has internalized it will not be a culture that "builds."</p>
        <p>it should not be that surprising that the Americans of 1918 could set up mixed civic-business-government organizations on the fly; they had just done the exact same thing at the exact same level of society two years earlier in order to sell war-bonds and rally the home front against the Hun. [2] Both efforts should be seen against the backdrop of an incredible nation-wide craze for institution building. In 1918, America was not even a generation removed from its frontier past; the frontier was only officially closed in 1890, and the state of Arizona was only admitted to the Union in 1912. The Americans of 1918 had carved towns, cities, and states out of the wilderness, and had practical experience building the school boards, sheriff departments, and the county, city, and state governments needed to manage them. Also within the realm of lived experience was the expansion of small towns into (unprecedentedly large) metropolises and the invention of the America's first multi-national conglomerates. The progressive movement had spent the last three decades experimenting with new forms of government and administration at first the state and then the federal level, while American civic society saw a similar explosion in new social organizations. These include some famous names: the NRA, the American Red Cross, the Salvation Army, the American Bar Association, the Sierra Club, 4-H, the VFW, Big Brothers, the NAACP, the Boys Scouts, the PTA, the United Way, the American Legion, and the ACLU. [3] To a large extent we wander in the ruins of the world this generation built.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think a lot of people conflate a culture of building with literal construction, which I think is a bit reductive. It's a broader mindset. Call it hacker culture, call it builder culture, call it whatever you will, it's a framework that says it is <em>possible</em> to do remarkable things, and so one way or another we will figure out how. It's a culture that prioritizes construction over critique, one that's doggedly pro-social and focused towards the long term, one that recognizes the sheer difficulty and fragility of what we've collectively achieved and is determined to work to keep it going one way or another.</p>
      <p>I saw a recent Twitter thread inviting people to describe their ideologies in five words or less. Here's my shot at my own:</p>
      <p>Build and maintain civilization. </p>
      <p>There's a lot more, of course. There are plenty of details that I'd highlight, including a <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/hbikja/rip_to_k_anders_ericsson_the_father_of_expertise/">focus on true expertise</a> and parts of my <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/cd9jeq/attraction_to_the_apposite_sects/etsphy5/">musing on secular religion</a>. I think the core of building strikes at an important, central urge, though, and can be usefully fit around a lot of related ideas. It's not a new concept, of course. Nothing ever is. But I believe people are prioritizing the idea much less than they should, and we need to collectively put more effort into spreading, and acting on, it.</p>
      <p>Here's the catch: I'm not much of a movement-builder. I'm disorganized, chaotic, and a rubbish self-promoter. I think this is a flag worth planting and aiming to rally people around, but if there's a better alternative than trying to wrangle a brand-new movement together, I would jump on it. That said, I <em>do</em> think it's possible for a few serious people to start an effective movement, and now more than ever, given the extreme voices directing current politics and the increasing atmosphere of hopelessness here, it seems like something new may be necessary. At worst, I'm hopeful that my own tentative attempts to get something going might prod someone else into doing it better.</p>
      <p>I haven't created anything of this yet. I don't know quite how serious I am just yet, and would hope to have a few other True Believers working alongside me to really try and get something going. But right now, US politics and culture are on a course that terrifies me, and I sincerely believe that a movement like this, if successful, would be an important element to add to the conversation. I'm curious to know how many others agree with my judgment here.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>