<post>
  <author>4bpp</author>
  <date>2021-02-13T00:11:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lf6ihw/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_08/gn4almw/</link>
  <title>How understanding public morale and political support for war can help you win at Civ 2</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think the logic behind it is most apparent when analysing human rights specifically in the context of rules of war (prohibition of biological weapons, cluster munitions, use of civilian hostages, ethnic cleansing, indiscriminate bombing, dim look upon human wave tactics...). Highly developed countries like the US have active economies, plenty of materiel and high human capital, so it's easy for them to throw precision-guided munitions, fancy planes and disciplined police that is well-equipped with sensors and AI at a problem. However, even minimal degrees of casualties and human suffering clearly sap their morale and war-fighting capability, sometimes even if those casualties are on the other side. On the other hand, mid- to low-developed countries have little materiel, but generally plenty of expendable humans and high tolerance for suffering. A system of universal human rights (whether imposed on them in memespace or enforced by coordinated action against defectors), therefore, turns out to selectively prevent them from using their comparative advantages while having minimal impact on those that the developed countries have.</p>
      <p>Similar arguments can easily be extended to the non-military domain: banning child labour in the US reduces competition in an already-overcrowded low-skilled labour market and makes sure more children go to school to accumulate even more human capital, whereas banning child labour in Bangladesh takes out a significant chunk of their potential to at least earn hard cash by producing cheap clothing. Forcing the US to not have a secret police that makes dissidents accidentally fall out of the window makes no difference because dissidents in the US just wind up looking like Occupy Wall Street, but forcing Russia to not have a secret police that does that would eventually make Russia go the way of Ukraine or Tunisia, which would be quite good for the US.</p>
      <p>(Do you know how in Civ 2, switching your government to Democracy boosts your research and economic output, but gives you two unhappy citizens for every unit beyond the first one that a city supports outside of your own territory? Now imagine if the Civ 2 democracies all agreed to attack any non-Democracy that fielded more than one unit per city. Effectively, the other nations would get all the disadvantages of Democracy and none of the advantages.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>