<post>
  <note>Removed crosslink to theschism.</note>
  <author>cincilator</author>
  <date>2021-02-15T11:28:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lk8abe/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_15/gnixl92/</link>
  <title>The Message of "Tech Needs Humanities"</title>
  <category>
    <li>coteries</li>
    <li>knowledge</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The single most flawed take that I see over and over again is "techies need humanities." Or more precisely, argument that "tech is broken and helps alt-right to flourish because tech nerds are ignorant of humanities." I can't stop anyone from making this argument, but I can prove that it is bullshit. And this is not because I hate humanities or anything like that, it is simply that the argument is wrong.</p>
      <p>What if I told you that there already exists a massively successful tech company that was initially financed by a humanities major, its CEO is well-versed in humanities, and its central feature was inspired by a great postmodern scholar? Yet this company is pretty much considered the nexus of everything wrong with tech by the very people who tell us that "tech needs humanities."</p>
      <p>Peter Thiel studied philosophy at Stanford University, graduating with a B.A. in 1989. Although Mark Zuckerberg is often seen as a prototypical STEMlord, his high school was actually pretty heavily humanities-based and he is known to recite the <em>Aeneid</em> in Latin. (Deeply ironic as tech critics tend not to know that fact about Zuck. Humanities-trained tech critics are surprisingly incapable of recognizing one of their own, likely due to his wooden affect. But isn't humanities training supposed to teach you to see beyond the superficial?)</p>
      <p>Anyway, it is known that Zuck and Thiel are both familiar with the work of Rene Girard. And Girard's big idea is a bit hard to explain but the gist is that people love to imitate the behavior of other people. For that reason, people seek the means to learn what other people are doing and what they like. Hence "like" button which empowers you to immediately signal to others what you "like" and -- more importantly -- to see what your friends "like". </p>
      <p>(More darkly, Girard theorized that collective human sacrifice rituals were precisely the result of people's tendency to imitate others. The hardest thing is to throw the first stone, the rest follows. "Cancel culture" thrives on social media because there it is much easier to trigger mimetic avalanches. Here's an <a href="https://www.tabletmag.com/sections/science/articles/sacrificial-games-cancel-culture">article on that</a>)</p>
      <p>Bottom line, facebook already did everything its biggest critics believe they want the tech company to do. And we all know what they think about the final result. I honestly have more respect for the assertion that tech is too "white and male." Tho this argument is racist and sexist, at least it is harder to debunk coz I don't know any massive tech company founded, financed and inspired from the start by minorities or women. So who knows, maybe that will save everything.</p>
      <p>More seriously, there is no guarantee that reading more humanities will make you think "my god, contemporary woke progressives are right about everything!" Reading about medieval history (as an amateur) didn't make me more progressive. In fact, it was a total shock to me that medieval church didn't in fact burn scientists at the stake (that is "Enlightenment"-era myth), but on the contrary medieval period started what amounts to the first real industrial revolution. And all that despite their despotism and turbo-misogyny (Or maybe <em>because</em> of it? Enter reaction). </p>
      <p>No, reading history didn't make me reactionary (I am still mostly a liberal) but it did teach me that reaction can sometimes get shit done. And note that I didn't read anything fringe -- simply books and articles on medieval technology written by perfectly mainstream scholars. I am convinced that the reason why academia is so left is not primarily due to the content of things they study but due to peer pressure. STEMlords don't exist in the same peer groups so they might get to entirely different conclusions.</p>
      <p>What if you force STEMlords to read some humanities and they get more reactionary? What if the whole thing backfires? After all, in the Balkans (where I live) many nationalist firebrands have history degrees as this helps them to better buttress their ultranationalist arguments.</p>
      <p>The reason why villains like Hannibal Lecter or Satan in <em>Paradise Lost</em> are scary is not because they are ignorant of the sublime beauty of poetry and philosophy. They use their very knowledge of that beauty to manipulate and harm others. They know what is good and true yet they <em>choose</em> evil. And that is a far scarier proposition than "smelly tech nerds are too ignorant to know what is going on."</p>
      <hr />
      <p>To elaborate a bit more on Girard connection. In his view, "cancel culture" is ritualized human sacrifice enabled by social media. Note that the goal is always to get the target fired -- not reprimanded or made to apologize, fired. Because extrajudicial killings are no longer legal, getting someone fired is the closest to killing someone that the mob can realistically get to. What firing also has in common with killing someone is that both actions have a definite climax (which e.g. demotion lacks).</p>
      <p>Girard's point is that the hardest thing to do is to be the one to throw the first stone (because you are not imitating anyone) but once that is done, the ritual is easy to continue. Meatspace governments are usually doing everything to disincentivize this -- thus penalties against vigilantism, against slander and so forth. But social media "governments" are doing everything possible to incentivize throwing the first stone (euphemized as a "call-out") -- via likes, upvotes or retweets.</p>
      <p>This makes for a magnetic spectacle. First, the dreaded call-out is made. The call-out is followed by a wave of mimetic behavior (bandwagoning) as the tension mounts. And when the tension gets unbearable it is followed by a release in the form of firing. Needles to say, engagement statistics go trough the roof.</p>
      <p>(I think the reason why reaction to that NYT article is so tepid -- besides the article being so poorly written -- is that Scott is now self-employed. He has no job to lose, hence there is nothing to ratchet the tension and no prospects for a release. A callout by NYT would ordinarily be a bat-signal to initiate the ritual but he is out of reach)</p>
      <p>The result is a perpetual free-for-all Hatfield-McCoy blood feud with periodic sacrificial spectacles that have tens of thousands of participants and millions of spectators. Social media are massive engines that turn human sacrifice into profit. I don't know how much of that was <em>consciously</em> built this way but Thiel (again, he read Girard) and the others had enough knowledge to anticipate at least some of that.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>