<post>
  <note>Not really happy on this one, but it's hard to get any level of context that makes it more readable.</note>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2021-02-17T01:48:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lk8abe/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_15/gnpt2et/</link>
  <title>The Insurgent Victory of 'Not Losing'</title>
  <category>
    <li>coteries</li>
    <li>culture</li>
    <li>media</li>
  </category>
  <context>
  <blockquote>I don't see why Gamergate veterans would be bitter. The movement may have gone it's separate ways - which was inevitable given it's diversity - but between the fall of Gawker and simply proving the impotence of everyone who tried to destroy it they came out ahead.</blockquote>
  <p>Major publishers are now very careful not to release games that will get them dragged on Twitter. Perhaps that's not exactly a loss for Gamergate -- it obviously reflects a broader social trend -- but it sure as hell isn't a win.</p>
  </context>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Not being a triumph is not the same as not being a win. Like in most conflicts, it depends on framing, and I don't believe the best framing for gamergate is a win or lose affair at all.</p>
      <p>If you evaluate gamergate in terms of two peer competitors competing for institutions like conventional armies seizing terrain, sure, it was a defeat if anything. Institutional control remained where it was at the start, in the hands of the establishment who hated the gamergaters and were hated in return.</p>
      <p>In terms of an insurgency, though, it was a huge win because 'winning' in a social insurgency context doesn't mean crushing your enemies, it means not losing despite the efforts of your enemy to crush you. Gamergate was the target of a deliberate social destruction campaign by institutional and cultural powers of note ranging from prestige media, non-prestige media, and corporations. It was a target of the progressive alliance for months/years, <strong><em>and was not destroyed</em></strong> as a message, cause, or identity. The gamergate movement wasn't destroyed by duress, it disbanded, and the distinction is significant as gamergater veterans have gone on to be part of a new socio-political environment. Those demographics are a reality of new American politics- the sort of anti-progressive foot soldiers and bitter veterans who not only helped Donald Trump perform a once-in-a-century upset in 2016, but prevented the Democrats from achieving a once-in-a-century counter-route in 2020.</p>
      <p>If you're familiar with how viable insurgencies propegate themselves for the long wars and ultimately succeed, it's not by triumphing over the evil empire and marching through the cities of your enemies. ISIS had victory parades and territorial conquests, and four years later their caliphate was destroyed and they were hiding in the deserts, politically powerless and barely relevant. The middle eastern government-equivalents of video game companies don't restrain themselves in fear of antagonizing ISIS; video game publishers are significantly more restrained about the prospects of chasing progressive praise and taunting the gamergaters if they want something more than a marginal market.</p>
      <p>Framing matters, and yeah, you can make anything look better for you. But as a movement that was never in the position of power in the first place, 'did not conquer the digital space of prestige media and wikipedia' is a poor metric.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>