<post>
  <author>GrapeGrater</author>
  <date>2021-02-15T21:18:16Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lk8abe/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_15/gnkpsk1/</link>
  <title>How Western foreign policy, when imitated outside the West, often alarms Westerners</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I would say that this new panic about how other nations perceive the west comes from changes in the way westerners have viewed themselves and conducted foreign policy.</p>
      <p>In the cold war, the US and NATO were all too willing to turn a blind eye to all sorts of authoritarian governments and ignore flagrant human rights violations in places like Pakistan. This was because the Soviet Union were seen as a greater threat and it was better to get along with people of questionable character than risk losing them to the Soviets.</p>
      <p>In the post-war era, there was no real alternatives. If you wanted money you had to cooperate with the demands of the west. There simply was no counterbalance and the counterbalances that did exist were western anyway. But this led to Western elites and foreign policy to get used to making all sorts of demands--these demands tended to coincide with culture war revolutions in the west that occurred at about the same time (acceptance of homosexuality, for example).</p>
      <p>But remember that the west is weird. The average Pakistani or African doesn't approve of gay marriage and has no interest in "overthrowing the patriarchy." Furthermore, there's not a clear reason why the leadership should either. So now the Chinese have appeared as a reasonable counterbalance to the west. Der Spiegel, like most of the Western establishment still believe that it is their duty to the world to impose their values and beliefs upon the barbarian hordes and still haven't re-calibrated their understanding (or tolerance) of the reality of the situation.</p>
      <p>One reason to cooperate with the Chinese is that it's simply prudent: by accepting Chinese support and giving favorable noises, said nations receive material gain and are able to start the bidding war with the west for favorable negotiations. But the other is that the western governments, particularly administrations like Biden's or Merkel's are strongly influenced by organizations like the Human Rights Campaign or National Organization of Women.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And now suddenly we are supposed to be worried about these countries wanting to emulate China.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>These developing nations aren't the only ones emulating China. I would say that the western nations are well on the way to emulating the Chinese style, if not substance, on equality between citizens and freedom more generally.</p>
      <p>Then you have the issues that stem from the western elite cracking down on internal dissent in a way that makes their claims ring hollow. Twitter banning Trump, and the reaction in India, is a great example. "Everyone" was cheering for Trump being banned. Until he was. And then the Indians, the Mexicans and the Germans all recoiled in shock. Now India is banning twitter users engaging in the farmer protests and Twitter's claims of "freedom of speech" are so hypocritical to be ignored (and the Government of India is threatening to imprison the local employees of Twitter). So when the US government inevitably attacks India for attacking Twitter... </p>
      <p>By engaging in widespread censorship, claims about "freedom of speech" or "equality for all" ring hollow. It's hard to say to what degree non-Americans pay attention to random citizens being censored, but when they see a clear example of hypocrisy, it tends to stick. Imagine what happens when African strongmen hear about the Italians declaring the Five Star Movement a criminal enterprise and throwing much of the leadership in jail!</p>
      <p>Then you have the issue where loans from organizations like the IMF have demands for human rights written into the contracts. China doesn't care. So it should be no surprise when these countries agree with Chinese assertions that "human rights are a western imperial wedge." The Chinese are jingoistic and imperialist, but they aren't the only ones... Considering the way the culture wars play out in the US and Europe, the culture wars are replicating and self-similar.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>