<post>
  <note>Removed some user pings, improved some formatting problems for readability. I'd be really badly tempted to remove the whole first paragraph.</note>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2021-02-18T02:31:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lk8abe/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_15/gnua14l/</link>
  <title>The Modern Citation System Does Not Optimize for Truth</title>
  <category>
    <li>knowledge</li>
    <li>media</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>/u/Sizzle50 has a post on <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/lk8abe/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_15/gnt0bro/">Wikipedia purging Race-IQ page</a> (of interest to him might be the specific banishment of <a href="https://archive.vn/k7Ses">«Ashkenazi Jewish intelligence»</a>). This reminds me, I recently wanted to talk about an adjacent issue: <strong>bad faith citations and belief regeneration pipeline.</strong></p>
      <p>Many people I respect, notably SA and Guzey, have opined that Wikipedia is rly awesome. I think it's a problem: so awesome it is, the power it has over consensus reality has grown unchecked, and this has attracted some actors who make it smell funny to me, in an ever so subtle a way. </p>
      <p>First, a question borne out of idly browsing Wiki, one as impolite as IQ differences, albeit less ideologically loaded: <em>do East Asians stink less than other peoples do?</em></p>
      <p>There is such a stereotype, and stereotypes tend to be "directionally" accurate. Some among East Asians themselves are <a href="https://youtu.be/B8_dRXoa4fk?t=154">strongly convinced</a> that this is the case. <a href="https://archive.is/jZfty">Wikipedia</a>, despite eagerly delving into East Asians in particular, is... less certain.</p>
      <p>On one hand, it lists a bunch of articles in support of tentative mechanism:
        <blockquote><em>«The ABCC11 gene determines axillary body odor and the type of earwax.[5][19][20][21] The loss of a functional ABCC11 gene is caused by a... polymorphism, resulting in a loss of body odor in people who are specifically homozygous for it.[21][22] Firstly, it affects apocrine sweat glands by reducing secretion of odorous molecules and its precursors.[5] The lack of ABCC11 function results in a decrease of the odorant compounds 3M2H, HMHA, and 3M3SH ... The non-functional ABCC11 allele is predominant among East Asians (80–95%), but very low in other ancestral groups (0–3%).[5]»</em> The citations are of varying strength and relevance, but generally okay-ish. Huh.</blockquote></p>
      <p>But Science Is Hard!
        <blockquote><em>«However, research has observed that this allele does not result in ethnic differences in scent. A 2016 study analyzed differences across ethnicities in volatile organic compounds (VOCs), across racial groups and found that they largely did not differ significantly qualitatively nor quantitatively after Bonferroni correction. Of the few observed differences, they were found to be unrelated to ABCC11 genotype.[23]»</em></blockquote></p>
      <p>And:</p>
      <blockquote><em>«It has been noted that there is currently no evidence that sweat secretion glands nor sweat production varies across ethnicities.[24] One large study failed to find any significant differences across ethnicity in residual compounds on the skin, including those located in sweat.[25] If there were observed ethnic variants in skin odor, one would find sources to be much more likely in diet, hygiene, microbiome, and other environmental factors.[26][27][28]»</em></blockquote>
      <p>So what's going on here?</p>
      <p>First of all, 2016 study [23] is the same thing as [27], which is alleged to support another point. [26] is a historian's retrospective of <em>«Race and Smell in Eighteenth-Century English Culture»</em>. [28] provides us with no new knowledge on odor, and admits that even microbiome data it presents is unreliable.</p>
      <p>So really we have [23]/[27], [24] and [25] left as possible objections to the claim.</p>
      <p>[24] is a review paper from 2002, preceding, it seems, <em>all</em> empirical work in the section (when touching body odor, it mentions «3 studies of less-than-optimal design», from 1922, 1926 and 1960).</p>
      <p>[25] (2014) in a nutshell:
        <blockquote><em>«Ethnicity, gender and age had no significant impact on the quantity of RSSC recovered from the skin surface [...] <strong>For the purpose of this study, the ‘Asian’ group comprised individuals from India, Pakistan and Bangladesh</strong>. [...] In contrast to previous studies [7,28,29,39,41,42], this study was based on a relatively large number of volunteers [(315)] and can be considered statistically robust (Table 3) [... in Table 3]  [51]: 1360 volunteers, all females, Ethnicity ... East Asian (207); Japanese (381) ... African-Americans showed significantly more secretion than East Asians and Hispanics ... Ethnicity specific results are not in agreement with the current study»</em>.  You be the judge.</blockquote></p>
      <p>At last, [23/7] – titled «<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4724538">"The Effect of Ethnicity on Human Axillary Odorant Production"</a>» – is the real deal, actual empirical study of body odor markers, low N but was big enough for Wiki I guess. So what does it find?  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The <em>ABCC11</em> genotype of each donor was analyzed. Nine East Asian donors were identified as TT homozygotes, while one was found to be a CT heterozygote. The remaining 20 donors (Caucasian and African-American) were all CC homozygotes.</p>
        <p>(3M2H) comparison revealing significant differences (<em>P</em> = 0.009, Kruskal-Wallis test) in the relative amounts of the <strong>characteristic axillary odorant</strong>, <em>E</em>-3M2H, among the three donor groups. with African-American &gt; Caucasian &gt; East Asian in the relative amounts produced. Mann-Whitney pairwise comparisons, using a Bonferroni-corrected <em>P</em> = 0.017, revealed a significant difference between samples from African-Americans vs. East Asians (U = 10.0, <em>P</em> = 0.002); no other pairwise comparison was significant.</p>
        <p>Previous findings suggest that individuals homozygous for the SNP 538G→A produced significantly less characteristic axillary odorant precursors than both heterozygous (C/T) and wild-type (C/C) individuals (Harker et al. 2014; Inoue et al. 2010; Martin et al. 2010; Nakano et al. 2009). Based on these findings, and the marked ethnic diversity of the <em>ABCC11</em> allele frequencies, <strong>one would predict East Asian donors to exhibit lower levels of axillary odorants as compared to donors of Western descent. Our findings are consistent with these predictions.</strong> </p>
        <p>The results, however, also reveal that despite exhibiting the same <em>ABCC11</em> genotype, there were marked differences in the levels of characteristic axillary odors between African-American and Caucasian donors. For example, a major contributor to axillary odor, <em>E</em>-3M2H, was significantly higher in African-Americans when compared to Caucasians.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It stands to mention that Bonferroni <em>severely</em> raises probability of Type II Error in such tiny studies; recorded differences in <em>E</em>-3M2H measures are like 400-1400%. I am not sure if further research will redeem or discard <em>ABCC11</em> hypothesis when it explains variation on <em>E</em> isomer, but «largely do not differ quantitatively» seems untenable already.</p>
      <p>And it's natural to wonder how all this data was twisted into the confusing and self-contradictory mess that's designed to make a reader leave with vague sense of genetics not being very important after all. And given prior conditioning, even with «race pseudoscience deboonked again» smug grin. How many would dig into the sources? </p>
      <p>But this is all hobby tier, not Real Science and academic citation culture, right? Wrong. Lest I be accused of (nit)picking on sleep-deprived Wiki editors, here's a recent <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell/fulltext/S0092-8674(21)00011-8">Cell "Fund Black scientists"</a> paper, calling for Anti-Racist update to NIH spoils system.  Money quote: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>«Black applicants’ award rates remained at ~55% of those for white PIs ... Black faculty are ~6-fold underrepresented relative to the US population in academic medicine (Erosheva et al., 2020).»</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Et tu, Elena Erosheva!? Not so fast. <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32537494/">NIH peer review: Criterion scores completely account for racial disparities in overall impact scores</a> is pretty much what it says on the tin.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>«...we examine assigned reviewers’ preliminary overall impact and criterion scores to evaluate whether racial disparities in impact scores can be explained by application and applicant characteristics. We hypothesize that differences in commensuration ... disadvantage black applicants [...] matching on key variables including career stage, gender, and area of science, we find little evidence for racial disparities emerging in the process of combining preliminary criterion scores into preliminary overall impact scores. Instead, preliminary criterion scores fully account for racial disparities—yet do not explain all of the variability—in preliminary overall impact scores.»</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>With Erosheva as the better case, the gig works roughly like this: progressive researchers investigate topics expecting «good» findings, in case of nastiness add some smoke and mirrors, cite dishonestly, perhaps give an ambiguous title or bury the lede (no doubt influenced by IRB/funding body/Twitter), and Wikipedia, citing them, processes this into meandering status quo affirmation. Reader leaves the page none the wiser.</p>
      <p>There's an awful lotta talk of bias in American culture (Cell again: <em>«For example, the NIH should study the cultural competency and unconscious bias harbored by its reviewers ... and why “matching criteria” (Erosheva et al., 2020) affect the funding disparity gap.»</em>.  </p>
      <p>I naively contend that the above is prime example of bias (and also an application of priming effect). It's a mighty thing: every biased handler, like a voluntary milli-Winston from <em>1984</em>, adds a small sensible spin to the data. And the more stages there are in the pipeline, the more watchers, the closer the output comes to the preconceived notion, regardless of input-level evidence. A faith regenerates.</p>
      <p>Nathan Cofnas suggests that <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10699-015-9421-3">science is not always self-correcting</a>. I'd go further: a Byzantian (or Talmudic, even) system like any modern citation-based knowledge-producing institution, in context of universal culture, <strong>is not built</strong> for self-correction. Where it matters, it's built for drowning data in textual ritual, and regenerating myths over and over. And Wikipedia editor is more than a scientist: he's a high priest of common sense, who casts evil-banishing spells on his domain. And he does it for free.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>