<post>
  <author>iprayiam3</author>
  <date>2021-02-17T17:36:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lk8abe/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_15/gnsbftf/</link>
  <title>Liberals of the gaps</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>In a comment last week, I called SA and his fellow Substack liberals as “liberals of the gaps”. I want to expand what I meant. (tagging <a href="/u/PontifexMini">u/PontifexMini</a> )</p>
      <p>My framework builds on Thomas Ziehe’s proposal that we went through a period of detraditionalization that has now become a period of post-detraditionalization. </p>
      <p>My thesis is that ‘liberals’ fall into camps, those who have joined post-detraditional  movements and argue them still liberalizing, those who dissent and have stopped liberalizing or moved right, and those who keep trying to find solution by further detraditionalizing.</p>
      <p>I call the third group “liberal of the gaps” because they are finding less and less to liberalize while staying nominally anti- idpol progressive zeitgeist. And they must stretch their frameworks thinner and thinner to address current social woes without getting caught by traditionalists and post-detraditionalists.</p>
      <p>Now, by liberal, I don’t mean just “American lefty” but neither am I talking broadly about folks who hold classically liberal / Enlightenment views. I am talking more about the sentiment that has been favorably aligned with the detraditionalization period. In discussion of public schooling, Labaree mentions that there is always tension inherent in <em>democratic liberalism</em>. </p>
      <p>In his conception democratic ideals include collective pursuits of equality, unity, common access to public goods, and liberalism to be focused on individual self-determination. (His core point and a good example of the tension: public schooling is asked to be both an equalizer and a meritocratic rewarder and constantly fights itself over the irreconciliation). I can’t do his specific definitions total justice here, but I hope I’ve given these terms enough particular context for the rest of this post.</p>
      <p>The intolerance paradox can be viewed as manifestation of this: democratic good at odds with liberalism.</p>
      <p>So, my point is that the detraditionalization period was a “liberalizing” phase. Its focus was on breaking ceilings, opening access to traditionally closed institutions, removing the public authority of institutions, or defeating the institutions all together. Overall this led to rapidly opening access on individual levels within different parts of society.</p>
      <p>But it also allowed a certain lack of scrutiny about what those institutions were protecting. This is occasionally visited in works like “Bowling Alone”. An easy cherry picked example was the argument that “gay marriage isn’t going to affect <em>you’re</em> life / marriage.” <a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/79054/here-comes-the-groom">Andrew Sullivan argues as much from a statedly conservative perspective in 1989</a>.</p>
      <p>Now, to argue that gay marriage has broken marriage or society in some unique way, seems a myopic and hard sell to me. But it seems very easy to argue that over the past 60 years, liberal concessions here and there (no fault divorce, sexual revolution, abortion, contraception, destigmatization of… everything) have generally exploded the social glue the institution previously provided for better or worse.</p>
      <p>Mostly, the liberal de-traditionalisationist sees this explosion as <em>good</em>. I am not here to argue that, though I personally disagree. I want to move on to my real point that, detraditionalization is mostly over. Ziehe:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“It has become clear that a continued push for the delimiting and destructing processes can hardly be a contemporary solution… the young people rarely any longer express their crises about themselves in terms of wishes for liberation…essentially wishes are much more about how to remove orientation diffusions and instability.</p>
        <p>By ‘post-destraditionalisation’, I refer to a context of experiences in which counterbalances of the contexts of destructuring are wanted… It is my impression that counterdesires for liberation and destructuring have arisen such as:
* Stable relations, integration and support and community
* Some kind of shielding in relation to continually being observed by society and authorities…
* For normative clarity…”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It’s hard to do his whole point justice without more of his context in terms of education. And certainly some of this is debatable. But I believe this forms a really good starting point for understanding the new illiberal progressive hegemony arising. </p>
      <p>These counter-desires appear in safe spaces, cancel-culture, deplatforming alt views, bio-pronouns, us vs them anti-racism and “ally”culture, wokisim in general as a moral guidepost, etc. etc. The dissent crushing on social media is a part of the post-detraditionalisation. This culture is done breaking down the old hegemony and moved toward reconstituting a new, more “inclusive/progressive/woke/whatever you want to call it” one.</p>
      <p>Returing to Labaree's paradigm, progressives are pushing back into a <em>democratic</em> consolidating phase: focused on rebuilding a common sense of understanding and expectations of 'equality' (now equity). They are trying to create a new standard not get rid of standards. They recognize, like the reactionaries, that institutional trust must be rebuilt and further liberalizing can't do that right now.</p>
      <p>So, I said in my previous post there are three groups of deconstructionist liberals (not post-liberal progressives, those are a different group). The joiners in the new project, who cast progressive idpol trends as just more liberalism, dissenters from the new project, mostly defecting “right”, and the “Liberal of the Gaps”</p>
      <p>These are the folks who dissent from modern ‘woke’/progressive/idop as illiberal. But at the same time, still cling to detraditionalizing frameworks. Unlike the first group, they don’t accept the idpol prog as also liberal, they don’t deny cancel culture. They don’t defend it. Unlike the second group though, they don’t say ‘enough!’ We’ve broken too much and need to rebuild some of the guardrails of the past.</p>
      <p>Instead they find smaller and smaller parts of the pre-existing order and 50-stalins them. More and more gets blamed on Moloch. Standards of social possibility are lowered and more faith gets pushed into techno libertarian dreams like “betting markets” that will solve all our inefficiencies. A great example exists in <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/webmd-and-the-tragedy-of-legible">SA’s recent defense of Faucci</a>. This post is too long already, so I can’t give it a good critique, so here’s an admittedly hasty deconstruction.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>WebMD is a failure because <em>Moloch</em>… “WebMD is too big, too legitimate, and too canonical to be good.”… “Dr. Anthony Fauci is the WebMD of people.”… We should just be impressed that we even ended up with him… The real solution is betting markets (with no defense or explanation)</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>His whole Zvi tangent is an acknowledgement that social trust can’t scale anymore, but just accepts that as Moloc. His solution is to liberalize more. Never does he double back and say, 'hey maybe WebMD is the result of wild-west projects built on market forces being mistaken for stable, trust-worthy institutions running on ideals more insulated from fickle legal, social, and market pressures'. His extension to Faucci is just more defense of a post-detraditionalized world needing more detraditionalization and even more fickle responses to liberalized market forces.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>