<post>
  <note>Added context.</note>
  <author>mister_ghost</author>
  <date>2021-02-16T18:35:05Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lk8abe/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_15/gno9vxe/</link>
  <title>The Problem of "Thesis-free Reasoning"</title>
  <category>
    <li>knowledge</li>
    <li>media</li>
  </category>
  <context>
    <p>What are people's opinion of the youtube channel "what I've learned"</p>
    <p>The videos hit all of the buttons I would expect a person interested in the truth to hit. He focuses on evidence, he quotes research papers, he gives evolutionary explanations, and he doesn't always seem completely certain.</p>
    <p>However the conclusions he reaches are always semi outlandish and out there. Example of video conclusions.</p>
    <p><a href="youtube.com/watch?v=ilZ_-bSWvsc">how red light can help with depression and skin quality.</a></p>
    <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zbzT00Cyq-g">how tongue posture can improve facial structure.</a></p>
  </context>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I watched <a href="https://youtu.be/amJ-ev8Ial8">this</a>, and though I think the conclusion has some merit, I can pattern-match this to a style of argument that drives me crazy, and is near universal on video essay YouTube. I call it "thesis free reasoning".</p>
      <p>The video doesn't have a point it's trying to make. You could tease one out, but it's not organically centered around supporting a claim, or even really investigating one. What question does this video answer? Supposedly it's "are you getting enough salt", but if the video actually structured itself around answering the question, it would be fairly unpersuasive.</p>
      <p>This style of video is not optimized for supporting a claim. Instead, it optimizes for moments where you think to yourself "That's an interesting point, I've never thought of it like that before". Every 20-30 seconds, your brain registers that it has heard a compelling piece of evidence, and then it's on to the next thing.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Even when I disagree with his conclusions though I tend to feel like I'm more informed.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>As is intended. At the end, you leave with the sense that you have learned something, but if you think about it you will be hard pressed to articulate what it was and how you knew it was true.</p>
      <p>After you watch a video like this, reflect on it for a minute - not a moment, a minute, with a clock if necessary - and ask yourself</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>How would I summarize the main claim of what I just heard?</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>How can I use the evidence or arguments I was presented with to support that claim?</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>and you may find you are confused. Maybe you can't come up with a clear answer to (1), maybe you can but the answer to (2) is "I can't", or maybe once you mentally restructure the video to be an argument you notice glaring holes and contradictions or a lot of extraneous content. If that happens, it's likely that what you saw was the persuasion equivalent of a Dorito: artfully designed to stimulate your "good point" receptors in a way divorced from their actual purpose.</p>
      <p>You would be surprised how much stuff fails this test.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>