<post>
  <author>ZorbaTHut</author>
  <date>2021-02-15T20:18:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lk8abe/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_15/gnki8kp/</link>
  <title>On the capacity of extant automobile AI to peg you for a jaywalker in advance</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So, I think you're underestimating the crazy stuff self-driving cars can do, which I <em>totally understand</em> because almost everyone does. I worked at a self-driving car company for a bit and here's why this is easier than you think.</p>
      <p>First, an SDC has a <em>big</em> sensor suite on the roof. Big is important because it means it picks up everything; on the roof is important because it means it can see over most vehicles. These together mean that in most cases it knows where every vehicle and every pedestrian is within about a hundred meters, and is actively tracking them, and knows their current velocities, and is feeding their body language into a machine-learning system to predict what they're likely to do.</p>
      <p>I've seen examples of an SDC drive up to a busy intersection with dozens of pedestrians waiting to cross, and isolate <em>every single one of them</em> as an independent entity, including future predictions; it highlighted one as "likely jaywalker" and like three seconds later that exact person dashed across the road.</p>
      <p>It's frankly kind of terrifying, but it means that in most cases, there's no situation where an SDC can be driving down a road at 50mph and be taken by surprise by a child running into the road 50 feet ahead. It's already recognized the child, it's already recognized the ball, it picked up on the child's movement ten seconds ago, it's probably already slowed down.</p>
      <p>I admit this all sounds like kind of a copout answer - "oh, well, an SDC wouldn't get in that position because it would be smart enough to avoid it" - but that really is what people are working towards, SDCs that are so good at recognizing what's going on that they <em>aren't taken by surprise</em>.</p>
      <p>(Another good example was an SDC driving along the continuous side of a T-intersection, approaching a corner lot with large bushes; the SDC slowed down for "collision avoidance" and a few seconds later a bike rocketed out of the side road without stopping. On review, it turned out the SDC had been able to pick up the bike through a gap in the bushes ten seconds earlier, then kept rough track of it through the leaves, so it knew that the bike wasn't going to stop and slowed down to give it room.)</p>
      <p>The other issue is that it suggests that the vehicle is incapable of slowing down enough, but <em>is</em> capable of swerving into an oncoming lane. Friction is fungible, more or less; if you've got enough friction to change lanes, you also have enough friction to slow way down. So this becomes less of a question of "hit the kid or run into a truck" and more of a question of "hit the kid really slowly or run into a truck at full speed"; you have to pay for the lane-change velocity delta and the slowdown velocity delta out of the same pool, you can't do both.</p>
      <p>Finally, these AIs are <em>shockingly</em> precise and aware. There's one rather infamous case where an SDC was driving along cheerfully and another car started lane-changing into it. Instead of moving to the next lane to avoid a collision, it started slowing down. The safety driver hit the emergency disengage and lane-changed to avoid a collision . . . running right into a bicyclist who was in that lane that the safety driver hadn't seen. Later analysis determined that "slow down to avoid the car" would have caused the car to miss by about half a foot - the safety driver actually caused an unnecessary accident (but wasn't penalized for it, if I recall.) In the case where a kid is running across the street it's entirely possible it can just dodge the kid - it takes a lot of velocity delta to change lanes, but a lot less to shift a foot or two in one direction or another.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I've been faced with a (lower-stakes) trolley problem myself, in which I was driving up a very icy, steep hill and my vehicle lost traction.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>See, the SDC answer would be "don't go up the hill". If you're faced with a lose-lose scenario, the right solution is never to enter into that scenario in the first place.</p>
      <p>And . . . yeah, that sounds like a copout answer, which, again, I acknowledge, it's like the slimiest answer imaginable :V But it's still a really good answer, insofar as you can accomplish it. If you have to engineer solutions to all scenarios in advance, then preventing that scenario entirely is a much bigger bang for buck.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>