<post>
  <author>CanIHaveASong</author>
  <date>2020-11-17T04:23:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gckuu0p/</link>
  <title>Order, Chaos, and the Creation Story</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="/u/CanIHaveASong">/u/CanIHaveASong</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>it's my perception that most of Christianity has been both over-spiritualized and ... how to say it... interpreted though a completely inappropriate western worldview </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="/u/XantosCell">/u/XantosCell</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Oh man. Now THIS is gonna be the kind of content I like to read! </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="/u/CanIHaveASong">/u/CanIHaveASong</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I've been thinking today, and I think the best place to start would actually be an exposition on the creation story. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Full thread <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/jmhoku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_02/gbop7qu/?context=3">here</a>.</p>
      <p>I have some time tonight, so I thought I'd give it a shot.  I have some things I should make clear first:  I'm not a theologian, and I have only really begun my journey into learning about the original context of Old Testament texts.  That said, I think I can still give you guys a really interesting and potentially useful take on the creation story.  The creation story is our introduction to God and our introduction to man.  I will be omitting the origin of sin from this analysis, as well as a numerological analysis, as I don't want it to get too long.  But taken together, the story of creation and of sin are the introduction to the rest of the Bible.  Understanding what they mean is crucial to understanding the rest of the book.</p>
      <p>I will be mostly interpreting the creation story from a symbolic worldview.  A symbolic worldview is not concerned with what things are, but rather what they mean.  It is not a scientific worldview. However, the creation story was not given to a scientifically literate people, and it isn't meant to be read in that context.  We will try to understand what the text meant to its original readers.  The original readers were more concerned with association, order, hierarchy, “image”, and duality.  This is what we will focus on.  </p>
      <p>Before I get on to the actual analysis, it's important to talk about some of the overarching themes we will encounter.  The first and most important is image.  In a symbolic worldview, an image is a small thing that is a reflection of some greater concept.  An (imperfect) example that might appeal to modern sensibilities is the family.  A family is an image of a country:  individuals banding together toward mutual benefit and goals.  Family is a microcosm of human relationships which reflects the macrocosm of country.  Among symbols, the most important is the order/chaos duality.  Order manifests in smaller related symbols and images like heaven, light, meaning, space, air, land, maleness, and even righthandedness.  Images of chaos are earth, darkness, matter, time, water, femaleness, and lefthandedness.  Right and lefthandedness (which don't come up in the creation story, sadly) are the easiest places to see these symbols still in action in the modern world.  The political right is associated with stability and sameness, while the left is associated with change.  It is important to note here that order is not always good and chaos is not always bad.  Chaos is associated with potential and renewal as well as destruction, and order can be associated with staleness as well as safety and stablitiy.  </p>
      <p>It's also important to note that words do not always have the same definition we use in modern times.  Fish does not mean a “ gill-bearing aquatic craniate animals that lack limbs with digits.“ That is a scientific classification, and the people who were to read this book were not a scientific people.  Fish mostly likely has a more associative meaning, referring to most water creatures.  Likewise, when we encounter words that are heavily symbolic, such as water, we have to realize it may not be referring to H2O, but may possibly be a stand-in for chaos, or any other fluid substance.  </p>
      <p>Now I'll get to it.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>“Heavens” does not mean space, and earth does not mean planet earth.  Earth is more properly understood as matter, and heaven as meaning, or organization.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The earth was without form and void, and darkness was over the face of the deep.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is a clear picture of matter without organization.  Key words here are “without form”, the mention of darkness, and the deep, referring to water.  Darkness and water are both symbols of chaos.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And the spirit of God was hovering over the face of the waters.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I promise I won't take this phrase by phrase the whole time, but these first few are just so very packed with information.  This is a particularly interesting verse.  The “spirit of God” is <a href="https://www.ccog.org/what-gender-is-the-holy-spirit/">feminine</a>, suggesting potential, birth, and creative power. She hovered over the face of the waters, which should be understood as primeval chaos.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And God said, “Let there be light!.” ...And God separated the light from the darkness. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In symbolic analysis, “Let there be light” is a clear reference to the imposition of order upon the primeval chaos of the previous verse.  When God separates light from darkness, we see order being separated from chaos, and a duality that is ubiquitous in the Bible is introduced.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And God made the expanse and separated the waters that were under the expanse from the waters that were above the expanse. And it was so.  And God called the expanse Heaven. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Again, God separates things.  He appears to create space (or at least sensible space) by separating water (or perhaps it's still primeval chaos) from heaven.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And God said, “Let the waters under the heavens be gathered together into one place, and let the dry land appear.” And it was so. God called the dry land Earth, and the waters that were gathered together he called Seas </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Yet again, we see God separate order (land) from chaos (water).  He continues to create space on this day.  I want to draw your attention to God naming things this time.  Naming things is also an imposition of order upon chaos.  It's also worth noting that God creates things by speaking them into being.  God has an idea.  He speaks it, and it manifests.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And God said, “Let the earth sprout vegetation, plants yielding seed, and fruit trees bearing fruit in which is their seed, each according to its kind, on the earth.” And it was so.  </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This creation event happens on the same “day” as separating land from water.  It is the only creation event after the first day that does not have a chaos/order duality.  However, we still see the imposition of order over chaos in this event.  Plants reproduce themselves in kind.  They are the first self-sustaining and self-replicating order.    </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And God said, “Let there be lights in the expanse of the heavens to separate the day from the night. And let them be for signs and for seasons, and for days and years, </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Again, God separates order and chaos.  This time, he does it by separating day and night.  He also appears to create time on this day, or perhaps he organizes time into predictable cycles. Regardless, we see that the primeval chaos of the first verses is further and further removed, and more and more order is imposed upon the universe.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And God said, “Let the waters swarm with swarms of living creatures, and let birds[g] fly above the earth across the expanse of the heavens.” So God created the great sea creatures and every living creature that moves, with which the waters swarm, according to their kinds, and every winged bird according to its kind </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I hate to sound like a broken record, but we see the order/chaos duality here again.  But here it's a bit less order and chaos, and a bit more heaven and earth.  Birds, as creatures of the air, represent heaven (or meaning).  Fish, as creatures that live below the water, represent earth (or matter).  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And God said, “Let the earth bring forth living creatures according to their kinds—livestock and creeping things and beasts of the earth according to their kinds.” And it was so. And God made the beasts of the earth according to their kinds and the livestock according to their kinds, and everything that creeps on the ground according to its kind. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>There is a reason land creatures are divided into two groups:  “Beasts” and creeping things.  It's the heaven/earth duality again.  Beasts that walk upon the earth represent heaven, and creeping things earth.  BTW, this has really interesting implications for the sin story, when you consider the snake.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Then God said, “Let us make man in our image, after our likeness.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>So God created man in his own image,
 in the image of God he created him;
 male and female he created them.</p>
      <p>You are all bored now of of me pointing out the order/chaos and heaven/earth duality, but it's here for the last time in the creation of ordered man and chaotic woman.  However, this passage is most interesting for other things.  What does it mean that God created man in his own image?  It means that man is a “microcosm” or small reflection, of God.  But what is God?  We've learned, over the course of the creation story, a great deal about him.  God is that which imposes order upon chaos.  God creates meaningful space and meaningful things out of matter.  God manifest his ideas on the universe.  God gives things identities (names them).  So, then, this is humanity's role also:  To impose order upon chaos, to give meaning to matter, and to bring our ideas into being.  And indeed, in chapter 2 of the creation story, God gives Adam his first job as an image of God:  Adam is to work the ground, or impose order on nature, just as God before him did in a grander way:  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The Lord God took the man and put him in the garden of Eden to work it and keep it,</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Adam's second job is also a reflection of God's work.  He is to name the animals, to give them identities.  </p>
      <p>(continued in comment below)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>