<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-11-12T16:36:55Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jqrmw5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_09/gc24pdu/</link>
  <title>Judge Instituitions Not One Purpose But On Effects</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>(2/2)</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Why do we make such a (to my mind) simple blunder? I suspect the reason (heh) why we continue to ascribe outright reasons to institutions is because of our deeply held psychological need to see the world in terms of moral agents. While it may be true that Microsoft and the US government aren't good or bad, and don't act for specific reasons, we can't simply think of them in these terms. We need to be able to judge, applaud, and condemn.</p>
      <p>If we really are committed to this kind of moralising (as I suspect we are), I think there are better ways to do it. In short, I think a simple 'cui bono' test can be applied: if this law hadn't been passed, or this institution didn't exist, who would be the winners and who would be the losers? Note that in doing this, we're not reconstructing any intentions: we're simply doing a cost benefit analysis.</p>
      <p>For example, it seems clear to me that if the police didn't exist, the primary losers would be the poor, insofar as the rich are able to afford private measures to protect their property. Insofar as I care about protecting the poor, this provides a moral justification for the existence of the police, regardless of the intentions of the people who founded police forces back in the day or run them in the present. BLM is a trickier case, but I think it's safe to say that Marxism would not be badly set back if BLM hadn't existed (in fact, some anti-idpol socialists would say the opposite). Perhaps BLM has helped black Americans to some extent, and perhaps it's helped the Democrats (or perhaps not). BLM's moral status, then, strikes me as unclear, and contingent upon a deeper empirical analysis than I'm capable of giving here.</p>
      <p>I would note that I think this kind of explanation provides about the best steelman of institutional or structural racism as I can come up with. I've not found many satisfactory justifications of these concepts, but if the claim is simply that "this feature of society disproportionately harms women/racial minorities/gay people" etc., then I think that provides some basis for assessing whether it's a generally benevolent institution or one that aligns with our broader moral commitments. That said, if we adopt this reading of institutional racism etc., then we should be careful not to slip back into the kinds of (to my mind, fallacious) ascriptions of psychological states to those same organisations and institutions, such as calling them 'racist' or 'sexist' in the primary psychological sense of these terms.</p>
      <p>All of which is to say, I think it's wrong-headed and confused to try to analyse the moral status of institutions etc. in terms of 'their intentions' or 'their purpose'. We might do a bit of useful explanatory work that makes reference to certain intentions of the members of the organisations, but this will merely be a small part of a causal-historical analysis of how they came about. If we're concerned to assess whether an organisation, law, institution, etc. is justified or justifiable, we should do so purely on the basis of its effects (and perhaps its structure), and this does not require us to personify it as an individual that acts for reasons or has intentions.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>