<post>
  <author>MajorSomeday</author>
  <date>2020-11-16T21:46:57Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gcji5yd/</link>
  <title>Seeing Your Political Enemies As Human</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A week ago I wrote a couple long-form comments that got buried because it was deep in the thread and posted late.  I was encouraged to repost them as top-level comments here, so if you’ve already seen this, that’s why. </p>
      <p>The context in case it helps:
I personally have made a lot of progress from seeing my political enemies as being morally bankrupt and evil to seeing them as humans and better able to understand their position.  I’m still on the same side as where I started, but my opinions are more nuanced and it makes me feel a lot better about the country as a whole when I’m not thinking that half of it is evil.   I offered as a part of this convo to attempt to write a somewhat less partisan defense of why leftists support BLM.  </p>
      <hr />
      <h1>Part 1</h1>
      <p>I’m gonna break this into two major parts (in two comments because of reddit comment limits).  The first is primarily “How to get into the right mindset to see your political enemies as anything but monsters.”.  The second will be my BLM defense, hopefully written in a way that makes the leftist position understandable.  To be clear, I don’t expect to change anyone’s mind with this.  I’d just like to turn down the temperature of conversation in the country a little.</p>
      <p>Some of this first part is going to make you say, “well, duh, of course.” But even if you know all these things, reading them together, and reading them right before the second part will hopefully have more of an effect.</p>
      <h1>How to get into the right mindset to humanize your political opponents</h1>
      <p>In order for this to work for you the way it worked for me, you really need three things:</p>
      <ol>
        <li> A belief that people are generally good.  Or at least, you believe that it is strongly unlikely that &gt;40% of the nation is actively evil.</li>
        <li> Compassion and Sonder</li>
        <li> Intellectual humility</li>
      </ol>
      <h2>1. People are generally good</h2>
      <p>Without this belief, I don’t see how you’ll have the conviction to stick through this doc, much less actually change your viewpoint.  If you’ve lived a very different life to me, it’s possible you don’t have this belief.     Hopefully you’ve met enough people in your life to realize this intuitively, but I think the only real argument I have for this is: </p>
      <p>Society wouldn’t function at all if a very large percentage of the population were actively trying to hurt each other.  People may be greedy, selfish, narcissistic, and they may not go out of their way to help, but it’s unlikely that a large percentage actively wants to see the people around them suffer.</p>
      <p>If you don’t have this belief, stop here, think about it for a while (preferably avoiding political contexts for your thoughts).  If you’re still not convinced, I don’t think the rest of this doc will help.  That said, I’m happy to try harder to convince you of this — I think it’s important.  Lemme know.</p>
      <h2>2. Compassion and Sonder</h2>
      <p>See here for a description of Sonder: <a href="https://www.dictionaryofobscuresorrows.com/post/23536922667/sonder">https://www.dictionaryofobscuresorrows.com/post/23536922667/sonder</a></p>
      <p>First of all, realize that every one of the people on the opposite side have rich lives.  They go to work, they have loved ones, they’re sad because their baseball team lost, they’re happy that they made a good meal last night but feel guilty that they overate and maybe drank a little too much.  They worry they said the wrong thing, and they’re still embarrassed by the dumb comment they made a few days ago.</p>
      <p>Noone’s life is easy.  It is often the case that if you swapped positions with someone else, one of you would find your life much easier after, and the other would find it harder.  But that feeling would fade — Hedonic adaptation happens to everyone.    (To be extra clear, this applies to most of your political enemies, but mostly doesn’t apply to people undergoing extreme hardship — it’s hard to argue with starvation)  </p>
      <h2>3. Intellectual Humility</h2>
      <p>Understand that you live in a bubble. Given that you’re here and reading this, it is probably a larger, more translucent bubble than most Americans, but it’s still a bubble. This leads to three things: </p>
      <ol>
        <li> At least some of the things that you believe are probably not true</li>
        <li> Some of those falsehoods are probably created by partisan interests. </li>
        <li> Even for the things that are true, the particular facts + narratives that you care about and that you read about, are influenced by your bubble.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>I have no good organization to this section, so I’m going throw some arbitrary stuff that will hopefully contribute to you seeing my point here:</p>
      <ol>
        <li> Most people have similar politics to their parents.  With this, I conclude that most people’s politics are really products of their environment.  Even if you differ from your parents, there’s something that set you on the course you’re on.  Did you really choose that course out of a rational thought process, or were you put on that course due to your environment?</li>
        <li> Relatedly, there was a study that asked people to tie two ropes together that were too far apart for anyone to grab both.  Participants had to come up with as many ways of tying ropes together as they could.  For some of them, they had a researcher bump into the ropes.  This gave those participants the idea of swinging the ropes so that they could reach each of them.  When the researchers asked the participants “how did you come up with that idea?”, very few of them said “Because you bumped into it.” And yet the study shows that that’s exactly how most of the participants came up with the idea.   Are you sure that your belief about your own mental processes is accurate?</li>
        <li> Most people believe that advertising doesn’t work on them.  And yet, companies spend an insane amount of money on advertising.  One of these two groups must be wrong — my bet is that the companies are right.  Assuming the companies are right, why do people believe that advertising doesn’t work?  It’s because they are not aware of their own mental processes around advertising.</li>
        <li> Given that, how sure are you that the things you’re reading are not swaying you in ways that you don’t know about?</li>
        <li> Lots of the things we’re arguing about CAN’T be known for sure.  We’re using a combination of numbers, PLUS intuition and expository writing to guess at what the numbers mean about the world.<br /></li>
      </ol>
      <h1>Being wrong about a fact doesn’t make you evil</h1>
      <p>Hopefully this makes intuitive sense.  If someone has been reading partisan sources their whole life, and doesn’t have the wherewithal to break out of it, I can’t blame them too much.  It’s hard to question your beliefs.</p>
      <h1>Avoid blindly cheering your own side</h1>
      <p>Avoid ‘cheering’ when your side gets a punch in.   Leftist sources publish a lot of “you won’t believe the awful thing Trump said”.  And sometimes they’re right, but lots of times they’re focusing in hard on a little misstep, or taking what he said literally instead of what he meant.  Before this whole process, I would’ve just mentally cheered my team winning, and moved on, even if I didn’t think the clip was that big a deal.  Now, I’m actively annoyed, shake my head, avoid that source a little more, and call out any democratic friends that send it to me.</p>
      <p>You’ve gotta learn to call out your own side too.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>