<post>
  <author>PmMeClassicMemes</author>
  <date>2020-11-13T03:32:47Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jqrmw5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_09/gc4ap70/</link>
  <title>Your Children Need Npt Share Your Genes</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There is a thread below regarding cuckoldry. It has generated many heated responses. Many of these responses rest on an impulse I cannot comprehend - the impulse to ensure your children have your genetic material. </p>
      <p>I am going to argue that people place far too much care on whether or not their children are biologically theirs. </p>
      <p>1) Parent-Child are social relationships, not those of biology. </p>
      <p>A) There are plenty of human societies in which children are raised  communally, or by people other than their parents (Nannies, Grandparents, etc)</p>
      <p>B) Even in mainstream Western society, we acknowledge that adopted children are their parents children. Adopted Children are given full status if you die without a will. Adopted Children aren't seen by courts as lesser children for purposes of making decisions about their custody. If you were to declare that X was not "really" Y's child on the basis of their DNA, everyone would look at you funny. </p>
      <p>2) We don't accept or tolerate biological discrimination in other areas of equivalent socially constructed relations. </p>
      <p>View the following statements :</p>
      <p>A) "I'm not going to go to that dentist - I want my dentist to have brown hair and green eyes like me" </p>
      <p>B) "I would never go to an Asian doctor" </p>
      <p>C) "I couldn't be friends with someone that doesn't share lots of my genetic material" </p>
      <p>Both of these statements are clearly insane. That is because what makes someone a member of a Doctor-Patient relationship is either a medical license or a need for medical care and agreement between the two parties and the acts involved. </p>
      <p>So it goes with parenthood and childhood - if someone many years older than you cares for you from the time you are an infant, they are your parent. </p>
      <p>3) Biological Parenthood doesn't mesh with the social relationships humans prefer. </p>
      <p>A) Plenty of Gay, Lesbian, and Infertile people can't have kids, despite desiring the ability to raise children and being capable parents. </p>
      <p>B) Most people do not put "No Chicks With Huntington's Correa" in their Tinder profiles. </p>
      <p>Yes, I understand fully that people have impulses via evolutionary biology. I'm not here to tell you that cuckolding is good. I'm arguing that people care far too much about having their own biological children. </p>
      <p>Why is it important to maintain a biological connection to your offspring? Why not raise a child that doesn't share your race? </p>
      <p>I don't see the main thrust of my argument as being in favor of women cheating - more in favour of adoption. </p>
      <p>Especially when you consider the Economics involved here - some women have relatively easy pregnancies, and some relatively harder. Some women enjoy being pregnant much more than others. Some men are good people with low-quality sperm. There are easily ways here that via wide-spread 'adoption' of adoption, we can have a society that more efficiently allocates birthing resources.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>