<post>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2020-11-17T07:15:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gcl8fen/</link>
  <title>The True Cost of BLM</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The trade-off is worth it. Given all of the above, the pay-off is extremely large — with even some small changes to how police officers operate, you can have a big effect on the black community. The cost of a few buildings burning just isn’t that high for something as important as this.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Hardly. Please familiarize yourself with a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national/minneapolis-police-shortage-violence-floyd/2020/11/12/642f741a-1a1d-11eb-befb-8864259bd2d8_story.html">few</a> of the follow-up <a href="https://m.startribune.com/amid-sharp-rise-in-minneapolis-shootings-slayings-a-solution-appears-elusive/573079021/">articles</a> came out last week about life in Minneapolis post-BLM. Cops, harassed and demonized, quit the force (during a recession) in unprecedented numbers. Homicides are up 64% year to date. Carjackings went from being so rare they didn’t have a numeric code to 63 over the past 5 weeks. Really sad story about a 72-year-old woman who was beaten, robbed, had her car stolen, and then was alerted that the 3 urban teens (aged 13-15) who had stolen it crashed it into a tree at high speeds and died gruesomely. There’s apparently a CHAZ-style autonomous zone that Mayor Frey is ‘negotiating’ with but unable to control. City council - which voted to ‘defund and dismantle’ MPD in June - now voting to allocate emergency funding to hire temp officers from neighboring communities. Yet they’re still set to cut police budget by ~10% next year. Cop who suffered burns when protestors lit the precinct on fire in May speaks about his PTSD and leaving the force. Vigilantes stepping in as violence soars and proactive policing dwindles, widespread breakdown of social order</p>
      <p>For the record, there was 1 black person killed by police in Minneapolis in all of 2019; <a href="https://minnesota.cbslocal.com/2020/03/02/minneapolis-police-officer-cleared-in-shooting-death-of-mario-benjamin-last-august/">he had just shot his baby mama in front of their kids while high on meth, paralyzing her</a>. There was never actually a problem with policing there, just a critical mass of naive people exploited by racial agitators, and a mayor who fed into their victimhood pathologies</p>
      <p>In NYC, De Blasio <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/nypd-disbands-anticrime-unit-as-city-leaders-debate-1-billion-in-cuts-to-police-11592263500">disbanded NYC's Anti-Crime Unit</a> which targeted illegal guns in response to activist pressure to diminish policing, and predictably enough the city has seen a <a href="https://www.insider.com/murder-shooting-count-up-high-unchartered-waters-new-york-2020-10">massive increase in homicides and shootings</a>, with shooting victims currently seeing a &gt;100% increase over 2019, year to date. Looking with more specificity, we can see that <a href="https://imgur.com/PPADNpr">shootings were completely in line with previous years through May, despite the lockdowns starting in March, and it wasn't until the post-Memorial Day riots and mid-June cuts to policing that shootings spiked dramatically</a>, with deadly results. In 2019, there was 1 single ‘unarmed’ black person killed by police in NYC, and he was shot after <a href="https://bklyner.com/body-camera-footage-released-of-police-involved-shooting-of-kwesi-ashun/">throwing a chair so hard he put an officer in a coma</a></p>
      <p>Hapless Portland mayor Ted Wheeler also acquiesced to the shouted demands of activists that harassed him at his apartment and <a href="https://www.wweek.com/news/2020/06/09/mayor-ted-wheeler-agrees-to-disband-the-portland-police-bureaus-gun-violence-reduction-team/">disbanded the city's Anti-Gun Unit</a>. Once again, as expected, the city saw <a href="https://www.koin.com/news/crime/stats-show-dramatic-jump-in-portland-shootings-during-2020/">a dramatic increase in shootings</a>, with September 2020 seeing a 250% increase in shootings over September 2019. There was 1 black person killed by police in Portland in all of 2019, <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/crime/2019/05/andre-gladen-was-holding-officers-knife-when-shot-and-killed-by-police-grand-jury-testimony-confirms.html">a schizophrenic home invader high on meth who pulled a knife on an officer</a></p>
      <p>Many other such examples of cities torn apart by crime surges abound <a href="https://covid19.counciloncj.org/2020/09/26/impact-report-covid-19-and-crime/">as homicides soared by an apparent 53%</a> across 27 major cities during the anti-police zeitgeist promulgated by #BLM and allies during 2020's summer protests</p>
      <p>Your reasoning seem to radically overstate the costs of ‘racism’ in policing - seemingly on complete assumptions - and to radically understate the empirically measurable destructive costs of the BLM movement. Let's just hope that with this new wave of chaos - unlike <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crime_in_Baltimore">Baltimore</a> and <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/11/13/despite-recent-violence-chicago-far-from-u-s-murder-capital/">St. Louis</a> which found that their 2015 post-BLM surges in homicides had multi-year staying power rocketing them to among <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cities_by_murder_rate">the most deadly cities in the world</a> - this time the destructive activists pushing harmful narratives and policies have the decency and shame to admit fault and get behind efforts that back municipal police in getting crime back under control</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>For the most part, most democrats are making a fairly reasonable decision given the things they’ve seen and read. In fact, most of the non-black democrats are motivated primarily by compassion for their fellow black Americans</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'd disagree that it's <em>reasonable</em> to be fiercely passionate and outspoken about something while remaining completely ignorant about the underlying facts. We live in the Information Age, all of this can be found very easily if anyone is actually interested in statistical realities and not just performative outrage. And the notion that BLM supporters are motivated by compassion - which is hard to reconcile with them making nowhere near the same fuss about the orders of magnitude more black lives lost to intraracial violent crime - assuages me about as much as it does that the Pizzagate shooter was motivated by compassion for child trafficking victims. Or less, rather, given how comparatively little damage he caused</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>