<post>
  <author>Standard_Order</author>
  <date>2020-11-12T21:29:35Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jqrmw5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_09/gc37a0v/</link>
  <title>The Unmaking of John T. Flynn: A Parallel to Greenwald</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>An excerpt from Ron Unz's <em>American Pravda</em> article <a href="https://www.unz.com/runz/american-pravda-our-great-purge-of-the-1940s/">"Our Great Purge of the 1940s"</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Take the case of John T. Flynn, probably unknown today to all but one American in a hundred, if even that. Given my much broader ideological explorations, I had sometimes seen him hailed as an important figure in the Old Right, a founder of the America First Committee, and someone friendly to both Sen. Joseph McCarthy and the John Birch Society, though falsely smeared by his opponents as a proto-fascist or Nazi-sympathizer. This sort of description seemed to form a consistent if somewhat disputed picture in my mind.</p>
        <p>So imagine my surprise at discovering that throughout the 1930s he had been one of the single most influential <em>liberal</em> voices in American society, a writer on economics and politics whose status may have roughly approximated that of Paul Krugman, though with a strong muck-raking tinge. His weekly column in <em>The New Republic</em> allowed him to serve as a lodestar for America’s progressive elites, while his regular appearances in <em>Colliers</em>, an illustrated mass circulation weekly reaching many millions of Americans, provided him a platform comparable to that of an major television personality in the later heyday of network TV.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>He goes on to quantify Flynn's prominence among the liberal intelligentsia, slow turn against the still-developing Enlightened Consensus on American intervention in the Second World War, and ultimate disappearance — deplatformed from both the mainstream media and the history books. He's just one of many significant journalists and public figures, Left Right and Center, who suffered this fate in the 1940s; Unz cites more examples in that article and its more controversial followup, <a href="https://www.unz.com/runz/american-pravda-understanding-world-war-ii/">"Understanding World War II."</a></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I sometimes imagined myself a little like an earnest young Soviet researcher of the 1970s who began digging into the musty files of long-forgotten Kremlin archives and made some stunning discoveries. Trotsky was apparently not the notorious Nazi spy and traitor portrayed in all the textbooks, but instead had been the right-hand man of the sainted Lenin himself during the glorious days of the great Bolshevik Revolution… And who were these other figures—Zinoviev, Kamenev, Bukharin, Rykov—who also spent those early years at the very top of the Communist hierarchy? In history courses, they had barely rated a few mentions, as minor Capitalist agents who were quickly unmasked and paid for their treachery with their lives. How could the great Lenin, father of the Revolution, have been such an idiot to have surrounded himself almost exclusively with traitors and spies?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>We're seeing this exact thing happen to Glenn Greenwald. He's the most significant leftist journalist and commentator of the last decade: a Pulitzer Prize winner, the co-founder of an award-winning publication, a staunch critic of interventionism, and a reliable opponent of right-wing populism in America, Brazil, and elsewhere. But he's been taking principled stands that turn him against the Enlightened Consensus, so there's no room for him at his own publication or in liberals' Twitter feeds. Every time he tells his former fans and advocates in the Democratic Party about the plank in their eye, even if that's what his principles demand, he inches closer to being remembered solely as a Trump defender or forgotten entirely. Matt Taibbi will suffer the same fate. I hope I'm wrong.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>