<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-11-17T02:16:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gckh5ca/</link>
  <title>The Enraging Thought of Student Loan Forgiveness</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>(originally written as a comment reply; I've edited it to fit as a top-level but if it still seems a bit disjointed, that's why)</p>
      <p>Earlier today, I saw <a href="https://twitter.com/DamonLinker/status/1328166615507230720">this tweet</a> getting ratio-ed on Twitter:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I think Dems are wildly underestimating the intensity of anger college loan cancelation is going to provoke. Those with college debt will be thrilled, of course. But lots and lots of people who didn't go to college or who worked to pay off their debts? Gonna be bad.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Predictably, it was followed by a wave of responses like, well, <a href="https://twitter.com/GramsciFag69/status/1328189901624520710">this</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/DennisPerkins5/status/1328378200725090314">this</a>, or <a href="https://twitter.com/jonrosenberg/status/1328186009083924480">this</a>, shrugging off the anger and saying that it's selfish to not want student loan forgiveness because some people already suffered, or a similar argument.</p>
      <p>As one who would be intensely furious, I feel some obligation to explain that rage. And to be clear, it would be rage. I see red just thinking about it, honestly. Really, it's one of the fastest ways to get me worked up, bar none.</p>
      <p>I don't have an ideological aversion to social welfare. I support a robust and universal safety net and enjoy universal public utilities. I <em>do</em> have a massive ideological aversion to student debt forgiveness, such that if Biden signs it into law and Republicans manage to nominate a candidate not in Trump's shadow, I will very likely vote against the Democrats next election off the strength of that single issue.</p>
      <p>The core issue I have with student loan forgiveness is that a lot of people structure their lives and make very real sacrifices to reduce or avoid debt: going to cheap state schools instead of top-tier ones, joining the military, living frugally, skipping college altogether, so forth—things, in short, that can dramatically alter their life paths. Others—including plenty of people who are or will be very well off—throw caution and frugality to the winds, take on large debt loads, and have the university experience of their dreams. These life paths look <em>very, very different.</em> People who choose the first can have later starts to their real careers, less prestigious schools attached to their names and fewer connections from their college experiences, a lot less fun and relaxation during their 20s, so on.</p>
      <p>In other words, it's not that A already suffered and got theirs, while B is suffering. It's that A got their reward (no debt) and B got theirs (meaningful university experience), <em>and now B wants to get A's reward too.</em> It's a pure <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Ant_and_the_Grasshopper">ant and grasshopper</a> story.</p>
      <p>In the same way it excuses the spiraling excesses of "grasshoppers", it excuses the spiraling excesses of universities. They can rest assured that they can let their costs go crazy because student loans will pay for it and then the government will diffuse their costs across everyone. </p>
      <p>I've been attending a cheap online university while working full-time lately, because I actively chose to avoid student loans. I'm paying my own way upfront. Here's a real dilemma I'm facing right now: Do I take out a student loan I'm eligible for but don't need, in case the government will turn it into free money down the line? I won't do it, because I think it's unethical to borrow money you don't intend to pay back, but <strong>a policy that invites people to ask that question is a bad policy.</strong></p>
      <p>Options like income-based repayment and making loans dischargable in bankruptcy <em>avoid all of this</em>. I don't want low-income people to struggle under crushing debt they can never pay off. I don't want the cost of college to spiral and become yet more unaffordable. I don't want people to have to make the tradeoffs I've had to make. But I <em>do</em> want people who got real benefits I missed out on to pay the cost they agreed to pay for those benefits, and I <em>do</em> want universities to confront their spiraling costs directly instead of masking it forever. If the goal is to help poor, struggling people? Great. Give a direct handout to everyone under a certain wealth threshold. Don't select an arbitrary slice of them, along with a slice of much more privileged people, and help only them.</p>
      <p>The core message I'm going for is that "universal" debt forgiveness <em>is not universal.</em> It benefits people who took out student loans at the expense of everyone who didn't take out student loans, privileging a class who are already likely to be privileged and telling the rest to suck it up and be happy for them. As someone whose life has been directly, and drastically, altered by decisions around this issue, I can't put into words how much it would enrage me to see this sort of student debt forgiveness enacted. It would stand as an immense betrayal of social trust, a power play that would give one class of people a direct, arbitrary material advantage at the expense of the rest.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>