<post>
  <author>zergling_Lester</author>
  <date>2020-11-13T17:40:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jqrmw5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_09/gc66eu9/</link>
  <title>When the Radicals are the Core</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I've been noticing a similar thing, that unfortunately on the left the radicals are more like the core than the fringe in terms of the flow of ideology, slogans, etc.</p>
      <p>Consider for example an Anarcho-Capitalist who believes that taxes are theft and should be abolished. He would vote for a Republican governor because at least he would get <em>less</em> taxes, but he would hold about zero ideological sway over said governor who believes that taxes are morally justified by the Constitution and that there's a distinctly nonzero societally optimal amount of taxes that is just somewhat lower than the current one.</p>
      <p>Or consider a Nazi who wants to work in an at-will employment state so that his company could fire all jews and blacks. He will not be able to persuade a generic board of directors who like at-will employment because it allows them to fire low-performing personnel and don't like the profit-hurting race-based approach the least bit.</p>
      <p>So on the right there's this huge moderate crowd with its own beliefs, own reasons for wanting things, own moral justifications, own arguments and accepted kinds of arguments, they own their own ideology. And there's all that fringe that hitch their wagons to it and try to influence or recruit more impressionable members but that's about it.</p>
      <p>On the left on the other hand it seems to me that moderates run almost exclusively on tempered down (or "sanewashed") ideology produced by the radicals. Liberal feminists repeat that "gender is a social construct" which actually has particular implications, economically left people might try to impress friends with a claim that there's no ethical consumption under capitalism, and so on. As the linked OP has noted, there's a general meta-shape of arguments, rooted in conflict theory and mostly based on pointing out unfairness and claiming that everyone who disagrees about fixing it is evil.</p>
      <p>And the problem with that is that moderates don't really have counter-arguments against the "fringe". The best they can do is to appeal to common sense, say that this is going too far, and anyway conservatives would not allow us to. Because all substantive counter-arguments are what those evil people say. This is worrying because "common sense" and "this is going too far" cannot hold in the long run, slippery slope is not a fallacy if there is a slope and no railings to stop the slipping.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>