<post>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2021-04-26T22:38:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/myr3n7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_26_2021/gvzh9wf/</link>
  <title>"Why do they have horns, hooves, claws, sharp teeth, so good eyes and ears, etc. etc.? What use would they be if we eliminate the potential for "bad" stuff happening, if any animal gets to live in safety to an equal degree? The whole animal makes no sense under such circumstances!"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>To me this seems deeply deeply misguided on a fundamental level. Suffering is not something built into the fabric of the universe. It's neural firing patterns involved in learning and adjusting behavior and for fight-or-flight. Negative reward feels bad, this is tautological.</p>
      <p>Animals freak out and get a high heart rate and dilated pupils so they can more easily gtfo of the situation they are in. This <em>is</em> suffering and pain and stress and fear. It's not some kind of floating "holy ghost" that you can eliminate from the natural world. Any feedback from the environment which gets interpreted as "don't do this" will feel negative. Animals that don't learn from such signals die out.</p>
      <p>Happy hormones are not inherently happier than stress hormones. They are just "neutral" molecules just with different shape. The kind of hormone that binds to the receptor with initiates sweating and higher heart rate etc. "is" the "bad" one, but it's only bad because we know that sweating and freaking out means it's time to run from bad stuff like a hungry lion, and the hungry lion's danger is the actually bad thing.</p>
      <p>Animals evolved these responses while evolving together with all these dangerous circumstances and the various ways of possibilities to die. The ones that did not have a way to sense such danger or their response was not strong enough died more easily. So the animals alive today are sensitive to the potential of looming danger and have the capacity to remember close encounters.</p>
      <p>Sure, in some cases pain and suffering present themselves without reason and not in response to anything real. It's one thing to feel pain on the hot stove so we can avoid burning our flesh, and it's another thing to live with chronic pain in the back where it's useless as a warning message as there's nothing to be done in response.</p>
      <p>But this article is talking about the literal central, default function of pain and suffering in the wild, literally the function it was evolved for. To guide behavior in the wild, in nature. This is pain's and suffering's primal nature of existence, right there in the wild, not in some abstract moral universe-fabric. This is what suffering <em>is</em>.</p>
      <p>If you eliminate this, something else will "tell" animals how to behave (because those that can avoid bad stuff somehow will reproduce more), and then <em>that</em> thing will become suffering. Suffering is just whatever tells you what to avoid.</p>
      <p>It's kind of like the euphemism treadmill. It's not the word, but what it signifies. It's not the neural pattern or the chemical that expresses suffering but the fact that some outcomes are worse for survival than others and detecting which is which and which is more likely has benefits for survival and reproduction.</p>
      <p>Animals are survival machines and suffering is but one feature of that machine. How can these people glance at an animal and not see what these things are. Why do they have horns, hooves, claws, sharp teeth, so good eyes and ears, etc. etc.? What use would they be if we eliminate the potential for "bad" stuff happening, if any animal gets to live in safety to an equal degree? The whole animal makes no sense under such circumstances!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>