<post>
  <author>thecanadianzoomer</author>
  <date>2021-04-23T19:19:26Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mtuhyd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_19_2021/gvlmwmy/</link>
  <title>"Our task is to replace *Wokeism* with something new, and the [alt-right] is in my view the only sphere that actually understands and appreciates that task."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Yes, the AR is fundamentally identarian. But that's a feature of the AR and not a bug. Wokeism has proven that individualism can't resist identitarian forces from acquiring power and using it to further group interests. The AR fundamentally understands this where nobody else outside the Woke does.</p>
      <p>Other than that your points are:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>It's not productive or healthy to hate an entire class of people.</li>
        <li>Don't define your ideology by resentment.</li>
        <li>Don't become defined by what you oppose.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>As someone who agrees with the descriptive claims made by the AR, I wholeheartedly agree with all your points there and I think this is very important advice for anyone who is red-pilled. But none of those points even attempt to challenge the world view of the AR:</p>
      <p>If Wokeism doesn't make people happy, why has it been codified in cultural and intellectual life? </p>
      <p>The AR has the only coherent explanation for this: the elites with influence over these core institutions in intellectual and cultural life have established Wokeism in order to to advance their interests. Accepting that truism, you only have to zoom in to those institutions, like Hollywood or academia, and ask "Why are the elites in these institutions promoting this ideology? Who does this ideology serve?" Answering those questions is tantamount to taking the red pill. </p>
      <p>Also, the AR is not just about resenting the classes of people at the helm of Wokeism. The AR understands that Wokeism and the contributions of certain groups to Wokeism are just symptoms of a broader problem: the root cause is liberalism itself.</p>
      <p>Conservatives, paleo-cons, or other high priests of liberalism will complain that Wokeism is a corruption or subversion of liberalism. But the AR understand that Wokeism is a logical extension and evolution of liberalism. You can't wind back the clock on human consciousness. It moves forward, it can't be rewound to the 1950s or whatever liberal bastion is imagined by conservatives. The root cause is liberal ideology. Wokeism and cultural subversion by certain groups are authentic expressions of liberalism and only <em>symptoms</em> of its failure.</p>
      <p>This gets to why being red-pilled can be depressing, and I think that mechanism is very different from Wokeism. From the perspective of the AR, Wokeism is a cult that worships the ugly, the weak, the degenerate, the dysgenic, and it most of all worships lies. I agree with that perspective, and I don't think it's a mystery why worshiping those things makes you unhappy. But it is a hegemonic ideology, so the masses are influenced by the power of conformity.  </p>
      <p>The red pill on the other hand offers the complete opposite of this. It offers isolation from 'polite society' and being recognized will earn you very, very low status. It even isolates you from the vast majority of opposition to Wokeism that doesn't understand how deep the rabbit hole goes. Being isolated is not very fun. From my perspective, the red pill is alternatively depressing and invigorating. Depressing because I don't like being isolated or threatened with ostracization, but invigorating because it gives you an appreciation for challenges at hand. </p>
      <p>Imagine the Founding Fathers of America deal with the weight of replacing the political, cultural, and spiritual tradition of the Monarchy with a new paradigm. Our task is to replace <em>Wokeism</em> with something new, and the AR is in my view the only sphere that actually understands and appreciates that task. That clarity is invigorating, and Wokeism is a far more obvious enemy than the traditional Monarchy.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>