<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-06-26T23:54:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/o4ooc7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_21_2021/h35qyc6/</link>
  <title>Tesla and a Blue Chip Bubble</title>
  <category>
    <li>economics</li>
    <li>moloch</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Tesla’s valuation isn’t going to collapse until the current asset pricing bubble bursts or (less likely) deflates. Unlike the below poster, I think this is true even if Elon Musk dies suddenly, in that I think you would probably see a 20-30% drop, but not the 90%+ to a more reasonable valuation.</p>
      <p>The reason Tesla is overhyped is because it consolidates the locus of the present boom, which began as a tech boom (that spread into equities and then almost all asset classes in general from around 2017), the basis for which is the idea of a <strong>‘fourth industrial revolution’</strong> that slowly became common around fund managers and other investors from around 2013-2014 onwards - though the name itself was coined in 2015. (It is not QE or cheap money, which contributed to the scale of the issue, but don’t themselves trigger speculative bubbles.)</p>
      <p>The fourth industrial revolution stuff, which is actually pretty prophetic, followed a lot of big macro thinking about booms and busts after 2009 commissioned of economists by major governments, businesses and policy institutes/think tanks between 2010 and 2014 or so. The big question was effectively ‘what does recovery look like?’ - what would characterize the next economic cycle?</p>
      <p>The argument goes something like this: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Mass automation will eventually render the bulk of the population either unemployed or non-reliant on labor for the majority of their income, at least during a transition period. But the vast infrastructure required - physically and digitally - coupled with ‘green infrastructure’ due to the impetus to do something about climate change, will lead to one last huge employment and economic boom <em>before</em> this happens. The role of governments and central banks in creating fiscal and monetary policy should be to facilitate and accelerate this transition. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>If you go back to 2015-2016, a lot of the research predicted that this boom would probably take place in the early-mid 2020s, possibly after a recession in the late 2010s after QE was tapered (which the Fed ended up chickening out of in 2018). But asset managers, having internalized this and adapted to a low rate, high change environment in which survival against algorithms, index funds and other people who didn’t take 2 and 20, decided to be a step ahead of the game.</p>
      <p>Tech is low risk because it almost always seems to do OK. Even legacy tech businesses like IBM, SAP and Oracle have still done well. Risks were perceived to be low, potential profits high. Money was funneled in, driving a cycle of slowly rising valuations. Numbers got better as big tech started employing people actually familiar with business to drive up margins and deliver the kind of profitability of which people had previously been skeptical. Multiples climbed, slowly but surely, year after year. In venture capital, the gold rush accelerated, with a new (or rather rediscovered) form of money creation - VCs buying in at absurd valuations to hit the magic Unicorn figure so a startup can go public at an even higher valuation, the VC exiting much richer - becoming ever more popular.</p>
      <p>By the time that people started seriously asking why even boring, blue chip businesses in boring, low growth industries that were maybe making 30% more money than they had been in 2007 (at similar margins) were trading at four or five times the valuation they were at the peak of the last economic cycle, it was too late. Even though the bubble hadn’t been built on cheap money, markets had become addicted to it in the process, as had governments. The colossal pile of corporate debt accumulated to fund attempted growth in a time of unprecedented share price gains (mainly to drive executive compensation) would become unserviceable in a higher rate environment. Stress testing banks meant little if refinancing debt in an even medium rate environment would fell a sizeable number of major corporations, let alone countless smaller businesses. And a sudden venture capital pullback would be tough for all those new businesses, youth unemployment and whatever.</p>
      <p>Letting things play out with rising inflation and maintained low rates was surely the best option. In any case, isn’t automation and big tech deflationary? Things should cancel out somewhere.</p>
      <p>The problem (assuming the plan works) is that even though the Fed won’t burst the bubble, that doesn’t mean it can’t collapse on its own. Plenty of railroad-driven market crashes in the 19th century weren’t spurred by increases in borrowing costs or even bank failures. Often it was little things, entirely trivial things. Sentiment is a beast. A single big tech hugely missing earnings estimates in a single quarter could be all it takes.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>