<post>
  <author>dnkndnts</author>
  <date>2020-06-06T23:31:58Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/ft7mtax/</link>
  <title>The Procrustean Enlightenment and the Shift from Fetishism to Uniformitarianism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think the most fundamental change that came from the enlightenment was a shift from fetishism to uniformitarianism. In older modes of thought, stuff had "special essence" based on its connection with mythological events: the Sword of Charlemagne, a Piece of the True Cross, the Shroud of Turin, the spot where Mohammad ascended into heaven on a winged unicorn, the bread and wine which are transformed into the Body and Blood of Christ, etc. You can still see this kind of thinking alive and well in most fantasy literature and video games, where there's worthless "common" items and super special powerful items like Thunderfury, Blessed Blade of the Windseeker. This extended to people groups as well: we are the Chosen People. We are the Elect. Our planet is at the center of the universe - the apple of the divine eye.</p>
      <p>All of this is fundamentally contrasted with the uniformitarian worldview: the common sword is not in any way inferior to Thunderfury, Blessed Blade of the Windseeker, and in fact is probably better, given that engineering knowledge tends to accumulate over time. The Piece of the True Cross is just a piece of wood, the Shroud of Turin a piece of cloth, and the bread and wine are no different than the bread and wine you can buy at your local Walmart. Our planet is not, in fact, the center of the universe, but orbits the sun just like all the other planets, and our sun is merely a star, just like all the other stars. There are no Chosen People and there is no Manifest Destiny.</p>
      <p>I think this shift in thinking has far-reaching social consequences, from Locke rejecting the divine right of monarchs in favor of social contract democracy to what we see today with racism and sexism being cardinal sins.</p>
      <p>My skepticism in all this is that I think somewhere in here we've been a bit <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Procrustes">Procrustean</a> with our model: we've conflated our confidence in this model for the physical world with a zeal to make the social world fit that same model. Everyone <em>must</em> be equal because our model said so, so if they're not equal, then we need to get out the saws and stretchers and make it fit.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>