<post>
  <author>dnkndnts</author>
  <date>2020-06-07T18:37:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/ftaia8x/</link>
  <title>The Conservative Response to Radical Feminism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>My most memorable encounter with feminism was in an obscure Damore interview back in the day (which I can't for the life of me find now, and Reddit's search is too shitty for me to find my own past links to it) with a feminist academic in one of the Nordic countries. It struck me because it was the antithesis of the noisy, stupid sirening you hear on mainstream sources - this woman was well-educated, thoughtful, and patient, and yet she was advocating positions I deeply disagree with. If she were a poster here, she'd definitely be considered a quality contributor.</p>
      <p>Suffice it to say that yes, I do think that the radfem perception of male behavior is more correct than we like to admit. Despite everyone blaming infidelity on women, somehow in homosexual relationships, lesbians are almost universally long-term monogamous, while male homosexuality is, well... if your relationship manages to last a month, you're doing pretty well. Men really are in it for the sex, and women simply aren't, and when you put these two together, it does get a bit ugly. As someone whose bulk of sexual experience is homosexual, I will admit that hetero relations and pornography often do appear downright rape-y to me, much in the way radfems describe. Even the most difficult, pie-in-the-sky platonic bottoms are nothing compared to the average woman.</p>
      <p>Further, I freely concede that the conservative prescription for women is indeed to have babies and rear children. That's not to say that everything else is forbidden, or that every single woman should be legally mandated to engage in fertility rites, but still, as a whole, yes, the conservative western paradigm is for women to have children and to be much more directly involved in rearing them than men. And I can see why radfems are annoyed by this: being pregnant and rearing children is an enormous investment, and as much as we all like to pretend it doesn't impact your career because it's legally forbidden for it to, let's be real, it absolutely does.</p>
      <p>So yes, I at least understand where radfems are coming from. Like you say, I think their diagnosis of the problem is not unfounded (although I will say it is biased - conservatism places heavy expectations on males, too, like the fact that if there's a war, it's the boys that are going to be sent to into the meat grinder while the girls get to stay back where it's safe.)</p>
      <p>And now for the problem. When you start from a fairness-based, Rawlsian-style view, I think there is a branch of feminism that makes a lot of philosophical sense. But life isn't run in a nice little computerized simulation built on Rawlsian principles. The actual foundation of life is adaptation due to natural selection, and it is by the Darwinian standard that societies are ultimately judged, <em>not</em> the Rawlsian fictions we've dreamed up. When you scrap Rawls and instead craft your philosophy on a Darwinian foundation, I think much of what at first seemed vestigial tradition is now not so negotiable after all. It does in fact matter whether your beauty standard says a good breakfast routine is an egg sandwich and running for 30 minutes as opposed to eating a bag of cheetos and washing it down with Mountain Dew. "Big and beautiful!" is not simply an alternative viewpoint; it's objectively wrong for humans in our current state. Similarly, the decision to assign women the role of bearing and rearing children is not arbitrary: unfortunately, only one of the two sexes is capable of birthing children, so a sustainable society <em>must</em> assign this role to that sex or it will simply be replaced with a society that does.</p>
      <p>That's not to say there isn't slack in the system - obviously it's not going to be the end of the world if you eat a cheeto - but there is none-the-less an overall shape to which sustainable society must more-or-less conform, and these fairness-driven philosophical formalisms heavily run afoul of those bounds. Nor is it to say that constraints and optimization are the same thing (I always get replies with "so u think we should become zerg and all have 50 children each?", which demonstrates like a 3rd-grade understanding of evolution) - provided you're sustainable, it makes little difference to Darwin whether you want to spend your resources optimizing for singing church hymns or colorful tail feathers or creating mathematical models of the universe.</p>
      <p>So in conclusion, I understand the radfem arguments derived from fairness formalisms, and to some extent even sympathize with them (it's not like my penchant for cute guys isn't better served under their framework!). And I think many who would bother to consider the Darwinian argument here, after squirming around a little, would admit there is a peremptory quality to it that just isn't there with Rawls, and the reaction I often get is "I get it, I just... choose the other thing anyway, because that's what I want."</p>
      <p>Fair enough. We were always told the path to eternal life would be taken by few.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>