<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-06-08T17:49:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gysmxy/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_08_2020/fte2cn7/</link>
  <title>How to Dive Into the Sociology of Philosophy</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is such a great question and a really admirable thing to be asking. The really key thing is getting sources that will tell you what arguments are <em>actually about</em> and what the real factions and agendas are. Comparison: imagine if you wanted to understand the abortion debate in the US, and someone gave a list of arguments for and against legalising abortion, ranging from harm reduction to personhood etc.. You might in theory understand the debate but you wouldn't understand how it actually functioned. To understand <em>that</em>, you'd need to get into red tribe/blue tribe, judicial activism, the sexual revolution, broader trends of religion vs secularism in US history, etc..</p>
      <p>Ideally you want similar insights about the big debates in contemporary philosophy, including the sociology of the debate. How do the ideas fit together? What's the big picture? What are the underlying worries that motivate opposition to this idea? And that's really hard to write down in a research paper, because it's inevitably interpretative and tendentious and in some cases borderline gossipy (e.g., "idea X is really overhyped and only took off because it started in Oxford at a time when they had no other good philosophers of mind and needed something to compete with exciting work of B that were coming out of Harvard"). It's the kind of stuff experienced philosophers will discuss over a few beers or if you're lucky in their office hours.</p>
      <p>Anyway - can you get this outside of academia? I think the answer is yes, although it's obviously a bit trickier. One good option is to listen to philosophy podcasts with academic philosophers talking to one another. They won't get into the really gossipy stuff or say anything too controversial ("field X has been in a state of continuous degeneration since the 80s" is the kind of insight you'll only get three beers deep) but the way they argue and talk will give you a good sense of the real points at issue, as well as modelling good high level philosophical dialectic. In this regard, I REALLY recommend <em>In Our Time</em>, a BBC radio show that's been running for 20+ years. I think it's the best radio show ever made without question. Format is basically three top academics providing a high level introduction to a subject in science, philosophy, history, religion, or art. They have thousands of episodes at this point. The philosophy section is <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p01f0vzr">here</a>. One reason it's so good - and much better than most textbooks - is that the chair, Melvyn Bragg, is <em>great</em> at asking difficult questions and forcing the academics to be direct.</p>
      <p>Otherwise, I think there are a few really good high level introductory textbooks (~first year graduate level) that will boil down debates for you with a bit of the history and will help you identify the deep fault lines in arguments, rather than just going through argument A, argument B, etc. as per regular textbooks. Again, they won't be too brutal, but the better ones can give you glimpses into the 'sociology of philosophy' which is where a lot of the real wisdom and insights lie. With this in mind, I can recommend is Peter Godfrey-Smith's <a href="https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/T/bo3622037.html">Theory and Reality</a>, which is the best advanced introduction to philosophy of science ever written and one of the best high level introductory textbooks in all of philosophy. Another - slightly less good but still great - is Botterill and Carruthers' <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/philosophy-of-psychology/7F301722FC97CAA0440D84E1B1D776FD">The Philosophy of Psychology</a>. Again, it actually helps you understand what's really going on in the debate rather than just the surface level arguments out there. Oh, and Andy Clark's <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/mindware-9780199828159?cc=gb&amp;lang=en&amp;">Mindware</a> is a solid introduction to Philosophy of Cognitive Science, though I haven't read it for a decade and so much has happened since it was published that I fear it might be a bit out of date. But a very solid book.</p>
      <p>There aren't that many books like this, though, and a lot of so called 'advanced introductions will just drown in you in excessive detail without getting to the gritty fun kernels in the debates. So ideally look for recommendations like these from people still in philosophy academia. Good luck and let me know if I can give any further assistance!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>