<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-06-07T14:42:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/ft9sih7/</link>
  <title>A Sex-Positive Rejection of the RadFem Narrative</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Fantastic post - reflective, thorough, and persuasive; I find myself feeling more sympathetic to the RadFems than ever before. Here are the two main reasons I still find myself unsympathetic to radfems, however - any clarifications appreciated.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(1) What makes sex bad?</strong> A lot of the time I get the sense that radfems regard <em>sexual use by men</em> as a terminal bad for women, perhaps indeed <em>THE</em> terminal biggest bad of all, where this is some kind of conceptual self-evident truth. But at other times, it sounds like a story rooted in a broader empirical story involving well-being: being used by men for sex (especially gross older men) is just <em>as it turns out</em> hugely bad for women's well-being.</p>
      <p>The first story just doesn't pass a basic philosophical smell-test for me. It sounds like a inverse caricature of Red Pill dude who basically says that thriving as a male means having as much sex as possible. I want to ask, yeah, but why? Why should <em>that</em> be my terminal good or my terminal bad? What if I decide I want to be a monk? Or what if I as a woman decide I really get off on the idea of being used? Am I making some kind of <em>logical</em> or <em>conceptual</em> mistake? That's crazy!</p>
      <p>The second story I'm much more open to, since I'm a consequentialist at least five out of every seven days a week, and I do actually worry about the effects of e.g. porn and online dating on our sexual mindsets, especially among the young. The problem is making this case persuasively requires getting into really detailed empirical work, which is a tendency that I find surprisingly absent among the few rad fems I've read; e.g., I taught a philosophy class on gender and love and read <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Only_Words_(book">some Catharine McKinnon</a>) at several friends' urging. I was pretty shocked - the book consisted of lots of lurid almost fetishistic anecdotes about male use of female bodies and strong rhetorical appeals to outrage and action, but at no point did she sit down to (for example) do a meta-analysis of studies looking at the causal relationship between porn use and sexual assault or promiscuity and well-being, which is what I'd need to see to be convinced that pornography or casual sex was really harmful for women. Meanwhile the pro-sex left is <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2013/10/06/books/review/perv-by-jesse-bering.html">really good at making the empirical arguments</a> (or at least looking like that's what it's doing).</p>
      <p>My hunch here is that most radfems aren't actually operating from a harm-based ethical playbook, and instead are going for the former option - certain things are just objectively bad for women even if all the evidence says they're otherwise well-adjusted and happy. Which basically makes them philosophical Romantics with a different value system from me, and all I can do is shrug.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(2) False consciousness is simply too corrosive an ideological superweapon to be used responsibly.</strong> A surprisingly large number of women I know are actually super into casual sex. To be crude about it, I think male sexual appetite is something like a bell curve (heh) while female sexual appetite is more like a power law distribution - 20% of women seem to be horny as fuck and 80% significantly less horny on average than the median male (I realise that's the exact opposite story from the one you get looking at average number of sexual partners by gender - but the amount of sex we have isn't just a function of how horny we are, alas). In any case, that's just my bullshit anecdotal reflection, so let's move on. The point is that among the women I've known who are <em>really</em> into casual sex, I've seen a few different motives. Three quick cases based on real people, slightly blurred for privacy -</p>
      <p>(a) One woman I briefly dated - call her Emma - seemed to be basically genitally fixated. She had a huge collection of sex toys, an incredible sexual appetite, and would ask me to perform oral on her even when she wasn't seemingly horny but just bored. She had lost her virginity at 13 to her 15 year old boyfriend, spent her teens having quite a lot of sex including fucking several TAs and professors at university, and on her gap year after university made an active point of trying to fuck at least one guy from every country she visited. She masturbated to porn daily. Surprisingly she's now happily married, and to a very good looking guy - I guess she must have finally found someone who can keep up with her, because based on our brief dating history I think she might have had a seizure if she went 24 hours without an orgasm.</p>
      <p>(b) Another woman I know - call her Becka - spent her teens fucking a bunch of surprisingly famous older male musicians. She seems to have enjoyed it well enough (she certainly looked happy and excited when she told me she'd just fucked the drummer of &lt;redacted&gt;), and I think the web of connections she built up through this was probably a factor in the sweet job she got after university for a top music magazine. Though only her therapist knows for sure, I think the sex was overall pretty liberating for her - she'd always been a bit of a bullied weird kid at school and suddenly around 16, 17 when she started with the groupie lifestyle she became incredibly cool and everyone was hitting her up for backstage passes (uh, are we still doing phrasing?).</p>
      <p>(c) Lastly, a very good friend of mine, Pam - a young woman, early 20s, with a successful modelling career. She has her pick of guys. Lives in New York. Finds herself totally unattracted to younger men. Every serious boyfriend of hers has been at least late 30s, often with a beer belly. They're always very smart professionals at the top of their game though. I've suggested she date people her own age and she basically rolls her eyes and says they're a bunch of lame fuckboys who think they're edgy because they read Bukowski. She wants a real man who's <em>seen shit</em> and actually has written or accomplished something more impressive than a senior thesis.</p>
      <p>All of these women are acting in ways that seem to reflect genuine agency yet which are at least <em>prima facie</em> the kind of sexual behaviour that a radfem might say is bad for them. So are these cases of false consciousness? If so, which of them? I've yet to find a satisfactory tractable answer to this. When I've asked it, I usually get a response like "it's false consciousness if they're acting on the basis of internalised patriarchal structures", which makes me want to roll my eyes and say, "look, numbnuts, I'm not just looking for a theoretical reframing here, I'm asking for an actual testable procedure we can use to tell in any individual case." And I've never gotten anywhere. I don't doubt that false consciousness exists in some sense (people <em>can</em> be tricked or brainwashed into acting against their own interests), but it's really fucking dicey to assign it on any individual occasion, because it cuts directly against autonomy and agency. At the very least, before diagnosing someone with false consciousness I'd want damn good justification for doing so, a much better one than "my abstract theory says that actions like yours are bad for &lt;abstract theoretical reasons&gt; so you're clearly not acting in your own interests."</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>