<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-06-08T01:19:37Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/ftbpenl/</link>
  <title>When Did Collective Achievement Fail in the USA?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Modern zeitgeist is actively hostile to the notion of constructive work with things, as opposed to "community organizing", "healing", "equity" or some such; perhaps because successful constructive work invalidates some of its core political premises, which amount to necessity of redistribution, just like technological progress obsoletes the labor theory of value. If you can increase prosperity for everyone, it's suddenly not so clear that we need to hate our richest and most productive; and not so easy to hide that material demands are obfuscating social status needs.<br />
I don't feel like saying much on this topic, but it's also worth asking why the billionaire the Twitter-Left hates most vocally is Elon Musk. By all rights he should be among the most likeable ones: he's self-made, down-to-earth, his enterprises are visionary and cartoonishly easy to understand, he claims that his goal is making human civilization interplanetary! What a shining testament to our way of life that would have been! Now compare this to, uhh... Larry Page? Zuckerberg? Bezos? Walton? What the hell do they even do with all their money? (Actually Bezos and Zuck are more than money bags, but that's not very well known.) But it's okay because they're supposed to be parasites in the progressive narrative; they're not visibly damaging it.<br />
When I was a kid, I sometimes asked myself why Abramovich is so damn boring; with his resources he could afford more fun stuff than yachts, British real estate and soccer clubs. So when Musk became well-known, in my eyes he was less an Iron Man and more an "oligarch done right". And some people, mainly tech geeks, still do think like this. But... The rest are yearning for some blemish, tearing into his dumbass inebriated tweets, <em>celebrating</em> every failure of SpaceX, savoring some tenuous nonsense about him being "born into wealth and connections" and profiting off slaves dying in an emerald mine, chasing out "real SpaceX founders"...  It is unbelievable how they recoil when corrected. For them, it is of vital importance that Musk's projects are illegitimate, a cover for exploitation, further evidence against the system.<br />
Let's not get started on Gates's philantropy.  </p>
      <p>I consider myself to belong to a civilization which dreams to build, to improve, to transcend and to get out of its cradle. When Americans got to the Moon, it was a victory of the same civilization, despite my immediate tribe and their being mortal enemies at the moment. I think that my species has "the great birthright we were given as builders of this world and builders of countless more to come" -- and this quote of a crank Alex Jones resonates with something deep in me. As do words of <a href="https://a16z.com/2020/04/18/its-time-to-build/">Mark Andreessen</a>, and it's trivially easy to seduce me with Thiel's futuristic soapboxing. This idea of substantial progress in our collective mastery over space and matter is so intrinsically valuable to me, that I would accept major collateral damage in return for its realization.  </p>
      <p>And I felt that so strongly, it was hard for me to understand that for many people it's just entirely worthless; it might have negative worth for them, even. They feel no connection to this great birthright, at best it bores them and at worst they feel excluded or insulted by it. For them, redeeming the world implies not transcendence but some status relitigation, and in practical terms it's about half the time about revenge.  </p>
      <p>I'm not sure what happened. But to be cynical, it's got something to do with ruling classes' failure to sell the public this notion of collective achievement, the feeling that everyone has a stake in the glorious future. In USSR, it failed along with the rest of Soviet ideology. When did it start to fail in USA?<br />
Maybe not so long ago.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>