<post>
  <author>qualia_of_mercy</author>
  <date>2020-06-09T03:45:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gysmxy/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_08_2020/ftfx1ya/</link>
  <title>How the CIA Made Polio Cool Again</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>(I posted about this in another place, but perhaps egotistically think it's worth bringing up here too.)</p>
      <p>So once upon a time while we were trying to track down Osama bin Laden, <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/news/2015/02/150225-polio-pakistan-vaccination-virus-health/">the CIA took advantage of an ongoing polio vaccination program</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In the spring of 2010, the U.S. Central Intelligence Agency's (CIA) search for bin Laden began to focus on a certain villa in Abbottabad, a garrison town in the Himalayan foothills of Pakistan. A mystery man was shuttered away on the villa's top floor. CIA agents suspected it might be bin Laden, but they needed to be sure before launching a raid. So they devised an imaginative plan to identify him.</p>
        <p>Operatives would hire a Pakistani doctor and nurses to conduct a door-to-door hepatitis B vaccination campaign in the neighborhood. After the children who lived at the villa were immunized, DNA from the used syringes would be analyzed to determine whether they were related to bin Laden.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>When this was inevitably discovered (as nobody in our government can keep their damn mouths shut) the result is that from that point on doctors trying to stamp out polio in Pakistan and elsewhere were believed to be associated with the CIA and found themselves getting chased out or even attacked. And so polio has had a resurgence in these countries when it was on the verge of being wiped out. The campaign to eradicate polio was collateral damage of people who thought their political objectives -- even noble objectives like bringing Osama bin Laden to justice like he deserved -- stood above maintaining the trust in medical authorities required to eliminate a deadly virus.</p>
      <p>The parallel should be obvious, except even worse since the doctors in Pakistan were mostly sincere people being manipulated by the CIA. In the case of these protest marches, the doctors and the CIA are the same people.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>