<post>
  <author>Stefferi</author>
  <date>2020-06-07T08:35:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/ft92izb/</link>
  <title>There are TERFs and There are "TERFs"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's obvious that there are TERFs and then there are "TERFS". The first category's pretty straightforward, flowing from the general radical feminist idea: there's two classes, men and women, men oppress women, these categories are set at birth, and they see what they call 'TRAs' as people who are fighting a battle to put dangerous men in women's spaces, and so on. The second category's more... incidental.</p>
      <p>Put it this way. During the recent years, there has obviously been a growing number of women who have, for whatever reason, become strongly anti-trans, ie. not just some vague distate against trans people but a conviction that the package of issues generally called 'trans rights' is dangerous to them, their daughters and the society, and a desire to fight against it. Fighting an ideological battle generally requires finding a movement, both for the chance of actually affecting things but also to have people who you can socialize with and go "I'm not the one going crazy, the society is, right?" and so on.</p>
      <p>There's generally four movements that make an effort to oppose or at least frequently argue against trans rights. There's the religious right; that's not going to work for women (or men) who are not religious themselves, or are religious in the wrong way, ie. belong to liberal churches or minority religions. There are the far-right nationalists; not only do they form a group generally considered to be toxic by a vast amount of people, there's a strong strain of misogyny, madonna/whore complexes (or should we say tradwife/thot?) in the subculture, making it very offputting for the vast majority of women. There are, to some degree, the Quillette-style look-at-the-science alt-libs, for the lack of a better term, but that frame of mind and line of argumentation doesn't seem to appeal to your average woman too much either, and compared to others, seems like thin sauce, the most apologetic and willing to concede things to TRAs - even if you aren't that radical yourself, you might want your movement to stay strong and never concede. And then there are TERFs.</p>
      <p>Thus, you have a lot of secular, liberal women attaching themselves to the cause of trans-exlusionary radical feminism not because they agree with everything the radical feminists say, but because they can agree with sufficient amount of it - opposing trans rights, supporting the general feminist causes like opposing sexual harassment or supporting reproductive health, and also relishing the chance to at least say openly that several factors of typical male behavior are, indeed, outlandish, offputting and even dangerous to women.</p>
      <p>At the same time, when you browse the spaces, it's obvious there are strains; many/most of the "TERFS" are heterosexual (and not willing to stop having sex with men, like many of the more radical ones would recommend), not all that willing to give up all factors of femininity like make-up, feel the misandry might go overboard, might not share the most radically feminist ideas or ideologies like anti-capitalism that go with the territory etc. If the movement keeps growing, it will probably eventually be separated into two ideologies by these strains, with the actual TERFs continuing to do whatever they've always done and the new ideology eventually forming its own thing, own lingo and own set of values and institutions, which might actually already be happening.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>