<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-06-08T04:03:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/ftc4qvr/</link>
  <title>Bridging the Inferential Gap: Why TradCons Dislike Consent Culture</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The fact that there is such a set of rules doesn't mean that promiscuity is a norm. Perhaps it means that the culture doesn't view it as abnormal either. And I'm sure it's contrary to some tradcons desires to have a culture that doesn't explicitly stigmatize it. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I have a story that might help bridge the inferential gap here a bit, one from a while back when I was still a practicing Mormon. </p>
      <p>We had a mandatory "consent"... I almost want to call it a rally... at my school. Brought in some overexcited speaker, ready with all sorts of stories and mediocre jokes—you know the drill. It sticks around in my memory as one of the most weirdly uncomfortable "you don't belong" experiences of my life.</p>
      <p>Why? Well, the scene: Up on stage, this guy talking about all sorts of norms around hookups at parties or bars, particularly with drinking, emphasizing how sex is fun and everyone does it and it's not a big deal, but make sure you consent. Down in the audience, me, a devout Mormon who would have been horrified by the idea of any sort of nonconsensual sexual encounter, but who was also about as removed as someone can be from a culture of casual, no-strings-attached sex, who was deeply uncomfortable with everything connected to hookup culture. Even the idea that I would ever be attending that sort of party was alien and unnerving.</p>
      <p>As someone with a minority moral stance, at some point you get used to the message that it is not yours to enforce on others: that you follow it, and you take it seriously, but you don't go barging in and, say, tell a bunch of people to quit swearing, give them the side-eye when you hear they hooked up, or lecture your friends on the evils of R-rated movies. There's a sort of truce in place, and secular culture knows to laugh at and shut down religious people who break that truce. </p>
      <p>For me, the best way I can describe my tangled impression at the time is something like (using strong wording for effect): "Look. I <em>have</em> moral rules, and they're a whole lot stricter than the ones you're shoving at me. There are people in my life who didn't even <em>kiss</em> until they got married. You don't have the slightest clue about my cultural norms; you're just trampling in acting as if everyone's living in the messy world you're living in. Why are <em>you</em> the one lecturing <em>me</em> about your alien, half-hearted morality?"</p>
      <p>The message of consent isn't wrong or immoral. But I agree that the way it's presented treats hookup culture as a given, and for someone outside of hookup culture it comes across as a bizarre and unnecessary imposition of a hostile set of norms. It's like a bizarro-world repackaging of the feeling a modern secular humanist gets hearing lectures about chastity at Catholic school. </p>
      <p>
        <a href="/u/SayingAndUnsaying">/u/SayingAndUnsaying</a> can confirm whether or not that feeling aligns with his own experience. No longer having a comfortable, distinct culture to stick with, I wouldn't have the same experience at something like that any longer, only flashes of residual irritation and a bit of yearning for something less... I don't know, unserious. But I get what he means when he describes it as an expectation of promiscuity. It mirrors my own experience with it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>