<post>
  <author>dasfoo</author>
  <date>2020-04-15T21:01:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fniqaml/</link>
  <title>The Left "War on Sex"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Seems to me like if anyone is trying to desexualize things it's the right.  The right is the side that, e.g., pushes abstinence-only education, has historically wanted the state to frown on or prohibit same sex relationships, put up barriers to people having birth control, it's a handful of conservative states where sex toys are illegal, it's the right that's more in favor of controlling sexual speech (like porn, but also things less overt than porn) - what's the way that the left is trying to desexualize men and women?  Frowning on flirting in workplaces?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think this response is reflective of the desexualization program of the Left. "Sex" as a biological imperative is a procreative act performed by a man and a woman. My argument isn't that civilization depends on healthy sexuality because it makes people feel good for a few seconds, but because there is a biological drive for men to propagate and for women to bear children. Devaluing that basic function of sex while trumpeting all manner of recreational-but-dead-end sex is part of the decay of sexual expression. The more sex means the more meaningless it becomes.</p>
      <p>There are so many facets of the Leftist "war on sex," from abortion and fears about overpopulation, to "women's liberation" (which means do anything but bearing and raising children; it's not liberation from the patriarchy that is the ultimate goal, it's liberation from biology), to the creep of "Rape culture" from actual rape to complimentary comments on a woman's appearance. The Left doesn't want biological sex, it wants fringe kinks that tweak the previous order of pious old men. It wants a post-sex society, with no male gaze, no biological consequences, no maternal impulses.</p>
      <p>It is a weird contrast between Left and Right (trust me, I have no fondness for the old Right's repressive puritanism either, but I think it got the job done better if not optimally): The New Left wants sex in-your-face, but sterile; while the Old Right wanted sex in private, but fecund.</p>
      <p>UPDATE: I also think that the Left's hostility to Incel culture is part of this. Incel culture is a by-product, I think of de-sexualization, or making the sexual marketplace more hostile to men. The cure to Incel culture, it seems, would be encouraging women to become sexual partners to young single men. It's the sex drive of men and the potential to partner with women that has a positive socializing effect on many young men. Take that away and you get Incels, hopeless and self-loathing with no female mirror to reflect their potential to themselves. But it would fundamentally violate the tents of feminism to suggest that women's part in a healthy society involves thinking of themselves as sexual partners rather than as individuals who are only out to advance themselves.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>