<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-04-15T16:42:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fnhuaga/</link>
  <title>The Devil-May-Care Nature of Coolness</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>When I reflect on the absolute central qualities of coolness, what stands out is the <em>devil-may-care</em> attitude, a certain insouciance and indifference to danger, a total freedom of action that sets someone apart from regular dorks. I think of James Dean, Ferris Bueller, Maverick, The Ballad of Easy Rider, the ronin, John Wick. I even think of /b/. The cool person sticks all their winnings on red and spins the roulette wheel, and doesn't even flinch when it comes back black. While the cool person stands up to authority and takes risks that others don't, his coolness isn't just a matter of bravery; it's a matter of being indifferent to the kind of risks that stymie others from taking bold actions. As Bob Dylan put it, when you ain't got nothin', you got nothin' to lose. This is part of why Achilles is the Ur-Example of coolness in the Western canon, whom most of the great classical conquerors aspired to emulate. He knows that if he stays at Troy, he's going to die. And he's decided to stay at Troy. Knowing that, he doesn't need to worry about the kind of dangers that <a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=096NDwAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PA88&amp;ots=kQgDe42YtE&amp;dq=odysseus%20temporarily%20deaf&amp;pg=PA88#v=onepage&amp;q=odysseus%20temporarily%20deaf&amp;f=false">make Odysseus temporarily deaf</a>. He has total freedom of action within his frame.</p>
      <p>Anti-coolness, by contrast, is about caution and risk aversion. It's the kid who says "guys, we should stop, if the teachers catch us we'll be in trouble". It's the person who folds when they're check-raised. It's the person who sticks their money in a Roth IRA rather than spending it on wild parties and sports cars. It's the person who cuts themselves off after three drinks because they have to get up early in the morning for an important meeting.</p>
      <p>The funny thing about all this is that I think coolness is anti-correlated with the qualities that are successful in the kind of sedentary agriculturalist society that has been trending recently in human history. The nomad is cool. The farmer is deeply uncool. The nomad may not know where their food is coming from tomorrow, but they also don't have to hand over their grain to the king of Uruk, or count how many bushels of grain they have in store for the winter, or engage in back breaking and physically deforming labour just to have enough to eat. Why this cultural motif of coolness should have persisted in Western society despite its being terribly maladaptive for pastoralists and agriculturalists is a bit of a mystery. But as James C Scott notes in <em>Against the Grain</em>, the best strategy for most of the peoples in early agricultural states was to get the hell out of dodge if they could. Maybe - just maybe - there's an echo of a primordial meme there, that leads us to look at the nonchalent barbarian with envy.</p>
      <p>To turn this to race: it may not be a coincidence that the coolest ethnic minorities tend to be economic underclasses - people who are less likely to have mortgages, savings, 9-5 office jobs with strict employee codes of conduct. They have freedom of action relative to the dorks because they don't have as much to lose. In fact, when black Americans are criticised for 'acting white', it tends to be precisely because they're adopting prudent but painful agriculturalist habits like saving their money rather than spending it, accepting the yoke of hierarchy in exchange for material comfort or safety, or thinking too much about tomorrow rather than today.</p>
      <p>Here's where Asian culture is interesting. The broadly Confucian cultures of China, Korea, and Japan are agriculturalists societies par excellence. Ideas like thrift, deference, and circumspection are deeply ingrained, far more so even than in the West. And while Asian culture is very attractive for many nerds in the West (possibly something to do with their 400 year old dragons like look middle schoolers), there's no denying that it's still deeply uncool. In most circles, the weeaboo is a figure of scorn and mockery. Jewish culture is another example of a minority group that I think almost no-one has sought to emulate in the hopes of boosting their street cred, despite its astonishing output of wealthy enterpreneurs and Nobel prize winners. Why not? Because it's uncool. It's prudent and restrained. It looks to the needs of tomorrow and the day after, not to the needs of today. And while many people <em>admire</em> these kind of virtues, they're not cool. They're not Achilles.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>