<post>
  <author>Mexatt</author>
  <date>2020-04-15T16:07:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fnhq0e3/</link>
  <title>In Support of Biden</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I imagine most of the people reading this will be looking at Trump as bad and Biden as also bad, but less so. I'm not in disagreement with this.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think Biden is bad in that I'm libertarian leaning and I think just about every politician at the Federal level is bad. But I think Trump is bad in a different way: He's incompetent.</p>
      <p>As I learn and grow up I'm really coming to appreciate competence. A government is a precious thing to lose, in the grand scheme of things. A competent, relatively uncorrupted government is the difference between the United States and Mexico in the long term.</p>
      <p>So, in that sense, no, I do not think Biden is as 'also bad'. In comparison to Trump, Biden is <em>good</em>.</p>
      <p>I don't share a single assumption or scrap of worldview underlying this post. I think this post is actually kind of bonkers and indicative of a bubble. I think Biden is actually fairly well equipped to beat Trump in November, although the real world has a habit of throwing surprises that upset assumptions, so who knows. Remember: Hillary Clinton lost a few key states in the Upper Midwest and Middle Atlantic by several tens of thousands of votes, in an election where tens of millions voted. She also lost or came close to losing several of those states in the primary. Biden has done extremely well in those states which have had primaries where Clinton lost or came close to losing in the primary, and polls very well in those that haven't. He doesn't <em>have</em> to win that many more voters than Clinton did to win in those states and early signs are showing that it's very possible he will.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, Trump isn't showing signs of having actually expanded his base. His approvals seem to have a fairly hard floor, but they're also struggling to break through a ceiling. If he wins the states Republicans traditionally win but loses the surprise states from 2016, he has lost the Presidency. He needs to be able to hold ground in the Rust Belt against a Democrat <em>from</em> the Rust Belt. Pennsylvania in particular has Biden as a Native Son candidate. Flipping Pennsylvania back means the Democrats are halfway there.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>If Biden loses, and Biden loses badly, then the DNC will be [hopefully] forced to rethink their plan to put forward geriatric neoliberals who will happily throw their voters under the bus for their corporate interests.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is why this looks like a bubble post.</p>
      <p>Let's get one thing straight: The centrist Democrats <em>are</em> the popular part of the party. The progressive left is a small minority faction <em>within the Democratic Party</em>, which itself only represents a third of the electorate. Two thirds of the rest of the electorate are Republicans or Independents. Flagship policies like Medicare for All poll <strong>horribly</strong> on the details (~70% support for the name alone drops to ~30% support when you tell people things like it bans private insurance). Socialism is still <em>very</em> much a curse word for the majority of the American populace. A self-identified socialist is less palatable to American voters than an outspoken <em>atheist</em>.</p>
      <p>This is <em>not</em> an easy win for the Democrats with Biden as the candidate, do not get me wrong. But it <em>would be</em> an easy win for the Republicans with Bernie or someone similar as the Democratic candidate.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>If you want your party to change, you can't look at these elections as an isolated event, it's an iterative one. In game theory, voting for your party is co-operating and voting against them, or not voting is defecting.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It is, but you're not the only players. If Biden loses in November, the Democrats are going to start lurching <em>to the right</em> to try to capture a larger portion of the Independent vote, not the vanishingly small left-progressive vote.</p>
      <p>This sub looks down on consensus building, from right or left. This post is a little too comfortable with being in friendly territory.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>