<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-04-16T13:24:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fnkz1rx/</link>
  <title>Why "The System" Gives Bad Candidates, and Steps to Fix It</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>If all the system is willing to give you is bad candidates, so you cannot vote for good ones, then you should vote for the worst one every time out of spite.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I mean, it depends. <em>Why</em> is the system only willing to give you bad candidates? This is the first cycle I paid really close attention to a competitive primary process, including visiting campaign rallies on the ground for various candidates, and I was honestly impressed by the whole thing. Look at the candidates who made it far: a self-proclaimed socialist, a mayor with a net worth of $100,000, an unknown tech entrepreneur, and a few more traditional candidates. Meanwhile, anointed hopes of the party like Kamala Harris and Beto O'Rourke crashed and burned when people actually saw them in action. The New York Times and its partners in prestige media tried desperately to push Elizabeth Warren through, while <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/01/20/politics/new-york-times-endorsement-joe-biden/index.html">one black lady in an elevator</a> undermined the whole thing by telling Biden how much she loved him. Ultimately, the person who had almost always led in the polls won out, but not before adopting major parts (in some cases altogether too much) of other campaigns people had shown serious interest in.</p>
      <p>On the Republican side in 2016, Donald Trump showed precisely how much "the system" matters if it's not in tune with its own base. He declared open war on the whole thing, broke every political norm, and got everyone with prestige influence lined up in full force against him—and what did it matter? Nothing. He waltzed to the nomination and found enough support to be elected president while "the system" looked on in horror.</p>
      <p>Organization matters. Organization is why we have two viable parties right now, both uneasy coalitions between a bunch of related but competing interests, at once targeting and creating two diametrically opposed bases. In Singapore, organization is what's kept a single party dominant throughout its history, even with free elections. For people to rally behind something, there needs to be something to rally behind, and it needs to be organized enough, visible enough, and attuned enough to their interests to give them something to stand for. But ultimately, no amount of organization suffices when nobody wants what you're selling.</p>
      <p>I'm under no illusions why my political ideas are unpopular right now. People I disagree with won the organization battle. They delivered a clearer message. They were more visible and more salient. They inspired more people to act. They successfully created structures to amplify, refine, and spread their messages on a broad scale. Right now, even if someone who agreed with me fully burst onto the national stage with enormous funding and full commitment, they would lose badly because nobody's bothered to build and sustain the infrastructure to amplify and sustain their cause. </p>
      <p>Voting for the worst options isn't suddenly going to fix that. Voting is a weak signal, and what voting for the worst signals is "I like this. Give me more of it." Following Trump's electoral success, the whole Republican Party suddenly reformed in his image, shifting the equilibrium from "two bad" to "one bad and one awful". The real work needs to go on at a much more fundamental level. In the meantime, at the top level, I can still do damage control. I liked Buttigieg as much as I could expect for someone embedded in the Democratic Party system, so I donated to him and supported him as soon as his campaign formally started. He didn't win, but he gained a much higher profile, and subsequently Biden adopted Buttigieg's <a href="https://www.democracyinaction.us/2020/buttigieg/buttigiegrules.html">"Rules of the Road"</a>, a minor but positive shift. </p>
      <p>Like, who's "the system" going to give us if we make things worse? Who's going to swoop in and make everything better once we've successfully pushed the system to the edge? Political, cultural, and social movements don't spring fully-formed out of nowhere, and they don't do anything if they can't pull a critical mass of active people to their side. "The system" isn't defecting, <em>people who are satisfied enough with "the system" are</em>, and the only way to win long-term is to put in the legwork to build something better and in so doing shift the reality of what people want.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>