<post>
  <author>UAnchovy</author>
  <date>2020-04-16T09:29:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fnkjfcx/</link>
  <title>Democrat Hostility Towards Christians</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Can you give me some citations for this general hostility? At least as of 2014 a plurality or majority of every branch of Christianity (excepting Evangelicals and Mormons) identified as or leaned Democrat.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In this context, I think you have to grant that 'Christian' is not a unified group, with common culture or interests, and as such when different politicians or journalists say the word 'Christian', they usually refer to something more specific.</p>
      <p>When Republicans say 'Christian', they don't mean Hillary Clinton, even though she is one. What they usually have in mind is a narrower tribe of high-commitment, right-leaning, culturally conservative Christians: generally this means an alliance of evangelicals and conservative Catholics. Mainline Protestants don't count. People who regularly go to church and pray and consider Jesus their lord and saviour don't count unless they behave in the specific, public/political way that the commentator has in mind.</p>
      <p>(Sometimes the language used here is 'orthodox Christian' with a small 'o', but I find that extremely irritating and in bad faith.)</p>
      <p>When you hear "Christians are singled out by Democrats", you should read that as "Christians who present themselves and behave in public in a particular way are singled out by Democrats".</p>
      <p>For what it's worth, I think that claim is probably true. Christians like Clinton or Joe Biden will not get in any trouble: they practice their faith privately, they don't talk about it, it doesn't seem to affect their political positions much, especially on culture-war-issues. Blue Tribe Christians are fine. It's <em>Red Tribe</em> Christians who will have trouble. The obvious recent examples would be <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-fix/wp/2017/09/07/did-a-democratic-senator-just-accuse-a-judicial-nominee-of-being-too-christian/">Amy Coney Barrett</a> ("the dogma lives loudly within you", the People of Praise controversy), <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2017/06/bernie-sanders-chris-van-hollen-russell-vought/529614/">Russell Vought</a> ("Muslims stand condemned"), or <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/outlook/2019/01/03/senators-shouldnt-be-afraid-knights-columbus/">Brian Buescher</a> (the Knights of Columbus controversy). I have deliberately linked only left-wing sources there. If you look you can find the usual conservative magazines furious about each case, and accusing the Democrats of anti-Christian or anti-Catholic bigotry. I'd also note that the Democrats involved there - Dianne Feinstein, Bernie Sanders, and Kamala Harris - are all sufficiently big names that I don't think we can dismiss that as a handful of cranks.</p>
      <p>At any rate, being a Christian <em>simpliciter</em> is not an issue, but being the <em>wrong sort</em> of Christian seems to be.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>