<post>
  <author>VassiliMikailovich</author>
  <date>2020-04-16T17:02:54Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fnlnl36/</link>
  <title>Russian Reflections on "Trespass"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>For an interesting cultural perspective on something you may have never considered, here's a <a href="http://xlt.narod.ru/texts/trespass1.html">Russian treasure hunter considering the concept of "trespass"</a> (if you want to read the rest Google Translate does an acceptable job):</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>So what is trespass ?
Literally, "trespass" translates as "violating someone else's right to own property." Accordingly, "trespasser" is "a person who has invaded someone's property without the permission of the owner ." Long and incomprehensible.
But the essence is simple. A man entered a strange lawn without demand, stole nothing ... What kind of criminal is he? What is the crime?? What to call him? Not an "invader" , not a "burglar" , not a "thief" , not a "gopnik" , not a "bully" - you will not understand who at all. There is no such criminal qualification in either the Russian legal language or the Russian criminal jargon. Although, perhaps, the closest will be the "uninvited guest". But then it will still be unclear why the law brings down such “Egyptian executions” on the head of the “guest”, albeit an uninvited one. Therefore, dear reader, I'm sorry, I leave the words "trespass" (this is the crime) and "trespasser" (the one who commits it) without translation...</p>
        <p>The most popular phrase "Trespassers will be prosecuted" (along with "No trespassing" and "No trespassers") in the West can be found on any pillar. Literally, it could be translated as "a person who has invaded these possessions without the permission of the owner will be prosecuted." And even worse... Without a pint you can’t figure it out :) And it’s not at all that prosecution here often threatens the violator.
Without going into too much detail, the translators find the Russian analogue of the last phrase as "No trespassing . "
Although the correct analogue will be - "Stand! I shoot without warning!"
The inscription on the American post, given in the epigraph above, is translated as follows:</p>
        <p>"Trespass is prohibited.
Violators will be shot.
Survivors will be shot again."</p>
        <p>It is funny at the same time that the owner does not joke at all... [the rest of the section consists of an explanation of the history of trespass in the West which I've omitted in the interests of space but which I recommend you read for yourself]</p>
        <p>But if foreign relic hunting colleagues suffer from the existence of the concept of "trespass", then Russian peasants suffer from its complete absence. What are the rights of the landowner? Fences from plots are sometimes stolen. The wire will go to a reception center for non-ferrous metals, boards for firewood, concrete slabs will also come in handy ... So that the fence is not stolen and burned, it must be done ONLY from worthless rusty iron. And so that the thief does not physically climb over it with a bag of potatoes, it should be 2-3 meters high and entangle the area around the perimeter. It’s nothing that the low northern sun will not break through such an “iron curtain”; the short day hours are reduced even more. The main thing is that "potato thieves" do not enter.</p>
        <p>Entire HOUSES disappear from their summer cottages in a day. Why buy a house in the country when a couple of kilometers away is an unguarded log cabin? Even if the owner finds his home, it is almost impossible to prove legally that this house was stolen from you. But to go for "illegitimate" measures of influence on the kidnapper and try to take away your own by force means breaking the law yourself. Not every spirit has enough. Therefore, "country houses" in Russia are very often built from all kinds of rubbish so that thieves do not stare at least at the house itself...</p>
        <p>Many vacationing Russians have been, say, in Greece or Cyprus. (We will not take Italy - there the art of petty theft is an old tradition, transmitted from generation to generation and dating back to the Roman era). The first thing that is surprising is that in these countries not only do not lock houses, but they also do not enclose gardens, and they put goods in front of a bench on the street without supervision, and cars park with open windows - there is no theft. There are no "storage chambers" - everything is put unattended on the floor in hotels and ports, nobody steals. Orchards without fences, apples lying on the ground, no one is missing. You need it - go to the owner, ask. No one will refuse, verified. And without demand, no one rushes through the gardens, does not tear fruit ...</p>
        <p>What a contrast compared to us - near Smolensk, for example, the fields of cherries and strawberries are enclosed by ditches with water, they pull the barbed wire and let the dogs go. A watchman sits on a tower, and the police drive along the roads (at least recently, he traveled), guarding the harvest. Otherwise, you can’t ...</p>
        <p>And our dachas are like fortresses before the attack, there is still not enough ditch and shaft, all the vain hope for trellises and fences. What's the use?...[this is followed by a song I can't do justice by translation and biblical verses]</p>
        <p>If a homeless person breaks into someone else’s garden, then he eats, how much he will fit, and what doesn’t eat - he will take it for sale. And what can not carry away - just break. Apple trees are broken to pick apples. Greenhouses break in order to hand over frames to non-ferrous metal. They take a tool that comes to hand in the hope of selling it. And not “sheaves” and “olives” leave gardeners to vagabonds, but wolf traps and poisoned vodka. The homeless who have bitten the hostesses “pay” the homeowners pay the owners with reciprocal courtesy - the arson of their country houses.</p>
        <p>It is not surprising that land in Russia is simply no longer cultivated. And not only because the population is rapidly declining - by 2500 people per day. Not only because of the extinction of the village. Farmers throw fields because of wild taxes, lack of loans and equipment. But the owners throw gardens and summer cottages because of total theft. And what to do? The summer resident thought in the spring that he planted potatoes for himself in order to feed his family in winter. But it turned out - he fed the homeless in the fall. Yes, they also stole a shovel in gratitude ... In the second or third year, many hands drop.</p>
        <p>Relic hunters know that when searching with a metal detector, the most common find in vegetable gardens is hidden shovels, rakes, choppers, crowbars. Gardeners hide valuable tools of labor in the traditional way for Russia - by digging into the ground. So to say, "treasures of the XX century." But alas, this does not save much from thieves ...</p>
        <p>First of all, those who cannot protect their crops — pensioners, elderly women, and invalids — are throwing the earth. The number of "potato thieves" does not decrease at the same time, they fall on the cultivated areas with great tenacity, forcing the owners to carry out round-the-clock defense of the crops and wonder why they need all this. If there is a crop, there is a headache. I did not sow anything this year - no one will come and steal, rest calmly. Summer vacation from physical labor in the fresh air turned into a dangerous occupation on the verge of crime. So far this phenomenon is a scourge of the province, but black waves are slowly rolling up to dachas and cottages near Moscow.</p>
        <p>The police’s case regarding the theft of agricultural products does not initiate “for insignificance” and there are frequent cases when a truck drives up on a potato field and a homeless person hired for a bottle of vodka cheerfully dig up potatoes right in front of the pensioner owner. Unarmed pensioners are not able to stop the robbers. Therefore, those who cannot live on retirement and intend to plant potatoes, are increasingly resorting to help ... no, not weapons. To the help of "lads", Russian gangsters. For example, all the owners of the Tver vegetable gardens that we inspect pay annually to the local mafia "for protection". The brotherhood, of course, does not bear any protection, but even homeless people in such gardens are afraid to appear in the open. Those who are not able to pay "for the roof" in the province are simply abandoning their land.</p>
        <p>The process of reducing the cultivated area to the joy of Russian fans of metal detection has taken an avalanche-like character. The fertile land is abandoned by the owners. Fields are overgrown with forest. Land capable of feeding people stands under a weed. People who are able to grow crops are sitting idle. Agricultural production is declining, and prices are rising accordingly. Homeless people snooping around abandoned gardens are starving ...</p>
      </blockquote>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>