<post>
  <author>4bpp</author>
  <date>2020-02-29T10:42:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f8me2d/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_24/fj38lwj/</link>
  <title>A Theory Of Mod Actions Drawing Ire</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I see there is a reasonable case for a timeout to be made from your case log, but the <em>way</em> the mod team has been handling these really reminds me of toxic "US police vs. ethnic enclave" dynamics. Consider the possibility that the following dynamic is in play: Every time you make a high-visibility ban of some right-wing poster for just about the most harmless transgression that still registers at one (often justified by a backlog of warnings for somewhat more serious transgressions, which to the casual viewer has zero emotional resonance next to the tableau of "1 week ban - <em>and of course it's Hlynka, with the other mods circling wagons around him downthread</em> - for a minor wisecrack"), a few people slightly to the left of the person you banned conclude that this community does not care about them anymore. Having concluded that, they stop caring too, and stop putting in the effort to suppress the urge to make cheap wisecracks and otherwise exercise self-control for the sake of maintaining the discussion culture in it. Before long, they to start wisecracking, and likewise get banned, and the unravelling moves a little further left. In the end, you are left with a growing set of people who are fed up with playing "cooperate", and a shrinking set that feels ever more threatened by the defectors and demands even more crackdowns.</p>
      <p>The worst possibility is that the frontier is not even a clean cut that leaves good posters to the left of the ban threshold, a narrow margin of snark posters just before it and nobody to its right: instead, to the right of the threshold you get all those right-wing posters who also stopped caring, but did not feel the necessity to express their alienation in a bannable fashion. These users can then go on posting perfectly rules-conforming, low-effort, boring posts, slowly drowning the community in a way that is almost indistinguishable from everyone just slowly getting senile.</p>
      <p>So yeah, consider the optics of your actions. Killing weeds is not the only thing that matters about gardening.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>