<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2020-02-28T21:39:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f8me2d/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_24/fj1r5ns/</link>
  <title>Red-Tribe Marketed TV Series</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The libertarian think tank Foundation for Economic Education did a video essay on this topic titled <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wo4V3GaXFBY">Jack Ryan Is Lying About Venezuela</a>.  It makes the same observations you do: it feels like gaslighting to tell a story about corrupt Venezuela regime impoverishing the country and make the villains <em>right wing</em>.</p>
      <p>What's utterly bizarre about this is that it's like a complete betrayal of the Jack Ryan audience.  This is baffling to me, not in a "how dare you" sort of way, but "why would you alienate your audience like this" way.  I don't understand this move for <em>commercial</em> reasons.</p>
      <p>When I hear "Tom Clancy," I think "dads living in red states." The villains of Rainbow Six are eco terrorists.  In Patriot Games, the terrorist group is an an ideologically Maoist splinter of a real-world socialist political party.  The military and their hardware are described in such loving detail that I'm sure if you poll people at any given gun range in America about how many Tom Clancy novels they own, it'll be measurably higher than a sample of the general population. </p>
      <p>A young writer in the neoconservative Washington Free Beacon <a href="https://freebeacon.com/culture/a-hunt-for-patriots/">described</a> Clancy saying:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The Hunt for Red October (1984) and Patriot Games (1987) are products of "<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EU-IBF8nwSY">Morning in America</a>." So, for a first-time reader born on the cusp of 1995 and who became politically aware on September 11, 2001, these novels are pictures of a society that seems to have looked at America with complete confidence—works of such patriotism that intellectuals today would greet them as farce (as intellectuals did when they were first published). </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>An aside: when red tribers say "Make America Great Again," the implied statement is that America used to be great, and <em>this</em> is what they're talking about: a time when people still had faith in their systems and institutions, an era that we knew had begun when Ronald Reagan told all of us, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EU-IBF8nwSY">"It's morning in America again."</a>  (Reagan told us that when running in 1984; clearly it was the result of him having delivered on his 1980 campaign promise to Make America Great Again.)  Even if you think that version of America only ever existed in our collective imaginations, for the people who wear red hats and pack arenas for Trump rallies, it feels real.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The Hunt for Red October is not just a celebration of systems working, but really of The System. The phrase Military Industrial Complex is never used here, but if it were it wouldn't be pejorative. Clancy loves the military. The whole range of Naval equipment and weaponry on display throughout Red October is undeniably cool. But more than cool, it feels right, the way things are supposed to work: reliably.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In ordering season 1 of Jack Ryan, Amazon's goal seemed obvious: this was high-budget television for people who wanted <em>that thing</em> that you get whenever you pick up a Tom Clancy novel.  You know, the kind of people who watched Harrison Ford in <em>Patriot Games</em> and <em>Clear and Present Danger</em> and thought, "more of that, please."</p>
      <p>Looking at the season 2 plotline and "right-washing" of the villains, I'm not sure what the motivation here is: are they trying to get some crossover appeal with blue tribers by trying to cater to their political sensibilities?</p>
      <p>You can get away with a certain amount of this, but you have to be measured with it.  <em>Designated Survivor</em> is a show that I see as somewhat similar to <em>Jack Ryan</em>.  Besides the plotline similarities (a kinda random wonky dude suddenly becomes president after everyone ahead of him in line for the presidency dies at the State of the Union address), it told the story of a soft guy taking the executive role and learning to be a hardass in a world where America had to be wary of enemies at every turn. (There's actually a moment in the first episode of Designated Survivor where the newly-inaugurated president is about to address the nation about the state of emergency, and he's told to take his glasses off before the cameras go live, because the glasses make him look like an egghead, and what America needs right now is to look at their president and see a tough guy who they trust him to keep them safe.)</p>
      <p>Red tribe dads loved it, but you need more than just red tribe dads to have a successful network TV drama, and like any writers room I'm sure <em>Designated Survivor's</em> creative staff was mostly registered democrats, so here and there they'd not-so-subtly sneak in a plotline about how "people of middle eastern heritage can be good loyal Americans too" and "it's heartless and incompassionate to stop people from immigrating across the southern border," and so on.  For its early seasons, Designated Survivor seemed to walk a delicate balance: it had an ideology that appealed to blue tribers (pretty much every individual "issue" it sided with the blue tribers), but all of that was balanced out by a premise that supported a world-view that appealed to red tribers (the world is full bad guys who want to hurt America, and we need a tough dude in the oval office to make sure no one fucks with us). But you can only push the red tribers so much before they break: after the show was canceled and season 3 was picked up by Netflix, the result was something that got responses like the ones summed up in <a href="https://np.reddit.com/r/DesignatedSurvivor/comments/evgpo3/pandering/">this thread</a> (which, based on the number of upvotes, seem to represent a reasonable consensus of people who watched this show):</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I'm halfway through season 3, does anyone else feel the harsh pandering? Every other sentence now is about how tough it is being gay, trans, latino, black, asian, woman, etc. and everyone around just says "yes you're right i see the error of my ways now"</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Honestly I got really sick of the SJW bullshit. I really liked the genetic terrorism fiasco since I think it’s a unique and genuine threat both in the show and in real life (especially with the coronavirus running around and with the advances in genetic research and CRISPER and such) but the “America is a terrible country” message didn’t need to be shoved down our throats.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Of course, it's not just red tribers who found it preachy: blue tribers found it preachy too, but for them, that was a feature, not a bug, or at least that's the impression I get from an editorial titled <a href="https://qz.com/quartzy/1675121/conservatives-should-watch-netflixs-designated-survivor/">"Designated Survivor was the political drama conservatives needed to watch"</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>While ABC’s two seasons—43 episodes in total—wove together breathless conspiracy theories ripe for broadcast television, Netflix charted a new course with season three (10 episodes). </p>
        <p>Netflix’s season three confronted issues that matter deeply to groups who are often underrepresented on screen. The show introduced Sasha, president Kirkman’s (previously unmentioned) sister-in-law, who is transgender. ...</p>
        <p>Throughout season three, the show exhibited a similar sensitivity toward Dontae Evans, a social media strategist on Kirkman’s campaign staff. The relationship (and specifically, a steamy sex scene) between Evans—an HIV-positive, gay black man—and Troy, a Secret Service agent, caught viewers off guard. But as Phillip Zonkel wrote for QVoiceNews, Designated Survivor became one of the first shows “to debunk the misinformation about what it means to be HIV positive and undetectable.” ...</p>
        <p>Throughout season three, Kirkman’s social agenda demonstrates that what affirms people’s dignity isn’t necessarily politically palatable. In addition to addressing LGBTQ issues and racism, he contends with hot-button issues that include fake news, assisted suicide, opioid addiction, and immigration. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I have not seen season 3, but this description makes it seem like a ten-long episode scissor statement: I imagine that many people who watched season 3 and didn't like it would point at exactly the same things that this writer praised and say, "Yes, that's the part that I didn't like."</p>
      <p>What's really baffling about Designated Survivor is that season 3 is exactly the place that they could have doubled down on appeasing the red tribe audience: I always felt like the leftist political leanings on basically every "issue of the day" that came up during season 1 were a concession to the fact that in order for a show to succeed on network television, you need everyone to tune in.  Streaming is the place where you can have shows that appeal to a dedicated fanbase and absolutely no one else.  (See: the Christmas Prince movies, which are almost universally reviled and roundly mocked but Netflix keeps making because some women <em>really</em> like Hallmark channel-style schmaltz).  Instead, they alienated their core constituency.</p>
      <p>I feel the same way about Amazon: when you have a service like Prime, each show's goal shouldn't be to locally maximize for ambivalent engagement to get as many people to tune in as possible to sell ad spots, it should be to find one specific audience who <em>really</em> likes your show and is convinced that show is a reason for them to be  subscribe to Prime.  Adding another "sorta kinda good show that everyone moderately likes" isn't going to move the needle for anyone; the problem that everyone has is that there is <em>too much</em> television to watch, and now it's just a matter of finding the stuff that you can't miss (not the general "you can't miss it," but the very specific, "you, the person watching this trailer, are the exact audience for this piece of content).</p>
      <p>I'm not sure what the point of using an IP like Jack Ryan is when you're going to spit in the face of the customers that made that IP valuable in the first place.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>