<post>
  <author>dazzilingmegafauna</author>
  <date>2020-02-25T21:43:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f8me2d/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_24/firm4t0/</link>
  <title>Ask And Tell In Gender Issues</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Now, though, that's right out. Not a chance! They want to be treated as equals, but also not really- the people already there are expected to modify their behavior and norms for the newcomers. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>There's no inherent contradiction between wanting to be treated as an equal within a given space and wanting the people occupying it to change their behavior. If the former condition isn't met, it necessitates a change in behavior.</p>
      <p>The problem is that things like men using the word "dongle" is being lumped into the same category as men treating their female colleagues in a way that no male colleague would tolerate. </p>
      <p>At the same time, I agree that male and female socialization are at least somewhat distinct from one another and there isn't any neutral social space where both sexes will feel equally comfortable. </p>
      <p>For various reasons, men are much more likely to <em>be asked to</em> compromise when their preferences come in conflict with those of women (who are themselves much more likely to compromise <em>without being asked</em>). Two women will typically send subtle signals of their preferences to one another and modify their own behavior in response. Men, on the other hand, will tend to explicitly ask one another for accomodations. These differing communication styles map roughly with the rationalist concepts of "guess culture" and "tell culture". </p>
      <p>When a woman is interacting with a man, the woman will often feel frustrated that her signals are being ignored and that she instead has to ask for anything she wants (something generally frowned upon in intra-female communication). She may also feel like none of the many things she is preemptively doing to accommodate the guy's preferences are being appreciated.</p>
      <p>Men, on the other hand, often feel like the relationship is unbalanced insofar as they almost are constantly being asked to modify their behavior while rarely if ever asking for anything in return. He isn't aware of the number of modifications she has made in order to accommodate (her model of) his preferences.</p>
      <p>This is of course a generation. There are men who prefer a "guess" style of communication and women who prefer an "tell" one, as well as men and women who adopt communication styles they don't prefer for pragmatic reasons.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>