<post>
  <author>Fevzi_Pasha</author>
  <date>2020-02-28T04:27:37Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f8me2d/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_24/fiziwl3/</link>
  <title>An Update On The Syrian Civil War</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It looks like vast majority of Americans (and in general Westerners) lost interest in the Syrian Civil War around the time ISIS was defeated and I see a lot of confusion in the early comments about the significance of the events so I decided to attempt to clarify some of the developments as the rare Turkish follower of this sub.</p>
      <p>What has been going on lately? </p>
      <p>Idlib is a northwestern province in Syria with a large border to Turkey, known for being more or less the last rebel bastion in the civil war. </p>
      <p>Since the regime's incursion into Idlib has begun, Turkey has been trying to negotiate with the Russians a deal that would stop the potential millions of extra refugees that would be fleeing for their lives once the Idlib region falls. It's important to mention that in the course of the civil war, Idlib has been used as the dumping ground for many failed rebel organisations. Assad regime has been literally bussing militias from other regions that agreed to surrender to Idlib for years. As a consequence much of the population has a serious reason to fear for their lives even in the event of a peaceful takeover, let alone a brutal battle. </p>
      <p>The Syrian refugee population in Turkey is currently approaching 4 million people and there is massive public disapproval about this issue (Open borders liberal left has never been a constituency in Turkey). Turkish army has been digging into the Idlib territory to stop the regime's advance with the hope that Assad (or more accurately the Russians) wouldn't dare an escalation against Turkish troops. Now this game of brinkmanship seems to be over. If the regime isn't stopping, the only way to stop millions of desperate new refugees from pouring inside the country seems to be stopping the regime by force. </p>
      <p>What has just happened? </p>
      <p>Well, the regime (and the Russians) hasn't stopped. </p>
      <p>The death tally stands at <del>29</del> 33 right now. My trust in the Turkish government with such numbers isn't very high but I don't think they are doing any serious manipulation. I also imagine it's going to be increasing in the following days since probably many soldiers are badly wounded as well. </p>
      <p>This is a very big deal for Turkey. The public outrcy is massive since very few people (even among Erdoğan voters) are on board with the government's somewhat hypocritical claim of "protecting civilians from the murderous Assad regime" and don't back any military action not intended to stop a Kurdish state along our border. Common sentiment seems to be that the government was putting our boys in danger for adventrous geopolitical games. My personal view is that while the government has made some very poor decisions in the early years of the civil war, the current brinkmanship was necessary if we have any hope to stop millions of more refugees and extreme destabilisation right next to our borders. </p>
      <p>The common view in my social circles upon hearing the news (more like hearing rumours in whatsapp groups. A common event since the media is almost entirely under government control here or at least very fearful and is very timid about broadcasting such news before the government sources) was that the government has to take drastic action to contain the domestic fury; either by totally evacuating the army positions in the Idlib region or declaring open war against the Syrian regime. The last couple of hours indicates the second option is now underway. I believe that the public opinion would be supportive (at least in the beginning) in the event of a war against Syria instead of the current proxy war through puppet militias. The nationalist mood is very strong in Turkey and the government has enough control to keep dissent in check. </p>
      <p>What does this mean for the West? </p>
      <p>If full scale war between Syria and Turkey materialises, Syria will be backed by Russia (both in arms and in personnel) and Turkey expects to be backed by its NATO alliance. It's useful to see the bizarre reaction of opening the western borders to Syrian refugees in this perspective. It's very likely that this move is a very open threat against the European NATO members who, after active encouragement of the rebellion and funding/arming of the initial rebel groups, have been largely sitting on their hands about the consequences of the civil war (obviously Turkey hasn't acted very nicely with its support for jihadi rebels either, but at least had to go through the consequences of this). The threat is probably that if they don't support the Turkish government in this matter, Turkey will not safeguard them from the refugee consequences anymore.</p>
      <p>PS. One of the comments had a rather funny take about why Turkey is punishing American tech companies. Well it isn't. It's just good old government cencornship. </p>
      <p>Sorry for bad English. I am writing from my phone and isn't my native language obviously.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>