<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-02-22T16:48:19Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f53qhm/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_17/fifil50/</link>
  <title>Child Abuse And Institutional Responsibility</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/156648/let-boy-scouts-die-out-already">This article</a> was brought to my attention and it seemed like an opportunity to further-discuss something that comes up rather a lot here: child abuse and institutional cover-ups.</p>
      <p>The subject is sensitive for what I take to be obvious reasons.  Not all of us have children, but all of us have <em>been</em> children, and humans tend toward protectiveness in connection with children.  Credible statistics are hard to find, but it is clear that sometimes children are abused, and in many cases we can draw compelling causal arrows between abuse and future suffering.  Public opinion comes down in favor of <em>making this happen less</em>, such that <a href="https://www.boston.com/news/crime/2020/02/21/in-letter-california-inmate-says-that-he-killed-2-molesters-in-prison">the likelihood of child molesters being murdered in prison</a> is sometimes regarded as a positive feature of American criminal justice.  (In the United States, the death penalty was once permitted for sex crimes, but not now.)</p>
      <p>When individuals and institutions are found to have been aware of abuse, this moves immediately to the center of criticism against them, at least for a while. The Catholic Church is the poster-child here, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Settlements_and_bankruptcies_in_Catholic_sex_abuse_cases">over a billion dollars</a> has been paid to victims in settlements over the past 20 years.  Now <del>the Boy Scouts of America</del> Scouts BSA is headed toward bankruptcy, likely precipitated by the institutional exodus of Mormons dissatisfied with the BSA's abandonment of various founding principles, but tipped over the edge by a rising tide of lawsuits from victims of abuse.</p>
      <p>The article I linked above is a victory dance on the BSA's financial grave, but as such it is premature.  Local "councils," like dioceses of the Catholic church, are financially distinct entities.  But aside from taking a series of culture-war potshots against the BSA (high-paid "non-profit" management, cultural appropriation from native American tribes), the piece shares some interesting numbers that I hadn't seen before.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The Boy Scouts have long known about the predators within their midst: Their own closely guarded “Perversion Files” tracked sexual abuse cases from 1944 to 2016. The numbers are staggering: 12,000 alleged victims—all children and teenagers—abused by 7,800 separately identified Scoutmasters. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Seventy-two years, 12,000 victims.  According to <a href="https://historyofscouting.com/history/history-1940.htm">this</a>, at the end of 1943 there had been 11,477,483 "members to date"--a number that appears to combine adult leadership with child membership.  Scouting "peaked" in the early 1970s but Wikipedia suggests about 110 million members-to-date.  Scouts BSA <a href="https://www.scouting.org/about/">currently claims</a> "more than 2.4 million youth participants and nearly one million adult volunteers."  Just doing some hasty napkin-math, let's say there were approximately 70 million youth participants in BSA from 1944 to 2016.  The "staggering" 12,000 known victims amount to less than <em>two hundredths of one percent</em> of all participants.  If BSA was unaware of <em>ninety-nine percent</em> of abuse cases, the rate of sexual abuse among boy scout troops would still be <em>less than two percent of all participants</em>.</p>
      <p>Long-time participants in these conversations will recognize the <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/09/16/cardiologists-and-chinese-robbers/">Chinese robber</a> and base-rate problems that are already cropping up.  Perhaps two percent is shockingly high; perhaps two hundredths of one percent is shockingly high.  We can of course say "whether the number is 12 or 12,000 or 1,200,000 or what, any number greater than zero represents a breach of trust and a serious moral harm."  But I'm not going to take up those arguments because my goal here is not to defend Scouts BSA, or the Catholic Church, or anyone, really. What I want to do instead is engage in some what-aboutism.</p>
      <p>Specifically, I want to talk about why nobody cares about child abuse in public schools.</p>
      <p>Well, okay, that's already unfair, actually.  <em>Of course</em> we care about child abuse in public schools.  Nevertheless, while articles with headlines like "Let the Boy Scouts Die Out, Already" and "<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/09/01/opinion/catholic-church-sexual-abuse-scandal-reform.html">Is the Catholic Church Beyond Redemption</a>" get a lot of play, I had a much harder time finding articles arguing that we should abolish public schools because they are hotbeds of child abuse.  Make no mistake--I am not an original thinker here.  <a href="https://www.commonwealmagazine.org/why-should-public-schools-be-exempt">It has definitely been noticed</a> that public schools are at least <em>similar</em> to other child-centered organizations, and arguably much worse, when it comes to instances of abuse. Any kind of principled approach to the problem would require us to take much <em>more</em> notice of public schools than of Catholic dioceses or BSA troops simply because of the raw <em>numbers</em> involved.  Again--statistics on the matter are fraught, but</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Often enough, bishops and their spokespersons have pointed to a 2004 study that Charol Shakeshaft, now a professor of educational leadership at Virginia Commonwealth University, did for the U.S. Department of Education. The study, required under the No Child Left Behind Act of 2002, determined that 6.7 percent of public-school students encountered physical sexual abuse during their schooling; with verbal or visual harassment included, the number rose to nearly 10 percent: 4.5 million children. These crimes might have led to an avalanche of civil litigation—except that most states have laws that make it difficult to sue public agencies, including public schools.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I am definitely prone, when looking out at the world, to notice patterns that are specifically detrimental to the institution of the family.  But I have always kind of seen the controversy over clerical abuse and scouting abuse as disconnected from that, or perhaps connected only in the sense that families sometimes need community assistance in pursuit of protecting their children.  I am now a little worried that I have apparently overlooked a significant advantage the government has in the struggle between parents and bureaucrats for control of the rising generation: child-oriented, parent-optioned non-governmental organizations (NGOs) are vulnerable to destruction-by-lawyer, while government agencies are not.  When you sue a Catholic diocese or Scouts BSA, a sufficiently decisive victory can wipe out unbounded quantities of social good.  When you sue the government, <em>even if you win</em>, the government doesn't close its doors.  All the government does is reallocate the wealth of some citizens, to other citizens.</p>
      <p>I don't want to draw a trend-line showing that over time, the government will be the only child-oriented, parent-optioned game in town; there is no reason in principle why some other child-oriented NGOs couldn't emerge.  Indeed, bankruptcy is clearly not the <em>end</em> for Scouts BSA, as it is for any other business entity; restructuring is not the same as death.</p>
      <p>Rather, I just wanted to raise the question of what a genuinely reasonable approach to protecting participants in child-centered government agencies and NGOs both might look like.  People like to throw around the word "cover-up" but given that public anger over this kind of thing can be quite extreme, it's not obvious to me that there is <em>any</em> benefit in, for example, publicizing the names and deeds of the accused (sex offender registries, for example, strike me as broadly inhumane, even though I understand the concerns presented by the possibility of recidivism).  Rules requiring various kinds of disclosure (like, for example, the Clery Act in connection with universities) also seem to raise more puzzles than solutions (for example by being murky about how to handle disputed accusations, as recently happened in <a href="https://www.dailytarheel.com/article/2019/11/cleryact-faq-1122">North Carolina</a>).  Requiring "background checks," aside from possible worries about invasiveness, doesn't appear to be especially effective <em>anyway</em>--except at creating a paper trail of "reasonable precaution" for organizations to avoid financial liability.  Indeed the standard institutional advice at present appears to be "how you can protect your institution from costly lawsuits by persuading juries that you <em>really tried</em>," and definitely not "how your institution can <em>actually protect</em> its participants."</p>
      <p>Though of course there are also disturbing cases of familial abuse, my sense from the literature is that children--and <em>especially</em> female adolescents--are safest when they are at home.  The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westermarck_effect">Westermarck effect</a> points to the possibility that being raised in a stable family environment has protective influence by (usually) neutralizing the drives of the most likely predators (namely, males who share the environment).  By the numbers, requiring children to attend public school appears to be one of the most dangerous things American governments have ever demanded of citizens.  If we could say with great confidence that the benefits outweighed the costs... <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Case-against-Education-System-Waste/dp/0691174652">but no, I suppose that's also, at best, an open question</a>.</p>
      <p>So this morning I find myself sliding further down the Bayesian slope toward "compulsory public education is a net harm," with the bonus suspicion that "the most vocal defenders of children are focused on destroying institutions, like churches, that do the least actual harm, while ignoring the most serious offenders."  But, as always, I invite assistance from the Motte's collective perspective.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>