<post>
  <author>Pulpachair</author>
  <date>2020-02-22T18:48:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f53qhm/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_17/fig98le/</link>
  <title>A Conspiracy In The Mock Government</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>My general rule is that a conspiracy must be able to be held within a motel room.  The more people "in the know" the more likely it is to fail, which makes grand conspiracies very hard to pull off.</p>
      <p>The corollary is that a well-positioned small set of individuals can successfully pull off a grand swindle as long as they have a sufficiently credulous target audience, and this happens All. The. Time.</p>
      <p>A real life example.  After the Advanced Placement exams, the AP political science class in my high school would run a month-long mock dictatorship.  One classmate was elected supreme leader and then all other classmates were assigned numbers in order of authority.  Rules were set for behavior in and out of school and observed violations of those rules would result in a loss of status in the group.  I was not in the class, but I was friends with most of the class.  They went from fun nerds to really obnoxious nerds overnight.</p>
      <p>As part of the mock dictatorship, a fictitious entity called the Anti-Leader Militia was created, that was supposed to be the boogeyman that unified the class in support of the leader.  Entirely fictitious.  Except that a small group of three of us who were very annoyed by the experiment got together and convinced a member of the broader student government to step forward as the figurehead of the militia.  It didn't take much convincing - they were very annoying.</p>
      <p>Once there was a figurehead, it was a simple matter of putting one of the higher-ranking members of the poli-sci class together with the head of the militia (at a lunch table in the cafeteria.)  We then made sure that a few people in the class received simultaneous information about the meeting, and that they could verify it with each other.  Because demoting someone meant that they would rise in the ranks, there was a strong incentive NOT to do anything more than surface checks on the validity.  That member was expelled from the government.  Then another.  Then another.</p>
      <p>At the same time, the small group sowed the seeds of a mockery campaign.  Anytime one of the poli-sci class members did the mandatory salute and greeting, we had an elaborate, Monty-Python inspired funny walk and salute that we did in response.  Other people in the high school immediately followed suit.  It was intentionally maximally disruptive.  The threat of being the subject of mockery by the wider student body was greater than the threat of status loss in the poli-sci class, so most of the poli-sci class stopped participating entirely. </p>
      <p>For the first time in 15 years, the experiment failed.  The mock government dissolved entirely in vicious infighting when faced with the internal chaos and unified external pressure.  Outside of the three of us that were in on the conspiracy, it looked like a spontaneous meltdown by the poli-sci class.  We weren't leaders of anything recognizable, just the catalyst for human tendencies.  It wouldn't have worked if it were known that this was anything other than a spontaneous reaction.  </p>
      <p>So, if a conspiracy relies on hundreds of participants and widespread societal opposition, I can pretty safely dismiss it.  If it relies on four people telling a flattering story to a credulous audience, it has a much greater chance of being true.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>