<post>
  <author>ThirteenValleys</author>
  <date>2020-02-28T19:52:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f8me2d/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_24/fj1gfzh/</link>
  <title>Overinterpretation, A Game</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The longstanding rhetorical dictum of "interpret everything in the worst possible light" doesn't just harm society and decency, it also dulls the skills of the people who practice it. </p>
      <p>The unspoken game back when I was on the left-blogs was to play a sort of Magic Eye with the enemy's words. For example, I once got praised for 'correctly' 'identifying' that Wisconsin governor Scott Walker's reference to Madison as a 'dark blue city' was veiled racism (even though Madison is 10% black or so.) My cohort probably thought Walker was racist in a generic sense, like all Republicans were, but did they <em>really</em> think that specific word choice was to deliver that specific message? I'm going to be generous and say no. But it <em>could</em> be. And once someone 'figured that out', it was a perfectly acceptable, if not the only acceptable, spin. </p>
      <p>The <em>point</em> of the game is esotericism. The more bizarre and obscure your logical leaps, the <em>better</em> you are at playing. Parallels to the liberal-arts educations of those who practice this abound: you spend four years honing the skill of "Describe the philosophy of this 19th century French author through the lens of 21st century American social justice politics", you get good at it, you get praised for it, you learn it at the expense of other, more generally applicable skills. "The Game" comes to be be seen not just as a diversion, or one lens among many, but a starting point, a truth-seeking device. </p>
      <p>So when the Guardian writer hears that Indian voters are trending Tory, I think it's not solely out of sour grapes about 'stolen' minority voters or Asians-are-actually-white nu-racism. I think the writer is subconsciously going "How can I spin this in the most esoteric way? What's the farthest leap of logic I can make without completely falling flat?" Because that's what you <em>do</em>, what you're <em>supposed to do.</em> That's what analyzing politics <em>is.</em> Statistical or economic explanations? Huh, what? They write this crap, on some level, because they think they have to write it. </p>
      <p>It should go without saying that most people don't think of things this way. Hence the disconnect between the media and the rest of us. Hence, to most of us, this article <em>does</em> fall flat. It sounds utterly ridiculous.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>