<post>
  <author>VelveteenAmbush</author>
  <date>2020-02-25T03:35:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f8me2d/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_24/fipaguu/</link>
  <title>Steelmanning Rape Culture</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Hmm, my most charitable interpretations of the "rape culture" memeplex suggest that it has much less to do with forcible stranger rape and much more to do with situations where there are elements or at least suggestions of consent in at least some of the facts at play.</p>
      <p>The canonical example is a frat party where alcohol is served with the intent of facilitating hookups. My own view is that by and large the men and women both understand the purpose of the alcohol and equally know what they are signing up to when they go to that party. But if you approach the exchange from the doctrinaire position that consent must be given at the time of sex and that it cannot be given while drunk, then (in a literal sense) a bunch of frat brothers planning the liquor menu at a party so they can get laid are conspiring to commit systematic rape. That is the rules-based argument that you use to defend your accusation after you've decided to make it.</p>
      <p>To persuade people to align with that rules-based argument and make the accusation, there is a <em>sentimental</em> terrain in which one observes that women are the more vulnerable sex (less physical strength, more value in the sexual marketplace, a culture and biology that each punish promiscuity more for the receiving partner), that some of them (in particular freshman girls) may have relatively less understanding of the dynamics of that type of party than those facilitating it, that those <em>regretting</em> their encounters (at least vocally) tend to be the women, that those who plan and organize these events have relatively more agency in this entire cultural phenomenon than those who merely show up (complicit as they may be), and that a few genuinely bad actors (e.g. that Stanford rapist, or anyone having sex with someone else who's literally unconscious) maybe looks to be more on the right tail of a smooth continuum with the intended activity than a discrete outlier. Arguably this whole mode of having sex isn't particularly good for any of the participants. Arguably it doesn't build relationships, it spreads STDs, it discourages more rewarding forms of pair bonding and leaves people feeling lonely and depressed, it makes for greater inequality in the sexual marketplace and creates a truly lamentable population of incels, and it echoes through our culture in any number of ways, depressing fertility and creating atomization and ennui throughout our civilization that will indelibly transfigure generations to come.</p>
      <p>So if you've (a) persuaded yourself that women at frat parties are directionally/intuitively victims, (b) satisfied yourself with the argument that the frat house men are all co-conspirators to commit massive, widespread &amp; frequent rape, and (c) observed that colleges and universities all seem to be indifferent at best or complicit at worst with this whole system, and that broader society seems to take the same attitude with respect to colleges and universities, I can empathize how someone might tie it all up in a bow and label the whole package "rape culture."</p>
      <p>I'm picking out frat parties specifically as the central example, but one could make similar arguments about any number of aspects of hookup culture that tends to predominate rather than the elaborate courtships of our grandparents' generation, and hopefully it's pretty obvious how the argument proceeds.</p>
      <p>I also want to be clear that I don't personally agree with either primary step of this argument. I think all participants in this culture are consensually participating in the transactions involved, that the transactions often include consensually surrendering your own ability to consent knowing and intending exactly where that will lead, that the various resulting social equilibria are in total <em>deeply</em> regrettable but that no individual is specifically culpable (nor either sex generally more culpable than the other), and that the inquisitorial intensity of the word "rape" is inappropriate to the project of condemning much less repairing collective action problems of this type.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>