<post>
  <author>wgk_elphinstone</author>
  <date>2020-02-26T02:05:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f8me2d/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_24/fisdg47/</link>
  <title>Reporting Someone In An Online Game - An Introspection</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Culture Warcraft</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Yesterday, I was about to talk to a friend of mine online, and was playing some Warcraft 3 while waiting for him. In a standard 1-vs-1 match, I've used my usual strategy of attacking my opponent’s base when he would be far away, destroying a couple buildings and promptly leaving with few losses just to reemerge later to do the same trick. After my first serious assault, I was called “a rude boy” in chat, to which I’ve replied “sorry :)”, after second – “a real n*****”, after third – “what a f*****”, both of which I’ve left with no response. By that point, discrepancy in our resources and armies was so substantial that it was clear that I would win, and other opponents would usually say “good game” and leave. However, my enemy would not do that, and continued to run in circles, prolonging the match by a good 100%. After being asked why he wouldn’t concede and leave, I was told that “because your strategy is gay”. Soon the match was over.</p>
      <p>My friend called me soon afterwards, and we were chatting about something irrelevant, and while doing so I was mindlessly clicking around my PC. Without thinking about it, I soon found myself looking at my ex-opponent in “recently played with” list, clicked on his profile, pressed the “report” button, selected “bad language” and typed “Used n-word and f-word in a match with me earlier today” and was about to click “submit”, as it dawned on me: “why am I doing that?” I immediately told the story to my friend, and we’ve proceeded to talk about it - not that fact that I got insulted online while playing a game (gosh!), but the fact that I almost reported the person for that.</p>
      <p>The comments themselves didn’t really affect me, as I am not black and not gay. Moreover, I am somewhat of a free speech absolutist, and don’t consider n-word or f-word to be valid grounds for, say, a firing, and probably would not stop being friends with someone who called me those terms in real life just on the basis of the words used. I know it is not the same for most people in US, but I <strong>personally</strong> don’t think that those terms are any more insulting than being called a “bastard” or a “bitch” (I do realize that for the broader society this is not true, and that's why I am able to spell out one set of insults and not the other). I also do realize that reporting for n-word and for "bastard" would be probably treated with different levels of concern by reviewers of reported comments as well, and, to be fair, I don't think that using those terms in a game is bad enough to justify the risk of being banned from multiplayer in a game you own.</p>
      <p>I've tried to explain to myself and to my friend <strong>why</strong> did I want to report this person? It wasn't him being rude to me, or not using those words, and not me losing the game - I've won it! Maybe it was the additional 10-15 minutes I've spent chasing him around the map, but that also seemed very weak to me. To my friend, I've tested out the idea of "well, if I don't say something, he will do it again to someone else, who would be more hurt", who told me that "well, if he does it again, wouldn't the other person report him? So, he will get reported quite soon, so whether you report him now doesn't make much of a difference". I've replied with something like "Wasn't that the logic used by people who don't report rape and so on?". Friend countered with "Well, today Weinstein got his, didn't he?" and I went for an obvious counter of "Well, how many years and victims later, because someone didn't report him when they could?" Our conversation moved on to other things.</p>
      <p>I was still thinking about it this morning. Why did I try to do it? And the closest that I came up with was as follows. It might've been sparked by my mild annoyance from having to chase the guy around the map, stress accumulated from previous matches or something else about my yesterday, but I feel that the true answer was that I felt it was "right", even though I could not rationally explain to myself or my friend why, given my beliefs. It just was "right", as I've read so many times in media, mass and social. In addition, there was a sense of temptation - it was a mini-power trip that the "cancelling culture" I so dislike was supposedly feeding on, that I could, with a few keystrokes, make this guy worse off for what probably was some angry typing during a losing game. I also realized I've felt "lucky": the feeling of "empowerment" would not be as good if I was called a "bastard" - oh no, I  had hit the lottery with n-word and f-word, they gave my potential report the real power.</p>
      <p>All that looking player up and typing up the complaint happened so very fast and without my thinking about it, and took half a day for me to analyse  (and I am not sure I am done with it, since I'm still rambling on here). I remember a common phrase used in arguments about Stalin's repressions, by Sergei Dovlatov - "who wrote the 4 million denunciations?" Supposedly, people could report their neighbors and friends for a chance to get their apartment, or position at the institute, or as revenge for a lost game of chess - but the account will not mention that, only the "crimes against the Soviet state".</p>
      <p>I still struggle to understand the exact motivations of cancel culture warriors or Soviet informers - but I feel much closer to them today than I did the day before yesterday. The things you learn about yourself by playing Warcaft 3!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>