<post>
  <author>zzzyxas</author>
  <date>2020-02-23T02:00:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f53qhm/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_17/fiimahd/</link>
  <title>An Inside View On Institutions Preventing Child Abuse</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Here are some surefire ways to eliminate child abuse:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Global nuclear war</li>
        <li>Universal forced sterilization</li>
        <li>Sufficiently many paperclips</li>
      </ul>
      <p>If you're going to permit kids to exist, then there's going to be a risk of sexual abuse.
Eliminating adults doesn't help; children are perfectly capable of sexually abusing one another.
The best we can do is reduce this risk, just like every other domain where bad things happen why is this so hard to understand it's not like going insane and abandoning the principles that reduced e.g. automotive fatalities is helping anyo—</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Back in the day, BSA disallowed gay adult leaders on grounds of youth protection.
I'd expect most people to look at this and round it off to an unconvincing fig leaf for rampant homophobia.
There's almost certainly a lot of truth to that.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, I've worked two summers at BSA camps and they take youth protection seriously, to the point where I'm inclined to give some amount of credit to an "overprotective to the point of harm" explanation.
At both camps, we had substantive trainings on youth protection, and trainings that weren't about youth protection often found a way to work in youth protection.
"Youth protection is our number 1 policy," it was said.
For instance, we had a really cool wilderness survival program that culminated in taking the campers, armed with nothing but a pocket knife, into the woods for two days.
The only reason this program could run was because we found an adult leader who volunteered two days of his time to accompany an adult staff member to provide two-deep leadership on an overnight expedition.</p>
      <p>Overall, I grant +10 for higher-ups having such a commitment to youth protection that they were willing to implement policies that didn't even accomplish that goal, but also -100 for failing to check whether it actually worked.
I have more trouble deducting points from lower-level managers (typically college students) who didn't enforce two-deep leadership in any number of situations because the alternative would have been not doing the job.
However, the trainings were clear: youth protection, not scouting, was our number one policy, so they get -20 points.
In fairness, they did what they could such that, even if there was a predator on staff, they would have at least had a hard time sexually abusing any of the campers.</p>
      <hr />
      <blockquote>
        <p>Rather, I just wanted to raise the question of what a genuinely reasonable approach to protecting participants in child-centered government agencies and NGOs both might look like.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I have, in my life, worked at three types of organizations that take some sort of responsibility for children:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>The local charity conglomerate, targeting poor middle-school children.</li>
        <li>The BSA, both for Boy Scouts and Cub Scouts</li>
        <li>A special-needs preschool (ages 3–5).</li>
      </ol>
      <p>The <strong>charity conglomerate</strong>, whose mission was to run various sub-agencies (e.g. a food pantry) each with their own mission (distribute food, don't lose funding), had no experience running this sort of program.
Their youth protection policies were nonexistent.
If something had happened to one of the... &lt;20 children in our care... it is entirely possible that the organization that (to my knowledge, solely) provided services to a population of ~50k could have been wiped out.</p>
      <p>The <strong>special-needs preschool</strong>, whose mission was to take children with extremely special needs and help turn them into adults who could feed and toilet themselves—as opposed to the no-intervention alternative we had until at least the 1960s, which would have seen the same kids grow into adults who could do neither of those things independently—was heavily-regulated by the state, which is where its funding came from.
I underwent the state-mandated training and now my fingerprints are probably in a folder in Washington or something.</p>
      <p>Like all the other staff, I was a mandatory reporter.
This is something we took extremely seriously.
The children we worked with were extremely vulnerable: unlike typically-developing children of that age, most of the kids we worked with could not communicate with written/spoken language and often had physical disabilities that led them to incur more bruises than kids of that age already do.</p>
      <p>However, unlike BSA, sexual abuse was not something that was really on special needs preschool's mind.
For instance, sometimes kids get bruises under their pants, which happens all the fucking time no matter what because they're developmentally delayed 3–5-year-olds.
So, we document that we noticed a bruise or whatever at such-and-such a time so it definitely wasn't something we did.
However, one day, we have a daycare inspector come in (did I mention that this organization was extremely regulated?), which dissuaded our staff from taking a child to the bathroom and taking pictures of him with his pants off.
I know exactly what that sounds like, which is the point: physical abuse was very much a part of this organization's culture and sexual abuse wasn't.</p>
      <p>Now that I've left, this organization is staffed entirely by white women (n≈20).
Looking at the incentives created by the demographics featured in <em>To Catch a Predator</em> and the coverage Casey Anthony received, I suspect that they're responding to incentives and doing an <em>effective</em> job of it.
(No comment about whether they're doing a <em>good</em> job.)</p>
      <p>This brings us to <strong>BSA</strong>.
My opinion is that the BSA has the best youth protection policies of these three organizations.
In particular, the special needs preschool had no version of two-deep leadership, whereas BSA did.
If we have a system where BSA goes bankrupt over sexual abuse and special needs preschool doesn't, something has gone wrong.</p>
      <p>(Alternatively, we could say that men have a much higher relative rate of sexually abusing children, even if it's still absolutely small, and foist all of childcare on women.
This is likely detrimental to mothers, fathers, and the children who wouldn't have been abused either way, with ambiguous effects on children who would have been saved from abuse.)</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Sorry, the question is what a reasonable approach would have been; we'd already established that something had gone terribly wrong.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>I</strong>
      </p>
      <p>There's a bigger question about how, in general, to make large organizations effective that I don't know the answer to and doubt anyone else does.
It's not like BSA leadership was indifferent to the sexual abuse that is inevitable once you're serving 10<sup>6</sup> kids.
They put forth nontrivial effort to do concrete <em>things</em> to try to prevent it.
That sexual abuse nevertheless happened is a fact about an organization being inadequately effective, not indifferent or evil.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>II</strong>
      </p>
      <p>But I want to come back to the special needs preschool.
I got a bit of continuing education at special needs preschool: <em>active shooter training</em>.
Active shooter training is when two cops come in and stumble through a script handed to them by, I shit you not, Wal-Mart.
I feel nothing but overwhelming indifference for Wal-Mart, but I can believe that they have skin in the game, if for no other reason than they'd prefer to not have a mass shooting occur at one of their locations.
And so, our active shooter training came with some nice, concrete, evidence-based tactics for not dying in if someone tried to shoot up our preschool [1].</p>
      <p>Mass shootings provide something of a natural data set: you compare what the people who survived did to the people who died and find patterns.
There's any number of reasons that such a simplistic approach wouldn't work for child sexual abuse.
But I don't think it's beyond the realm of science.
If the research hasn't yet been done, then go out and do it yourself.
Or, more accurately, because you're an organization with no experience doing science, go out and find an organization that's good at doing this sort of science and hire <em>them</em> to figure it out.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>III</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Tort reform couldn't hurt.
I know that there's some legal scholars that have done some good work in developing good theory here, even if it hasn't yet promulgated to becoming law.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>IV</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Demand that we use the same risk-reducing approaches that we use everywhere else and have proven to work, rather than using approaches that have proven to not work.
It's totally reasonable to have emotional responses to child abuse—the only time I took a break when I was slogging through the state-mandated training for the special needs preschool was because they child abuse section was too emotionally difficult to do in one sitting—and there's probably something wrong with anyone who <em>doesn't</em> have a strong emotional response to it, but evolution granted us these neat higher-order reasoning abilities precisely so we could deal with evolutionarily-novel situations precisely like this.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>[1] Run; hide &amp; barricade; as a last resort, attack.
As it turns out, preschools are equipped entirely with implements that are designed to not be able to hurt anyone, no matter how they're used: we decided the best weapon we had at our disposal was a plastic <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Little-Tikes-Classic-Alligator-Teeter/dp/B000059EI8">alligator teeter totter</a>.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>