<post>
  <author>4bpp</author>
  <date>2020-04-25T01:40:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/foi4zrb/</link>
  <title>Diversity Casting as Nagging</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>My best attempt at vocalising why it would bother me (subjunctive because I have not so far been in the position of having media I care about get forced-looking diversity injected into it) is that it feels like something akin to nagging -- or, perhaps an even better metaphor, the PBF version of <a href="https://pbfcomics.com/comics/cave-explorer/">Cave Explorer</a>. Consuming a piece of fiction amounts to a sort of dialogue or transaction with the author(s): author says "humour me for a bit, we are going to imagine this fictional world and see where it gets us", and starts narrating a just-so story that might have happened in this world; as we progress through the story, I will ask the author some questions in my head, which hopefully eventually get answered by the story implicitly or explicitly, and in the end we both walk away entertained and with our curiosity about the setting satisfied. (This illusory dialogue is presumably not a one-way street for the author either, as when writing they have to constantly anticipate the questions the readers would ask in the imagined dialogue in <em>their</em> heads; and if the readers are unsatisfied with the author's answer, they will let the author know via the comment section or sales figures.)</p>
      <p>What is the imagined-dialogue version of the story getting preachy about the author's politics, though? It is as if you started having that collegial and interactive storytelling session, and suddenly the author tells you, "okay, now that I finally have your attention, <em>sit down</em>.", and launches into something that no longer amounts to having fun exploring a fictional setting together, but more into the author unilaterally chewing you out. You could pretend that you are still playing the game and ask the author some more questions the way you used to - like, what is the mechanism by which the people who lived in a tiny isolated mountain village for centuries exhibit a near-50-50 split into two visually distinct races? - but this is as likely to be deigned with a response as talking back to your mother after she has started chewing you out for your bad report card, having baited you out of your room with the promise of sweets. At this point, you ought to feel betrayed: you were promised a game of Cave Explorer, but actually it was just a ploy to lure you into the school bus. Will you lend this person your time and trust again next time they tell you to bear with them because you are going to play a game of Fictional World Explorer and it will be fun?</p>
      <p>Coming to think of it, there are some non-diversity examples of preachy media that trigger a very similar reaction in me. Further downthread, there is a subtree where people discuss the Log Horizon anime. Its second season has a <em>terrible</em> story arc where a side character (Akatsuki, the ninja girl) messes up this or that thing and falls into a despair spiral thinking she is sad and useless. After a lot of flailing around, the way this is resolved is... by her coming to the realisation that all her friends have her back, and she shouldn't try to solve problems alone, be independent or hide her issues from others. This is presented as the key insight that solves <em>all</em> problems, no self-improvement or overcoming of concrete external adversities required; and in the imagined consumer-author dialogue, you can imagine that asking any inconvenient questions ("what if she is actually inadequate and could do better by training?", "how would she distinguish this situation from one in which leaning on her friends would actually just have been an annoyance and waste of everyone's time?") would just earn you a disapproving glare and you'd be told to not talk back while being taught a much-overdue lesson. (See also: the second season of <em>Higurashi no Naku Koro ni</em>, wherein just believing in your nakama is the solution to murder-inducing paranoia, abusive parents and a sprawling medical conspiracy with military involvement.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>