<post>
  <author>BergilSunfyre</author>
  <date>2020-04-23T23:26:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/fodggnj/</link>
  <title>Constructing a Feel-Good Civil War Historiography</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I've thought about this sort of thing. The old "romantic south" historiography was basically a compromise to allow the South to revert to being patriotic Americans as quickly as possible. And it worked fine as a compromise between white Northerers and Southerners, but gradually fell apart once we started to care about what black people thought. We have recently convened on a new historiography, which meets the requirements of the ostensible heirs of white Northerners (I.E., the Blue Tribe.) and black American culture, but makes no attempt to welcome the Red Tribe, and indeed serves largely as a memnetic beatstick against them?</p>
      <p>Could we have a historiography of the Civil War that ends with an America that the modern involved parties, I.E., the red Tribe, the Blue Tribe and black American culture, can associate with, that's also true enough to survive contact with a primary source and gives us some cool Civil War films? I think we can. in Hackett-Fischerian terms, we just have to blame everything on the cavaliers. The plantation elite owned most of the slaves and provided most of the southern leadership, so why not hold them responsible for the whole mess. As has been observed, the modern Red Tribe is pretty much pure Borderer memnetic material, so they're excused the sins of their fathers, but we acknowledge that the civil war was totally about slavery. How could it not be, fighting against a bunch of crypto-aristocrats who would probably have enslaved white people if they thought they could get away with it! It's close enough to history for some awesome works of historical fiction, where heroic Union forces with an unusual preponderance of West Virginians and former Underground Railroad conductors fight against hordes of grey-clad mooks who the audience has some sympathy for, given how callously the real villains of the piece are throwing their lives away.</p>
      <p>Of course, this appeals to me ideologically as an unapologetic classical liberal individualist.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>