<post>
  <author>bsbbtnh</author>
  <date>2020-04-24T07:02:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/foeqy3v/</link>
  <title>Molding the Care/Harm Model Around Partisan Politics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Where does your brother fall with regards to abortion? Pro-lifers care for the fetus. Pro-choice cares for the woman. What's the 'harm' in each situation? With pro-lifers, the harm caused is up to 9-months of a woman carrying a baby she doesn't want, and a slight potential for death. With pro-choice, the harm is the guaranteed end of a fetus' life, and a miniscule chance of death for the mother, as well as possible mental health issues related to that choice.</p>
      <p>If your brother follows the care/harm model, he should be pro-life.</p>
      <p>But he'll probably hand wave that away and say that the life of a fetus hasn't 'began' so there's no value there.</p>
      <p>Where does he stand on climate change and the environment? Most people living today will not experience the negative consequences from climate change or damaging the environment. So we should exploit the environment to provide the best life for humans alive right now (caring). Yet most people would say "what about the generation that hasn't been born yet?" </p>
      <p>People are willing to use an inconsistent care/harm model that reinforces their political views.  But you can twist it anyway you want.</p>
      <p>Both parties use the care/harm model. One side wants to care for victims of harm, one wants to prevent harm to reduce victims.</p>
      <p>Healthcare. Break you leg? Liberals want to care for you. Conservatives want you to not break your leg in the first place, or buy insurance if you're going to do dangerous activities.</p>
      <p>Crime? Liberals want to reduce the number of criminals through social programs. Conservatives want to reduce the number of victims through self-defense.</p>
      <p>Rape? Similar. Liberals want to reduce the number of rapists. Some people realize rapes will always happen, so it's better to empower people so they don't become victims (gun, pepper spray, tasers, self-defense).</p>
      <p>Economics? Liberals want to reduce poverty by providing money to the poor, paid for by the rich. Conservatives want to reduce poverty by lowering taxes, allowing more spending which increases demand, and that demand leads to more jobs, which lift people out of poverty. Those coming out of poverty spend more, which increases demand, which leads to more jobs, which lifts more people out of poverty. </p>
      <p>Anybody who uses care/harm model to reinforce their political positions is just blind to what their opponents motivations are. </p>
      <p>No different than fairness/cheating. Liberals view Affirmative Action as fairness, conservatives see it as cheating. Liberals view meritocracy as cheating, because the rich are given a leg up in early education. Conservatives view it as the ultimate measure of fairness.</p>
      <p>It's easy as hell to apply 'morals' to your own ideology. Most people won't even attempt to apply them to their opposition. "If my position is moral, than my opponent's <em>must</em> be immoral."</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>