<post>
  <author>LushWithMoss</author>
  <date>2020-04-25T14:37:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/fojnr3c/</link>
  <title>Japanese Military Songs</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A (classical) interlude. In Shōwa 15 (1940), Nippon celebrated 2600th anniversay of its foundation by the Emperor Jimmu (神武天皇). 
Many <a href="https://www.jacar.go.jp/english/shuhou-english/timeline/nenpyo19401110.html">celebrations</a> and <a href="https://www.jacar.go.jp/english/shuhou-english/topics/topics02_04.html">events</a> 
were held and the first olympics in Asia were planned to take place in Tokyo, but were cancelled due to Japans intervention in China.</p>
      <p>But focusing on the music, Japanese government commissioned classical compositions from seven countries. 
The US declined, UKs Benjamin Brittens "Sinfonia da requiem" was rejected by the Japanese side for not being celebratory enough, 
Jacques <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kVP-N2D64Pk">Ibert</a> of Frances "Ouverture de fête", Ildebrando <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6KxSeRfbaHg">Pizzetti</a> of Italy's "Symphony in A Major", 
Hungaries Sándor <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aJjhukvhv50">Veress's</a> "Symphony No. 1", Germanies Richard <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZCde-o6szQA">Strauss's</a> "Japanische Festmusik (Op. 84)", 
Japans Hisato <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o_5h0zw0_-g">Ohzawa</a> (大澤壽人)'s "Symphony No. 3".</p>
      <p>The latter five countries entries <a href="https://www.prestomusic.com/classical/products/8048271--celebrating-concert-for-the-2600th-anniversary-of-the-japanese-imperial-era">were played</a> at the 
"Celebrating Concert for the 2600th Anniversary of the Japanese Imperial Era" on S15-12-14 (14th of December 1940).
Other compositions commisioned for the 2600th anniversary, but not THE concert, were: Shiro <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PkyME8tdZ-4">Fukai</a> (深井 史郎)'s Ballet Création, 
Isotaro Sugata's(須賀田礒太郎) Peaceful Dance of Two Dragons, Qunihico <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wXyjPhWRSVw">Hashimoto</a> (橋本 國彦)'s Symphony No.1 in D.</p>
      <p>10) Next Gunka <em>Getsu Getsu Ka Sui Moku Kin Kin (月月火水木金金, Monday, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, Friday, and Friday)</em>, from 
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fFJYSHnMM6Q">Shōwa 15</a> (1940) with music by Eguchi Yoshi (江口 夜詩) and lyrics by Takahashi Shunsaku (高橋俊策) 
central lyrical idea of abolishing weekends came from a quip by a navy colonel in Meiji 41 (1908). In light of "5:5:3"  treaty of Taishō 10 (1922), which limited Japanese
capital and secondary ship tonnage to .6 of that of the US and also .6 of that of the UK, more diligence was required if Japan was to overcome this handicap. 
Its composer was a member of a navy military band.
It was covered by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RNr0mzcTYVc">'70s</a> Japanese comedy group The Drifters.
Lyrics:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>'Tis the morning, 'tis the dawn,/ The tanned chests inhale the breath of tide,/ It is full of pride of a man of the sea/
Working at the fleet/ Monday, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday,/Thursday, Friday, and Friday.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>11) More hostile lyrics characterize <em>Eikoku tōyō kantai kaimetsu (英国東洋艦隊潰滅, British Oriental Fleet Sunk)</em>, from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZWPvNIz8KLo">Shōwa 16</a> (1941) with music by <strong>Yūji Koseki (古関裕而)</strong> and lyrics by Takahashi Kikutarou (高橋掬太郎)
While most Gunka upto this point in time have been more about praising Japan and her forces, rather than denigrating her enemies, such positive Gunka decline in number. 
This one is about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinking_of_Prince_of_Wales_and_Repulse">Naval Battle of Malaya</a> of S16-12-10 (10th of December 1941) in which
Japan sunk the battleship "HMS Prince of Wales" and the battlecruiser "HMS Repulse", at the cost of four aicraft and two seaplanes. 
Occuring just three after the Pearl Harbour strike, it showed the strength of aerial assault against maritime targets. Lyrics:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>It was devastated. It was devastated./ British eastern fleet was devastated./ It has sunk right now off Kuantan, Malay Peninsula/ 
They are distinguished services, eagle fighters of the sea./ Repulse sank! Prince of Wales sank!</p>
        <p>We fought the battle.We fought the battle./ We the tough fought the battle./ Just now, the fate of the empire depends upon us./ 
The eastern fleet from Britain being arrogant,/ We sank it! To the nasty sea!</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>12) Another Anglophobic Gunka is <em>Amerika Bakugeki (アメリカ爆撃, Bombing America)</em>, from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-rwqBIzHZ8M">Shōwa 17</a> (1942) with music by <strong>Koseki Yūji (古関裕而)</strong> and lyrics by Toshio Nomura (野村俊夫).
Its composer also wrote <a href="https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%8F%A4%E9%96%A2%E8%A3%95%E8%80%8C#%E4%B8%BB%E3%81%AA%E4%BD%9C%E5%93%81">many other songs</a>, among them "Bells of Nagasaki"(長崎の鐘) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z-000VudpMg">video</a>.
Lyrics are rather fantastical in that Japans capabilities only allowed her to use incendiary balloons and not bombs, to strike at the continental US.
Italian <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7nwWEJeUpss">song</a> "Adesso viene il bello" similiarly exaggerates the threat that Axis bombers posed to the Anglos. Lyrics:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Bombing America mainland, we have been looking forward to this day/ Pray to God and listen to the [air defense] sirens starting to blow/ 
That is a song to mourn to in the U.S./ Don't panic, it's too late! We are invincible fighting troops!</p>
        <p>The U.S. is enemy of whole of Asia. Continue to attack until they whine!/ We trained hard to have this day/ 
Here we go! My war comrades!/ Knocking out! Hurling bombs! We are invincible fighting troops!</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>13) Similiarly divorced from facts on the ground was <em>Shori no Hi made (勝利の日まで, Till the Day of Victory)</em>, from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sY0Xu7hNxd4">Shōwa 19</a> (1944) with music from Koga Masa (古賀 政男) and 
lyrics by Hachirou Satou (サトウハチロー). With the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timeline_of_World_War_II_(1944)#/media/File:1944-05-15JapWW2BattlefrontAtlas.jpg">Red</a> 
closing in on Japan, a song to raise the morale on the home front was ordered by the NHK. A comedy containg the song was released on S20-01-25 (25th of January 1945),
but later American invaders destroyed all copies of it. <a href="https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%B5%E3%83%88%E3%82%A6%E3%83%8F%E3%83%81%E3%83%AD%E3%83%BC#%E4%BD%9C%E5%93%81%E7%B4%B9%E4%BB%8B">Lyricist</a> of this Gunka was quite prolific, and his other works includes also the lyrics for previously mentioned "Bells of Nagasaki"(長崎の鐘)" 
and for the Japan's first feature length anime Momotaro: Sacred Sailors (桃太郎 海の神兵) he wrote the lyrics for <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3KpfRUrvlpA">AIUEO no Uta</a> (アイウエオの歌), with music by <strong>Yūji Koseki (古関裕而)</strong>.
The composer of this Gunka, an important figure in postwar popular music, is said to have wrote over 5000 songs. Lyrics:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Our eyes looking up/ At the Rising Sun flag/ Waving on the hill/ Are filling with tears of appreciation,/ The fire in our hearts starts kindling,/ 
We will fight to the best of our strength,/ Till the Day of Victory,/ Till the Day of Victory.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In conclusion one sees that Meiji Restoration and its consequences have been a mixed blessing for Japan, while she gained the title of First Industrialised Asian Power,
and temporary status of Asian Piedmont it also caused the death of Japan as a state with unique political system and distinict culture, the emergence of
Japan as merely another Parliamentary Democracy, albeit one in which the Ceremonial Head of State wears a Sokutai, and not a Top-Hat, Crown or a Baseball Cap and in which they play and compose songs and symphonies indistinguishable from those from Europe. 
It further caused her to overextended herself in her attempts to enforce the Asian Munroe Doctrine, and has since the occupation been irrelevant
in international politics. </p>
      <p>The Restoration also set the precedent of the West allowing her only advantage, technology, to be given freely to other peoples, without those peoples accepting to be
ruled by Westerners. The most obvious negative conseqeunce of this "dissemination of industry", currently, are the hypothesised "Chinese Century" and 
outsourcing that causes the West to be dependant on others for its very survival and lowers Western wages, leading to a rise in populism.</p>
      <p>sources:</p>
      <p>a) <a href="http://cubeaki.dip.jp/gunka/">http://cubeaki.dip.jp/gunka/</a> [Japanese]</p>
      <p>b) <a href="https://www.nihongunka.com/">https://www.nihongunka.com/</a> [Russian]</p>
      <p>c) <a href="http://gunka.sakura.ne.jp/en/index.html">http://gunka.sakura.ne.jp/en/index.html</a>  [English]</p>
      <p>Satoshi Sugita (1972): Cherry blossoms and rising sun: a systematic and objective analysis of gunka (Japanese war songs) in five historical periods (1868-1945)</p>
      <p>SJ McClimon (2011): Music, politics and memory: Japanese military songs in war and peace</p>
      <p>Kodama Takeshi: Popular songs of the Meiji Era - A Study of Hayariuta and their popularity</p>
      <p>Maulia DINI, Ruhanisa LIYANA, Febrina RIA (2018): Aikoku Koushinkyoku Song, Japanese Heritage in West Sumatera Period 1943-1945: A Historical Record and in Memoriam</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>