<post>
  <author>mokoroo</author>
  <date>2020-04-25T14:59:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/fojpti3/</link>
  <title>One More Drop of Lead in the Academy's Coinage</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Part of this just feels like an immense boo outgroup, and that's interesting because of who the author is.</p>
      <p>If this had been posted off, say, Facebook, or some no-name feminist blogger, I would have reported this. Weakmanning at its finest, something absurd posted by some fringe person looking for notoriety.</p>
      <p>But this is from a professor at Oxford, which is more-or-less the top of prestige in terms of the academy - perhaps Oxford stands above or below Harvard, but to the average person "professor at big ultra-famous university" is more-or-less the maximum prestige you can get out of "professor" without adding things like "Nobel Prize" to the list of accolades.</p>
      <p>So rather than address any points she's making, I think this is a great point to use to go into meta-discussion about the ailing nature of the academy's grasp on trustworthiness.</p>
      <p>I personally believe, like the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/g717ft/two_views_of_survey_data_the_modal_motte_user_a/">modal user of this sub</a> that anthropogenic climate change is occurring. </p>
      <p>Lots of people don't, though.</p>
      <p>One reason that I think contributes is a group of potential beliefs <em>about</em> the academy. Firstly that the academy is right about everything, or at least right <em>enough</em> that "putting your faith in science" is always going to work out. The second is that the academy is lying to you about most things and really you can't believe much it says - it'll get the verifiable questions right provided that there's no political will leaning the other way, but that's about it. The third is a more complex belief where you get close enough to the academy to see that well, some of the psychologists are clearly lying, the engineers are pretty good, the biologists are ok, the gender studies people are for the most part making things up, the mathematicians might be lying or telling the truth but it doesn't seem to actually matter, and so on and so forth.</p>
      <p>I think there was a SSC post about this, or I might be generating that memory because it seems like the sort of thing Scott would write about, but there's an important phenomenon I can't remember the name of so I'm just going to call 'dilution' because it sums everything up.</p>
      <p>The position the academy is in vaguely analogises to the position of the word 'racist'. It still holds a lot of power, but the more you call, say, <a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.com.au/entry/milk-white-supremacy-racism_n_5bffad35e4b0864f4f6a3e28?ri18n=true&amp;guccounter=1">milk racist</a> the less people are concerned about the other people and things you call racist. If you associate milk and, say, refusing to rent houses to black people, sure, you've tainted milk, but you've also to some degree lifted up actual prejudice. This is part of the normal cycle of using an epithet - a word gets coined, becomes powerful, and is overused to the point of uselessness at which point we need a new one. If words weren't renewable resources we'd be speaking in grunts by now.</p>
      <p>The academy is in the same spot.</p>
      <p>If you're in a position to sort of see the academy and what parts of the sclerotic machine still seem to be functioning okay, you'll rapidly notice that the reason we trust our STEM group is that they're one of two things - they're either verifiable, or don't matter to the ordinary person. </p>
      <p>I did an undergrad in maths at a fairly ordinary institution, but it was enough for me to grasp the basis of mathematics in the sense I can see the mechanisms for verification and that they work. A reasonably simplified exposition on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%E2%80%93Tao_theorem">Green-Tao Theorem</a> is 30 pages, and I have no intention of ever going over the work myself to try and verify it, but I understand enough how the proof could be verified and trust enough in the competence and honesty of the field in this case that the result is correct.</p>
      <p>To me personally, mathematics is verifiable - some small part of it, to a degree. And I trust in the rest because of what I understand of that small part. To the average person, though, it's not. Verifiability comes to the average person in the form of physical proof - engineers work is verified by bridges and skyscrapers, the work of a doctor is verified by curing disease, and so on and so forth.</p>
      <p>The reason mathematics gets a free pass is because it doesn't matter to the ordinary person. If the Green-Tao Theorem had all been a great hoax and the mathematics community had fallen for it it would be a lot of egg on faces, but the result doesn't inform policy, or our view of human behaviour, or what we should feed our children, or so on and so forth. Maths can sit in the corner mumbling about transfinite numbers because no matter the result it won't change our views on trans people.</p>
      <p>Conversely engineering matters a <em>lot</em> to the ordinary person. While they might not care as such as to what the equation for tensile strength is, if we changed it and forced all engineers (at gunpoint, say) to use a new and completely wrong equation in their plans, a lot of people would die or be hurt. However, the work is verified by reality - people trust engineers when they tell them how to build a bridge because they might die if they don't.</p>
      <p>The problem arises at the next juncture. It's easy enough for people to trust engineers. But what about when they need to trust climate scientists?</p>
      <p>"Well", you might say, "Climate science is ultimately modelling of our climate, it's not opining on gender roles or telling people parts of their religion is false like evolution. Why <em>shouldn't</em> people trust it?"</p>
      <p>Because when the academy puts out two things - verifiable useful things such as engineering and unverifiable nonsense such as much of our replication crisis-savaged schools of science combined with bizarre ideological rants (I still recall Fine's Testosterone Rex as the most astounding denial of reality - to deny male and female sexual reproductive variability in a world where Genghis Khan existed was a moment where it was fairly obvious that the academy wasn't particularly trustworthy on issues of gender ), people with passing familiarity with the academy might divide them by school of thought. Sociology out - it's infested with people who have strong incentives and desires to see a certain ideology proliferate. Physics in - you can be the most devoted communist but you won't change f = ma, and so on and so forth.</p>
      <p>For people who aren't close to the academy at all that's not a viable strategy. Rather, anything you can easily verify <em>or</em> things that make zero social demands are probably trustworthy. Engineering? Trustworthy. Mathematics? Weird, but trustworthy. Look at those blackboards. Medicine? Definitely trustworthy, doctors save lives.</p>
      <p>As it happens, the parts you can check <em>and</em> make social demands are often false. Men and women exactly the same brain-wise? Average person wouldn't believe that in a million years! Women and men equally primed to be promiscuous and 'spread their genes'? Only an idiot would believe that. Weird gender things that go against common sense - all obviously false. But they're mixed in with say, evolution, which you can't verify. And climate science, which you can't verify. But global warming is asking you to make sacrifices - taxes, more expensive fuel, electricity, less oil jobs, etc, etc. But when it comes to the academy making social demands on statements you <em>can</em> verify, those statements tend to be lies.</p>
      <p>Why on earth would you let them lie to you about other things?</p>
      <p>Some people call this anti-intellectualism, but it's more of an <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/03/repost-epistemic-learned-helplessness/">epistemic learned helplessness</a> - if I can't trust you, I'm just going to ignore the things you say and go do my own thing. Stop rolling coal? Eat shit, hippy. You've taken a dump in the drink you're trying to sell me, and perhaps it <em>is</em> otherwise good fresh water, but all the parts I've tested myself have smelt <em>bad</em>. When I see rural poor people rejecting climate science out of hand I used to get mad at them, now I get mad at the academy for debasing their coinage so badly people won't take it unless you let them <a href="https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/TastyGold">bite it</a> first.</p>
      <p>This article is just one more drop of lead in the academy's coinage mix.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>