<post>
  <author>NoWitandNoSkill</author>
  <date>2020-04-25T03:05:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/foid6fj/</link>
  <title>Where Ezra Klein Went Wrong in the Klein-Harris Debate</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think Klein really bungled that debate because the only relevant point in the whole discussion, which Klein does not make until over half way through the discussion, is the following:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Ezra Klein</p>
        <p>I doubt that we have, given the experiment we have run in this country, given the centuries of slavery and segregation and oppression, given locking people out of jobs, out of good schools, out of building wealth, out of going into top professions, out of being part of the social networks that help you advance; the amount of violence and terror and trauma that we have inflicted on African Americans in this country, I absolutely doubt — I truly, to the core of my being, doubt — that we are at a place where any of us should have confidence saying that the differences we see in individuals now reflect intrinsic group capacity. I think that at every other point in America history where we have said that —</p>
        <p>Sam Harris</p>
        <p>But even Murray wouldn’t say that.</p>
        <p>Ezra Klein</p>
        <p>That is exactly what Murray says.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Followed later by:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Ezra Klein</p>
        <p>I think there is what you would call confusion here. I do think it’s just important to say this. I have not criticized you, and I continue to not, for having the conversation. I’ve criticized you for having the conversation without dealing with and separating it out and thinking through the context and the weight of American history on it.</p>
        <p>Sam Harris</p>
        <p>The weight of American history is completely irrelevant to—</p>
        <p>Ezra Klein</p>
        <p>It can’t possibly be irrelevant on something that even you admit is environmental!</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The point Ezra seems to be making is that you cannot measure IQ differences between groups, claim factors for differences are both heredity and environmental, but then ignore the environmental impact of America's treatment of black people when drawing conclusions from the data. In Ezra's mind, it is highly plausible that every hint of difference or inferiority is a direct result only of the way black people were universally, horribly abused for hundreds of years. For Murray to say that IQ differences are immutable is to ignore America's racist history. And Klein's main beef with Harris is that Harris didn't push Murray on something so obvious. When Harris says "the weight of American history is completely irrelevant" he is obviously incorrect. "The science" relies entirely on an assumption about the impact of American history. And Murray's assumption is one that many believe can only be made by someone working within a racist tradition of making that same assumption. </p>
      <p>Klein brings this up explicitly in the interview. He claims that "the science" of Murray is in no way different from "the science" of racist Europeans hundreds of years earlier, who looked at outcomes in the present, assumed the historical context was not the cause of the outcome, and concluded that the differences were innate. When Klein says "Tell me why it is unfair to put your conversation in that lineage. Why the burden of proof is not actually on you to say here is why it is different this time." He is NOT saying that the <em>conclusion</em> is in a racist lineage and is therefore invalid. He is saying <em>the scientidic method itself</em> that led to those conclusions appears identical to the entirely unscientific method of reasoning used by those historical racists. He is saying Murray is in a racist lineage of failing to account for highly relevant data when performing analysis. It is up to Murray, or to Harris if he wants to defend him, to show how the method was different this time. </p>
      <p>The fact that large numbers of people have concluded from this debate that Klein was arguing that the science is irrelevant in light of America's racist past, apparently what Harris thought he was claiming also, is remarkable. This very thread is remarkable to me. I can't help but see it as a strawman. But it's really all on Klein for being so unclear - he could not stay on point.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>