<post>
  <author>oaklandbrokeland</author>
  <date>2020-04-23T17:11:35Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/fobob8q/</link>
  <title>Self-Improvement and the Art of Feeling Like Trash In Your Bed</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>What does drug withdrawal tell us about self-improvement and the art of feeling shitty in your bed?</strong>
      </p>
      <hr />
      <p>Imagine for a moment that you live in a society which is completely addicted to alcohol. Everyone drinks, and everyone starts drinking at a young age. The thought of someone quitting alcohol has simply never come up before. Everyone has 5 drinks a night, firmly fitting the definition of alcoholism. Through some random series of events, you happen to accidentally quit alcohol -- which was a debilitating process you'd never begin of your own volition -- and notice weirdly <em>positive</em> benefits. "This is so strange," you think. "For around 40 days I felt like complete shit, and couldn't get anything done, but I <em>swear</em> I feel amazing now, better than I ever have. And I can think more clearly and accomplish more. Even my heart rate seems lower. But I felt like <em>bad</em> for so long. How could it be?" </p>
      <p>Soon after your experience, you tell your closest friends of what transpired. "Wait, but you just texted me two weeks ago that you were spending 14 hours in bed," says Dubito. "And now you're telling me after <em>all of that</em>, after weeks of feeling like shit, you magically began to feel incredible?" </p>
      <p>Aporia was similarly skeptical. "By what mechanism would your new change make you feel the worst you've ever felt, and yet the best you've ever felt afterward? When you repair a car, is it worse before it's better? When you learn something, do you know of less before you know of more?"</p>
      <p>After a couple hours of discussion, you finally persuade Dubito and Aporia to give up alcohol. But two weeks later, with <em>Vodka Titi</em> in their hands, they angrily confront you outside your home. "We did exactly what you said," went Dubito. "We stopped drinking and we only felt <em>worse</em>. You said we would feel better! I did as you said for two whole weeks and no good has come of it but nausea, sadness, anxiety, and one less friend!"</p>
      <hr />
      <p>There's a view of addiction that I find dangerous, which is that <em>substance</em> dependence is a more legitimate form of addiction than <em>phenomenon</em> dependence. Alcoholism and opiate addictions are <em>real</em> addictions, they say: not only does your body experience physical withdrawal, but you also become psychologically dependent. But ask a recent widow whether she wouldn't undergo feeling queasy, achy, and mentally confused for years in exchange for her husband back. Ask a parent whether she wouldn't gladly sacrifice a kidney to have her child back. Ask a son whether he wouldn't experience fatigue, aches, pains, broken bones, and confusion in a 9-month deployment in Iraq if it meant he could save his brother's life. Ask a father whether he wouldn't sacrifice four years of sleep in exchange for raising a child. And ask an abuse victim whether she wouldn't go back to her partner despite the constant physical abuse. The physical side of addiction, while important from a clinical perspective, is a <em>red herring</em> in understanding what legitimizes an addiction -- that is, what makes addiction so <em>bad</em>. It is the psychological dependence which leads a recovered heroin addict back to heroin in spite of having recovered from the physical withdrawals -- he would pick the psychological (<em>qua</em> phenomenon) dependence over the physical withdrawal <em>time and time again</em>. </p>
      <p>If the psychological, or "phenomenal", dependence is what makes addiction so shitty, then I wonder to what extent phenomenal addiction affects our daily life, particularly from a self-improvement or "positive change" perspective. There is no real difference between an addiction to a person, an addiction to a behavior, or an addiction to a substance. While it might appear different within your body, the <em>addictive</em> part of it is purely phenomenal -- there is no emotional difference between one or the other (benzos the exception). So how many people are addicts without knowing it? It's not uncommon to hear about someone making some personal change and failing with two weeks. Often the method is blamed, and not the addiction. </p>
      <hr />
      <p>"Real" drug addicts are often expected to, even <em>told</em> to spend more time in bed and to take it easy for a while. This is a curious thing. Because spending more time in bed is <em>bad</em>. Not being productive is <em>bad</em>. We can't just do these things if we can help it, us normal people. What diet program tells you to spend three extra hours feeling sad in bed? But in drug treatment centers around America, spending more time in bed and doing fewer things is what almost all recovering addicts do. There is no shame or anxiety or sense of personal failing when this happens, because it's expected -- with the <em>knowledge</em> that they will be better off at the end of the recovery process. Now in some phenomenal addictions this is permissible, e.g. in the death of a loved one. When in grief, a person can sleep as much or as little as they want, and this is merely an expected part of the process. But what other phenomenal addictions? What about for someone addicted to junk food? Soda? (if the <em>President</em> cannot quit drinking 12 cans of soda a day, allow me to be the first to boldly claim that soda addiction is as serious as heroin from an emotional perspective.) Gaming? Social media? A teenager in the UK just killed herself because "the coronavirus lockdown felt like 300 years". Is this not an addiction to social engagement? It drove her to kill herself -- how is this not an addiction? My (household name extremely successful) neighbor lost his wife and house in a divorce because he couldn't stop fucking whores. Is this not an addiction? No reasonable man would choose a whore over a house.</p>
      <p>I say: these and many more are all addictions. Further: these and many more are all <em>equally</em> addictions and should be <em>treated</em> as addictions. Lastly: nearly every shortcoming we have and improvement we want to make in ourselves is rooted in addiction, and should factor in treatment for addiction. What does this mean practically? If you want to significantly improve yourself, you should <em>expect</em> that you are going to have to feel shitty and tired in bed for some periods, and should plan to feel quite shitty for at least a week.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>