<post>
  <author>PachucaSunset</author>
  <date>2020-04-25T14:04:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g5j7zm/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_7/fojkt0b/</link>
  <title>COVID-19, Respiratory Diseases, Strokes, and When to Panic</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/common-cold-flu-can-increase-risk-of-stroke-in-kids/">Common cold and flu can increase risk of stroke in kids</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Comparing two groups of more than 350 children -- one set had suffered "ischemic" clot-based strokes and the other had not -- researchers found that those with stroke were six times more likely to have had a minor infection the previous week than those who didn't have a stroke.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>...</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Of all participants, 18 percent of those with stroke had an infection -- including flu, colds, or to a lesser extent, urinary tract or gastrointestinal infections -- in the prior week. Only 3 percent of the children who didn't have a stroke had had an infection the week before. The association between infection and stroke was short-lived, lasting no longer than a week, experts noted.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, children who had received some, few or none of their routine vaccinations were seven times more likely to have a stroke than those who received most or all of their vaccinations.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="https://newsroom.heart.org/news/flu-flu-like-illnesses-linked-to-increased-risk-of-stroke-neck-artery-tears">Flu, flu-like illnesses linked to increased risk of stroke, neck artery tears</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>researchers found that having a flu-like illness increased the odds of having a stroke by nearly 40 percent over the next 15 days.  This increased risk remained up to one year.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>...</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>There are many proposed mechanisms behind the flu-stroke link, but no definitive reason has been described to explain the association. Researchers suspect it could be due to inflammation caused by the infection.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19355997">Infection, its treatment and the risk for stroke</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Besides the established stroke risk factors (e.g. hypertension, diabetes, hypercholesterolemia, atrial fibrillation) both acute and chronic infectious diseases have emerged as risk factors for stroke. Mainly acute respiratory tract infection but also urinary tract infections independently increase the risk of ischemic stroke. Such additional risk was shown to be highest for infection within 3 days before ischemia and the risk steadily declines with increasing time intervals between infection and stroke. Associations between stroke incidence and mortality and influenza epidemics have been demonstrated. Observational studies showed an inverse association between influenza vaccination and stroke risk; however, interventional studies in this field have not been performed so far.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Sorry for the link dump, but I really wanted to drive the point home. As with my prior comments on GGO, although it's concerning to see increased stroke in the wake of COVID-19, this isn't unprecedented for a respiratory infection. So far it appears to be a rare complication, thankfully.</p>
      <p>PSA: whenever you encounter a claim like "COVID-19 is also causing [X]" or "People with COVID-19 are also dying/suffering from [X]," and [X] is some scary debilitating condition, do your own research to see if this has been reported for other infectious diseases, and adjust your priors accordingly. </p>
      <p>While it remains to be seen if COVID-19 causes these problems more frequently than other pathogens, it is largely a difference of degree, rather than kind. There are <em>many</em> ways things can go wrong in the normal course of infection.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>