<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2020-05-27T20:40:12Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fs0mbdr/</link>
  <title>Every Society Restricts Speech of Opposing Ideologies</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's really interesting to me that people seem to struggle with the inevitability of this. </p>
      <p>Think back to before the internet. In every major western country, including the United States, obscenity laws existed until the late 20th century. These affected everything from pornography to discussions of contraceptive methods. In an age before digital media, the federal government effectively banned the transport by mail of anything it disapproved of. Almost all states passed further laws. Per Wikipedia:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In places such as Washington, D.C., where the federal government has direct jurisdiction, the act also made it a misdemeanor, punishable by fine and imprisonment, to sell, give away, or have in possession any "obscene" publication. Half of the states passed similar anti-obscenity statutes that also banned possession and sale of obscene materials.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>What was the definition of obscenity? </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>obscenity was material whose "dominant theme taken as a whole appeals to the prurient interest" to the "average person, applying contemporary community standards," and was, "utterly without redeeming social importance."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Given 'contemporary community standards' is euphemism for 'what people who went to Harvard and Yale Law think everyone else should be able to consume', this would seem to apply to 'things Twitter/Facebook/Google are censoring' pretty easily. </p>
      <hr />
      <p>
        <strong>Every society has historically restricted speech it considers in opposition to its guiding ideology</strong>. This includes earlier forms of the United States. It was always naive and stupid to assume that the internet would remain free of this guiding desire (by politicians and other powerful economic and cultural interests) forever. If you're in established power and someone is printing propaganda against you and the guiding cultural and social mores of your civilizaton, are you now supposed to allow it because "it's, like, the internet bro - it's free". Obviously not. </p>
      <p>None of that is to say I approve of the guiding cultural and social mores of our civilization - they're pretty trash if you ask me - but they are the views of those in power. And at some point they were always going to be exerted online.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>