<post>
  <author>Faceh</author>
  <date>2020-05-29T16:30:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fs7qg6i/</link>
  <title>Why Not Give In To Violent Impulses Against Rioters?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I assume this is just your initial reaction that is ultimately mediated by the 'higher' thinking of your rational mind.</p>
      <p>In either case, I think one reason it causes such revulsion is there's a reminder of how thin the veneer of civility is in some areas. You look around at your neighbors and are forced to wonder which of them would immediately drop their basic 'decency' and start looting and burning and otherwise demolishing the neighborhood you've both <em>ostensibly</em> chosen and agreed to maintain.</p>
      <p>The barriers between order and chaos are not so thick as we'd like to think. At least in some places. We'd rather not be shown this fact.</p>
      <p>And of course they're doing it on <em>our</em> nation's soil, sullying <em>our</em> nation's good name, and otherwise violating the general rules of how you go about voicing your earnest concerns whilst respecting the interests of your fellow citizen.</p>
      <p>As you say, why should they expect to be shielded by the same contract and social norms they eagerly flout? How dare they? </p>
      <p>Well, because we can <em>afford</em> to let it happen, for the most part. One of the benefits of civilization is surplus wealth that is squirreled away just to be used when things break down. </p>
      <p>Not that we wouldn't get angry at those who break things but its more like, I guess, a child throwing a tantrum and pushing over chairs and breaking plates. Once the tantrum is thrown, you clean up, fix, or buy replacements and keep moving. We don't kick the child out of the house and force him into indentured servitude to pay back everything. </p>
      <p>If we were a poorer society then we might react more harshly. We're not so poor.</p>
      <p>For my part, I am moving towards the conclusion that most street-level actions aren't likely to generate positive changes anyway. A sustained and directed campaign might, but so many of these are now just spontaneous, opportunistic, and completely uncoordinated actions that arise purely from self-interest and object-level thinking. It creates entropy without doing useful <em>work.</em></p>
      <p>
        <em>Armed</em> protest seems significantly more likely to generate a decent response, but even so, is not likely to create a lasting change for the better.</p>
      <p>I haven't been able to form a conclusion as to whether a sustained, directed, <em>armed</em> campaign might actually work towards getting quick concessions or not. It has precedent.</p>
      <p>But the government usually seems to care little about large groups gathered in public spaces yelling slogans since the political implications are minimal, when it comes time for actual legislation or elections.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I find myself thinking that if Trump were to send in the tanks and gun down every last member of these mobs, openly and without any discrimination on the basis of race or gender or age, it would be one of the few decent decisions (I support the Supreme Court justices chosen, but that would have happened under any GOP figurehead) of his presidency so far.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think the political calculus would very, VERY much not favor such an action. We have such wealth in this country that most of damage the rioters do will be undone and fixed and will make barely a dent in our accumulated wealth. Even a full week of constant riots wouldn't be 'noticeable' in the grand scheme, so letting them peter out is probably the right choice. The damage of sending tanks in to gun down U.S. citizens (as much as we might like to exile them to the desert and forget they were ever our countrymen) is, in my view, not so easily repaired, and would likely as not trigger increasing violence in response.</p>
      <p>They've measurably harmed their own community, they've weakened (or shown the weakness of) the social fabric in their city, and the damage to the small business owners and such is more severe, and possibly not recoverable I am sure. And that kind of disregard for the fellow citizen, who is ostensibly your ally and friend, probably triggers deep-rooted feelings about tribal loyalty that we've evolved to maintain.</p>
      <p>But giving in to the gut-level reaction is definitely not how I'd want to see the Federal Government respond.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>