<post>
  <author>FCfromSSC</author>
  <date>2020-05-29T07:25:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fs6evwr/</link>
  <title>The Power of Violence to Secure Change</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Is it, though?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Fuck yeah it is. Insert the Heinlein quote here. Ask the Southerners if Sherman burning down Georgia and the northern army shooting their husbands and sons into worm food changed a thing or two. Ask the freed blacks if KKK violence constrained their new options. In particular, violence that can't be effectively <em>punished or escaped</em> is super effective at making you change what you're doing.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I'm sure people will dispute the older left-wing groups, but bear in mind that they wanted a literal communist revolution.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>My finger doesn't pick which buttons I type. My brain does. There is an influence gradient, and the people committing, planning, and even explicitly encouraging the violence are at the very bottom of it. The people contextualizing, defending, and exploiting that violence for actual political gain are almost universally much higher on the gradient, not least because they aren't violent criminals.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>MLK is the patron saint of white liberals, not Huey Newton.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>MLK's success was greatly enhanced by the fact that, if his appeal was rejected, the alternative was race riots and possibly a race war. If the alternative was black people quietly accepting their status as second-class citizens, the civil rights era might have gone quite differently.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>People in this thread are claiming that BLM was a deep state project to stir up racial tension and beat Trump. How'd that work out?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't think that's the claim at all. I think the claim is that BLM was intended to exploit and magnify racial tension, and that when it started looking like this iteration of the strategy was backfiring, the breaks were applied. Once the election was over, the breaks were removed via things like the 1619 project and similar rhetoric. And now we're seeing major riots again, and I think we'll see people defending those riots again.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>What I was hinting at in the OP was that there still needs to be an inciting incident, one that actually gets people in the streets, one that the contextualizing and defending is a reaction to. And I don't get how this model gets from resentment and muttering to riots and violence unless you're assuming that the rhetoric itself is causing it.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>For a fire, you need heat, fuel, and oxygen. Of those, generally the oxygen is the easiest to obtain. "Inciting incidents" are the equivalent of oxygen; in a nation the size of ours, there are probably dozens of potential inciting incidents a day, and that's excluding the ones that can simply be manufactured from whole cloth.  The fuel is the narrative: it's stable long-term, and provides the potential energy. The specific story is the heat: it connects the oxygen of random violent incidents to the fuel of the narrative, creating a runaway reaction.</p>
      <p>There's variance, of course. A compressed air line is going to feed a big fire way better than a paper fan. The incident we're looking at genuinely is extremely unusual in the clarity and sheer horror it provides. But a lot of the damage it's doing is being done because of the narrative that incident is connected to, and the narrative is there because people built it intentionally and with great care and effort. And they built it because it benefited their values to do so.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Most people will see this video and see a man who had at most, committed a non-violent crime get suffocated to death by a policeman who didn't seem to care if he lived or died.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I remember a very similar case, maybe ten years back, where a white homeless dude got arrested by the cops, handcuffed, put face down, and then one of the cops put a knee on his back. The dude spent something like ten, maybe fifteen minutes pleading that he couldn't breath, pleading for them to let up, pleading for mercy, crying out for his parents, before he suffocated to death, and while this was happening the cops stood around laughing and making fun of him and generally shooting the shit. All this was caught on video, with audio.</p>
      <p>No riots happened then. I don't think the video made the national news in any big way. And that isn't surprising to me.</p>
      <p>This video hit, and now three days later we have a major riot. And I don't think anyone is surprised by that, because there is a narrative that tells us that this killing isn't an isolated incident, it's part of a vast, systematic, unjust oppression that branches into every facet of modern life, and whose roots burrow through every moment of our history. And we all know what when one of these stories blows up big, the chance of a riot is relatively high.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I question if the majority of the rioters know or care about what the left-wing press has to say about them, even if it is complimentary.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I bet a large majority of the rioters have strongly positive opinions about the BLM movement, and have strong opinions about how and why the police are racist against black people, and strong opinions about why rioting is an appropriate response. Those opinions are coordinated, strengthened and cohered by progressive culture generally, of which the press, academia, and activists are the vanguard. I readily agree that most of them don't have a favorite NYT columnist. That doesn't mean that the ideas don't penetrate down to the level of the people stealing and burning shit.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>