<post>
  <author>Mexatt</author>
  <date>2020-05-26T20:38:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/frwprn0/</link>
  <title>The Continuing Cyclic Pattern of China</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Maybe China isn't run by sober technocrats anymore (to the extent it ever was). Maybe the post-Deng thaw was just a moment in time when the right confluence of circumstances came together to make things <em>work</em> in Chinese politics. Now, enough of those circumstances have changed that the 'it <em>works</em>'-ness of Chinese politics is going way.</p>
      <p>I mean, look at the rise of Mr Xi: after Deng, there were a few Chairmen that felt kind of more like normal politicians. They were in charge of the Party and the State but, in some sense, responsible to the System. Now, Xi is moving more in the direction of autocracy and his own personal power rather than the integrity and effectiveness of the system.</p>
      <p>Now, he may be a symptom or a cause, but maybe that post-Deng moment wasn't the result of Deng founding an inherently mature, rational, forward thinking system but instead something more transient.</p>
      <p>This is something relatively common in Chinese history. It's a bit foolish to belabor analogies to pre-Revolutiory China, but you see it over and over again in Dynastic China: a competent Emperor or two impart a ton of forward momentum on the state that allows some of their successors to kind of just coast until one or several of them utterly fails to respond well to a crisis (that they may or may not have had a hand in causing). Then the dynasty suffers permanent damage and just limps along until dissolution or conquest ends it.</p>
      <p>You can hang stylized tellings of the Ham, Tang, <em>and</em> Song off of this framework. Hell, you can even say the <strong>Zhou</strong> followed the same general outline, depending on how much you want to trust the written details on that very ancient past.</p>
      <p>Is history destiny? Of course not, especially naive, simplified history.</p>
      <p>But is there perhaps a kernel of truth about how ultra large scale, non-democratic government tends to work out, both in China and elsewhere (you can tell a similar-ish story about the Macedonian dynasty in medieval Byzantium)?</p>
      <p>There very might be.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>