<post>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2020-05-28T13:57:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fs37yir/</link>
  <title>Anti-Black Bias in Policing: A Counter-Argument</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>America does not require reforms regarding 'police killing black men' because the race aspect of the issue is a media fabrication, curated through intentional propaganda</p>
      <p>Black Americans make up around 25-30% of Americans killed by police in a given year, while constituting ~13% of the base population. This presents an over-representation when compared to base rates, but a significant <strong>under</strong>-representation <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EZEbtpgWkAE15MJ?format=jpg&amp;name=large">when compared to the black share of people who kill police (40+%) or commit theft, burglary, assault, or especially robbery or homicide (50+%)</a>. Ergo, the issue is actually outsized black criminality, <em>not</em> disproportionate police killings which are actually disproportionately in the black community's favor when properly controlled. A <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/07/12/upshot/surprising-new-evidence-shows-bias-in-police-use-of-force-but-not-in-shootings.html">2016 study</a> by a black Harvard Professor, Roland Fryer, analyzed police shootings while controlling for encounter characteristics found that blacks were statistically <em>less</em> likely to face lethal force from police per encounter than the modal citizen, as well as <em>less</em> likely to be fired on without first attacking the officer</p>
      <p>The race aspect can be further debunked by looking at other factors - <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2019/national/police-shootings-2019/">of the 1004 Americans killed in police shootings last year</a>, over 95% of them are men. Police killed upwards of 345 white men in 2019, and only 6 black women. Of those 6 - which included a Black Hebrew Israelite anti-Semitic murder spree through a kosher deli, a schizophrenic woman firing a handgun at cars, a woman filmed seemingly trying to run over an officer, a woman who tased an officer while resisting arrest, and a woman killed in an armed standoff after pointing her gun at several neighbors - only 1 was unarmed, and the officer responsible for that shooting has been indicted on murder charges. Meanwhile, the killings of 16 white men and 8 black men were coded as unarmed</p>
      <p>The above does not demonstrate that our law enforcement institutions have rampant issues of institutional sexism against men - it is simply an artifact of the obvious truth that men commit a hugely disproportionate share of violent crime, are vastly more likely to resist arrest, and are vastly more likely to enact violence against an officer. Everyone in our society intuitively understands this. For some reason, when these same characteristics are invoked along racial lines, people become extremely mindkilled and act like they have trouble with grade school level reasoning; from what I recall about lower school, kids are taught about numerators and denominators at Grade 3</p>
      <p>The current case being used to prop up the media's obvious <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/09/16/cardiologists-and-chinese-robbers/">Chinese Robber fallacy</a> with regard to police killings, George Floyd, is indefensible and consequently undefended. It's a clear case for some level of police reform. However, contrary to <a href="https://twitter.com/greg_price11/status/1265687744845688832?s=20">fake memes</a> spread by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h4UqMyldS7Q">legendary</a> rappers, nothing whatsoever suggests that either this incident or the larger issue of police shootings is driven by race. The fact that the media doesn't cover the plurality of police killings that are of white men is only an indicator of the media's mendacity, not systemic racism. That this brushes up on uproar over another white-on-black killing (non-police) from several months earlier is only an artifact of the media's priorities, not racial realities. Ditto for the lack of coverage of lurid black-on-white violence over the same period <a href="https://fox6now.com/2020/05/20/texas-police-union-voices-outrage-after-recently-released-career-criminal-fatally-stabs-grandma-80/">[1]</a><a href="https://www.the-sun.com/news/820010/dead-couple-identified-delaware-veterans-cemetary-police/">[2]</a><a href="https://fox6now.com/2020/05/22/online-video-shows-20-year-old-beating-elderly-nursing-home-patient/">[3]</a>. The notion that the dog owner in the Central Park incident "<a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/05/27/us/amy-cooper-central-park-call-police-trnd/index.html">tried to bring death by cop</a>" on the elderly bird enthusiast's head - premised on the absurd misconception that police indiscriminately kill black people as often as not - is still utterly ridiculous and should be ridiculed. Whites are still far, far more likely to be killed by a black criminal than any black person is to be killed by a cop, warranted or otherwise. Look through the WaPo's exhaustive database above and try to find more than a literal handful of egregious cases that fit the racialized media narrative - then realize that claiming that 40+ million people validly fear for their lives on that basis is preposterous and stop buying into irrational hysteria</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>