<post>
  <author>solowng</author>
  <date>2020-05-29T18:41:35Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fs87a4d/</link>
  <title>Why Not More Anti-Police Riots In the South?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>For what it's worth as a white southerner I have a few thoughts on this that aren't necessarily congruent but here goes. </p>
      <p>The first is that black southerners don't riot against the police because the outrage stories that get media attention from here tend to involve white civilians as the perpetrators. If white civilians are more dangerous than the police (and black criminals <em>are</em> a problem, see southern murder rates) then it would follow that the police are at least tolerated as a necessary evil.</p>
      <p>The second is that while harsh the deep southern states have the least unfair criminal justice systems if one looks at <a href="https://www.sentencingproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/The-Color-of-Justice-Racial-and-Ethnic-Disparity-in-State-Prisons.pdf">sentencing disparities</a>. Alabama, for example, has a merely average rate of black incarceration, not far off from Minnesota, while a while Alabamian is nearly four times as likely to be incarcerated as a white Minnesotan and about twice as likely as a white American in general. New Hampshire lives up to it's "live free or die" motto with relatively low incarceration rates both white and black while Vermont has a below average rate of white incarceration and the highest rate of black male incarceration in the country. Are black men in Vermont really three times as criminal as those in New Hampshire? </p>
      <p>Three, rural white southern culture has a lot of the same peculiarities as black southern culture, namely honor culture, intense reaction to perceived disrespect, and an atavistic preference toward vigilante justice over rule of law. I'd bet that your average white suspect in Alabama is more hostile and dangerous than in Minneapolis; the latter if young and outspokenly liberal may be a mouthy pain in the ass but they'll submit to force while the Alabamian redneck <a href="https://www.ajc.com/news/teen-suspect-faces-new-charges-after-alabama-sheriff-killed/tVEpF1EN4sIHxDKXWap04I/">might actually shoot the sheriff</a>. Both suspects and cops draw from this cultural well such that I'd say that both are less likely to be surprised by each other's reactions and thus will act appropriately or be willing to suffer the consequences. Likewise the public at large are going to be less surprised by these things happening.</p>
      <p>Building on three Minnesota is 6% black (and 84 percent white!) while Alabama is 26% black so I would say that an urban police department like Minneapolis is going to have a harder time recruiting someone culturally fit to police black people than a southern city would and may well have leadership who lack cultural sensitivity to the issue as well. I am 100% confident that the police department in the mixed southern city I live in would've fired Officer Floyd before it got to the point of him killing someone and I dare posit that a white midwestern cop is more scared of a random black man than his southern counterpart. These are the same sort (not the same department, but the same Minneapolis/St Paul region) who killed Philando Castile, another event that I don't think would've happened where I live. As it happened the big news in law enforcement here was <a href="https://www.al.com/news/tuscaloosa/2019/09/his-star-was-so-bright-thousands-honor-slain-tuscaloosa-police-officer-det-dornell-cousette.html">a black suspect killing a black officer</a>.</p>
      <p>Funny enough I was talking to a guy in a bar from Indiana last night who is in grad school to become a social worker about this and he just couldn't relate to the fact that while I'm willing to be rational about the issue for the sake of civility as someone who grew up in the country my emotional impulse is to say that both Minnesotan officers and both Alabamian murderers should've expected the aggrieved communities in question to want them imprisoned or killed <em>immediately</em>. Particularly, I would have been completely untroubled if the white man (another cop's son, ironically, from a different county) who killed the black Lowndes County Sheriff for having asked him to turn his music down had been lynched on the spot.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>