<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-05-29T16:36:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fs7r9hr/</link>
  <title>A Sense of Deep Revulsion Towards Rioters</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I don't want the rioters and looters to die, but I experience the same deep disgust reaction to them. For context, I consider the Floyd killing to be a travesty and agree that there are systemic issues with the US police force, and I support peaceful protests. I'm also categorically, unambiguously, against this sort of rioting.</p>
      <p>If you legitimate approaches like this as a path to change, you damage the structure of the system as a whole in a way more extreme than the original flaws you’re aiming to solve. Riots introduce an incentive that can go two directions:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Cede to their demands. Lesson: every time people want something and the government isn’t providing it, either cheer riots on or shrug and say <a href="https://chainsawsuit.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/20141015-theperfectcrime.png">“he does NOT represent me. but you should probably do as he says”</a>. Result: More riots, more instability, more tearing down social trust, more harm.</li>
        <li>Law-and-order style backlash, more state power. Strongman leader brought in. Absolutely effective at reducing riots. Absolutely something people turn to when rioting becomes serious. Absolutely not what people mad about abuses of government power want to see.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Purely pragmatically, both options are all kinds of bad, and right now I’m seeing way, way too many people for my taste shrugging and saying either “I’m not condoning the riots, but they were inevitable” or “woohoo! about time”. Yes, the original injustice exists. Yes, we need to improve the system. No, compounding injustice on injustice is not a way to heal the world, thinking either morally or pragmatically. I do not believe these riots will lead to a good outcome, and I believe that an atmosphere that excuses them, makes them ‘cool’, treats them as inevitable, validates them, or any other than strict condemnation ultimately leads to a worse, more divided, more unjust society, not one providing proper incentives to improve a system.</p>
      <p>I’m trying to attach a tangible prediction to this but I’m not certain exactly which angle to predict in. Basically, I think realistic outcomes of this riot are that Minneapolis sees a major uptick in crime and significant economic damage, broad abandonment of those neighborhoods by people with any options, incentives against good people joining its police force, and other spiraling negative effects. See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1992_Los_Angeles_riots#Rebuilding_Los_Angeles">the Rodney King riot aftermath</a> for a direct comparison:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The majority of the local stores were never rebuilt. Store owners had difficulty getting loans; myths about the city or at least certain neighborhoods of it arose discouraging investment and preventing growth of employment. Few of the rebuilding plans were implemented, and business investors and some community members rejected South L.A.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <hr />
      <p>Going more fundamentally than that, I see civilization as a whole as part of a tremendous struggle against entropy, decay, and lifelessness. I take a firmly Hobbesian view of the world, that life in a state of nature is solitary, poor, nasty, brutish, and short, and that it's taken tremendous concerted effort to get us to the level of civilization we're at now. Decay, not a sudden glorious reconstruction, is by far the most likely outcome of rioting. Building takes hundreds of times more effort, time, and understanding than destroying. Good intentions don't lead automatically to good outcomes. It takes understanding, planning, organization, and serious work. </p>
      <p>Rioting and looting are primal, anti-civilization acts. They indicate a rejection of the social contract, a refusal to build, and an apathy towards the damage they cause. They're a fundamentally destructive way of engaging with the world that indicate to me a lack of respect for the sheer difficulty of getting the world into even the deeply flawed (but somehow advancing) state it's in. They cause immense damage to their own causes, lead to steeply increased potential for violent or authoritarian backlash, and threaten the fragile defenses we build against genuinely horrifying outcomes. They aim to destroy things that take decades to reconstruct. I see them as unambiguously selfish and evil, a reflection of our worst instincts.</p>
      <p>That, more or less, is the source of my revulsion.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>