<post>
  <author>Ame_Damnee</author>
  <date>2020-10-10T19:28:16Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g8cvfov/</link>
  <title>Identity Markers Ranked In Order of Importance By Partisanship</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I think the crux of the confusion is that there is a difference between political identity  vs. political beliefs  vs. public beliefs.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>To go along with this, there's an interesting <a href="https://religionunplugged.com/news/2020/10/6/are-democrats-influenced-by-religion-as-much-as-republicans">poll</a> done which concentrates on religious beliefs and political identification, but as part of it there's a breakdown of six identity markers (Being American, Close Family, Religion, Local Community, Race/Ethnicity and Party ID) which were ranked in order of importance along the Partisanship spectrum from "Strong Democrat, Weak Democrat, Lean Democrat, Independent, Lean Republican, Weak Republican, Strong Republican".</p>
      <p>Religion was the marker of most interest to this poll and the one that had the largest movement, but for Party ID everyone <em>except</em> Strong Democrat it comes in at number six out of six (for the Strong Dems it's five out of six, but for Strong Reps it's still six out of six).</p>
      <p>Order for the left side:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Close Family</li>
        <li>Being American</li>
        <li>Local Community</li>
        <li>Race/Ethnicity</li>
        <li>Party ID</li>
        <li>Religion</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Order for the right side:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Being American</li>
        <li>Close Family</li>
        <li>Religion</li>
        <li>Local Community</li>
        <li>Race/Ethnicity</li>
        <li>Party ID</li>
      </ol>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The general pattern is one of fairly small movements. In fact, for five of the six identities the ranking never moved more than one position up or down from strong Democrats to strong Republicans. For instance, being an American was the second most important for all Democrats, but only bumped up to the first position for those who classified themselves as strong Republicans.  </p>
        <p>However, the outlier here is religion. For strong Democrats, it ranked as the least important (sixth out of six). But, as one follows the yellow line from left to right it begins to rise - becoming more important. For independents, it was in the fifth position, but then jumped up to fourth among weak Republicans. Finally, it ends as the third most important for strong Republicans just behind being an American and close family.   </p>
        <p>The clear consensus is this: the higher the level of religious importance, the more likely a respondent was to give President Trump a positive approval rating. That result holds for Republicans as well as Democrats. For instance, a white Democrat who said that religion was not at all important placed Trump’s support around 5%, but for those who said it was very important, predicted support jumped to 25%. For Hispanic Democrats, the increase was from 12% to 25%, as well.  </p>
        <p>In fact, President Trump’s job approval was always higher for those who said that religion was very important than those who said it was not important at all. This was true even among non-white Democrats and Independents. Clearly, Trump’s approval turns (at least in part) on religious concerns. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>So what's the takeaway here?  Religion is one of the Top Three for Strong Republicans, but Party ID will be more important to a Strong Democrat than a Strong Republican.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>