<post>
  <author>CanIHaveASong</author>
  <date>2020-10-11T17:19:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g8i5o0h/</link>
  <title>The Impact of Waiting Until Marriage For Intimacy</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>We're both very religious, and believe it's wrong to have sex before marriage.  We didn't think kissing before engagement was wrong, but my husband wanted to experience his first kiss with the woman he would be with for life, so we waited.  I had a great deal of fun teasing him.  </p>
      <p>There are irreligious reasons to wait to have sex until marriage, though.  The conventional wisdom that you need to test sexual compatibility before commitment is wrong.  Waiting until marriage confers about a 20% increase in marriage stability <em>and sexual satisfaction</em> compared to having sex before engagement.  </p>
      <p>My feeling, having lived it, is that since our first sex was with eachother, we ended up developing our sexual tastes around eachother.  But not just that, we did discuss what we thought we'd want before marriage, and we ended up being largely correct.  There were surprises, but they were things like preferring sex at one type of day or another, and it is easy to accommodate eachother.  </p>
      <p>As for the relational aspect, I found that I lost the ability to evaluate my husband objectively after we began having sex, and that difficulty remained for about a year.  I was very thankful that I had already evaluated him rationally, given how compromised sex made me.  If I had not had the chance to evaluate him dispassionately for an extended time before sex, I think it would have been really hard to determine if he was right for me or not.  </p>
      <p>To go off the religious script, though I was committed to following my God's commands, I think we could have begun having sex during engagement without losing the practical benefits of waiting.  My husband disagrees, and thinks it would have been confusing for him.  I looked this up, and it turns out we're on to something.</p>
      <p>Generally speaking, the longer a couple waits to have sex, the more stable and happy their future marriage is.  I'm not going to look up the study right now, but the benefits of waiting to have sex on future marital happiness are really huge until 6 months into the relationship.  It's significant enough that I would exhort anyone, regardless of beliefs, to wait at least 6 months into a relationship before having sex.  After six months, the benefits of waiting start to drop off a bit, until engagement, where there's another inflection point.  People who have sex beginning in engagement get almost all of the benefits of waiting until marriage.  This is the most important inflection point:  Beginning sex after you have committed to eachother confers huge benefits in future relationship quality, even if you haven't actually married.  </p>
      <p>For optimal relationship quality, you need to have time to evaluate eachother without sex in the mix, and you need to commit to eachother without sex in the mix.  Otherwise, you risk mistaking sex for love and compatibility.</p>
      <p>edit:  I want to make sure I'm explicit:  Waiting to have sex probably does not make a particular relationship better, it decreases the chances of marrying someone you don't actually like.  Sex clouds judgement, and people who are bad for eachother but having sex are much more likely to stay together and marry than people who aren't.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>