<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-10-09T23:04:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g89hy20/</link>
  <title>Is the 'sexual market value' of the median 25 year old straight guy decreasing?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <em>tl;dr - is the 'sexual market value' of the median 25 year old straight guy decreasing, as men become more socially awkward and less personally capable? Are subs like Female Dating Strategy onto something? And does any of this have something to do with the Incel phenomenon?</em>
      </p>
      <p>I'm really glad that people's subscribed subreddits are private, because I'm subbed to a bunch of insane places right across the political spectrum (mostly for curiosity's sake). But one place I'm subbed to that seems to come in for a lot of criticism is Female Dating Strategy. I've heard people call it grossly sexist against men and totally ludicrous and even question whether it's a psy-op or troll job by MRAs to make women look bad. But honestly, a lot of it seems to be pretty reasonable. For those not acquainted with the sub, you might want to go check out the best of all time (I'm deliberately avoiding links), but a lot of it boils down to complaints that modern day men are (i) pathetically unwilling to commit, (ii) shockingly lacking in basic personal life skills, (iii) sorely deficient in core emotional and relationship management abilities.</p>
      <p>That's the kind of qualitative claim it's hard to get data on, but I have to say it resonates a bit with my personal experience, especially with some of my younger straight male friends. My perspective is skewed towards the cosmopolitan young-ish upper-middle class, but broadly speaking, they seem to fall into two groups.</p>
      <p>The first group is charming but sleazy fuckboys who who will fuck around a lot but largely avoid committing to relationships, aside from accidental rare occasions when their therapist prescribes them an unusually rambunctious cocktail of antidepressants.</p>
      <p>The second group is closer to the 'basement dweller' archetype, with the main difference being personal and professional success: nerdy and awkward, lacking experience in relationships, and often seeming (to my mind) to be clueless about core lifestyle stuff like how to dress well or decorate their apartment.</p>
      <p>Most of the complaints raised in FDS seem to target one or another of these groups specifically: the fuckbois get called out for being sleazy STD-ridden assholes who'll have your abortion but not be seen with you on social media, while the dorks get called out for their inability to do basic stuff like put up shelves, launder clothes properly, or buy a throw pillow (and be attractive).</p>
      <p>What I find really interesting about the FDS take on men, though, is how tantalisingly closely it tracks some of the same ideas prominent in the incel/redpill/doomer communities about dating. The core of the incel/redpill complaint as far as I can tell can be boiled down as follows -</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Thanks to online dating and related phenomena, friction (of one sort) in the 18-35 dating market has been reduced, meaning that a relatively small group of elite males end up dating and/or having sex with a lot of single women simultaneously, the 80/20 rule at work. But since women can only really get away with this in their 20s, and the 20% of elite guys ultimately end up marrying (and we're still a socially monogamous society), these de facto harems can't last forever. So what happens when the 50th-percentile-attractiveness woman who's spent her 20s fucking 10th-percentile-attractiveness guys hits 35 and finds it harder to get dates with these guys? Now she starts worrying about having a family. Her options are drying up. What she does is <em>settle</em>  - go for one of the guys she'd have passed over in her 20s, but who now constitute the best option left on the table ("betabux/alpha fucks").</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'm not going to argue that this narrative is correct, though speaking as a man who basically did 'harem dating' for most of my 20s before eventually settling down in my early 30s (when my therapist prescribed me an unusually rambunctious cocktail of antidepressants, in fact), I feel there's at least some verisimilitude to it. But <em>conditional on its being true</em>, note that one consequence would be precisely the pattern of complaints you see coming from FDS. Seen from the female perspective, this incel/redpill narrative would result in (i) a relatively small core of 'fuckbois' who were sexy and charming but a nightmare to get to commit, (ii) a much larger group of cringey inexperienced guys who went through most of their twenties without getting into relationships and consequently failed to build relevant interpersonal skills, in turn becoming in many cases lame husbands when the music stops and some luckless woman eventually decides to sit on them.</p>
      <p>One key assumption here that I haven't yet defended is the idea that 'being a good romantic partner' is a skill that grows with experience. I firmly believe it's true, though, at least for men: so many of the significant lifestyle improvements I've made over the years have either come from women I'm dating ("you know, you should really put some pictures up on the walls so you don't look like a serial killer"), or else because I wanted to make myself more attractive ("I should learn more about fashion so I have more success on dates"). But if a significant chunk of straight men these days are simply not getting dating experience in their 20s, it would follow that they might be suffering from a kind of romantic-interpersonal arrested development, in turn leading to FDS-style complaints about lame partners in their 30s.</p>
      <p>Anyway, all of this makes me wonder whether some of the various people complaining about relationships at the moment - FDS, redpill, Incels, etc. - might not be climbing the mountain from different sides. Put simply, perhaps the problem is that our current dating market disincentivises one group of men from committing to relationships early, while simultaneously depriving a larger group of men of the opportunity to build 'relationship skills' through dating in their early 20s, leading to them becoming inadequate spouses down the line.</p>
      <p>While I realise a lot of the above is skewed towards metropolitan dating markets (and things may play out very differently in Peoria), I'm curious as to what others think about this, especially from the women in the sub who I'd expect to have a different angle on these things. Is the median 25 year old straight man's "sexual market value" decreasing these days? Does this have anything to do with either lack or surfeit of relationship experience? And if there is a problem here, how on earth do we fix it?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>