<post>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2020-10-12T23:19:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8n2bcm/</link>
  <title>The Contradictory, Curious Nature of Hungarian Nationalism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's a really special situation. Hungarian nationalism is not really like Germanic/Western European white nationalism. The focus is not on white skin / blond hair / blue eyes Nordic whiteness, or at least not until the recent weird and somewhat reluctant ideological convergence of "European nationalists" in the face of Muslim migration.</p>
      <p>In terms of national consciousness, Hungary is really an outlier, a nation between East and West, a relatively late arrival to the party. Accordingly, Hungarian nationalists come in all sorts of flavors. Some are about white Christianity, but many are about Turkic pagan tradition, of the old myths, the esthetic of the fierce steppe nomads, Scythians, Huns etc., of quaint peasant life, etc. There are those who think Habsburgs were legitimate rulers of Hungary (monarchists, legitimists) and think the liberal nationalist awakening movements were a leftist subversion of a long-held stable order of empires etc. While other nationalists say Hungarian independence from Habsburgs was important and we were subjugated by the Habsburgs etc.
Some nationalists say adopting Christianity was a mistake and our first king Stephen was a traitor who murdered the legit guy (Koppány) with the aid of German armies and ruthlessly forced Hungarians to adopt a foreign religion. Others say it was a wise decision, which helped preserve our nation, instead of going the way of so many nomadic tribes lost to history.</p>
      <p>It's a huge mess and all these different types rarely agree much, other than how bad Trianon was and how bad Gypsies are. Accordingly, there is a lot of infighting and it's a difficult tribe to hold together politically.</p>
      <p>EDIT: also, up until recently Hungarian nationalists had no problem with Muslims and Arabs, chairman of then-nationalist Jobbik party, Gábor Vona, famously said "Islam is the last hope for humanity". They also regularly organized protests in support of Palestinians and Vona also said in a big public speech that if he gets on government he'll call in the Iranian Revolutionary Guard to help keep elections pure (I'm not making it up...). Despite what you may expect, the Turkish-Hungarian relations have been pretty good, despite the Ottoman occupation (even during the occupation it wasn't too bad, it was not so clear at all whether the Habsburg or the Ottoman side is more favorable.). But also one of the most important novels in the Hungarian language is about how Hungarians bravely defended the castle of Eger against the invading Muslim hordes (Gárdonyi: Eclipse of the crescent moon), and the book is not at all sympathetic to Turks. But the book is loved by even those who are otherwise pro-Turkic.
Given all that, this paragraph wouldn't be complete without pointing out the perhaps obvious, that support/tolerance of Muslims was little more than a way to express anti-Semitism. Indeed the whole Turkic/Turanic pro-east thing is hard to disentangle from anti-Semitic anti-western-cosmopolitanism. They are <em>not</em> one and the same but have been baked together for so long that it's hard to separate them.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Overall note: I'm concentrating on more fringe nationalists here, this is not the mainstream Hungarian national consciousness. There was plenty of modern cosmopolitan thought in the national awakenings, and there have been great statesmen in the 19th century who were able to get on with the times. Industrialization, railways, economic innovations, national banks, all that stuff was very modern in those times and we were on the forefront of adapting them.</p>
      <p>I'm focusing on the more fringe extreme right, because their contradictory nature fascinates me and it illustrates so much about the nature of human tribalism. Alliances are in constant flux, people can hold contradictory ideas and can unite against external enemies, seemingly forgetting yesterday's conflict. Like when Hungarian and Slovak nationalists had a common protest with a shared stage against the Muslim immigration wave of 2015. When they normally spend their time defacing each other's memorials...</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>