<post>
  <author>JTarrou</author>
  <date>2020-10-10T11:31:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g8b45yv/</link>
  <title>Conversation as Casual Tennis: The goal is not to win, the goal is to keep the volley going. </title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I can't tell you what will work for you, but I can tell you what I did, and it worked for me. </p>
      <p>I was no good at meeting new people. It was uncomfortable to me, and while I enjoyed conversation, no one wants to talk about the things that interest me. I had to learn the very specific skill of chatting up strangers. Not even women specifically, just learning to meet new people, talk to them on a superficial level, and sustain a conversation for some time. </p>
      <p>So I set myself a set of progressively ambitious goals. Every time I went somewhere, be it the grocery store, the bank or the bar, I had to talk to someone, engage in conversation. The more appropriate the setting, the longer the conversation had to be. Over time I developed a set of stories, jokes, and questions that could work in most situations. </p>
      <p>Then I scaled those contacts I was making into a superficial social circle that in some cases became less superficial over time. This made me a visible part of a community, provided social validation. When I met a girl and asked her out, I would take her somewhere comfortable for me, where I already knew a few people, and make sure to chat briefly with some of them on the date. By the time I met my current SO, I couldn't walk into a bar on the main strip of my town without knowing at least two people in there. I'd made friendly acquaintances with the bartenders, the waiters, the chefs at the restaurants, the bouncers, the guy at the jewelry store, the bands etc. In addition to social validation, this provided me with a much bigger pool of dating prospects. As it turned out, I met my SO on a fluke while wingmanning for a friend of mine, but prior to that, I got a lot of dates from my network of acquaintances. </p>
      <p>The social skills from that translated well even after I was done dating. It's twenty years since I started this project, and talking to people I don't know still is uncomfortable, and I still despise small talk. But I do it all the time. Every activity I do, I talk to everyone I can, within reason. This means a lot of boring, repetitive conversations, but it also means contact with people, the opening of the beginning of a relationship. </p>
      <p>I read somewhere that one should think of conversation as a friendly game of tennis with someone worse than you. The goal is not to win, the goal is to keep the volley going. </p>
      <p>This was all stage 1 of my romantic development. Stage 2 was learning that women are bad people just like men, and mostly less interesting (other than sexual interest). Stage 3 is learning that women, as Roissy used to say, are incapable of loving men the way that men want to be loved. That's not on them, that's on us. We have to deal with reality rather than fantasy.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>