<post>
  <author>Namrok</author>
  <date>2020-10-13T03:29:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8nrsya/</link>
  <title>Reflections On 20 Years of Game Development: A Journey To 1997 PC Gaming</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So, this is a weird one.  Lately I've embarked on a journey to 1997 PC gaming with a Retro PC I laboriously ordered (and frequently returned) part by part off Ebay.  It's a storied tale I won't go into again here.  Check the Friday Fun Threads if you are interested.</p>
      <p>You know what's been nice about a 1997 PC?  No internet.  No multitasking.  No social media.  No launcher overlays.  No <strong>launchers</strong>.  I just play my fucking games unbothered by the outside world like God (or Carmack) intended.  And I organize my games with a folder on the desktop called "Games".  My library is a literal library of CDs.  Actual, tangible ownership.  It's beautiful.</p>
      <p>The 90's were a fascinating time.  Computers got powerful enough to really push the action envelope.  I'm reminded how reading Masters of Doom, one of Carmack's early genius moments was actually getting a PC to draw sprites fast enough to make a Mario clone.  That clone later became Commander Keen.  The NES was the gold standard of responsive, action oriented gameplay, and the PC, judging by CGW's old issues, was mostly a land of turn based wargames or role playing games.  With a smattering of plodding simulators.</p>
      <p>So PCs are powerful enough to have everything action oriented.  Action oriented role playing games, strategy games, first person shooters, first person action oriented role playing strategy games!  It's like the mold of PC games was formed in the 90's, and changed little since.  You get some technical innovation around having massive, load screen free, open worlds.  And that changes things some.  Mostly games have a lot more empty space with less to meaningfully do.  And an avalanche of survival games.</p>
      <p>So what have we really done with the last 20 years of game development?  Turned everything into a god damned service it seems.  I loath it.  I loath it for it's practical effects on ownership.  I loath it for what it's done to preservation.  I loath it for requiring a constant tether to the rest of the world which I can never break, no matter how much I long to.  I loath it for removing the option to amicably break up with a company I no longer wish to support.  No more "Well, I gave you $50 and you gave me my CD-ROM and we can walk away from any future entanglement".  Now even playing the games you already paid for ends up in some investors slides about engagement.  If you want to break up with some company, they get to keep all the games you paid for, effectively.</p>
      <p>Lately I loath it for a new reason.  I've begun blaming the increasing presence of the culture war in fucking everything, but especially gaming, on gaming being turned into a service.  We're all, constantly, every time we try to play a game in peace, forced to share a space with people we loath.  The obnoxious user names.  The obnoxious global chat.  The obnoxious pub channels.  Every fucking game has a "community".  Does anyone even feel a part of the "community"?  Of any game?  The entire concept feels like such a forced fiction.  Is everyone who rides the Metro a "community"?  What about everyone who shops on Amazon?</p>
      <p>All the "community" seems good for now is staging a battleground for people to fight over.  Codes of conduct to let certain users know they aren't welcome.  "Community Managers" who try to brow beat the unwashed adolescents who partake of their product into something resembling civilized behavior.  And a constant undertone that lurking under every pebble is a hidden wellspring of "toxicity".  The "community" is something to be feared and ruled with an iron fist.</p>
      <p>I hate "communities" and I think gaming did plenty well before it even had them.  And I hate that the last 20 years of game development seem have achieved nothing but turning everything into a service, and thereby a "community".  It's a malformed, spiteful little monster, and I wish we'd dashed it's head upon the rocks when it was born.</p>
      <p>Now don't get me wrong.  I'm not saying that there cannot be communities in gaming.  I've been in clans, guilds, small enthusiast forums of about 20-30 people, a crew that LAN partied weekly for 4 years, etc.  But there is <strong>no</strong> "Blizzard Community" or a "Diablo Community" or a "Steam Community".  Those are deranged fictions attempting to put a smiley face on the Hobbsean chaos of shoving absolutely all your customers into the same, disgusting, global ball pit.</p>
      <p>And don't get me wrong about "people we loath" either.  Somebody out there loathes me, somebody out their loathes you.  This isn't any set type of person.  This isn't "insert outgroup here", or a call to go get them.  Everyone hates someone, and someone out there hates you.  That's just the reality of it.</p>
      <p>Now if you'll excuse me, I'm on the last act of the original Quake.  I forgot how short this game was.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>