<post>
  <author>OverthinksStuff</author>
  <date>2020-10-10T22:36:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g8dulbu/</link>
  <title>Siloing of social groups makes for fertile ground for a 80-20 situation in online dating</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>You're onto something. However, I believe the problem is rooted in social dynamics that precede the online dating phenomenon.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Hypothesis</strong>: <em>People learn from proximity. The ease of forming min-maxed cliques means that nerds get nerdier and the fuck-bois get fuckier. The lack of social attenuation leads to worse outcomes for both groups at large.</em></p>
      <hr />
      <p>This mirror's my personal experience too. I have been incredibly fortunate in having experienced the whole spectrum of social group hierarchies.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>'Scum of earth' bullying victim all through k-12 school.<br /></li>
        <li>Leader, public speaker, drama dude through university</li>
        <li>Knows-everyone friendly nerdy guy through grad school</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Throughout this time I was a virgin teetotaler for personal reasons. 
<span class="md-spoiler-text">I hated pop, dancing and had an unreasonably high beauty standard and only male hobbies/ career choice. I still am fiercely anti-tribalistic and refuse to ever lie. Was approached frequently, but after a traumatic highschool wanted to work on myself first. Was also incredibly miserly when funded by parents, so never spent on ANYTHING. Go figure</span> I'm a Late bloomer but am now in a relationship with a very attractive and intelligent woman, so don't mourn for me. </p>
      <p>This has allowed me to be part of literally every group. </p>
      <ol>
        <li>The fuck-bois/ musicians (as the Designated driver) </li>
        <li>the nerds/ tech-dudes (fit right in) </li>
        <li>the nice guys/gamers (the counselor)<br /></li>
        <li>mostly female groups / drama club (the harmless vocally single-by-choice guy).<br /></li>
      </ol>
      <p>What blows my mind is how siloed these groups are. If you have have a certain hobby or lifestyle, then your access to certain other kinds of people is completely cut off.<br />
I learnt an insane amount of what was considered 101 information from women friends and the popular kids a lot later in life than I would have thought. A majority of my nerdy-male friends only got that 101 information through me. Similarly, a lot of 101 information about men, introverts and nerds came as a total surprise to women and popular men.<br />
The crazy part is that this isn't information that is protected. It is given away freely. But the complete lack of a casual &amp; comfortable conversation across these groups siloes even this 101 tier info. The internet surprisingly doesn't do a great job of disseminating it either.<br />
There are places it exists, but the signal to noise ratio to makes it really hard for an amateur to discern it. So, it is a sort of catch 22.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>The siloing of social groups makes for fertile ground for a 80-20 situation in online dating and the exact situation you describe. But, I think your observation is a symptom rather than the cause.</strong>
      </p>
      <hr />
      <p>Back in the day, you didn't choose your social circle. Neighbors, family, 2nd order networks and randomly assigned groups were far more important. Building one-dimensional groups was hard because filtering the network was hard. My hypothesis is this caused social networks to be far noisier and thus more diverse.<br />
Transferring 101 info was far easier and the everyone knew the basics of interaction with the other group. </p>
      <p>This mirrors my experiences too. I have ended up in far more socially diverse groups when the groups were randomly formed at first. <span class="md-spoiler-text">eg: a foreign language class, a group of people who happened to land together and stuck together, my roomates who were assigned randomly in a mixed-gender international community home</span></p>
      <p>
        <strong>As long as the internet allows for more and more personality and gender homogenous groups to form. This problem will continue getting worse.</strong>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>