<post>
  <author>RogerDodger_n</author>
  <date>2020-10-12T06:30:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j8trco/the_bailey_podcast_e016_the_banality_of_catgirls/g8kiqow/</link>
  <title>The Joys of Superstimuli</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>My general takeaway of the discussion is that "superstimulus" is not a very useful typology. Nobody could agree on what one is, or even whether it's a problem. It's the perfect recipe for a lot to be said about nothing.</p>
      <p>One speaker said the distinction lies somewhere between Ke$ha and Death Grips, with Ke$ha being the superstimulus... and then went on about all the ways in which Death Grips is more interesting. The irony was hard to miss.</p>
      <p>I'm surprised how little addiction was mentioned. I feel like the standard clinical approach to addiction—that a behaviour is a problem if it causes fixation and prevents you from doing things that <em>you want to do</em>—is a lot more grounded than what this discussion amounted to. It also avoids the unpleasant paternalism of assuming people's desires for them.</p>
      <p>One speaker suggested that addicts have impaired judgement akin to a child. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H6ZFzEW7_Q4">Listen to this interview of a homeless heroin addict.</a> If you have time, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WQ5bkdFuFhg">listen to this interview with Asmongold, who is almost the Ur-example of a WoW addict.</a> Lots of addicts have a surprising amount of self-awareness. It's not that they're stupid. It's that they're weak.</p>
      <p>What helps these people overcome their addictions isn't saying, "Your judgment is impaired. You don't actually know what's good for you. I do." That's just unhelpful moralising. They know they're addicted. They know it's a problem. The trouble is that getting out of the rut is <em>hard</em>, not only because feeding the addiction genuinely feels good, but because taking the first steps to getting out of it is a genuinely hellish experience. It's a boring answer: time preference is real. What helps is the tedious task of making the path out of that rut just a little bit brighter, bit by bit.</p>
      <p>From this perspective, the question to ask isn't, "Which stimuli are <em>too awesome</em>?" which leads to the absurd conclusion that music is a problem—almost nobody becomes debilitated by a music addiction—but, "Which stimuli are more likely to lead to addiction?" or the normative question, "Which stimuli, if any, are so likely to lead to addiction that they should be banned/shunned?"</p>
      <p>Admittedly, this perspective doesn't do a good job at answering the question of wire-heading (or The Entertainment from <em>Infinite Jest</em>). I think TracingWoodgrains' answer that this is only a failure mode of pure pleasure/pain utilitarianism is on point. It's pretty easy for people who lean towards deontology or virtue ethics to reject wire-heading.</p>
      <p>Video games and pornography specifically pose a question <em>to society</em> given:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.econlib.org/archives/2012/02/what_is_the_mar.html">The Male Marriage Premium</a>. Men who get married are substantially more productive. The causal effect here seems pretty obvious if you've ever known a man before and after getting a serious partner.</li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.economist.com/the-economist-explains/2017/03/30/the-link-between-video-games-and-unemployment">Young men are rapidly dropping out of society (employment and marriage) to play more video games.</a>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>It's not clear if the carrot of "loving wife and family" can even <em>currently</em> compete with video games and pornography, and it's only going to get worse as they get better. This isn't just a matter of addiction. Video games and porn for many men <em>is</em> the epicurean choice. Designating these superstimuli doesn't help at all. Getting out of this mess requires at minimum a strong cultural rejection of epicureanism and anything adjacent to it. Otherwise, you can expect to see more and more men <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g7091nv/">"wasting their neuroplasticity on DotA tournaments with high prize funds and inflated prestige, memorizing worthless patterns instead of seeking mastery over physical and mental"</a>. </p>
      <p>Now, you might not think that's a problem either, but that's a little more specific than saying you don't think superstimuli are a problem.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>