<post>
  <author>titus_1_15</author>
  <date>2020-10-11T15:43:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g8hv2tz/</link>
  <title>"No taxation without representation" is a canard</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>So "no taxation without representation" and all the rest of it was a blind?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Actually, interestingly, "no taxation without representation" <em>is</em> a total canard. The English government was in fact quite willing to have American MPs sit in the House of Commons; this is something that the previous Whig PM, Lord Grafton, had explicitly offered to the colonies in October 1769, and which his successor Lord North was also willing to grant.</p>
      <p>The radical wing of the American colonists emphatically did <em>not</em> want this; they wanted the chance to build their own much more radical government form in the colonies, and they knew that fuller integration into the Empire would only harm their cause. It was conceptually simple, and a rallying cry for some moderates, but it wasn't a serious aim of the colonies to achieve representation in parliament.</p>
      <p>I mean, compare with any later conflict where the main participants actually sincerely <em>did</em> want to play a greater role in existing political structures, like the suffragettes. The history of the vote for women in the English-speaking world is mainly a history of campaigning and political process. Or consider US territories in the west after the US-Mexican war, who sincerely aimed at achieving statehood and "joining the party". It's quite a different history to the colonists' tepid, insincere interest in joining the English parliament.</p>
      <p>There are no great portraits of Franklin pounding on the doors of the Palace of Westminster, demanding entry for his loyal colonial countrymen. There's no great story of Jefferson pouring all his oratorical flair into some great address to his king, begging to stand alongside his fellows from Cornwall to Northumbria. </p>
      <p>Because: the radical wing of the colonists, those who drove the American revolution, wanted independence, not equality in the empire. </p>
      <p>In fact, as all the senior players knew very well, American colonists payed a <em>substantially</em> lower tax burden than their peers in the home country; this was one of the chief incentives to get people to immigrate. This was a deliberate policy of the English Crown, which was endlessly trying to find ways to induce free men and women to people its colonies. The tax burden of the average US colonist rose substantially after independence also.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>