<post>
  <author>wlxd</author>
  <date>2020-10-13T06:19:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8o4rsi/</link>
  <title>The System Hasn't Even Tried To Quash Riots</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>My take on it is that pro-gun activists were right all this time: it really is hard to put down a popular revolt in a country that has more civilian-owned firearms than people.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Maybe it is, but even if I grant that we're actually dealing here with a "popular revolt" here, I observe that the law enforcement and the justice system <em>haven't even tried</em> to quash it.</p>
      <p>Why do I think that? Well, I just happened to read about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2015_Waco_shootout">2015 Waco shootout</a>. The way the story goes roughly like this: in Waco, TX, there was a meeting of motorcycle club members about some political rights for motorcycle riders. One thing led to another (what exactly happened is not really important), and shots started flying. Cops were close by, observing the meeting, and they started shooting too, after, as they claimed, they were shot at (again, whether this is really how it went is immaterial). </p>
      <p>As a result, 9 people died, 18 others were injured, but more importantly, <strong>177</strong> people were arrested, and their bonds were set to <strong>$1M each</strong>. The bail conditions included "ankle monitoring, surrendering of passports, abstention from drugs and alcohol and no contact with club members or potential victims or witnesses". The cops managed to arrest all of them, despite being heavily outnumbered, and despite recovering <strong>hundreds</strong> of handguns from the motorcycle club members. </p>
      <p>How is it that they managed to do so, despite being so heavily outgunned by, as you put it, civilian-owned firearms? Well, my hunch is that after the cops shot and killed 4 of them, it was clear that the cops mean business. The motorcycle club members (or at least, an overwhelming majority of them at least) are normal people just like everyone else, and they don't want to throw their life away by getting shot or dying in jail.</p>
      <p>Now that we established that the cops actually <em>are</em> able to arrest hundreds of people, most of them armed, and, moreover, people generally perceived as somewhat less agreeable and compliant than average, let's consider the following hypothetical. What if the Wauwatosa police, reinforced by state police and National Guard, simply <em>arrested every single person outside after curfew</em>? What if the local prosecutor sets $1M bail for everyone arrested (with an option of reducing it after making the case for it in the hearing)? What if people posting bail are required to wear ankle bracelets, and not contact anyone who was also arrested for breaking curfew? What if this was standard response of law enforcement and justice system to riots? How many riots would we have had then in our Summer of Love, if this had be the standard procedure?</p>
      <p>I wanted to preempts some obvious objections to the above. First, that it might be just impractically hard to arrest and detain so many people. Ignoring for a moment that the fine LEO of Texas succeeded at arresting <em>177 armed bikers</em>, what makes it so hard in practice? Here are some ideas (these might sound glib, but after hundreds of days of riots I might have become just a little bit embittered):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>people might resist arrest: use violence until they submit</li>
        <li>their friends might try to "<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Portland/comments/hvkh5a/protesters_successfully_dearrest_someone_getting/">dearrest</a>" them: use violence on them too</li>
        <li>law enforcement might be outnumbered: use force amplification, i.e. guns. Worked in Waco to arrest the bikers.</li>
        <li>arrest paperwork, reports and bureaucracy are time consuming: just ignore them, this is a state of emergency. You can worry about these when you get habeas, but this will be next day at the earliest, which is plenty of time to catch up.</li>
        <li>no detention space available: just pack them like sardines in a can, whatever, this is a state of emergency. I've heard that there are plenty of vacancies in state jails, after many offenders where released due to """pandemic risk""", maybe use those.</li>
        <li>not following proper procedure might jeopardize the cases against offenders: it doesn't matter, when they are released and the system grinds it gears to the end, it will be months or years after the riots are dissipated, and <em>the process is the punishment</em> anyway. None of the Waco bikers has been convicted of anything.</li>
        <li>subsequent civil lawsuits will bankrupt the local government: if the juries of peers, local to the city, overwhelmingly vote against this sort of law enforcement and in favor of rioters, well, in that case <em>the riots, and the bankruptcy is the outcome they want, so they shall have it</em>. Riots are, of course, expensive too.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>I think the real reason why Texas law enforcement can successfully deal with 177 bikers, and Minneapolis, Portland, Seattle, or, for that matter, Wauwatosa police cannot, is that the Texas cops know that the local prosecutors, judges, and most of all, local people, <em>have their back</em>. This year's riots in many American cities are a sad indictment of the dysfunction of all branches of their respective local governments. I wanted to say that the American people deserve better, but, at the same time, I can't help but agree that they also deserve what they ask for.</p>
      <p>Last few months I started to seriously consider leaving the United States, and to go back to country where I was born and grew up, in Eastern Europe. Having grown up in extreme (by US, not local standards) poverty, and looking up to the West, which our society was trying hard to copy in every aspect after breaking the chains of Communism, I would have <em>never</em> imagined that I will feel <em>immensely privileged</em> to have a right to live in my poor backwater, and that I will feel actually <em>sorry</em> for native born Americans, who don't have anywhere else to escape to, and who must, for better or worse, prepare for very uncertain future. Cthulhu always swims left of course, and even there in my country of origin, you can see blatantly ridiculous attempts by young activists to reuse the exact same American narratives, regardless of how poorly they work in the local setting. However, there are (or at least so I hope) too many people there who lived under totalitarian regime to not notice, and fight back against, as Rod Dreher calls it, the soft totalitarianism, that's descending now on America. Seems like I'm not actually American enough to stay here and fight for its future, but I hope this kind of cowardice doesn't blemish my character any more than it does that of people climbing the Berlin wall back in the day.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>