<post>
  <author>GeriatricZergling</author>
  <date>2020-07-25T22:24:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fz8thpx/</link>
  <title>Compatibility of Space Colonization and Harmony With Nature</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>It may not be “anti-civilization in general,” but it’s certainly “anti-civilization where civilization is defined by Mottezan nerds that want to colonize space.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>See, I think the nerds are wrong about this, and I'm one of the nerd who want to colonize space.  Colonizing space isn't about rockets and warp drives and space elevators.  Those are just <em>getting to space</em>, which is admittedly a prerequisite.  But to set up a colony that isn't completely reliant on Earth, as is necessary to avoid X-risk situations (and to colonize anywhere sufficiently far away by the mode of transport of the day)?  You need exactly this sort of view - how to make a society with a small number of people and keep in running, prioritizing food production (and air and water), lowering resource consumption.</p>
      <p>"Living in harmony with nature" may sound weird if you're talking about a lifeless world, but can mean something as simple as adjusting to and accommodating the natural geology and weather rather than fighting against them.  You can ship assloads of materials to Mars to build structures strong enough to survive 95% of the massive sandstorms (but what about the "100 year storm"?), or you can build structures which are undisturbed by them (e.g. underground or aerodynamically sleek).</p>
      <p>I've started to say that the biggest obstacle to true, independent colonization isn't space travel, FTL tech, etc., it's our understanding (and the limits thereof) of ecology.  Look at what happened to Biosphere 2, twice.  Space aliens could drop off FTL drives and limitless power sources tomorrow, and we still couldn't make a colony that wouldn't need constant re-supply and adjustment.  Generation ships are even worse - at least on Mars you have dirt and CO2 and ice, as opposed to literally void.  Even terraforming wouldn't solve it - how do you know what species to bring and leave behind, and how many?</p>
      <p>I'm 100% certain that people living in an actual, self-sustaining extraterrestial colony will make the Lorax look like a coal-mining executive.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>