<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-07-27T12:54:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/fzedvrq/</link>
  <title>A Moment of Scorn Towards Anglo Culture</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Huh.</p>
      <p>"Red-pill bomb" was half sarcastic; my point was that they reinvent some /pol/ tier "red pill" take without understanding its context and reasons for it being taboo, and contrary to their expectations the reaction ends up being all «what did China suggest by this? Are they trying to sow discord? Are they behind white supremacists?!» meta debate. In a very direct sense, frog posters from /pol/ have more cultural power than all of China, so naive Chinese gotchas are interpreted in the context of their memeplex. I thought, and still think, that this was clear and reasonable.  </p>
      <p>That said, I'm not even sure what half of those words Hlynka wrote have to do with any of mine, so I just sorta shrugged. «Apologia»? Lolwut? Speak plainly, please. What is there to need excuses? On the other hand, two of my pals predicted «they'll keep banning you, for this too», so perhaps I'm just losing it. If so, good riddance for folks here. In any case, my previous utterances in the same vein are brought forth as evidence of more depravity, of continuous fall into sin from some vaunted "quality contributor" post (which I never asked for), but I saw those bans (and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fxizaxc/?context=3#fx9sdsb">outraged, incredulous</a> mod comments) as overreactions too, so the value disagreement and its eventual result are evident. </p>
      <p>Still, here's how I see this. My rather low opinion of Anglo peoples (~the Commonwealth + USA) as conductors of a certain destructive, consistently hypocritical elite will, either too naive and drinking their own kool-aid or simply too biased in their own favor (not ethnocentrically, though; perhaps civo-centrically?) is unwelcome here because it insults people like Hlynka (and those who report me) for exactly these reasons of bias and narrow-mindedness; whereas broad accusations of Chinese people in immoral collectivism, cynical readiness to commit atrocities on CCP behalf etc., borderline rallying against their nation ("what to do, then, if not sanctions?") are okay, because this is an Anglo-American forum, and Chinamen and Russians have their own spaces to go to. So I'm accused of "not writing like everyone is reading", or at least not like the target audience of this place is. Or something. Well I very much <em>am</em> writing like everyone is reading. My value disagreement may insult something very fundamental to you, but it's not "a letter to end all communication", at least not on my part.<br />
It is not without bias when I write what I write: Anglos did much evil to my Russian people, benefited from our diplomatic ineptitude time and time again, and to this day continue to harbor our traitors and enemies, get fat off our stolen riches and reward the corruption of our elites. Still I do think that the evidence is on my side: Anglos, as a <em>thalassocratic</em> civilization, are uniquely evil and annoying. They're evil in that they invent shallow and boring, frankly tenuous "universalist" moral principles which happen to serve their geopolitical and mercantile agenda by enforcing global competition on whatever axis they are dominant on at the time ("White man's burden", "free trade", "free speech", "utilitarianism") and then express outrage that some competitor, some lowly filthy barbarous Ork tribe that doesn't even have great English culture, dares disobey (their bizarre, welcomed even here, distinction of target nation and its leaders, "CCP is pure evil but oh, we don't mean Chink... Chinese, they're a great nation, we wish to help" is, IMO, mere divide et impera; obviously elites are the product of the nation, presenting both its character strengths and flaws – unless the helm is de facto usurped by another nation, as happens after e.g. Color revolutions that Anglos back). They're annoying in that it never occurs to them that this march of "Whig history" is seen as inconsistent, bare-faced psychopathic opportunism from outside; they're fine practitioners of intolerant <em>Judeo-Christian values</em>, only their silly chutzpah has long been backed by gunboats; and, adding insult to injury, they cover their most <em>interesting</em>, immune to value drift, and suspicious institutions like Freemasonry and hereditary aristocracy in thick layer of performative indifference, denigration and pedestrian humor so as to "flood the zone with shit", as Bannon put it. At the same time they're uniquely productive and capable of birthing exceptional people of high moral character. We the rest of humanity have to accept all this as fact, but with Anglo vice grip over communications even this possibility is slipping. </p>
      <p>The one word which puzzled me most is "weakman". Who was I weakmanning, even? Out of respect for this community I won't quote <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Opium_War">Wikipedia</a> at length, you can read it or better sources and likely know the story already. The parallels between {Britain pre-1839; trade balance; "free trade" ideology; Chinese self-isolation attempt; Opium war} and{USA pre-2020; trade balance, "universal human rights/free speech" ideology; Chinese Great Firewall attempt; economic war} – should be obvious enough to everyone in this 140+ IQ gentleman club. The gentlemen could consider that their forefathers, too, might have been particularly indignant about Russian barbarism and backwardness when the goal was to win the Great Game, to block Russian Empire from reaching the Straits and completing its centuries-old civilizational project. Anglos are easily stirred by their masters, and easily project their own universalism on smaller forces which attempt to survive in poisoned, Anglo-dominated world. So, come 2020, <a href="https://amp.theguardian.com/world/2020/jul/24/mike-pompeo-says-free-world-must-change-china-or-china-will-change-us">ex-CIA director Mike Pompeo says free world must change China or ‘China will change us’</a> and everyone laps it up, or goes along with it. </p>
      <p>As Galkovsky  puts it:(this post continually gets removed by Reddit, so I guess we are not supposed to discuss this and I remove the link):</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Nabokov, studying in Cambridge, argued for hours with English students about Russia, and in particular with a certain "Bomson" (pseudonym), who later became a major scientist:</p>
        <p>"When I asked the most humane Bomson how he justifies the despicable and abominable terror established by Lenin, the torture and firing squads, and all other madness, - Bomston [...] said that if there was no allied blockade, there would be no terror. All Russian emigrants, all enemies of the Soviets, from the Menshevik to the monarchist, he calmly heaped together in a pile of "Tsarist elements" [...]. It never occurred to him that if he and other foreign idealists were Russians in Russia, the Leninist regime would exterminate them immediately. In his opinion, what he rather cynically called "some uniformity of political beliefs" under the Bolsheviks was a consequence of the "absence of any tradition of freethinking" in Russia [...]</p>
        <p>Nabokov ascribed this conduct of his acquaintance to his "ignorance". But the ignorant man, of course, was Nabokov himself. He could have noticed that if a Cambridge graduate, "graciously smiling", rants about the humanism of Soviet Russia, the game here is more subtle. [...]</p>
        <ul>
          <li>How many fingers, Winston?</li>
          <li>Five! Five! Five!</li>
          <li>No, Winston, it's no good. You're lying. You still think there's four."</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Eton's graduate, say now, "Pasha Liamtseva exposed "kulak cutters." I want to correspond with her because I am a conscious representative of the British proletariat." </p>
        <p>And he'll say it, and won't blink. Because it's Eton - with rod discipline, with the rituals for humiliating and twisting the personality of a teenager, with the Masonic psychology of "Inner Party" and secret knowledge.</p>
        <p>You're a clever man, Comrade Orwell. Crafty. But in the end you turned around and still shouted before your death: "Four fingers! Four fingers!!!" Well, when you were 35, you quacked with "duckspeak" and at 45, you had an epiphany? Such an epiphany is only possible in closed societies. Or in a distorted consciousness.</p>
        <p>[...] There was a bifurcation. Writing the novel, is the process of finding the personal root, which was smashed by the Masonic Oceania; and then death, as in the fate of Winston. Divisiveness, doublethink, is the highest type of thinking in Anglo-Saxon IngSoc society. It allows a person to retain the advantages of individual selective reaction to reality, and at the same time still not be a person.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>From this wellspring comes Anglo culture with all its love for freedom and burning desire to share it with lesser men. <em>Ultima Cumaei venit iam carminis aetas; Magnus ab integro saeclorum nascitur ordo. iam redit et Virgo, redeunt Saturnia regna, iam nova progenies caelo demittitur alto.</em></p>
      <p>Some might say quite reasonably that I'm being a loon. I'll respond that being a loon allows to much better correlate and predict the ongoing conflict, if not understand it. The downside is having to reject the framing implicit in this culture, one that presupposes <em>good faith</em> on behalf of Western order, even if not any specific Pompeo who enforces it. I might try to stay silent on these topics, if I survive the next ban, but in the long run it's a futile endeavor.</p>
      <p>
        <em>In China, the year 1839 is considered the beginning of modern Chinese history.</em>
      </p>
      <p>For my people it's 1917, but it should be at least 1825, or better yet the establishment of first secret societies led by foreigners, which later gave birth to Decemberists and then, sectarian communist insanity. One man I respect much has said: «To survive, the people should have long memory. In principle, nothing else is needed much at all.» Ironically I can't recall the precise citation, but I sure wish Chinese have stronger memory than Russians. Thus, I side with "them" and not "you" (even though I love your culture and characters), and believe it's the cause of conflict.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>