<post>
  <author>marinuso</author>
  <date>2020-07-28T06:29:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/fzhlkf8/</link>
  <title>"Fifty Stalins" Protests Can Do What Others Cannot</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>These are "fifty Stalins" type protests though. They're in agreement with the ruling class on almost everything, except intensity. Imagine if it were another kind of protest. Imagine if these were, for example, actual white supremacists claiming a city block. Then it absolutely would be over in a day. In fact, it would never be permitted to reach this intensity to begin with. The protests are not only tolerated by the ruling class, but to some degree even caused, if not quite orchestrated - it seems to have been a concerted effort by the media to not only light this fire but stoke it afterwards.</p>
      <p>This does not happen only in Western countries. Consider for example the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012_China_anti-Japanese_demonstrations">anti-Japanese protests in China in 2012</a>. It's actually very comparable. There's what seems like a trigger event (the Japanese government buying a disputed island from its private (but Japanese) owner). The media pushed for an uproar (under direction from Beijing, no doubt, as in China that relationship is inverted to what it is in the West), and got one. Here too, it went further than Beijing would probably have liked. Once people were in the streets, it was self-sustaining. A protest is an opportunity to let off steam, if nothing else, so there they all went. The protests, even though spontaneous by then, were not really interfered with. After all, they were still nationalists, and hating Japan is a good distraction from people's own woes. </p>
      <p>And once a crowd is riled up, a riot is almost guaranteed. The police response to those, in the beginning, generally seems to have been late and half-hearted. <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120921050100/http://ajw.asahi.com/article/asia/china/AJ201209170070">One time they even attacked a Communist Party building</a> - then, they were quickly repelled with tear gas (see, there's even a parallel to the attack on the CNN building); but still, no lethal force was used. They certainly didn't just do a Tiananmen. The looting of Japanese stores on the other hand seems to mostly have been tolerated, at least for a while. (The "protest" at the CCP building had been because they didn't think them jingoistic enough. Fifty Stalins indeed.) </p>
      <p>Then, after about a month, the Chinese government decided that enough had been enough, and so they simply prevented people from gathering. They shut down public transport near the hotbeds, put police in the streets in numbers, sent a mass text to everyone telling them to stop, and that was that. And still no lethal force was used. </p>
      <p>It never got as far out of hand as the current American protests, but the whole thing certainly seems comparable. </p>
      <p>And if the protestors had chanted "down with the CCP" instead of "fuck Japan", they would've no doubt been shot on day one <em>despite the fact that some of them later attacked a CCP building and got away mostly unharmed</em>.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>