<post>
  <author>marinuso</author>
  <date>2020-07-25T18:33:26Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fz7wbvs/</link>
  <title>The Isolation of City Folk</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The most charitable I can possibly be is that the author is somehow ignorant</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is probably the case.</p>
      <p>I grew up in a rural area, this was one of the first things I noticed when I went to college. Food production is simply not a part of their world at all, nor are other rural endeavours.</p>
      <p>I've met people, and not dumb people but people with titles, who thought sheep are skinned to get the wool, just as you would get fur. Presumably they'd seen the animal rights propaganda and extrapolated, and that was all they'd ever seen. Similarly I've met people who thought strawberries grew under the ground like potatoes. They're all terribly shocked when they see footage from a slaughterhouse, and then they go vegan for a week. Where did you <em>think</em> meat came from? But that's the thing, they don't think about it, because it's not a part of their world. Meat comes from the supermarket and the rest is abstracted away.  (This also means that they don't know about any advances. For example, veal crates are long gone, but you try telling the activists that.)</p>
      <p>These people have been enmeshed in the service economy for generations. If your dad's in marketing, your mom's in advertising, all your friends' parents while growing up are the same, and you go to school to get a business degree, then you've probably never seen any actual production of anything.
I'm going to go a bit further, and say that I don't think they really know why money has value. They know it in the abstract, like I know in the abstract that there is a lot of AIDS in Africa, but they've never really seen anything tangible being produced, let alone participate in it. Imagine how that would affect someone's views on society and the economy.</p>
      <p>They certainly don't know how much technology and science goes into modern farming. I have been asked multiple times, seemingly in good faith, whether we have paved roads and whether we still shit in the fields. It seems they mostly think time has stood still, except when there's a story about agricultural pollution in the news, and then the mood changes and the opinion basically seems to be: why are those farmers destroying nature just to make a couple of pennies, it's 2020, why don't they get a desk job. It's really not implausible that they may actually think "organic" subsistence farming is still a viable option to feed everyone.</p>
      <p>You can also tell the writer of this piece has never been out of the city, by the fact that he still thinks it will be "diverse" and "inclusive". Rural communities are small. A rural community cannot support a dozen diasporas so you can go to all their restaurants, not even today. You can only have that in a big city, with a large population density, and trade infrastructure that makes imports cheap due to economy of scale. This will be a thousand times worse if there's no technology. The smallness also means that there's no room for segregation, so even if your starting population is "diverse", they will meld together, or there will be a cleansing. I suspect the most "diverse" would be a de facto caste system like India or the old American South.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>