<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-07-24T21:50:09Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hx6u9x/on_heritage_a_pioneer_day_reflection/fz4wcse/</link>
  <title>If It Can Be Destroyed By The Truth... Should It Be?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Thanks for sharing this.</p>
      <p>Some years ago I enjoyed reading Scott Alexander's "<a href="https://archive.fo/RsStS">Mormonism: The Control Group for Christianity?</a>" (and <a href="https://archive.fo/K04Ap">Part II</a>). (The fact that Scott lived in Utah for a while doesn't come up a lot in what he's written since starting SSC, but it seems worth mentioning today, if only to file under "nothing is ever a coincidence.")  But while I think these essays are great meditations on Mormonism and Christianity, what I really want to read is <em>Part III: Mormonism: The Control Group for Christianity: The Control Group for Civilization</em>.</p>
      <p>Interlude: There is a moderately-famous moral theorist by the name of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_A._French">Peter French</a>, whose lasting contribution to American civilization might, if certain institutional insiders are to be believed, actually be <em>Citizens United</em> (to his obvious dismay).  But before he was being blamed for inadvertently advancing the cause of corporate personhood, he wrote an essay entitled <em>Losing Innocence for the Sake of Responsibility</em>, which suggested rather boldly that parents had a responsibility to expose their children to suffering.  His critics basically accused him of carving out moral justification for child abuse, even though he explicitly says this is not what he's doing (having your theories aggressively mischaracterized by other people is something of a professional hazard I guess). But French's ideas found a more sympathetic ear in Michael McKenna, in <a href="https://cdn.ymaws.com/www.apaonline.org/resource/collection/305C30F7-608F-411F-9CFA-BE03BEBCE990/v07n2Law.pdf"><em>The Loss of Innocence and the Things That Remain</em></a>.  <em>That</em> essay is about the "moral illusions" of childhood--basically the simplistic, ingroup-good-outgroup-evil kind of thinking that children so easily acquire.  McKenna summarizes his thinking and evaluation of French in closing:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>French closes his essay by noting that all of us retain some of our illusions. Stripping away all of them, French remarks, would result in psychic annihilation. As regards aiding our young in losing their innocence, we need only hope to strip away as much as needed to help bring children into the moral community. I agree. I would add that the moral illusions we begin with as children, and the critical stance toward them we are encouraged to adopt even in our early youth will play a large role in the stability of the transition of losing innocence. Although concerned to make a very different point, in “When you gonna wake up?” Bob Dylan scolds his peers for living in moral blindness, and he tells them that they had best wake up and strengthen the things that remain. The loss of innocence, I think, is best encouraged with similar advice. While bringing innocents into the moral community, and so causing the loss of their innocence, what we want, after they lose the illusion of innocent moral description, is for them to come to the sort of mature moral understanding whereby they can strengthen the illusions that remain. Hopefully, then, they can still take joy in life, even as adults who know the moral world.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>More than ten years later, I still find myself meditating, occasionally, on the idea of retained illusions, and how losing them would constitute "psychic annihilation."  It is actually pretty difficult for me to not slide into vague nihilism, because I have spent so many years first being trained, and then training others, in the arts of dismantling ideas.  My intellectual reflexes are not merely hard-determinist, materialist, and moral anti-realist; my intellectual reflexes are <em>intensely</em> skeptical, to the point of an almost grotesque degree of open-mindedness.  I am happy to entertain absolutely absurd ideas simply because they're interesting to talk about.  This was actually the tradition for most of the life of Plato's Academy, once he was gone; he himself had some very critical things to say about skepticism, but skeptics more or less controlled the Academy for centuries.  They even feature in the New Testament, in Acts 17:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>18 Then certain philosophers of the Epicureans, and of the Stoicks, encountered him. And some said, What will this babbler say? other some, He seemeth to be a setter forth of strange gods: because he preached unto them Jesus, and the resurrection.</p>
        <p>19 And they took him, and brought him unto Areopagus, saying, May we know what this new doctrine, whereof thou speakest, is?</p>
        <p>20 For thou bringest certain strange things to our ears: we would know therefore what these things mean.</p>
        <p>21 (For all the Athenians and strangers which were there spent their time in nothing else, but either to tell, or to hear some new thing.)</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This would totally have been me.  "Oh, you have a new story for me?  Great.  No, I don't believe a word of it, but who cares? Half the stuff I already seem to believe is probably false anyway. Just give me something novel."  And yet I also <em>want</em> to know true things.  It's just that I'm not really convinced that "knowing" is something I'm actually capable of doing.</p>
      <p>Anyway...</p>
      <p>...founder's myths!  My Facebook feed this week is being cluttered by Matthew Inman's <a href="https://www.theoatmeal.com/comics/believe">latest bit</a> and it makes me want to strangle someone.  I don't know how someone who so clearly agrees with me on so much can still manage to sound condescending and wrong <em>every damn time he writes a comic</em>.  I think maybe he's just constitutionally incapable of recognizing his own hypocrisy? Well, that's not an uncommon problem. The people who would benefit most from internalizing that comic include some people whose beliefs he most clearly gores (and intends to gore!), and yet if he'd generalized his point better, to actually challenge some of his <em>in-group's</em> beliefs (as well?), I think it would have been a <em>far</em> more effective bit of work (albeit probably still not very effective).  Because as interesting as the statement "George Washington had a set of false teeth made from the teeth of human slaves" <em>is</em>, it's also a statement that people will try to contextualize.  <em>Why</em> do you share that fact, instead of any of an infinite set of other facts?  Is it because you like trivia?  Do you know lots of other dental archaeology?  If so, I'm going to hear "George Washington had a set of false teeth made from the teeth of human slaves" <em>very differently</em> than if you follow it up with, say, a comment about the descendants of Thomas Jefferson and Sally Hemings having a common male ancestor from the Jefferson line.</p>
      <p>Which is not to say that there is no value in knowing something about the source materials of dental prosthesis in colonial America!  But there is a <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2016/03/13/destroy/">phrase from P.C. Hodgell</a>, commonly misattributed to Carl Sagan and even <a href="https://www.hpmor.com/chapter/23">featured in HPMOR</a>, that claims:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>That which can be destroyed by the truth should be.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It seems like a very nice, rationalist kind of quote, one to which I am so reflexively drawn that it <em>never even occurs to me to question it</em>, until I remember what French and McKenna had to say about the "illusions that remain."</p>
      <p>If I can be destroyed by the truth... should I be?</p>
      <p>If my nation can be destroyed by the truth... should it be?</p>
      <p>If the entirety of the human race would be destroyed by having their illusions stripped away, their minds exposed to naught but the pure, unvarnished truths of the universe...?</p>
      <p>I <em>like</em> facts, to the extent that I can convince myself there are any.  I cuddle up to the cold, hard truths of life in ways that frankly horrify some of my family and friends.  I suspect a lot of people in this community would say the same.  But when I am at my most rational, I'm afraid I am also almost always at my most nihilistic, my most frightened, my most utterly consumed by existential despair.  We don't tell stories about George Washington because it is crucially important to know the truth about where his teeth came from; we tell stories to persuade others to share our illusions (especially, our illusions about <em>what matters</em>).  As anyone who has ever cleverly opined that "fiat currency is a mass illusion" or "the idea of a nation is a shared hallucination" or "technically, the only things you like are serotonin and dopamine" can attest, it's not hard, in our age, to reduce the things people cherish to absurdity.</p>
      <p>The question is, why do that?</p>
      <p>If I may be forgiven a certain bleakness, Jane Brice is dead.  Even if her beliefs about eternal life turn out to be correct, she is regardless well past seriously caring what you think of her.  Soon enough, the same will be true for you, and me, and everyone.  As a certain economist opined, in the long run, we are all dead.</p>
      <p>And yet I can't help but wonder at the words, bowdlerized from <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0156849097">a certain essay</a>, "It mattered to that one."</p>
      <p>Jesus Christ is supposed to have said something like "let the dead bury their own dead."  I am probably not the best person to consult for Christian exegesis, but I doubt he meant this literally.  Stories of the Utah Pioneers are not there to glorify those who are gone, but to give the people who followed after them something on which to build their own lives, and their own stories.  <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/8tpcyn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_25_2018/e1a4jp7/">Dust we are and to dust we shall return</a>, but while we are yet alive, our dreams are real. We need not bury our dead nor worry excessively about their truths; they will eventually tend to that themselves, and we with them.  To adapt the words of David Brooks in a new context--</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>By dissolving the dream under the acid of an excessive realism, you trap generations in the past and destroy the guiding star that points to a better future.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Thank you for celebrating Jane Brice here, with us, today.  She sounds like quite a guiding star.  Happy Pioneer Day.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>