<post>
  <author>pusher_robot_</author>
  <date>2020-07-25T16:19:12Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fz7haaj/</link>
  <title>On Mask-Wearing: The Virtue Is In the Choosing</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>"I have the freedom to do what I please." </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>More directly, "fuck you, I won't do what you tell me."</p>
      <p>And I can identify heartily with this.  I thought the early anti-mask directives were ridiculous and am pretty well convinced that they are probably the biggest bang-for-buck (or inconvenience) method for controlling diseases spread by fluids.  I'm actually losing confidence the longer we go on with these mask mandates without the infection rate slowing, but I would not argue that it seems a decent common-sense measure.</p>
      <p>BUT...my <em>personality</em> cannot stand lecturing, nagging, scolding, condescending propaganda.  I struggle not to rebel against reflexively against anybody trying to force me to act a certain way.  You could call it a type of contrarianism but I am actually quite a conformist person.  When I can <em>choose</em> to conform.  Give me a choice between anarchy and order and I'll live in an orderly way and enjoy it.  Try to force me to live in an orderly way and I'll not enjoy it.</p>
      <p>I think there's also something going on at a, I don't know the precise term, an ethical level?  I know this is something that I've thought about a lot, as someone with a passing interest in ancient philosophy and how practical to living it seems compared to modern philosophy.  But in brief, a lot of the most popular, and it seems most useful ethics, distinguish duty from virtue.  </p>
      <p>So, you can describe a set of duties by whatever ethics and these define the sort of minimally viable life.  Fail in your duties and you fail at life.  Fulfill your duties and you will not necessarily be a great person, you will not necessarily achieve happiness, but you will succeed at being a full member of society.  As such, failures in duties will be punished.  To the extent possible, society will attempt to require you to fulfill your duties by whatever means are reasonable.  As a result, meeting your duties is not particularly praiseworthy - it is not a marker of success or achievement, or even personal accomplishment.  It is the baseline.</p>
      <p>Then you can describe a set of virtues that go above and beyond these duties.  Achieving virtues is key to achieving happiness and personal fulfillment, and necessary to achieve goals, but failing to achieve virtue it not a failure in your duty to society, moreso a failure to yourself.  It is a personal failure.  Likewise, achieving virtue is not attributable to society, it is a personal accomplishment that one should be rightly proud of and receive praise for.</p>
      <p>Depending on who you believe, achieving virtue is <em>the</em> critical component to living a happy life.  Partly for materialistic reasons, but mostly for psychological reasons.  Without that foundation, you cannot achieve contentment, you cannot achieve fulfillment, and you cannot experience self-regard.  This in particular was the insight of the ancient Stoics - that true happiness comes not from without but from within, and that almost any circumstance is tolerable over time armed with the knowledge that you did the best you could, which typically means acting in a virtuous way.</p>
      <p>So suppose you have been living this way, acting virtuously and feeling good about it.  But now some other people come along and tell you, no, you weren't acting with virtue at all, in fact you were barely fulfilling your basic duties.  This is shocking!  This completely invalidates all of your self-regard and cancels any good you thought you did.  In fact, your barely avoided falling below the baseline of failure!  This is how I ultimately feel about a lot of mandates, from mandatory wealth redistribution to mandatory seatbelts to mandatory mask-wearing.  They are raising the level of duty to ever-higher levels, and thereby <em>robbing virtue</em> from people.</p>
      <p>And by robbing people of virtue, by making what should be praiseworthy and a source of pride into the minimal requirements for existing, they are robbing them of their self-regard and tragically, their ability to actually be happy with their lives in a meaningful way.  Because ultimately all the material welfare in the world cannot fill the psychological hole that having personal accomplishments does.</p>
      <p>An objection might be, if there's clear agreement about what is virtuous, why cannot we mandate that everyone be virtuous and thereby achieve this for all?  But first, not everyone can be virtuous.  Some people are vicious (in the meaning of partaking more vice than virtue), but still productive members of society.  Sometimes the most productive members!  It seems desirable that there be room in society for such people, so long as they meet their basic duties.  And also, a cosmopolitan society is going to have at least some disagreement on the existence and/or importance of different virtues and vices, so some discretionary latitude is wise.</p>
      <p>But more importantly, because the <em>personal</em> accomplishment is in the choosing!  You cannot achieve personal virtue from being forced to do it, it is simply a logical impossibility.  You can only achieve compliance and maybe a small amount of virtue from complying peacefully.  That's the truly insidious thing: the more virtuous your society is to begin with, the more damage such reduction in choice does, even though the outcome barely changes at all!  A mask mandate, as opposed to a plea for the commonwealth in a mostly virtuous society, achieves only slightly higher rates of compliance at the expense of robbing virtue from everyone.  Such things can certainly be justifiable depending on the necessity, but this is real psychological damage that must be accounted for.</p>
      <p>In short, I'm happiest when I'm wearing a mask because I chose to and that makes me a better person.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>