<post>
  <author>Southkraut</author>
  <date>2020-07-28T14:19:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/fzij7u8/</link>
  <title>Putting On a Preaching Hat</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Hey! Let me put on my preaching hat, I do so enjoy it and get so few opportunities to wear it. This may sound a little aggressive, so please know that when I make a second-person address, it's really just to a strawman and not to your actual self.</p>
      <p>What is best in life? Perpetuating your genes and memes! Knowing that what you do matters! Hearing the loving adoration of those who are important to you!</p>
      <p>Fun is irrelevant. Happiness is overrated. Only that which transcends the individual matters, and all that disappears with the individual only matters in so far as it helped the individual contribute more to the ability of subsequent generations to do even better.</p>
      <p>Individualism is a dead end. What will future generations think of you and your shallow pursuits? They will not. You will have played no role. At least in scarcity societies you are forced to make economic contributions; even that would lack in the Brave New World - you would be truly irrelevant. Not even your contemporaries would have any interest in you - you add nothing to their lives, they do not need you or benefit from you. Past generations would curse you for squandering their efforts; entire lines of descend stretching back to the earliest organisms have worked and suffered to give you the best starting position they could manage, and instead of continuing this work you descend to the level of a rat with a wire stuck in its brain, determined to pull a lever until you die of having ignored all but pleasure.</p>
      <p>Does yesterday's shallow pursuit give you fulfillment today? When on your deathbed, will you look back on a lifetime of hedonism and consider it time well-spent? Nothing of you will remain; nothing will be passed on. Your pleasure dies with you. You may as well never have been born. Why should anyone bother to build and maintain Utopia for you? You can only hope that there should be enough others of the same mind as you.</p>
      <p>As for the opposite species, those who honor what the past has yielded to them and are making every effort to preserve these goods and add to them: Do you think they are doing it in the hope that their descendants will one day sever this continuity and become like you? Just waiting for the day when technology and social engineering will allow their inheritors to give up and lean back and live one full lifetime without effort, without commitment, without responsibility, without any of the things that had to be provided again and again to make a better life for subsequent generations possible?</p>
      <p>You are a dread calamity to anyone who looks beyond himself; a sink of invaluable resources that returns nothing of value, a dasher of hopes and violator of the most basic and natural trust between generations. What thousands and millions and more before you have worked for, you put an end to.</p>
      <p>I hope this illustrated a counter-position, even though it is admittedly more rambling than reason. I would have liked to simply describe it in neutral terms, but I do get too emotional when thinking about the subject. So, sorry for the form of the thing; hopefully you can glean my point regardless.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>