<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-07-29T01:43:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/fzksflb/</link>
  <title>In Defense of Tracking</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I can tell you that being in a mixed class is better for less capable students because 1) if only a few students are struggling, I can give each some help. If half the class or more is struggling, because all of the more capable students are in a separate class, forget it. 2) struggling students can get help from advanced students.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I appreciate you chiming in with your experience here, more so because I strongly disagree.</p>
      <p>There are two parallel scenarios I like to imagine here:</p>
      <p>1: Imagine a K-12 school without an age divide. High school seniors are placed in the same classroom as kindergarteners. Why? Same reasons. The 12th graders, having already mastered the material, will be perfectly placed to help kindergarteners struggling to learn for the first time. In addition, with fewer kindergarteners in your class, you can give each some help. In a class of only kindergarteners, forget it.</p>
      <p>2: Picture a coach with a bunch of kids on a basketball team, talking about her preference for mixed-ability groups. The star players can help the stragglers, and so can the coach, so it works out great.</p>
      <p>Both of these scenarios are near-identical to same-age, mixed-ability classrooms, but they both (at least to me) feel much weirder. I think that's because we've gotten used to rationalizing same-age, mixed-ability classrooms in a way that we haven't for those. </p>
      <p>The fact is, it's impossible to have a classroom that isn't mixed-ability. One of my own most memorable teaching experiences came as a substitute teacher when I spent a few days in a transitional school for ~18-year-olds with intellectual disabilities. All of the kids in the classroom were somewhere around the mental level of five-year-olds. And yet the same patterns popped up. There were a couple of students who were eager to learn, participatory, relatively sharp, and ready to help the other students. There was one who spent around two-thirds of the day in one long tantrum of sheer rage.</p>
      <p>On the other end, you reach the absolute pinnacle of performance in a discipline, and what do you find? Mixed ability. Back to basketball: You have teams comprised of <em>literally the best players in the world</em>, and you get the full range from stars to benchwarmers, with visible skill gaps between them in every area.</p>
      <p>Now zoom back in to a standard, same-age, mixed-ability classroom. What do you find, by reifying the idea that kids should be tossed in with whoever happens to be their age? I'll focus in on the less capable students, because they're the ones your argument hinges on:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>They will never, ever, ever get the experience of being the star. Every classroom they step into in the subject, they will feel they are worse than the others around them, they're struggling to keep up, they're the one the teacher needs to spend extra time with.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Their curricula will never be built around them. As such, they will never learn at a comfortable pace. Rushed from point to point without the time to fully absorb them—because the class schedule must be kept—they'll barely get the feel for one subject before it's whisked away, never to be seen again, in what feels to them to be a mad rush to keep up.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Seeds of resentment are planted between them and the other students. Both notice where the teacher's attention is going. The one is requisitioned as an unofficial assistant while they're aiming to learn, the other becomes a project. How can either be comfortable with the division?</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <hr />
      <p>I believe that, if something is worth doing, it is worth doing explicitly. If it's worth having more capable students act as mentors, establish a mentor program (possibly between grades, letting "less capable students" from one grade go down to mentor kids a couple of years younger than them. If there's value in deliberately having a wide ability range in one room, no need to restrict it by age--keep it as wide as possible, to maximize the value. If the whole class is struggling with the material, simplify it until it's at their level and they're not struggling to keep up. My impression of the reasoning behind same-age, mixed-ability classrooms is that it's a retroactive justification for a previously established system, established independent of the systemic flaws.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>