<post>
  <author>Verda-Fiemulo</author>
  <date>2020-07-25T04:03:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fz5ytae/</link>
  <title>Thoughts on "Ethnicity Without Groups"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I just started reading "Ethnicity without Groups" by  Rogers Brubaker, and I'm finding it quite interesting so far.</p>
      <p>The first chapter introduces the distinction between groups, categories, and organizations.</p>
      <p>Basically, a <strong>group</strong> is a population that acts more or less as one unit in society - it is a conglomeration of people with relatively unified goals and interests. The book argues that  group-ness is something that ebbs and flows, and interacts with <strong>categories</strong> - which might be thought of as putative groups, or classifications of people within a society.</p>
      <p>In the book's conception of things, the "ethnoracial pentagon" in the United States (African American, Asian American, White, Latino and Native American) is a collection of highly heterogeneous categories, and only African Americans have really been partially groupified in modern America. (The book was written in 2006.)</p>
      <p>Basically, a big part of the book's argument is that we shouldn't necessarily start from groups when examining history or politics. Humans have a coding bias that causes them to classify events as things like "ethnic conflicts" or "ethnic violence" too readily. The book wants to start from the experience of categories, and examine many of these events as "ethnicized conflicts" and "ethnicized violence" instead - as events that are made about, and defined by the media and society as about ethnicity even when that might not be the best lens to examine them through, since conflicts are often about many things.</p>
      <p>Rounding out this characterization is the idea of <strong>organizations</strong>, which are organized bodies of people that claim to speak for  and represent a larger group. Examples might be the IRA in Ireland claiming to speak for all Catholic Irish people, ISIS claiming to speak for all Muslims, or Black Lives Matter claiming to speak for all Black people. Organizations have different amount of "representative-ness" relative to the categories they claim to speak for. You could have a lot of people of a particular category agreeing with them and their actions, or most of them rejecting them.</p>
      <p>The book argues that the "protagonists" in many ethnic conflicts are organizations, and that often violence proceeds a category making the jump to being a group (or increasing in group-ness.) Basically, if an organization does something violent that provokes a state acting violently against people of a particular category, it can increase the degree to which people coordinate their actions as a single bloc.</p>
      <p>None of this strikes me as particularly "surprising" or new, but I do think it's a fairly clearheaded way of breaking down how ethnicity and other cohorts work in society.</p>
      <p>In the United States, we might say that racial categories of white and Black might be becoming groupified in the current moment, due to the actions of the organization Black Lives Matter and the retaliation that this is provoking from police and law enforcement.</p>
      <p>Part of the danger of identity politics and cancel culture is that they take categories in society and essentialize them, trying to make and sustain the groupification of these categories. It makes "genderified and ethnicized conflict and violence" more likely in society.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>