<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2020-12-05T23:43:33Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k3pgku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_30/ger2vnr/</link>
  <title>/u/DeanTheDull on the independence of Scotland</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The Scottish Independence is borked, and not in a good way, by being a victim of the SNP's own success. Scottish independence realistically only has a good chance of winning a referendum within the next five years/next PM- afterwards, most of the underlying contexts supporting it dry up, and aren't liable to come back.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>Part 1: The SNP doesn't have a leg to stand on</p>
      <p>The SNP is functionally a regional advocacy party that managed to seize the role of 'primary opposition party' (or 'dominant regional party' if you prefer) vis-a-vis the British Tory Party due to the utter collapse of the British labour party in the North as it become dominated by London-based progressive interests. As a First Past the Post system, Britain only has room for two main parties in any given region, and the SNP took up what was once a Labour, the other then-credible national party, power center. From there, Labour has done very, very well for itself... but not because Scottish Independence got really really popular across the entire public.</p>
      <p>The SNP is successful beyond the scope of support for independence for the same reason any regional-identity parties are strong in other countries where a regional identity is at odds with the identity of the national center- they aren't the ruling party, the ruling party the ethno/cultural outgroup, and they do advocate regional interests against the other-regional national power center. More money for social spending, certain symbolic concessions and increased autonomy, etc. Same thing that you see in Quebec in Canada, Catalonia in Spain, Hong Kong in China, Okinawa in Japan, etc. 'Regional interest parties' are popular wherever you go, and in a FPTP system only the biggest two parties stay competitive over time. The SNP stealing Labor role is rare, but hardly unprecedented.</p>
      <p>The issue for the SNP, though, is that their primary lever for getting the government to give them an independence referendum- namely, 'We will let you rule the UK if you let us leave it' is useless, because anyone who needs the SNP's help to rule in the UK won't be able to rule if they do leave, and anyone who doesn't need the SNP's support doesn't need to give them the referendum in the first place. The Tories right now are demonstrating they can rule with quite comfortable majorities without a single SNP member of parliament, and they've no need or incentive to give the SNP what it wants.</p>
      <p>There's been some discussion on the possibility of short-sighted or reckless leaders, and if Corbyn were still relevant they'd have a point, but that and even the function of Labour as a nationalist party in its own right still largely misses the point that even <em>if</em> a hypoethetical non-nationalist labour government came to power with the help of the SNP, it couldn't <strong><em>stay</em></strong> in power beyond separation without it. Which means they either break the agreement- in which the SNP has no leverage because no one wants to support it- or the SNP keeps the alliance going despite not getting independence- in which case the SNP has no leverage because it's demonstrated it doesn't actually care about said independence- or Scotland does go independent, and the ruling coalition is thrown out the moment the Scots can no longer provide votes in Parliament.</p>
      <p>The moment a Labour-SNP alliance loses the SNP, Labour is doomed to a generation (or more) of being a permanent minority party to the English Tories, who will even <em>more</em> outweigh the rest of the UK combined. The only way that doesn't hurt the government that allows it is if the Scots are so detested the English <em>want</em> them gone... at which point the SNP, again, has no leverage, because if kicking the Scotts out were popular in the first place the English wouldn't need the SNP's help for it.</p>
      <p>And that's the issue- the SNP has nothing to offer a party of enduring political interests, because it's offer offers only short term gain (getting into government) with severe long-term costs (never getting back into government).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>