<post>
  <author>Folamh3</author>
  <date>2020-12-08T10:17:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k8bxy1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_07/gf1ht8i/</link>
  <title>/u/Folamh3 explores moral panic in connection (hah) with social media</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The social-networks-as-utility argument possibly does not quite work because consumers of a utility do not affect how others use said utility</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I once read that, shortly after the invention of the telephone, there were calls for it to be banned specifically because it would enable criminals to plan crimes without meeting in person. Rephrase this in the language of modern identity politics ("racists will use the telephone to plan hate crimes without meeting in person") and it looks pretty similar to the modern debate about allowing "undesirable individuals" on social media.</p>
      <p>The telephone, electricity supply and postal service have been fixtures in our society for so long that I think we have all collectively made our peace with the idea that "undesirable individuals" are just as entitled to use these services as anyone else. It's "liberalism" in its original sense of the word. If I went into a phone shop in order to buy a mobile phone, and was required to sign a statement outlining my commitment to equity, diversity and inclusion before they would allow me to buy one, that would be a grotesque violation of my civil liberties and right to privacy.</p>
      <p>(I'm curious whether anything along these lines ever happened in the era of Joe McCarthy.)</p>
      <p>If one stops and thinks about it for five seconds, it should be immediately obvious that, whatever phone network you use, there are thousands if not millions of people on the same network who are, by any metric, rather odious characters - drug dealers, gangsters, wife-beaters, whatever. Some of these people use the features of the phone network in order to conduct their nefarious activities (arranging drug drops, scheduling kneecappings <em>etc.</em>). Anyone who thinks about this for five seconds concludes that a) yes, this is obviously true and b) it would be absurd to hold the network operator personally responsible for this state of affairs. Supposing I wanted to drum up some negative publicity for a particular mobile network operator - all I need to do is to create a list of local  drug dealers, gangsters, far-right politicians, child molesters, wife-beaters; do some digging to find out which mobile phone network they're on; and hey presto, the Twitter campaign writes itself: "can you <em>believe</em> the kind of human garbage that Verizon allows on their network? #dumpsterfire #cancelled"</p>
      <p>I don't think it's reasonable to expect phone network operators (also electricity providers, water <em>etc.</em>) to conduct rigorous background checks on every potential customer in order to ensure that they have never (or <em>will</em> never) done or said anything which could potentially embarrass the brand via guilt by association. I don't think anyone else thinks this is reasonable either. However, a great many people seem to think it is reasonable to expect Facebook, Twitter, Google <em>etc.</em> to do something which, in effect, is rather similar.</p>
      <p>I think this may be partly down to the relative novelty of social media. Telephones and electricity have been so firmly entrenched in our society for so long (upwards of three generations depending on what part of the world you live in) that everyone, regardless of age, understands that not having a phone renders you more or less incapable of full participation in modern society - how can an employer contact you with an invitation to an interview? how can you be called to jury duty in a timely fashion? how can you pay your utility bills <em>etc.</em> The common refrain when conservatives (and other "undesirable individuals") complain about being booted off of a given social media platform is "if you don't like it, build your own platform" or "it's not like you need Twitter". Telephones are treated as a necessity, whereas social media is seen as a luxury. Of course, no one under the age of 35 <em>really</em> believes this: every Millennial and Zoomer implicitly understands that Facebook, Twitter and LinkedIn are just as important for professional networking as owning a mobile phone (if not moreso). But the defence sounds plausible to the ears of the Boomer who got his first job by "knocking on some doors" and could never make head or tail of this new-fangled "email" thing.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>