<post>
  <author>GeriatricZergling</author>
  <date>2020-12-07T18:16:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k8bxy1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_07/geyscyw/</link>
  <title>/u/GeriatricZergling on the mind/body problem in transsexual therapy theorizing</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm going to get on my old hobby-horse once again: the importance of understanding <em>mechanism</em>.</p>
      <p>Like it or not, transgender individuals <em>exist</em>, and like any phenomenon which exists, there must be a cause.  Except right now, we have almost zero idea of what that cause is; there are some intriguing preliminary studies, but we are so far from a mechanistic answer that it rounds down to zero.  Is it purely psychological? Due to environment (social or chemical)? Pre-natal, post-natal, or both?  Is it genetic (lumping epigenetic and gene regulation in here for simplicity)?  Consequently, all we have to go on is the individual's self-reported internal mental state and experiences, but humans are <em>terrible</em> at accurately understanding their own minds, leading to both false positives and false negatives, especially when young.</p>
      <p>This is true for lots of other behavioral/mental phenomena too (e.g. sexuality), but none of those require making decisions before adulthood which are irreversible. If someone think they're gay, but turns out not to be (or vice versa), the consequences are largely social and mental, not physical/medical.  Even with genuine psychological pathologies (e.g. schizophrenia, OCD, autism), few of the treatments are totally irreversible.</p>
      <p>If we actually understood the <em>mechanisms</em> which make individual trans (including any sub-types within that), it would be possible to accurately assess whether someone genuinely would be helped by particular treatments (e.g. by taking an fMRI or genetic test), just like we do with physical diseases ("is that leg pain sciatica or a deep vein thromosis? Get a doppler ultrasound, an ACT, and a D-dimer test.").  But as it is, we're having to make major medical decisions about minors (technically, denial of treatment until 18 is still a decision) based only on the self-reported internal mental states of individuals who have imperfect understanding of said states (as we all do) compounded by their age.  Regardless of your views on the cause or optimal treatments, this is a recipe for a LOT of false negatives and false positives.</p>
      <p>Of course, "just figure out the mechanistic cause for a complex human behavior" is approximately the same as saying "you can easily solve this murder if you just invent a time machine so you can go watch it yourself!".  I have my own personal hypothesis (mutations to non-coding gene regulatory regions), but I'm in no position to actually test it (my expertise is in a very different area of biology).  Still, I actually think it could make for a fairly tractable study system, as far as these traits go, especially given the urgency of the situation.  The biggest problems would be avoiding social landmines ("transmedicalism" and accidentally proving a biological basis for male-female psychological differences, to name a few) and sample size.</p>
      <p>TL;DR - This is simply a fundamental problem of having to make medical/surgical decisions based only on self-reported mental states in minors.  Any solution without a mechanistic understanding of the system will just be shifting the balance between false-positives and false-negatives.  The only way out is more information.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>