<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-12-01T20:54:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k3pgku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_30/geaqfk1/</link>
  <title>/u/Ilforte translates Dostoevsky on Asian Russia</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Does Russia prefer a future where it's China's lapdog rather than <em>primus inter pares</em> in Europe?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'll answer in my own post. For now, I'll let a wiser man speak.<br />
Since it has proven burdensome to find a free English copy, this is a partial translation of Dostoevsky's «Geok-Tepe. What Does Asia Mean to Us?» - one of the last sections of <em>Writer's Diary</em>, a warning he left before his death. </p>
      <p>«[...] Thus it is necessary that Russia be not only in Europe, but also in Asia; because the Russian is not only European, but also Asian. Not merely that: perhaps even more of our hopes lie in Asia than in Europe. Not only that: in our future destinies, maybe Asia is our main outcome!</p>
      <p>I anticipate the indignation with which others will read this retrograde assumption (and it is an axiom for me). Yes, if there is one of the most important roots that we need to improve, it is our view on Asia. We have to banish the lackey's fear that we will be called Asian barbarians in Europe and will be told that we are Asians even more than Europeans. This dread that Europe will consider us Asians has haunted us for almost two centuries. But especially this shame increased in us in this nineteenth century and has reached almost something panicked, reached the "metal and bugbear" of Moscow merchant wives. This erroneous shame of ours, this erroneous view of ourselves as only the Europeans but not Asians (who we have never ceased to be), - this shame and this erroneous view have been costly, very costly to us in these two centuries, and we paid for it both with the loss of our spiritual independence, with our unsuccessful European policy, and finally with money, money that God knows how much we have spent to prove to Europe that we are only Europeans and not Asians. But Peter's push to bring us into Europe, which was necessary and life-saving in the beginning, was still too strong, and this is already where we are not the only ones to blame. What didn't we do so that Europe were to recognize us for her own, for Europeans, and Europeans alone, not the Tatars! We bothered Europe continuously and incessantly, we volunteered to meddle in all her affairs and rogue ops. At times we scared her with force, sent our armies there to "save the kings"; then we bowed to her again, as we shouldn't have, and assured her that we were created only to serve Europe and make her happy. In the twelfth year, having driven Napoleon out, we did not reconcile with him, as a chosen few visionary Russian people advised and wished then; but moved with full force to make Europe happy, freeing it from its captor. Of course, the picture was vivid: on the one hand, there was a despot and a kidnapper, on the other - a peacemaker and resurrector. Yet our political forte at that time lied not in the picture, but in the fact that this kidnapper was in such a position (for the first time in his career), that he would have made peace with us firmly and sincerely, and for a long time, maybe forever. On the condition that we would not interfere with him in Europe, he would have given us the East, and our current Eastern question - the threat and the trouble of our present and our future - would have been resolved long ago. The kidnapper said this himself later, and probably he did not lie, that he could not have done anything better than to be in alliance with us, so that we would have the East, and he would have the West. He probably would have dealt with European nations even then. They were too weak then to prevent us in the East – even England. Napoleon, perhaps, would have fallen afterwards, or after his death his dynasty would have, but the East would have remained ours. (We would have had the sea then, and then we could have even met England on the sea as equals.) But we sacrificed everything for the picture. And what of it: all those nations who were liberated by us – immediately, even without having finished Napoleon, began to look at us with the most rabid ill will and with the worst suspicions. At the Congresses they immediately joined together against us in lockstep and seized everything, and not only left us nothing, but also were granted commitments, though voluntary, but very unprofitable to us as it turned out later. Then, despite the lesson learned, what have we been doing in all the other years of the century and are even doing today? Have we not helped to strengthen the German powers, have we not created strength for them such that they may now be even stronger than us? Yes, to say that we contributed to their growth and strength is not exaggerated. Didn't we, at their call, go to tame their strife, didn't we protect their rear when they could be threatened by trouble? Didn't they, on the contrary, come to our rear when we were threatened by misfortune, or threatened to come to our rear when we were threatened by another misfortune? The end result is that now everyone in Europe, every [untranslatable] there, holds a stone that has long been prepared for us, and is waiting only for the first collision. So what was it that we have won in Europe, serving her so well? Only her hatred! [...]</p>
      <p>But why this hatred for us, why can't they all believe in us once and for all, believe in our innocence, <strong>believe that we are their friends and servants, good servants, and that even the entire European purpose of ours is to serve Europe and its welfare.</strong> (And isn't it so, haven't we done the same for the whole century, have we done anything for ourselves, have we achieved a whit for ourselves? Everything has gone to Europe!) No, they can't believe in us! The main reason is that they can't recognize us as their brethren in any way.</p>
      <p>They will never believe that we can truly participate together with them and equally with them in the future destinies of their civilization. They have recognized us as strangers to their civilization, aliens, impostors. They recognize us as thieves who stole their enlightenment and appropriated their dresses. The Turks, the Semites, are closer to them in spirit than we, the Aryans. There is one extraordinary reason for all this: we do not bring to humanity the same idea that they do - that is the reason!</p>
      <p>And this despite the fact that our "Russian Europeans" are trying their best to assure Europe that we do not and will not have any idea, and in the future it can not be so that Russia is able to have an idea, but it can only imitate; that in the end we will just imitate everything and that we are not Asians, not barbarians, and are quite like them, the Europeans. But Europe, at least this time, did not believe our Russian Europeans. On the contrary, in this case it, so to speak, coincided in its conclusions with our Slavophiles, although it does not know them at all and at most has heard something about them. The coincidence is in the fact that Europe also believes, as well as Slavophiles do, that we have an "idea", our own, special and not European, that Russia <em>can</em> have an idea. Of course, Europe does not know anything about the essence of this idea of ours yet, because if it did, it would immediately calm down and even rejoice. But it will surely find out one day, when the most critical moment in its fate will come. But now she does not believe; she is afraid of the idea, admitting it for us. And finally, we disgust her, even personally, although they are sometimes polite around us. They, for example, willingly admit that Russian science can produce a few remarkable figures now, to present some good works, even ones that have served their European science already. But still there is no way that Europe will believe that Russia can give birth not only to scientific workers (even very talented), but also to geniuses, leaders of humanity such as Bacon, Kant and Aristotle. They will never believe this, because they do not believe in our civilization, and do not know our future idea. And in reality, they are right: we will indeed have neither Bacon, nor Newton, nor Aristotle, until we hit the road and become spiritually independent. Everything else is the same, in our arts, in industry: Europe is ready to praise us, to pat us on the head, but does not recognize us as its own, despises us secretly and obviously considers us inferior as people, as a breed, and sometimes we just disgust them, inspire disgust in general, especially when we throw ourselves on their neck with brotherly kisses.  </p>
      <p>But it is difficult to turn away from the window to Europe, there is a fatum. Meanwhile, Asia - this may indeed be our outcome in our future - I exclaim it again! And if we had at least partially assimilated this idea - oh, what a root would have been healed! Asia, our Asian Russia, - this is also our sick root, which is something not just to refresh, but to resurrect and recreate! A principle, a new principle, a new look at the case - that's what is essential!»</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>