<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-12-08T21:50:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k912yq/the_superscary_theory_of_the_21st_century/gf3jzn1/</link>
  <title>/u/Ilforte objects to Noah Smith's theorizing on technology and statecrafting</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This article is derivative so I'll also just rehash my usual argument (also, sleep deprivation).</p>
      <p>I posit that Noah Smith is another intelligentsia member who, <a href="https://www.takimag.com/article/666666666-immigrants/">like Yglesias</a>, has deduced that China hawkism will be a dominant trend of US political and cultural life in the decades to come, and endeavors to find his place in this grift. His "theory" is an act of testing the waters. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Many people believe that the so-called “color revolutions” in East Europe and Central Asia played an important role in destabilizing the USSR and, later, checking Russian power. Some claim that those revolutions were fomented by the CIA. I think that’s unlikely, but whether it’s true seems pretty immaterial. The much more important fact, it seems to me, is that this sort of instability is a feature of the modern, interconnected world</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Shallow take, very <em>chef's kiss</em> 2009 rationalist. The most important fact is that some countries have privileged control over global networks (as in, they literally hold their CEOs, board and most employees by their asses), and thus can enable or foment protests selectively. No, I'm not buying the idea that The Yellow/Red Peril is less scrupulous than US Intelligence services. Less professional, maybe; even certainly so. And therefore more visibly brutal. Waterboarding and gulags are signs of failure to do the job discretely: the faintest hint of investigation into "harboring foreign agents" or even "monopolism" and "tax evasion" would be all it takes to bring Dorsey or Zuck or Pichai to heel (and Congressional hearings are a not-so-subtle reminder). This is why TikTok is a threat to democracy human rights freedom, but selling it to Microsoft would fix everything at once. And it's also not a coincidence that Microsoft has exclusive license for GPT-3. Or that said Dorsey can ridicule Trump and doodle over his tweets; or that, much like Chinese networks, his one prevents <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/10/15/21516729/facebook-twitter-new-york-post-hunter-biden-emails-laptop-story-social-media-moderation-problems">private sharing of wrongthink</a> that could jeopardize "election integrity". You only need a sufficiently cynical understanding of actual power structure in a given country to see it all fitting together like a grand interlocking puzzle. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Social media dramatically lowers the cost of both organizing a protest and spreading a protest-related ideology.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Does it? What about Metcalfe's law and superstar effect? If everyone you can "organize" is already on TweetBook, and TweetBook demands identity verification (by phone, similarly-controlled corporate mail, ID...) and bans dissent of specific sort, whether algorithmically or manually, who ya gonna call?  Will you even bother risking your accumulated <em>social credit</em>, followers and memes stored in conversations on a server you don't own? You can go to 8ch*n, to connect with a small group of similarly "redpilled" refugees from corporate platforms... aw shucks, it's gone! It can be crushed instantly, if need be, since the justifications are commonly known and obviously true! All dissenting internet lives on borrowed time. </p>
      <p>Dodging censorship, exchanging directions to free platforms, is still easy. For 140 IQ individuals, I mean. Normies are already safely locked up in their pens, without an inkling as to how the lock works or whether it exists; when they get into Qanon or some other nonsensical narrative en masse, you can rest assured it's a product of conscious choice by the platform to not expend effort or invite controversy with a crackdown.<br />
The water level will keep rising.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>This, then, is the Scary Theory of the 21st Century: Perhaps the internet is not a tool of freedom so much as evolutionary pressure that selects for authoritarianism. Perhaps social media has changed the nature of great-power competition into an endurance match in which control of the internet is key.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>What disingenuous framing. Great-power competition is offensive in nature, only kept in check by MAD (or, more traditionally, risks that come with overstretching oneself). It's not that China and US compete on robustness to chaotic shocks generated by some collective unconscious toxicity in the web. It's that US demands that China be open to "free trade" of its ideas (read, propaganda), just like 19th century Britain demanded, and enforced with violence, that it be open to free trade of opium (yes, I love that example) and just like US demanded, under threat of military force, that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_C._Perry#Perry_Expedition:_opening_of_Japan,_1852%E2%80%931854">Japan</a> opens wholesale. You won't even consider protectionism when your merchandise is obviously superior across the price range. You don't need 50 Cent Army when you can cultivate millions of true believers who'll eagerly mock and jeer at every move of your geopolitical opponent, and <a href="https://nypost.com/2020/11/30/australia-demands-apology-from-china-for-faked-image-of-soldier/">whine disingenuously</a> when the response comes. 50 Cent Army is a joke in comparison. Have you seen them in action? They're nationalist dorks who sabotage their very project. </p>
      <p>(Curiously, the Power sees it fit to censor <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsargrad_TV">Russian outlets which host Dugin</a>. He attributes it to his personal importance, but maybe that's not the reason). </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>But unlike the U.S., China has enthusiastically bent this new technology toward creating a deep and robust system of government surveillance and social control.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Good thing that the US can outsource this to companies like <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/10/21/magazine/palantir-alex-karp.html">Palantir</a>! And that everyone forgot about PRISM and history of clipper chips, evidently. Yet NSA works all the same, and Intel ME is a non-removable <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clipper_chip">clipper chip</a> maybe 60% of Western desktops have inside. We don't hear as much about its equivalents. </p>
      <p>On the broadest civilizational scale, I believe in collective responsibility. I do not buy the usual Anglo excuse about private entities, be that East India Company or opium smugglers or Twitter or New York Times. Reshuffling and decentralizing evil does not absolve those with power and obligation to quash it of guilt for tolerating it. Naturally this cuts both ways, so I can't very strongly object to being on the side which goes up the stake rather than into inquisition; but then again the debate over good and evil is at the heart of humanity's attempts at  coexistence. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The more China goes from strength to strength while increasing its social control, and the more its democratic rivals seem to lapse into division and chaos, the more I worry.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Don't worry Noah. US leads by a significant margin in all sorts of innovation. It has vastly greater access to compute, and is poised to increase the gap in the next decade, even without the <a href="https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/techno-optimism-for-the-2020s">'Endless Frontier' Act</a> you along with MIT eggheads beg for – market forces will suffice. Which country has better chances of building a digital panopticon – one that still struggles with <a href="https://www.techpowerup.com/275653/china-develops-tools-for-28-nm-silicon-manufacturing">28 nm</a>, or one which is home to the teams building <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/cerebras-teases-second-generation-wafer-scale-ai-chip/">Cerebras 2</a>, <a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/ai-machine-learning/google-breaks-ai-performance-records-in-mlperf-with-worlds-fastest-training-supercomputer">TPU v4</a>, <a href="https://nvidianews.nvidia.com/news/nvidia-doubles-down-announces-a100-80gb-gpu-supercharging-worlds-most-powerful-gpu-for-ai-supercomputing">A100 with 80 Gb of HBM2e </a>... Like, come on, man. This is not serious. </p>
      <p>Feigning the sense of dread over some inferior "rising empire of evil" is a staple of American preparations for war.</p>
      <p>Ultimately though, he could be almost correct in his <em>implied</em> concern - were the US to tarry for 15-25 years more. I'd have vastly preferred this outcome, and a chance to enjoy peace into my older days. The Chinese are trying, they really do. I was just reviewing the progress over the last years, they write <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31875537/">such cute little papers</a>. <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2019.12.17.876862v1">Such valiant attempts</a>. <a href="https://academic.oup.com/nsr/article/6/3/480/5420749">And deliciously "unethical"</a> ones too. Contrary to stereotype, they are succeeding at the most important forms of creativity. I think that for all the panicked rhetoric, you'll be surprised when they don't fold like a paper tiger once the war starts. But a real tiger is still no threat to F-35 Lightning II. </p>
      <p>Now if you'll excuse me I'll go fangirl over <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OLpN8Cco3mU">SpaceX Starship test</a>. Long live America, so long as it allows a man with vision to reach such greatness.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>