<post>
  <author>MakeTotalDestr0i</author>
  <date>2020-12-03T03:19:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k2v0zo/what_are_you_reading_currently/geg7ngc/</link>
  <title>~~Bert~~ /u/MakeTotalDestr0i brings pigeons out of their pigeoholes</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Jokes aside, it sounds like pigeons are kind of "your thing"; would you at some point be interested in elaborating on the uncharted territory of pigeons and their arcane art?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I only really became interested in pigeons because i have been sort of a homeless drifter for most of my adult life and spent time being friends with pigeons, but then once i ate some i REALLY liked them, those things are so delicious if you cook them until the skin is like crispy duck. </p>
      <p>Recently some racing pigeons have been selling for over a million dollars each, now that China's bourgeoisie have become highly competitive pigeon fanciers and racers trying to flex on each other via the pigeon sports things are heating up again in that space.</p>
      <p>Most of the known genetics of pigeon and all the focus has been on aesthetic considerations such as color and feather patterns, for Fancy pigeon Fanciers. The agronomically important characteristics have been neglected. From what i can tell there is nobody in the united states scientifically breeding utility pigeons. The only serious utility pigeon breeder is in France and they haven't published anything about any genetic stuff.</p>
      <p>There is just so much you can do with them from sending flash drives to your friends, to eating them, to racing them , to starting a business releasing white ones at weddings only to have them fly back to your house so you can release them again. You can even make explosives using their poop with some primitive chemistry.</p>
      <p>the history of them is also entertaining, One of the richest and most famous families in the world amassed its wealth, certainly in part, as a result of exploiting the pigeon. In the early 1800s the Rothschild family set up a network of pigeon lofts throughout Europe and used homing pigeons to carry information between its financial houses. This method proved to be quicker and more efficient than any other means of communication available at the time. The speed of the service and the ability to send and receive information ahead of the competition helped the Rothschild family amass a fortune, which still exists today. 
There are tons of things where pigeons altered the course of history.
Reuters news service got its start using pigeon networks back in the 1850s to build a news empire.</p>
      <p>here is a <a href="http://kippenjungle.nl/kruisingDuifSpecial.html?DATA=S;Pigeon%20Calculator%20Next%20Gen%20plus%20Pied%20genes;;F;pigeon/;GIF;1,G;Bh;Baldhead;;,G;Sp;Spot%20(dom.%20and%20rec.%20implementation);;,G;Fc;Face;;,G;Bb;Bib%20(Crescent);;,G;Wt;White%20Tail%20(probably%20multiple%20genes);;,G;Ws;White%20Shield%20(rec.red%20only);;,G;En;Enabler%20white%20shield;;,G;Sh;Shield;;,G;Wf;White%20Flight;;,G;Cp;Cap%20(bulleyed%20baldhead);;,G;Z;Gazzi;;,G;E;Recessive%20Red;;,A;Bh;Bh;;baldhead-;H;baldhead-;;1,A;Bh;bh+;;;R;;W;,A;Bh;bh%5Ebd;;beard-;R;;;1,A;Cp;Cp+;;;D;;W;,A;Cp;cp;;cap-;R;;;1,A;Cp;cp%5Ebh;;baldhead-;R;;;1,A;Sp;Sp;;spot-;D;;;1,A;Sp;Sp+;;;D;;W;,A;Sp;sp;;spot-;R;;;1,A;Fc;Fc+;;;D;;W;,A;Fc;fc;;face-;R;;;1,A;Bb;Bb+;;;D;;W;,A;Bb;bb;;bib-;R;;;1,A;Ws;Ws;;ShieldRR-;D;;;1,A;Ws;ws+;;;R;;W;,A;En;En;;Enable;D;;;1,A;En;en+;;;R;;W;,A;Sh;Sh+;;;H;;W;,A;Sh;sh;;shield-;H;Shield-;;1,A;Sh;sh%5Eou;;shoulder-;H;Shoulder-;;1,A;Wf;Wf;;flight-;H;incomplete-Flight-;;1,A;Wf;wf+;;;D;;W;,A;Wt;Wt;;tail-;D;;;1,A;Wt;wt+;;;D;;W;,A;Wt;wt;;tail-;R;;;1,A;Z;Z+;;;H;;W;,A;Z;z%5Ep;;(magpie);R;;;,A;Z;z;;gazzi-;R;;;,A;Z;z%5Eb;;belly-;R;;;,A;Z;z%5Enk;;neck-;R;;;,A;Z;z%5Ewh;;white;H;;;,A;E;E+;;solid%20%20;D;;W;1,A;E;e;;solid%20Rec.Red;R;;;1,C;EC;white;;white;,C;RP;ShieldRR-;Enable;ShieldRR-Enable;,C;RP1;ShieldRR-Enable;Rec.Red;shield-;,C;RM;ShieldRR-;;;,C;RM;Enable;;;,C;RP;beard-;cap-;beardcap-;,C;RP1;tail-;belly-;hind-;,C;RP1;belly-;bib-;breast-;,C;RP;beard-;face-;facebeard-;,C;RP;Shield-;Shoulder-;shield-;,C;RP1;Shield;flight;shield;,C;RP1;Shoulder;flight;shield;,C;RM;Shield-;;;,C;RM;Shoulder-;;;,C;RP;flight-;(magpie);wing-%20belly-;,C;RP1;(magpie);Flight;rosewing-belly-;,C;RP1;shoulder-;(magpie);shield-;,C;RP1;shoulder-;belly;shield-;,C;RP1;shoulder-;gazzi;shield-;,C;RM;(magpie);;;,C;RP1;Flight;;flight;,C;RP1;shoulder-;flight;shield-;,C;RP1;tail-;shield-;hind-;,C;RP;beardcap-;face-;head-;,C;RP;facebeard-;bib-;face-%20bibbeard-;,C;RP;beard-;bib-;bibbeard-;,C;RP1;solid;-;pattern;&amp;ID=pigeonnextgen4IE">pigeon calculator</a></p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>