<post>
  <author>titus_1_15</author>
  <date>2020-12-05T19:01:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k3pgku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_30/geq2now/</link>
  <title>/u/titus_1_15 on the importance of Ireland to the UK and the EU</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>definitely not making a territory grab out of spite</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think it's slightly more nuanced than that. The EU yes has a desire to punish the UK for obvious strategic reasons, but there's a reason it's doubling down on <em>this</em> punishment and not, say, torpedoing the City of London.</p>
      <p>The EU doesn't want to fall prey to the same unequal power dynamics that are currently pulling the UK apart; ie a large centre of power that makes the decisions, and small states that do what they're told. (The appearance of) solidarity and equality among small states is of critical importance to the EU. Greece is not a counter-example, but rahter a constant reminder of what happens when this goes wrong. Nobody looks at Greece and concludes that the EU is a wonderful idea. Germany may be the biggest member, but it's not dominant enough to call the shots like England in the UK. There is genuinely a more equal distribution of power than that, especially since many competencies still operate with a veto.</p>
      <p>Essentially every political party in Ireland is in favour of eventual reunification (though some more ardently than others). Moves toward (peaceful) reconciliation with the North are extremely reliable vote-winners for Irish politicians.</p>
      <p>If citizens of EU states know anything about the republic or Ireland other than our tax policies, they tend to know we are somehow "un-British", or at least not part of the UK. They understand there's a history of conflict; the situation has analogues in the history of many central European countries. And these same countries' governments can see EU solidarity in action with Northern Ireland, and see a historically weaker state using EU leverage to achieve its policy aims against a much larger rival (cf all the Eastern states and Russia). So yes, the tension in the North is to punish the UK, but the reason the EU is leaning into <em>this</em> punishment is because it also scores a PR goal by advancing Ireland's aims.</p>
      <p>But why does the Republic of Ireland want reunification with Northern Ireland?</p>
      <p>Put simply, Northern Ireland is far more valuable to Irish politicians than it is to British ones (who generally hope the whole place would just "resolve itself", รก la elderly relatives in nursing homes), and also genuinely critical to Ireland's national strategy. Here's why:</p>
      <p>The republic attracts a large amount of migration from other EU states, entirely driven by jobs/growth from Dublin. Dublin is only a mid-sized city with very middling infrastructure though, and is basically bursting at the seams. For boring reasons similar to many other cities globally, it can't grow fast enough to accommodate the influx of relatively well-off migrants. Unlike many other countries though, this is causing large disruption at a national political level, since about 40% of members of Parliament represent Dublin constituencies (Ireland is even more Dublin-centric, in both population and economic terms, than England:London or France:Paris).</p>
      <p>The republic's economic success (predicted to have the <a href="https://www.irishtimes.com/business/economy/ireland-on-course-to-be-fastest-growing-economy-in-world-in-2020-1.4427464">highest GDP growth in the world in 2020</a>) hinges entirely on FDI. However, Dublin per se isn't the attraction for FDI: it's Ireland's tax, regulatory and commercial environment that's attractive. Dublin is the only real "city" by international standards in the republic. If only the Irish state had another real city, similar in size to Dublin, but massively cheaper and with huge unused housing, transport and human capacity, to take some of the demand pouring into Dublin, and balance the state's regional development...</p>
      <p>Enter <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belfast">Belfast</a>, the capital and largest city in Northern Ireland. Belfast is a 19th-century, Victorian industrial city in design, about 100 miles north of Dublin along the east coast. There's good rail and road links between the two cities, and you can easily reach one from the other in about 90 minutes. </p>
      <p>Belfast has about the same population as Dublin, but their economies couldn't be more different. Rents for residential and commercial property are about a quarter of Dublin rates. Wages are lower in the UK than Ireland, but in Northern Ireland they're lower still than in Britain, such that it's not unusual for the same job to pay literally half in Belfast what it would in Dublin, 100 miles south.</p>
      <p>The UK has a dozen Belfasts; somewhat grim post-industrial cities with a million or so people, crap economies, high unemployment, few jobs, and low human capital. Frankly, the whole of Northern Ireland is a burden to the UK, and it receives a large annual subvention just to stay afloat. For the republic however, it represents much-needed overflow. It's reasonable to assume the same "small, nimble" economic strategy which has brought Ireland from 3rd-world to "wealthy EU state" in 50 years will work also in Northern Ireland; the republic is much better placed to make a success of the place than the UK, which frankly doesn't need or want it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>