<post>
  <author>uFi3rynvF46U</author>
  <date>2020-12-08T05:53:47Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k8bxy1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_07/gf11b6g/</link>
  <title>/u/uFi3rynvF46U takes the NYT to task over the Trump administration's COVID planning</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>First time poster on the culture war roundup thread. I apologize if this doesn't fit or breaks some rules (there's a sentence near the end that I'm nervous about... we'll see what people think).</p>
      <p>Earlier today, a friend of mine sent me an article to discuss: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/07/us/trump-covid-vaccine-pfizer.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/07/us/trump-covid-vaccine-pfizer.html</a></p>
      <p>Since writing the response that I'm going to post below, the Times has added a paragraph or two that might make some of my points seem awkward. I think it's valuable to react to the original version, since that's the version which many Times readers (like my friend) read. Here's an archived version, I think it's pretty close to what I saw originally: <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201207231523/https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/07/us/trump-covid-vaccine-pfizer.html">https://web.archive.org/web/20201207231523/https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/07/us/trump-covid-vaccine-pfizer.html</a></p>
      <p>My friend and I have argued in the past about how reliable the media is. So anyway, here's what I sent to him, in case anyone finds it interesting or wants to react or tell me off:</p>
      <p>This is how media bias happens.</p>
      <p>The media exercise control over which stories to cover, and which not to. They exercise control over which questions to pose, to whom, what portion of the answer to print, and what supplementary context to provide, if any. At every step, the decision to exclude content is as important as the decision to include it.</p>
      <p>As an analogy, if we think of reading an article as a game of "connect the dots", the media is supplying the dots and the reader is supplying the connections. The aggregate effect of editorial decisions is to determine what dots make it onto the page, which can powerfully determine what connections (inferences, thoughts, reactions) are available to the casual (uncritical) reader, even when all the dots are true and factual.</p>
      <p>The story as reported by the Times is probably 100% true. It is phrased in a largely neutral, unbiased tone. It presents simple facts. The NYT has given you all of the dots and now you need only connect them to see a vivid picture: the Trump administration is wildly incompetent, had no plan, didn't take the virus seriously, and totally screwed up by not doing the prudent thing of buying up the highly effective Pfizer vaccine when they had the chance.</p>
      <p>But what dots, if any, did the NYT decide not to put on the page? When I finished the article, I was left with two questions:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>When exactly is "late summer" and what was the state of vaccine development then, at the time the no-buy decision was made?</li>
        <li>Why did the Trump administration only decide to buy the first 100 million doses? Why did they decide not to buy more? What were their reasons?</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Okay, so let's try to remember: what did the world look like in "late summer"? Well, it's hard to know exactly, because the NYT's "people familiar with the matter" decline to state when "late summer" was.</p>
      <p>But here are a few things we know generally:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>By summer, there were more than 100 vaccines in development worldwide, with more than 10 already having started human trials.</li>
        <li>During the summer, the Oxford vaccine was thought to be the most promising. It was certainly farther along in the development pipeline than the Pfizer vaccine. (Since then, the evidence for Oxford has been very murky, with some trials producing ~60% efficacy, which I suspect to be the reason Britain ended up going with Pfizer-BioNTech rather than their own Oxford-AstraZeneca one)</li>
        <li>Generally speaking, 90% of pharmaceuticals ultimately fail to get approved. I tried to get information more specific to vaccines, but couldn't in the time available.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Commentary: <strong>The reporter could have found this information; they chose either not to find it or not to print it.</strong> These are all dots that are absent from the page. People consuming the story casually probably do not have a clear memory of the circumstances of the summer. Although the decision to remind them, or not to, is one that can be made benignly, <em>it is a decision which has consequences</em>. What were the reasons for, and consequences of that decision in this case?</p>
      <p>So anyway, by the "late summer", the government faced a difficult problem of reasoning under uncertainty:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Many vaccines were being developed simultaneously by multiple credible international partnerships.</li>
        <li>Despite the resources at their disposal, the reality is that somewhere between a few and many of these partnerships might ultimately fail to produce a viable vaccine.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>So given limited money, what is the most prudent thing the government could have done? I would suggest that it would be to buy up doses of multiple promising candidate vaccines even before there's conclusive evidence of efficacy, in order to maximize the chance that we get <em>some</em> doses of <em>an</em> effective vaccine, among possible duds—that we not put all of our eggs in one basket, as it were. If I were in charge, faced with that situation, that would have been my plan.</p>
      <p>Commentary: Go skim the story again. Does the NYT say whether this was the government's plan? Does the NYT say whether the government had a plan, or even claims to have had a plan? E.g., do they state whether the government declined to buy its <em>next</em> 100 million doses of the Pfizer vaccine <em>in order</em> to buy its <em>first</em> 100 million doses of something else—to spread the eggs among more baskets? Did the "people familiar with the matter" tell the NYT whether this was the plan (or what the plan was)? Did the NYT even claim to have asked what the plan or the rationale was for the decision? If they did and got an answer, did they just decide not to print that? <strong>Whatever the reason, at the end of the editorial pipeline, the article is left providing no description of whether the government had a plan for vaccine purchases, or what that plan could be. Crucially, and this is how the sausage is made,</strong><strong><em>in a world where the government did have a plan</em></strong>, <strong>the result of these editorial decisions would be a failure to dispel from the mind of the reader the</strong><strong><em>in-that-world false notion</em></strong><strong>that the government did not have a plan.</strong></p>
      <p>So anyway, can we tell which world we're living in? Can we infer based on the <em>actions</em> of the government whether they did have a plan, and if so, what it was? As was reported on August 24, 2020:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>By mid-August, the United States had secured 800 million doses of at least 6 vaccines in development, with an option to purchase around one billion more.  </p>
        <p>(<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02450-x">https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02450-x</a>)</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>So let's be clear here: By mid August, the Trump administration had staked a claim on behalf of the United States to 1.8 billion doses of 6 different candidate vaccines.</p>
      <p>Commentary: I found that information in literal seconds on Google. Like, fewer than 10 seconds. <strong>The reporter must have had this information; if they didn't, they are an unskilled journalist and the NYT wouldn't employ them.</strong> So they, or an editor, affirmatively chose not to print it. Why not?</p>
      <p>So to summarize, it appears that the Trump administration <em>did have a plan</em>, and it was what I think was <em>probably a good plan given information available at the time</em>, and <em>they acted on it</em>. Does that conclusion seem possible to draw by connecting only the dots that the article chooses to provide to you?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>