<post>
  <author>WokeandRedpilled</author>
  <date>2020-12-11T23:49:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k8bxy1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_07/gfglzc8/</link>
  <title>/u/WokeandRedpilled contemplates the financial incentives of the divorce industry</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Money in Divorce Effort Post</p>
      <p>This is part one of part one of the promised part two on Family law (sorry, finals has made me hate writing essays. But I do this for you, the people). I’ll be dealing only with Property Division here, going over the basics. Part two of part one of part two will be a deep dive into Wendt v Wendt, which is an illustrative case into the difficulties involved in valuing stay-at-home work, and part two of part two will be Alimony. After this, I’ll probably do a deep dive on a pair of cases (Garska v McCoy and Young v Hector), which deals with child custody, and end the series there. </p>
      <p>Money in Divorce can broadly be divided into two broad categories: 1) Property Division and 2) Alimony. Although people tend to focus on Alimony, the bulk of litigation and interest goes instead into Property Division, which is necessary in all divorces, whereas alimony is only awarded in a surprisingly low percentage of marriages, a fact which is partially attributed to the fact that judges deliberately modify property division in order to minimize the need for alimony, and a partially attributed to breadwinning women striving to reform alimony (Ironic, considering only 3% of the 400,000 alimony recipients are male) <a href="https://money.com/alimony-reform-spousal-support/#:%7E:text=Unlike%20child%20support%2C%20which%20is,of%20law%20at%20Marquette%20University.">Alimony Reform Is Being Driven by Women | Money</a>.</p>
      <p>There are three basic schemes states follow in dividing property. First, the most popular is common law dual classification equitable distribution. Under this scheme, the court divides the property of the couple into ‘marital property’ and separate property, then subjects the marital property to equitable apportionment. Importantly, <em>this doesn’t mean equally</em>. Instead, courts look at a series of factors. The Missouri Supreme Court in Ferguson v Ferguson listed:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Substantial contribution to the accumulation of the property. Factors to be considered in determining contribution are as follows:</li>
      </ol>
      <p>a. Direct or indirect economic contribution to the acquisition of the property; </p>
      <p>b. Contribution to the stability and harmony of the marital and family relationships as measured by quality, quantity of time spent on family duties and duration of the marriage; and </p>
      <p>c. Contribution to the education, training or other accomplishment bearing on the earning power of the spouse accumulating the assets. </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>The degree to which each spouse has expended, withdrawn or otherwise disposed of marital assets and any prior distribution of such assets by agreement, decree or otherwise. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The market value and the emotional value of the assets subject to distribution.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The value of assets not ordinarily, absent equitable factors to the contrary, subject to such distribution, such as property brought to the marriage by the parties and property acquired by inheritance or inter vivos gift by or to an individual spouse; </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Tax and other economic consequences, and contractual or legal consequences to third parties, of the proposed distribution; </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The extent to which property division may, with equity to both parties, be utilized to eliminate periodic payments and other potential sources of future friction between the parties; </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The needs of the parties for financial security with due regard to the combination of assets, income and earning capacity; and,</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Any other factor which in equity should be considered. . . . </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>These factors are used to come up with a % which ‘seems fair’.</p>
      <p>The second most popular is the minority common law state scheme, the all property equitable distribution. Also called the hodgepodge or kitchen sink approach, it just skips splitting property into marital and separate, and just subjects all property acquired to apportionment, regardless of how or when they’re obtained.</p>
      <p>Finally, community property states make up the minority, with 9 states following the law. These states divide property into <em>community</em> property and separate property. Community property is then divided in half. Apparently, the reason for the departure from common law is the fact that these states are influenced by the Spanish legal system (versus the British system in the rest of the US). As such, the 9 states are generally found in the southwest and west of the US. </p>
      <p>If we look at the factors, what is probably the most contentious, and as such the most interesting, is the attempts of courts to value <em>housework</em>. That is, how does one place a $ amount on the necessarily unpaid labor of a stay at home mother/wife? Historically, work within the household has not been treated as comparable as work in the marketplace. Although statements like “The GNP only measures paid market activity, which reflects a bias against housework” is probably an overreach, it is the case that historically, marketplace work conferred significantly more prestige and importance. </p>
      <p>Current precedent is clear, that ‘homemaking and marketplace work is to be <em>valued equally</em>’, but in practice, judges have difficulty figuring out what this <em>actually</em> means. It has at times resulted in ½ of all assets being awarded to the wife (Ferguson v Ferguson), while at other times resulted in significantly less being given to the wife (Arneault v Arneault, 35/65 spread).</p>
      <p>What makes courts so hesitant to apply this precident is the elephant in the room; honestly, homemaking often time <em>is</em> significantly less valuable than marketplace work.</p>
      <p>We'll look at Wendt v Wendt to see how this plays out in courts.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>