<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-06-20T03:45:35Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fvep7n1/</link>
  <title>On Knowledge of 'Hate Facts'</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>My sense is that the vast majority of liberals and people on the left have very little clue about most of the “hate facts” and to the extent that they’re aware of them they have no clue as to the robustness of the relevant data or how extreme certain disparities are. I base this largely on the fact that until relatively recently (2014ish?) I was a mainstream centre leftist rather than the messy heterodox clusterfuck I am these days, and I was genuinely shocked on multiple occasions by certain facts I came across.</p>
      <p>For example, I was vaguely aware that there were some differences in crime rates across different ethnic communities but I assumed they were fairly small, inconsistent, and could be readily explained by poverty and other structural issues. Genuinely quite shocking and an aporetic moment for me when I saw some of the breakdowns. These days the 13/53 meme is widespread but my guess is most people think it’s a horribly distorted half truth at best and an outright nasty 4chan fabrication at worst.</p>
      <p>Likewise, the stuff on race and IQ, etc. - I was vaguely aware of the Charles Murray stuff but like most people with one foot in the humanities I assumed it was dangerous speculation and quite possibly motivated by racial animus. I assumed IQ was basically discredited nonsense and had no inkling of how robust the science behind psychometrics actually was and when I came across a particular controversial Wikipedia page I was utterly stunned. I was so stunned in fact that I naively mentioned it to a couple of academic friends, one of whom seemed as clueless as me (not just good acting: she asked a bunch of questions!) and another who basically said “yeah i know the data, it’s out there for people who want to follow this stuff but I wouldn’t think too hard about it if I were you, you’ll drive yourself crazy and it doesn’t help anyone.”</p>
      <p>The anti-blankslatism side I’ve been more familiar with for a while, but only because Chomsky and Pinker and Fodor and a few others have made nativism into a very respectable tradition in some bits of cognitive science. What was more of a shock for me was discovering the apparent lack of influence of parenting, which I got later from Harris, Plomin, and a few others.</p>
      <p>Gender stuff has always been an outlier. I’ve been super interested in sex and hormones and male and female differences in behaviour since I was a teenager (heh) and I never considered it political except in a generally sex positive, celebrate-the-differences kind of way. It was only living in the US in my late 20s that I started to meet people who were radical social constructivists about sex and they struck me from the outset as crazy people, and I said as much to friends and colleagues. I didn’t feel like I was saying anything particularly radical at the time, but this was early 2010s so maybe it wasn’t back then. These days I’d be much more wary of talking publicly about  any kind of innate differences (even just in preferences) between men and women. Though in a pinch I can talk about the effects of taking sex hormones as reported by trans people and emphasise the importance of “respecting their lived experiences”.</p>
      <p>As another side note: I used to find it quite fun to come up with really progressive linguistic and conceptual framings of my ideas like that. It didn’t feel like finding my way out of a maze or paying the Danegeld, like it often does now; it was more a matter of scaffolding what I was saying in terms of the maximally persuasive concepts of the people around me and my own in-group. So I wonder to what extent some of the heightened paranoia and claustrophobia a lot of us here feel (especially former liberals and progressives) is partly due to a shift in our mindset. Obviously it’s getting easier and easier  to get cancelled so it’s not like the paranoia comes from nowhere; but “fitting in” can be fun and effortless or it can be draining and oppressive depending on your relevant identity. That in turn drives some positive feedback loops associated with people’s personal political shifts: it gets a little harder to defend your in group one day, and that creates negative associations, which make it a bit more effortful and demeaning to fit in the next day, and so on.</p>
      <p>But anyway, that’s just a digression. My general sense though is that most people probably vastly overestimate how widely the relevant data is known and appreciated. And even if people are dimly aware of it, they’re not interested in exploring it or seeing where it takes them or how much it might explain and they just push it out of mind. Kind of like <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fnord">fnords</a>.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>