<post>
  <author>gattsuru</author>
  <date>2020-06-18T19:51:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fv9iuqe/</link>
  <title>The Cancel Mob May Be Inescapable</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Leave the big cities. Move to a small town in a red state. Work a blue collar job or open your own business. Now the Twitter mob has no power over you.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'm gonna criticize this bit, directly.  Because I've done it.</p>
      <p>I work in a field far more conservative than myself, where I have to worry about being cancelled for being bisexual rather than for having the wrong twitter opinions, and in a state where I'm supposed to have to worry more about my dildos being banned than my guns.</p>
      <p>Except... that's not quite how it works out, in practice.  There are a thousand thousand work-arounds for the piddling bans on sex toys to the very limited extent they've not been invalidated by the courts, while red flag laws on guns have taken the country by storm, even where they violate rights the ACLU supposedly cares about in <em>addition</em> to the Second Amendment.  The next likely Democratic administrations have pledged to bring the full force of federal law against me and my ilk on firearms; it doesn't matter where we move.  I can no longer be fired for liking cock, but my employer can be liable if they <em>don't</em><a href="https://www.eeoc.gov/wysk/what-you-should-know-about-eeoc-and-shelton-d-v-us-postal-service-gadsden-flag-case">investigate me for wearing the wrong clothes</a>.</p>
      <p>And that's not some unique dichotomy.  I'm rather unlikely to have kids for much of the same reason that I don't exactly mind the sausage fest.  But if you do want to raise kids, you're stuck choosing between public schools that err on the side of child abuse, and homeschooling, and there's a growing movement to ban the latter.  The limited extent I interface with them for STEM outreach <em>absolutely</em> is vulnerable to cancellation -- I work with colleges and shake a senator's hand to make a tiny project work.  If you volunteered to serve your country and were injured, you get to visit a VA office where the only doctor that the veterans like is a Sikh, because unlike the locally raised experts, he doesn't think a military truck driver signed up to murder children.</p>
      <p>Beyond that... Hugh Akston worked in a diner because he had to work somewhere.  Not because he couldn't be canceled there, but because <em>literally no one would think he'd be there</em>, even with his name of the mailbox -- several characters thought he was dead!</p>
      <p>That's not an available luxury in the internet age, where your employers and romantic interests and random acquaintances will check your identity online.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>