<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-06-18T16:39:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fv8wso6/</link>
  <title>An Atomized Soiciety Can Survive Outrage Mobs</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="/u/a_midwesterner">/u/a_midwesterner</a> created a thread titled "How best to respond to twitter outrage mobs?" in the other sub, and it predictably got locked. I wanted to point out that he'd be better off discussing it here, and now that he'll see this by virtue of this mention, I'll add some thoughts.</p>
      <p>a_midwesterner enumerated several strategies of mob-victim interaction: apology/appeasement, ignoring, doubling down and I think 2 others. The fundamental error behind all those is thinking that you're dealing with <em>the mob</em> and not with your own social circle. Of course, once you're under attack you've got to choose a strategy, but a principled solution would be engineering a social circle that is invulnerable to begin with.<br />
Consider these ideas:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>If the mob against you is significantly large (e.g. JK Rowling. Potentially Tsu) it becomes more complicated. You may have to defend yourself from your employer or protect your reputation from your friends/family, and the mob may take longer to die down. In this situation I feel like a short denial may be best. Do not give an irrational mob additional talking points that they can once again refute.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>No. It doesn't matter what talking points mob has; if it has leverage, you will be forced into making some concessions, and if it doesn't, then that's the end of it. Mob, by itself, is immaterial. It's a focal point of rage and injustice, moving like a sundog across collective consciousness in social media. Maybe if you're Tucker Carlson you'll have serious enough interests behind the mob, or enough low-level notoriety, that some nutjobs will wander under your windows; but most of us aren't Tuckers. For the mortals, the mob only has effects inasmuch as the spot it falls on absorbs heat well.</p>
      <p>My spot, for example, is mirrorlike. I do not give a fuck about mobs (for now). Why? My friends will consider me cool if I were to be "canceled". My employer couldn't care less. My family, seeing the mob accuse me of racism or sexism or whatever, <em>would come to think better of racists or sexists rather than think worse of me</em> (I suspect this would be the case even if I did something actually evil). My colleagues are, for the most part, in exactly the same situation and would also laugh anyone who's credulously listening to the mob's nonsense out of the room. </p>
      <p>Of course, by far the biggest factor allowing me such luxury is simply me being Russian and thus having an environment not subjected to unadulterated propaganda of this particular American kind. But I think there's something else, too: the degree of trust in people you know, versus trust in some "common wisdom" espoused by strangers. The distance to complete atomization in a given network.<br />
Russian society is said to be atomized. It's called a low-trust one, too. Fair. Ceteris paribus, I'd rather have business with Anglos of Germans than with my fellow countrymen, even ethnic Russians. But on the flipside, people you <em>do</em> trust (because of learning over time that they are trustworthy) have near unlimited benefit of the doubt. It's a sparse network with strong links, approaching a clustered clannish one. I have semi-consciously endeavored to make this arrangement even more pronounced. So now I have friends who'd protect me in a street fight, low trust for an average acquaintance and negative trust for some amorphous, manipulable online sentiment. This cost me some friends: the compromised, impressionable, "everyone thinks" types. Had to let them go.  </p>
      <p>I've seen arguments to the effect that people in developed countries can <em>afford</em> atomization; that extended families and informal networks and lifetime friends are cumbersome crutches for Monty Python peasants and boring dorks who don't change cities like gloves, and "thrive" is a natural choice when you're sure of survival. It's possible that the opposite is true: <em>social media</em> is a crutch for disconnected people, and it's incomplete, for it does not replicate trust. Without genuine emotional trust in specific people, all you've got to go on is <em>consensus opinion</em>, so self-organized unstoppable mobs emerge in the first place, no longer inhibited by breakwaters of outgroup suspicion. And the consensus of hundred thousand nicknames in the mob is enough to convince a son to go against father. Importantly, you can't run or hide: if every city and every Discord server is subject to the same emergent process, all this liberal choice amounts to freedom of choosing one among a thousand McDonald's.</p>
      <p>Now, people can't live on small family farms and only interact with those they trust 100%. So this creates incentives for communities to establish some common signals of not being defectors who'll sell you out to the mob. I guess you see where I'm going. In a thoroughly atomized world, mobs running on groupthink sentiment become inevitable. They destroy everything which plays by their rules, and thus drive people into clusters, even bubbles, which reject those rules wholesale.  </p>
      <p>I predict that bubbles will merge into a tribe - not the one we call Red, but something new, despite being made of largely the same individuals [smaller though]. And this is the only principled solution to the problem of online mobs: to be entirely surrounded by people who do not respect them. </p>
      <p>The question, long-term, is whether this tribe would argue for physical separation with the mob-run remainder of the country.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>