<post>
  <author>LooksatAnimals</author>
  <date>2020-06-20T12:16:19Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fvfmyn5/</link>
  <title>The Idiocy of 'Most People'</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think it is important to remember that <em>most</em> people are <a href="https://www.unz.com/akarlin/stupid-people/">functionally innumerate</a> and don't really seem to have <em>any</em> real understanding of anything they don't do for a living (and even then, they often only have a shallow grasp of the bare essentials), despite seeming to have very strong opinions on a lot of those things.</p>
      <p>If you told them that 13% of the population commit 52% of violent crime, only a small minority of people would be able to tell you how many times the average member of that 13% commits violent crime compared to the rest of the population. An average person might see that 52% is 4 times 13% and guess that meant four times as much crime. A below average person would just see numbers and give up. Add a bit of motivated stupidity by implying that understanding the numbers might make them come to inconvenient conclusions and most people suddenly drop to that level. Push them on this and they just get angry and repeat rote phrases and insults as if they were arguments.</p>
      <p>Smarter than average people will simply discard the evidence which doesn't match the desired conclusions and retreat to another argument. Destroy a couple of arguments in a row and they react like stupid people.</p>
      <p>Almost nobody is capable of looking at a bunch of data and arguments and evaluating them logically. Maybe one person in ten can do that with a subject they are emotionally detached from. I doubt that one person in a hundred can do it with a political subject (and the population capable of doing it is likely to be disproportionately Asian, Jewish or White, XY, and somewhere on the Autistic spectrum).</p>
      <p>Seriously, most people don't know why temperature changes at different times of the year, or how technology they use every day works. Despite having Covid-19 as the top news story for months, they don't know basic facts about it like what their odds of dying are if they catch it <em>despite apparently being very concerned about this.</em> They never seem to check anything they are told, or bother to look up alternative sources unless they don't like the first one. They have a vague idea that the authorities they get their opinion from should somehow use numbers and evidence, but so long as some numbers and something that looks a little bit like evidence is somehow associated with the emotional associations they are given, they are generally happy to believe everything they are told by the right people.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>