<post>
  <author>Lykurg480</author>
  <date>2020-06-20T12:37:16Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fvfohhx/</link>
  <title>On Statues and the Goodness of Man</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Very good post, and Ill try to give the right-wing response.</p>
      <p>One of the classic left vs right discussions is the inherent goodness of man. You seem to think that really, essentially, at the bottom of their heart, deep down, with their true nature etc people already agree with you, and are only stopped by distorting memeplexes. Now, I think "how humans would behave without memeplexes" is ultimately a confused idea and unanswerable, but I wont try to make a conceptual argument here (Id totally discuss if someone wants to though), so lets ignore that for now.</p>
      <p>First, why do you think we would all agree? The view may be indexical. It certainly seems strange to suggest that people "naturally" care just as much about a child in Africa as about their own. Second, even if we all agreed, why do you think the leftist view is the thing we would all agree on? It has risen to prominence in a society heavily influenced by memeplexes, why would something free of them just pop up and gain traction?</p>
      <p>And quite a bit of this also seems questionable at the object level. For example:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>You have the same basic empathetic drives human beings feel towards each other regardless of race, <strong>and that human beings feel even towards injured animals</strong>.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Those human beings have also killed animals for food since forever, and even more so before the evil oppressive agriculturalist showed up. With just a basic regard for evopsych, do you think the most fit hunter-gatherers are the ones who deep down feel bad about killing animals? And again, consider your child vs the one in Africa. Yet, modern leftism suggests that True Morality has to give them equal weight.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>It is only through a very, very powerful, evil superweapon of a memeplex, that you can reject, supress, and ignore those feelings, and justify your actions, especially in the context of the enlightenment. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Not just especially. I would say that those decent moral feelings that are supressed are themselves the product of memeplexes, and the moral feelings you want to pervail today are those of the enlightenment memeplex. That is what the rationalisations are trying to defend against.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Imagine yourself being born an intelligent white man in 1776 in South Carolina. If you truly see slavery for what it is, it would drive you insane.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I dont think so. Its rather more likely that you just dont consider anyone to Truely Understand unless he agrees with you. I think I could pass the intellectual turing test for vegan EAs, but I eat meat and hunt and I dont fell guilty about it at all. It is true that more intelligent people have generally been more in line with enlightenment standards - I attribute that to something like <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/aHaqgTNnFzD7NGLMx/reason-as-memetic-immune-disorder">this</a>.</p>
      <p>In terms of conservative reactions, theres first what Id call the neocon take: The True Morality comes from the enlightenment, and leftist who dont realise this end up destroying it and its support structures in their effort to tear down the oppressive stuff. Jefferson was a hero for the enlightenment, and the constitution a great victory. America is the shining city on the hill and a force for progress in the world.</p>
      <p>If you move further to the right, people see the tearing down as the actions of the enlightenment instead. Theres what Ill call the "west in crisis" take: The enlightenment is tearing down itself. This isnt some weird abberation, its just what it naturally does at this stage. Therefore we are all doomed, or we somehow need to reform enlightenment philosophy itself.</p>
      <p>Lastly theres the ethnat take: The True Morality is the Volksgeist, and thats what the enlightenment is attacking. This needs to stop already so we can go back to dominating the world. There a similar religious one, but the True Morality that needs to be reinstated is the divine law.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>