<post>
  <author>PmMeClassicMemes</author>
  <date>2020-06-20T08:04:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fvf7w89/</link>
  <title>The Left's View of Europe</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I read something <a href="/u/NationalismIsFun">u/NationalismIsFun</a> posted earlier this week, and I wanted to make an effort post response to it. </p>
      <p>I don't think Europeans in general are, or were uniquely evil, immoral, or whatever other bad adjective you want to use for bad behavior. If Genghis Khan had gunpowder, we'd likely have Mongol Supremacist institutions instead of White Supremacist ones, and I suspect they'd be much more explicitly violent about it. </p>
      <p>That said, the history we live in is the only one we have, and in my view part of the leftist project is trying to right the existence of wrongs that were perpetrated, not wrongs that may have, could have been, and not ignore wrong that would have been done anyways, or would have been worse under some other hypothetical or entirely possible set of circumstances. </p>
      <p>I want to discuss specifically the psychological processes at play in historical acts of wrongdoing by Europeans. Because aside from a few notables - Cortez, Columbus, etc., I think <a href="/u/NationalismIsFun">u/NationalismIsFun</a> 's thesis is entirely correct - there is/was nothing uniquely immoral or evil about the acts and thoughts of the average European for the past few hundred years. </p>
      <p>I want to make clear that for example in the case of slavery, there were thousands (perhaps hundreds of thousands) of Europeans who rounded up human beings against their will, put them on ships, and sold them and their lineage into permanent chattel servitude with the status of farm equipment. </p>
      <p>There was nothing <em>uniquely</em> immoral about these individuals. This is because the word unique implies to me :</p>
      <p>A) That they were the only people who could</p>
      <p>or </p>
      <p>B) That they were the only people who would</p>
      <p>have done such acts. </p>
      <p>But we have history of other groups being slaves and enslaving, war crimes, etc. we know these acts aren't the sole circumstance of enslavement. </p>
      <p>When leftists discuss the historical consequences of racism, colonialism, etc., we are not doing so in order to prove that Euro = bad. We are doing so in order to discuss to what degree those systems and modes of thinking continue to influence us today. </p>
      <p>I want to delve fully here into a discussion of psyche. Imagine yourself in the position of a European slave trader in the 1700s. You are not a moron, you have eyes and ears. When you whip a black man, he bleeds just like you do, and he cries out in pain. You have the same basic empathetic drives human beings feel towards each other regardless of race, and that human beings feel even towards injured animals. </p>
      <p>Moreover, Europe at the time of the enlightenment was not a stupid, brutish, illiterate, "law of the jungle" society. It had courts, and in many instances, at least the beginnings of belief and acknowledgement by society and powerful institutions of the idea that all persons ought be afforded some form of basic common respect, rights, decency, etc.</p>
      <p>It is only through a very, very powerful, evil superweapon of a memeplex, that you can reject, supress, and ignore those feelings, and justify your actions, especially in the context of the enlightenment. </p>
      <p>Extremely powerful cultural programming must occur, to teach you that the people you are trading as cattle are not people, lesser than you, undeserving of dignity, could not handle freedom, are backwards, etc. All manner of justification must be employed, any shred of evidence obtained and used for confirmation bias. </p>
      <p>Imagine yourself being born an intelligent white man in 1776 in South Carolina. If you truly see slavery for what it is, it would drive you insane. The only understandable reaction would be for you to assassinate the Governor and as many other leaders as you can take out before you go down. What is the alternative? You spend your entire life advocating for abolition and then die before a single slave is freed? How could anyone exist in such a state, believing their entire system is built on a horrid injustice that they come face to face with daily, without going completely insane? You must adopt racism at least as a psychological defence mechanism, reality is much too horrifying. </p>
      <p>It is much, much simpler for you to go along to get along, and all our cognitive biases point us in this direction - accept the common knowledge, don't rock the boat. </p>
      <p>Most people, placed in such systems, be they commoners in the antebellum south or drafted SS members, will simply follow orders, and live and die without making any serious waves. Milgram experiments, etc.</p>
      <p>European racism is not the first, nor the only powerful long standing memeplex the earth has. Christianity is another long standing memeplex, whether you view it as a force for good or bad. Most of us on this forum are atheists, or at least non-Christians, frequently people who for, at no point in their lives, has any core part of the Christian memeplex about Christ on the cross ever held any meaning in our personal lives. We may not have ever even stepped into a Church for a religious service without a wedding attached to it. Yet we speak with language full of biblical idioms, gather for feasts on Easter and Christmas, and take Sundays off. </p>
      <p>TL;DR : When leftists want to take down confederate statues, or suggest there is institutional racism or white supremacy, it is not because we think Europeans are uniquely evil, that history must be destroyed, etc. Europeans did the same thing every other culture has ever done - create memeplexes to justify their acts and omissions. The difference is that Europeans won the OG culture war, and the actual wars, and thus their memeplexes lived longer, long enough for you to believe some of it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>