<post>
  <author>Rabitology</author>
  <date>2020-06-19T15:26:16Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fvcg9ez/</link>
  <title>Black Culture - Problem or Soultion is a Matter of Prespective</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I don't think blacks will ever be as successful as whites in the US.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You are correct.  You are also correct that the issue is culture, and yes, IQ is tied into it, but not as you suspect.  Where you are incorrect is in locating the problem within <em>black</em> culture, because to you, middle-class white culture is so normalized that you assume that when another culture does not meet its standards, the problem is with the <em>other</em> culture.</p>
      <p>Black culture is not perfect.  It's failure points in contexts of stress and relative deprivation  are well-documented, its extreme durability is inextricably connected to an equally extreme inflexibility, and its matriarchal structure struggles to socialize young men when older men are not present.</p>
      <p>All this being said, it typically produces individuals who are happier and less neurotic than white culture.  Just look at the difference in suicide rates between blacks and whites/Asians.  There has been a lot of ink spilt on explaining this difference without noting what is simple and obvious - that white people are crazy as hell.</p>
      <p>The most significant problem for black culture i<em>s that it has to compete with white culture.</em>  And <a href="https://hotelconcierge.tumblr.com/post/113360634364/the-stanford-marshmallow-prison-experiment">modern white culture is a machine turning human beings into emotionally-impaired, high IQ test-taking units</a>.</p>
      <p>Once there was a white culture that was like the black culture of today.  It did things like widen the Cumberland gap and drive cattle from Texas to Chicago.  Then, <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2016/07/25/how-the-west-was-won/">it summoned a demon from beyond the void</a>, and now it barely hangs on in backwaters of Appalachia and the Ozarks.</p>
      <p>I hope black people <em>never</em> become as successful as white people.  I would never wish that on anyone.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>