<post>
  <author>titus_1_15</author>
  <date>2020-06-19T10:26:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fvbp96t/</link>
  <title>IQ and Ireland: A Test Case</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I really do believe [iq] is at the root of the problem. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Putting to one side the question of black people ever catching up to white people in the States, I think this assertion can be challenged with reasoning you'd find agreeable.</p>
      <p>I think you implicitly have a model here where IQ is a pretty immutable property of individuals, and also a good predictor of individual success. So scaling up to a whole ethnic group, you make the case that IQ serves the same role. But I'm not sure that move is justified.</p>
      <p>When we look at how average IQs work for groups, it seems to me there's something a lot more complex going on than when we look at individuals. Specifically, it doesn't seem as immutable, and sometimes will correlate with success <em>as a trailling indicator</em>. </p>
      <p>I'd like to bring up the example of my own country, Ireland. We historically have had the lowest national IQ of any western European country (as noted by countless researchers, notably <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=eysenck+irish+iq&amp;oq=eysenck+irish+iq&amp;aqs=chrome..69i57.17102j0j7&amp;client=ms-android-samsung&amp;sourceid=chrome-mobile&amp;ie=UTF-8">Hans Eysenck</a>), and not by a small amount: in the 1980s international scholastic comparisons put us about 1 SD behind the next-lowest, which I think was either Bulgaria or Portugal. We had been way behind the class in comparisons like these for centuries. Bad stuff.</p>
      <p>Unsurprisingly, alongside this poor IQ we had an intellectual tradition among the non-Anglo descended majority that was basically worthless for many centuries, from about the 12th century to the 20th. The "thick Irishman" stereotype was essentially accurate; from a lot of reading it seems we really were a wretched people for most of the past millennium. Poor, ignorant, unable to better ourselves (to the embarrassment and despair of our few worthy national leaders), and reliable failures. It was only the <em>luck</em> of having been colonised by such a people as the English that kept us from violent anarchy, and surely we needed a firm hand to guide us.</p>
      <p>I was born in the 80s, and can honestly remember how much <em>stupider</em> Irish people seemed compared to, say, Americans. I recall furrowed brows, and dim, good-hearted smiles, when presented with fancy, complex ideas "from abroad", that Americans I met could grasp easily. Pub fights as a national sport. Excelling in procreation, stupid piety and religious violence, and little else. Behind the curve.</p>
      <p>I cannot see <em>any way</em> in which pure genetic determinism was not as good an explanation for the pathetic misfortune of the Irish as it is for American or other blacks. I'd be happy to look at any important differences anyone can think of. Irish immigrants eventually thrived in the States? Yes, and so do African immigrants today. American readers, don't think of Irish-Americans: think of the original, crap, undiluted stock.</p>
      <p>And yet, and yet. In the 90s, as a site for cheap labour and offshoring, the nation began to get its shit together. Virtuous cycles began, as the country began to reap the reward of its government following the simplest economic plan imaginable: "we have cheap labour, and will let you do tax avoidance". A lot of our economic success since the 90s is kind of paper tigers, but that doesn't matter to the argument: the point is people's lives, ideas, jobs and outlook changed significantly. We are now, even discounting the scammy distortion of offshoring etc., undoubtedly a rich country.</p>
      <p>And a really interesting thing has happened: our national IQ has risen substantially as well. We're now mid-table by European standards, high by global ones. In a couple of generations. This came <em>after</em> the economic improvement. If this is possible for my ethnic group, the Irish, why not others? What does this say for the idea that IQ works for groups the same as it does for individuals?</p>
      <p>I want to re-emphasise: we were a basket case for <em>as long as black people have been in the Americas</em>. This wasn't a blip. All the same dysgenic pressures were there.</p>
      <p>Ireland's case is a very strong challenge to anyone positing unfixable, genetically-determined low IQ as a reason why black Americans can never have their shit together, or be as competent as whites, and I've never seen anyone answer the challenge satisfactorily.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>