<post>
  <author>CPlusPlusDeveloper</author>
  <date>2020-01-22T21:13:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/es62tg/the_richest_families_in_florence_italy_in_1427/ffa4ceb/</link>
  <title>Rules 1 and 2 for Economic Success</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Intelligence is an important component of economic success, but is not the only determinant. Joel Spolsky has a famous maxim about the only two criteria he uses when hiring or investing:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Smart</li>
        <li>Gets things done.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>On point two, Spolsky paints the archetypical "smart and <em>doesn't</em> get things done" as the career academic. As the tenure system grows more sclerotic, this is only becoming more true over time. From personal experience, I'll add that this usually goes double for academics in the math and physics department. Or at the very least,  the mathematicians and physicists who "get things done", tend to leave academia for quant finance or industry AI/ML. </p>
      <p>This distinction is also true on a cultural level. Modern-day Anglo cultures just tend to "get more things done" than the French, Germans or Scandinavians. The cultures of the Eastern Mediterranean are even better at "getting things done". Armenians, Greeks, and Maronites typically have an enormous amount of success in free market economies. Even though they have no group-level IQ advantage over Spaniards, Italians or Frenchmen. </p>
      <p>One of the reasons for capitalism's historical success is its ability to create structures that allow the middling intelligent to leverage practicality, determination and risk-tolerance into enormous productivity advantages. </p>
      <p>Von Neumann likely would have produced a lot in any society. But your typical small-business owner falls well short of that standard. He probably is no more than one standard deviation above average intelligence, but has boundless drive and ambition. Under socialism he'd waste away in a basement backwater as a minor bureaucratic functionary. Under feudalism, he'd likely be stuck with the same plot of land as his father and his father before him.</p>
      <p>But capitalism enables our hero to generate orders of magnitude higher economic output than the average. It's not unusual for the stereotypical Armenian-American car-wash owner to earn a million plus dollars a year.  That's possible because a lot of the intellectual heavy lifting is already done inside the price system. </p>
      <p>The market's pretty transparent about broadcasting the relative value of products. The limiting factor is often just who's willing to hustle and put in the elbow grease required to turn cheap inputs into expensive outputs.</p>
      <p>You don't need to be <em>that</em> smart to build a spreadsheet forecasting a car wash's potential profitability. But you do have to be willing to wake up on short notice at 6 AM on Saturday because your teenage wage slaves called in hungover. German mathematicians are not hustling to clean toilets at 6 AM.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>