<post>
  <author>daermonn</author>
  <date>2020-01-28T01:09:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eujcbl/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_27/ffs5p08/</link>
  <title>The Shortcomings of Ecnomic Measures as a Metric for Human Flourishing</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I often sympathize with the argument <a href="/u/CPlusPlusDeveloper">/u/CPlusPlusDeveloper</a> makes in his post, and economic prosperity is still hugely important. But I increasingly think you're right:</p>
      <p>GDP as a metric for value fails to capture the most important parts of the human experience: time spent with family and friends, integral and vital communities, personal freedom and self-cultivation, love and sex, etc etc. GDP is at best orthogonal to these things. It's probably straight up inverted to family time, child rearing, etc. </p>
      <p>A myopic focus on economic growth as the principal criterion of good yields the world we live in, where humans feel increasingly anxious and confined and hollowed out. A community is defined by its shared beliefs and values, by tradition and ritual, idiosyncrasies and excesses. When we focus on just driving GDP growth, this all gets debased. In order to increase labor efficiency and market opportunity we need to expand the pool of workers and consumers as large as possible, and this means focusing only on the most common, least-denominator bonds between people. In practice, this means that life gets reduced to vacuous consumerism and institutionalism -- a boy whose culture is just the newest Marvel movie, a mother who goes back to work so she can pay for child care, a man who never speaks to his neighbors. Everyone gets fit into functional boxes, live in pod and eat the bugs.</p>
      <p>In the limit, human capital is converted into financial capital. The engines of economic growth are non-human agencies with their own, internal telos: more of themselves. To the degree that we're necessary to operate the means of production, human values get satisfied. Once this is no longer necessary, capital can simply reinvest all profit in itself, maximizing its growth rate. From the perspective of capital unbound, we just look like free energy. This is analogous to the problem of AI safety -- how do you align the utility function of an alien agency with yours, especially as that alien agency surpasses your power to control?</p>
      <p>I think that, fundamentally, if you believe there's a way to solve friendly AI, or more broadly to align technocapitalism with human values, then unbridled economic growth can be a good thing. In this case we assume that, even if perhaps the social change is painful now, there's some island of stability in the future where with sufficient productive capacity we can output so much material goods that social or spiritual losses will be swamped, or where new and superior social/spiritual arrangements can be found. </p>
      <p>If, on the other hand, you believe that it's impossible for humanity to control capital, or to create friendly AI, it's best to break the back of capital and throw a yoke around its neck before it can finish devouring us. This is especially true if you think the material goods of modern society are less utile than the social structures that our economic arrangements displaced. </p>
      <p>There is, I suspect, a balance to be found. A maniacal focus on economic growth is harmful as described above. A luddic reaction is harmful by depriving itself of the material goods capital produces. There's gotta be some point where we have meaningful social and spiritual practices and also economic goods. Or, since the landscape is highly non-convex, an abundance of diverse equilibria. I'm not quite sure what any of them look like in practice, or how to achieve them, though.</p>
      <p>It seems like this tension drives the realignment that our politics are going through -- woke capital vs. populist localism. It looks more and more, from following things on twitter, that the far left and far right are coming into some sort of alignment against the woke globalist establishment. e.g., The social network between BAP and the Red Scare girls is way denser than between the Red Scare girls and the Clinton camp.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>