<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-01-24T11:58:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/er8kug/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_20/ffevbej/</link>
  <title>Against Dissolving the Modern Monasteries</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Research could be taken up by dedicated research institutes like RAND or SRI analogues</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In principle I don't have a problem with research being carried out by dedicated not-for-profit institutes like the ones mentioned, but I worry that we'd see a precipitous decline in basic/very long-term research as a result, especially in the arts and humanities. One function currently provided by universities is to fund research that the private sector doesn't care about, whether it's exploring the reception of Homeric texts in 17th century Germany, developing new theories of knowledge, or charting the development of historiography through the 19th century. There's no reason that the government couldn't fund not-for-profits to undertake the same research, of course, but without the institutional Undergraduate-&gt;Phd-&gt;Professor pipieline, I worry that the quality of research would suffer.</p>
      <p>I realise that many here will wonder why these kinds of inquiry are valuable in the first place, and why the taxpayer should fund them. I'd note that the arts and humanities are pretty cheap compared to the sciences - rather than particle accelerators, they only need pencils, paper, and erasers (and in the case of philosophy, not even the erasers). Still, this is obviously a complex question, and one I won't attempt to offer a thorough answer for here. However, I'll throw out three quick considerations, with neoreactionaries particularly in mind.</p>
      <p>First, I think that a lot of the frustration and antipathy many neoreactionaries feel about academia is basically political - academia skews left/progressive, and a lot of professors see themselves as activists as much as researchers. I share some of these concerns, and while I think politics has a place in academia, I think some fields and disciplines are effectively ideological monocultures, and that's a problem. But it's a problem that's gotten worse recently, and it's as much a reflection of the sharpening political and class lines in our society as an issue unique to academia. If someone had this as their major objection to the humanities, then, I'd suggest that they be better off renovating the Cathedral rather than burning it to the ground.</p>
      <p>Second, I'd note that many neoreactionaries place a great weight on aesthetic values, and I'd appeal to them on these grounds. A society that encourages great minds to reflect on our literary and cultural traditions and explore fundamental issues of value and identity is, to be blunt, a more <em>beautiful</em> society than a more crudely utilitarian one in which labour is assigned solely by the whims of Mammon. For my part, I feel something similar about farming: even aside from considerations like food security, there is aesthetic value in preserving farming, and perpetuating the tradition of people cultivating the land.</p>
      <p>Third, I'd make an appeal to tradition and to Chesterton's fence. Most great societies - from Han China to the Roman Empire and Victorian Britain - have placed a great emphasis on scholarship, the preservation of cultural learning and understanding, and <em>ars grata artis</em>. If these societies that we might wish to emulate placed such value on scholarship, perhaps we might do well to copy their example. By contrast, many of the most destructive ideologies of recent history - from National Socialism to Maoism and Stalinism - have held up the intellectual as a figure of contempt, and have explicitly attempted to destroy or else dramatically constrain their roles so as to serve state interests. Perhaps this is merely a matter of correlation, and the attack on the arts and humanities had nothing to do with the other negative consequences of these ideologies. But again, the connection is suggestive.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>