<post>
  <author>Gloster80256</author>
  <date>2020-01-26T12:47:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/er8kug/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_20/fflqp8h/</link>
  <title>Heresies of Cultural Canon</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The most irksome aspect about these woke tendencies is that the "Western culture" is effectively being flogged for reforming itself and becoming more humane, universalist and empathetic.</p>
      <p>I can't shake a heretical thought in the back of my mind that says "Well right on we should promote our canon above all others, by right of cultural conquest!" E.g. the Chinese just <em>know</em> they are the best on the planet and have zero qualms about making darn sure everyone else understands that, subject only to practical limitations and reach of their power - which is <em>exactly</em> the test of anyone's true greatness. Of course the Realm of the Middle teaches its people first and foremost about its own cultural production, conceding to other influences only where, and to the degree, necessary. There is no hand-wringing about insufficient diversity of figures - the more monolithically Chinese the cultural canon is, the stronger the testament to national greatness. Behold our inventiveness, genius and craft!</p>
      <p>I am sure one of the major problems is that US population just doesn't see the European part of its tradition as its own; Precisely as a result of identity politics<sup>1</sup> labeling, separating and othering people into cordoned ethnic groups, instead of a single unified nation with its own continuity and influences. Instead of <em>Americans</em> asking "So how did our current culture develop? What is the backbone and which contributions shaped it?" you get Hispanics and gays asking "Why are there so many people from the <em>outgroup</em> involved? Where are <em>my</em> people?"</p>
      <p>I am no fan of the Chinese system of planned national monoculture in practice. But in terms of building asabiyyah and a unifying narrative for a large, diverse polity (in which the success of one member accrues to <em>all</em> others, instead of sparking cries that the other subgroups are left out and must now also be represented) they seem to be on to something.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>1 Well, that. And also all the racism and xenophobia before, should be noted. But those tendencies were memetically defeated and have no real say in the current political and cultural discourse. So it is deeply disheartening to see them replaced not by an ethos of civic unity but one of identitarian fracturing.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>EDIT for typso</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>