<post>
  <author>KlutzyTraining</author>
  <date>2020-01-27T18:40:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eujcbl/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_27/ffr4pxf/</link>
  <title>Virtuous Victims Bias</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Topic: what I believe to be a common and under-recognized cognitive bias which motivates a lot of people in the culture wars- I will refer to it as the "virtuous victims" bias. This is a bias I used to have myself, and deprogramming myself of the "virtuous victims" bias radically shifted my view of the world. </p>
      <p>The "virtuous victims" bias is the presumption that victims can be assumed to be more virtuous people than the group which is abusing them. </p>
      <p>An extension of this bias is the belief that we can trust victims to behave better than the previous powerful people, if and when the previously victimized people are entrusted with power. So, the "virtuous victims" bias motivates a lot of voting behavior, too. </p>
      <p>Interestingly, the virtuous victims bias is semi-opposite the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Just-world_hypothesis">"just world" bias</a>, which is the belief that the world is a just place, and so if we see someone being victimized, "they probably deserved it".  Huge numbers of people believe in this bias, too. </p>
      <p>The "just world" bias is mostly motivated by people <em>wanting</em> to believe that the world is a just and fair place, because that is more psychologically comforting. So they start with that emotional motivation and then rationalize that victims "had it coming to them". </p>
      <p>I think there are three main causes of the virtuous victims bias:</p>
      <p>
        <strong>1</strong>- Some of it can be blamed on stories. [Edit- most replies are focusing on stories. Stories are the least important &amp; provable cause of the bias, which is exactly why I devoted the most space to it. The bias would exist without stories.] </p>
      <p>Victims are almost always shown as being fundamentally virtuous people. Victims are virtuously depicted, partly to heighten the moral contrast with the aggressors, so that the audience will feel more invested in the story of the victims ultimately toppling the aggressors.  </p>
      <p>Also, while sometimes the audience is primed to see someone being hurt as a bad person who deserves it (such as a previously-proven-to-be-criminal being roughed up by a "good guy" cop), <em>normally</em> someone being hurt in a story can be assumed to be highly virtuous. </p>
      <p>It is extremely rare that someone who is a victim in a story is then later shown to have been a terrible person who actually deserved their previous bad treatment. </p>
      <p>Also, even when the victims aren't the heroes of the story, a <em>huge part of how we know someone is a hero is because they saved previously-victimized people</em>. This creates the meta-narrative that a fast track to being seen as a good person, is finding victims and helping them. </p>
      <p>There are other more realistic shades of grey which are also almost never depicted-</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>Virtuous people who are never victimized. Heroes and the people they save are <em>always</em> shown enduring significant and unnecessary suffering during the course of the story. One of the meta-narratives of most stories is that a hero <em>must</em> experience suffering. There is no such thing in the world of stories as someone who is a central hero who never suffers. Not only do heroes save victims (fostering the assumption in audiences that you can only consider yourself a good person if you help victims), but also victimhood is <em>required</em> to be counted among the most-virtuous. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>If the virtuous people start off the story being more powerful, they are always shown as being wrongly toppled, causing great suffering for all who are virtuous, and <em>then</em> we know that proves their virtuousness, and then they are allowed by the story-makers to claw their way back to power. Powerful virtuous people are never shown as simply spending the whole story quelling immoral rebellions. They and their tribe must be victimized first, before we will believe that they deserve to defeat the rebellion. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Bad people are rarely shown torturing or otherwise harming other bad people. Either the victims are virtuous, or (more rarely) the people being tortured are bad people who are a part of the previously virtuously-victimized hero's revenge story. The all-too-realistic depiction of a bunch of morally dubious people hurting other morally dubious people, is rarely shown. Audiences typically prefer to have someone to root for, and story-makers cater to that. But this means that what audiences see is skewed away from the fact that most victims in real life are average or below-average in their virtuousness, not above-average in virtue. </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <strong>2</strong>- Many people do have some real-life experiences to fall back on, to empathize with victims or to consider their own victimhood to be a virtuous status. </p>
      <p>People who have been victimized by someone more powerful can feel guilty or feel that they deserve it, but more commonly they feel victimized and indignant, and seeing oneself as innocent and virtuous strengthens the feelings of self-righteousness. </p>
      <p>The feeling of self-righteousness is one which most people love to experience (and is a great salve and buffer to alternatively feeling shameful or guilty, intensifying the attractiveness of the feeling), so victims often play up their rationalizations of victimhood to make themselves feel better (and also to appeal for sympathy from others).</p>
      <p>And for someone who has been victimized, but has little else to feel proud of, their past experiences of victimization can be the biggest possible source of feelings of pride (from feeling like a survivor) and righteousness, to outcompete the feelings of shame and worthlessness they might otherwise feel. </p>
      <p>Perhaps at the worst end, a lot of people play up their own victimhood status in their minds, and in the minds of others, in order to rationalize their own selfish behavior. A classic trope being "it's ok to steal from this group, because they victimized us, therefore we are virtuous and they are not, even though we are knowingly harming them". </p>
      <p>
        <strong>3</strong>- Most simply, it's easy for the powerful to hurt the powerless, so we tend to have lots of evidence of this. It's easy to observe.  </p>
      <p>And then we also have little evidence of the powerless groups hurting the powerful groups, precisely because they lack opportunity.</p>
      <p>So, it actually takes an act of imagination, or large amounts of real-world experience, to realize that <em>once the powerless become powerful</em>, they are also likely to behave abusively. It is in the very nature of power to show powerless people being victimized more often than powerful people are victimized.</p>
      <p>I think this virtuous victims bias is easy to observe in the culture wars, because every group recognizes how common the bias is, so they try to appeal to it by constantly playing up their own victimhood status. To be perceived as victims is to be perceived as virtuous and trustworthy by many people. </p>
      <p>I myself used to make this default assumption, and it took a MASSIVE amount of exposure to information about different power dynamics all throughout history and the modern world, to realize that literally every victimized group will behave badly at some point, once they do gain power.</p>
      <p>Some victimized groups may in fact be kinder on average, but victims are not inherently trustworthy people. </p>
      <p>In fact, victims may behave even worse on average than the previously powerful once given the chance, because not only do they have just as much reason to be selfish as their previous exploiters had had, victims can also have revenge narratives fueling their actions (and it's well-known that humans are not good at assessing reciprocal punishment, so they often punish people unfairly, even when consciously trying to be fair). </p>
      <p>And, pragmatically speaking, victims also often lack practice in competently wielding power, including wielding power in a just and fair fashion, so they sometimes do particularly poorly in wielding power, until they get sufficient practice.</p>
      <p>I don't want to deny that victims <em>sometimes are</em> the more virtuous group. And <em>sometimes</em> people are victimized specifically because they are too virtuous and trusting and gullible and unwilling to use violence, etc. </p>
      <p>And some victimized groups DO behave better than their oppressors, when they get power. They don't always act out revenge fantasies or prove to be incompetent or lacking in the discipline to rule wisely.  </p>
      <p>I just want to point out that many people start out with the <em>bias</em>, the <em>presumption</em>, that victims are fundamentally more virtuous people.</p>
      <p>In hindsight, to me this explains some of my mystification about why members of seemingly victimized groups often didn't support their own group as much as I had thought they would.</p>
      <p>Members of oppressed groups often have the closest contact with other members of their own group (family members, lovers, colleagues, local leaders, etc.), and that helps them to realize that members of their own group often behave just as badly when they get power, as any of the most powerful people in the society will behave. Outsiders miss this, precisely because they are outsiders. </p>
      <p>....</p>
      <p>My opinion is that we should prefer as a society that genuinely virtuous people get support instead, <em>even if some virtuous people are already powerful</em>. </p>
      <p>And we should also support virtuous people <em>even if the virtuous people were never victimized</em>.  </p>
      <p>The virtuous-of-any-status probably most deserve support, and also will probably do the best job of using their increase in resources to help all others. </p>
      <p>And actually, looking at things from the standpoint of risk, it probably makes sense to normally vote for and support already-powerful people who have a proven record of fair and virtuous behavior <em>relative to others with power</em>. (And this may explain some of the reason for why many members of the public often have a seemingly-odd bias in favor of voting for the wealthy and powerful.)</p>
      <p>Powerless victims are not proven to be virtuous and wise in their use of power, but relatively kind powerful people have proven their virtuous use of power as well as it can be proved.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>