<post>
  <author>Mountain-Dig</author>
  <date>2020-01-24T18:10:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/et039t/independent_ssc_survey_analysis_autogynephilia/fffq6zd/</link>
  <title>A Personal View of Autogynephilia</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Discovering the concept of autogynephilia helped me understand myself. Being a woman was my primary sexual fantasy since my teenage years, although there was some desire to be a girl at even younger ages. It was this weird, shameful, embarrassing thing about me. I'd get off on reading gender-swap erotica online, while everybody else was watching normal porn.</p>
      <p>I have a few beefs with the trans activist community. First, they deny people like me exist. I find the idea that I'm really a girl on the inside preposterous. I'm muscular and hairy, I like MMA and video games, I program, I'm a systematizer rather than an empathizer. I couldn't be a more stereotypical guy. It just so happens that I also fantasize about wearing fluffy dresses and being an object of desire.</p>
      <p>The idea that I might be really a girl on the inside *turns me on*, and that's the secret sauce to egg culture and trans evangelism. Having my own set of boobs, yes, I find that very *hot*.</p>
      <p>My second beef with the trans activist community is the medicalization of gender play, and especially the medicalization of children. These medical interventions are traumatic and irreversible. Before I started putting the pieces together, I could have easily been convinced to permanently alter my body. Again, I would have found the whole process *very hot*. But I believe my life is much, much better having an organic male body than a medicalized trans body. The older I get the more health matters to me.</p>
      <p>The last beef I have with the trans community is censorship. On the daily, you have 16 year olds wandering into reddit saying "I stole my sister's skirt, wore it, and wanked off. Am I trans?", and you have a chorus of voices unanimously trying to convince them they are trans. The community has a bias towards medical treatment and shares tips on how to bypass medical gatekeeping.</p>
      <p>I think these confused young people would be much better served if people like me were allowed to chime in and say, hey, maybe you have a fetish, and it's perfectly fine to live life as a male with a crossdressing fetish. I was just like you as a kid, and I'm not trans. But the lore in the trans community is that if other points of view are allowed, then people will kill themselves. This is a species of ideological terrorism.</p>
      <p>The TERF view of autogynephilia rings true to me. My autogynephilic fantasies developed at a time of sexual frustration (for religious reasons, I wasn't allowed to date as a teenager). I do wonder if I got some action as a teenager, if I would have developed quite as strong of an autogynephilic impulse. The incel -&gt; transcel pipeline is real.</p>
      <p>And I have quite a lot of sympathy for lesbians being forced to share their spaces with people like me. There is a huge cultural aesthetic distance between your average lesbian and your average transbian, think Indigo Girls vs. Evangelion. I understand why the poor dykes are pushing back. </p>
      <p>Adding insult to injury, from their view it's a bunch of straight men getting turned on by being validated as lesbians, and often acting as caricatures of lesbians rather than the real thing. Us AGPs <em>tend</em> to feminize ourselves more than the average girl, and <em>way</em> more than the average lesbian.</p>
      <p>Ultimately, I think everything wrong about the trans movement stems from the emotional mechanics of political activism being injected into a high stakes personal medical issue. Activists care about political wins more than they care about actually helping people, which would require nuance and caution.</p>
      <p>AGP is a controversy for me because I think lesbians have a right to defend their culture, females have a right to female-specific services, autogynephiles have a right to better psychiatric and medical advice than a pure affirmation model, and autogynephiles who are not trans should be allowed to share our experiences. The exponential rise in transgender identification (Britain has good youth statistics) seems troubling to me, not because I give a shit what clothes someone wears, but because bodies matter.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>