<post>
  <author>oscarjeff</author>
  <date>2020-01-28T07:39:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eujcbl/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_27/ffsxz6j/</link>
  <title>The Jurisdiction of Federal Courts</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>If courts exist to declare and enforce the law, a universal injunction makes sense attractive. From this perspective, there would be a "correct answer" that law should be enforced across the country.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>They don't. I know you said this is where the disagreement lies, but this broader idea of judicial authority is directly contrary to the limited conception of the judicial power outlined in Article III of the Constitution and the basic premises on which the federal courts have operated throughout the history of the US. </p>
      <p>Federal courts have jurisdiction only over the individual cases brought before them, and Article III restricts the courts' jurisdiction to "cases or controversies" satisfying specific criteria (which is what we mean when we talk about parties having standing—without proper standing, the courts do not have any authority to hear and decide a case). Courts have never had broad authority to declare and enforce the law. When we talk about courts declaring laws unconstitutional it is always in the context of deciding an individual case, and deciding the proper constitutionality of a law must be necessary to decide the particular dispute in front of it and grant relief to the parties. Courts may not go beyond what is necessary to decide and grant relief in a particular case brought before it. (In a similar vein, fed appellate courts may not even rule on particular issues in the case in front of it when those specific issues were not the ones raised in the appeal. The only exception is that a court may always decide an issue of standing even when not specifically raised by a party b/c if the parties lack standing the court has no authority to hear the case.) </p>
      <p>The reason a single federal court's decision that a fed law is unconstitutional can apply beyond the particular case and parties in front of it is b/c it binds the courts below it. But a court's decision only has the effect of binding lower courts in future cases on the same issue within the court's geographical and subject matter jurisdiction. Only a Supreme Court decision is binding on all other federal courts. </p>
      <p>But even a Supreme Court decision only applies to the parties in front of it. The Court does not actually have the authority to strike down a law; we only talk about it that way b/c the consequences of such a decision are essentially the same as if it had the power to directly strike a law from the books. But what happens is that SCOTUS's decision in one particular case that a fed law is unconstitutional binds all lower courts to treat the law as unconstitutional in any cases that come before them. The executive branch could technically continue to apply the law as written to anyone who was not party to the original case, but each time it applied that law to a particular person that person could just go to court and every federal court would be bound by the Supreme Court's decision and refuse to enforce the law. Instead, the executive branch skips the whole process of continuing to apply the law only to be unable to enforce it in any court and just respects the decision of the Supreme Court from the get-go. </p>
      <p>In the case of a circuit court decision, that decision will be binding in future cases in all district courts within its jurisdiction (but not on other circuit courts or district courts in other circuits) until such time as the Supreme Court overturns the circuit decision or the same circuit court decides the issue differently in a future case. (A district court decision does not bind any other district court.) That's why we have circuit splits—different circuit courts will decide the same issue differently and each circuit's decision will bind the district courts within its particular geographical jurisdiction but nowhere else. When that happens the executive branch will respect the decision within that circuit (usually while petitioning the Supreme Court to hear the case), but it will absolutely still continue to apply the law outside of the circuit in question until such time as the Supreme Court rules on it (which may or may not ever happen). </p>
      <p>Because courts are effectively limited to the case and parties in front of it, injunctions are supposed to be no broader than necessary to grant relief to the particular parties in a case. To properly grant injunctive relief beyond the named parties in a case to the broader class of people nationwide who may be similarly affected by application of a particular law (other than through this process of respecting court decisions as binding within a particular court's jurisdiction as outlined above), you need a class action suit. But class actions have more procedural hurdles that make them more difficult to bring precisely b/c it means that a single court's decision will then be binding on parties outside the named parties in the case, which is why the idea of sidestepping this process and obtaining a national injunction is so attractive to those who oppose the administration's actions. (Probably most importantly, you first need to get the class certified, which requires demonstrating that the class is similarly situated and the individual differences in class members' circumstances wouldn't really matter to a court's resolution of the case if those members' challenges were each brought separately. This generally involves a lot of arguing about issues of class cert, which can also involve appeals, and all of that has to happen before you can even get to the merits of the case.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>