<post>
  <author>professorgerm</author>
  <date>2020-01-24T19:24:29Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/er8kug/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_20/fffxd40/</link>
  <title>The Relationship between a Diverse a Elite and a Diverse Underclass</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Hmm... I do have mixed feelings about it overall, so you could say I'm not making a "best faith" argument, but I think that would be a substantial step towards matching their actions to the supposed goals, so let's call it "medium faith." Middling? Lukewarm?</p>
      <p>On one hand, I think a quota system is stupid and prone to grift, scams, all sorts of negative tomfoolery. It's pretty explicit tokenism, but maybe we've moved away from that being considered a negative.</p>
      <p>On the other, if people are honest about the value of diversity in general and life experience in particular, then adding  riders on top of "woman" and/or "not white" like "from low to middle class background," "<strong><em>didn't attend a top 20 university</em></strong>," would go a hell of a long way towards actually increasing the diversity of the board and not just giving a couple token spots. </p>
      <p>I'm reminded a bit of Rumsfeld's "unknown unknown" quote, and of an interview I read with the people that founded one of the early consumer 3D printer companies, maybe MakerBot? They thought it would revolutionize prototyping, democratize the inventing process, and they were shocked when the Defense Distributed guy released the gun files. It hadn't even crossed their mind, because they were from such a bubble. If there's any value to diversity it's in bursting those bubbles to cover the gaps that a homogenized group are going to miss (or deliberately ignore), <strong>so yes, if there need be a quota, I want them to be pulling those women and minorities from outside their usual bubble.</strong></p>
      <p>I mean, I don't expect Goldman Sachs of all companies to actually care about anything other than profit, and this is probably a good way to charm the "woke progressives" and get some goodwill, giving them support against the "old left" that actually cares about the flaws/risks/horrors of the financial industry beyond "male, pale, stale." </p>
      <p>I care quite strongly about "the 99%" even if the original usage of the phrase irked me. This kind of things strikes me as great for giving an ass-cover for companies to keep on keepin' on without changing anything that will affect that majority of the population. </p>
      <p>Does it help the average woman or minority person more to have a member of a disconnected, disaffected elite that looks slightly more like them but has no understanding of their lives? "It doesn't matter that you're all stuck in miserable fragile jobs in miserable apartments you can barely afford: our corporate board with its vast variety of skin tones and genitalia voted that it's A-OK to keep our policies crushing the little people!"</p>
      <p>As a white guy, to the contrary, I think if anything it's been detrimental that Jeff Bezos and Bill Gates are white, because now several media outlets have so much fun talking about how evil white guys are. I don't look at Bill Gates and think "I could be him!" just because we share skin tone any more than I could look at LeBron James and think "I could be him!" despite <em>not</em> sharing skin tone, yet I do feel "someone" decided it's okay to attack people that share skin tone with Bill Gates for that factor alone. An argument can be made about representation being important, and I could agree, but I think our current media writ broadly provides ample demonstration that representation can also be a significant negative. This likely says more about the incredibly low quality of our media (and I must acknowledge, the incentives to which they're responding) than it does about the pros/cons of representation.</p>
      <p>I had similar feelings about MeToo; I figured a slim chance it would help "normal people" and a big chance it would be rich, disconnected people patting themselves on the back for being "so brave" with no change for "normal victims." It would be hard to quantify but I am 99.9% confident Mariska Hargitay alone has done more for sexual assault victims by setting up Joyful Heart back in 2004 than all of MeToo did combined.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>