<post>
  <author>sinxoveretothex</author>
  <date>2020-01-27T18:53:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eujcbl/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_27/ffr6125/</link>
  <title>Accountable vs Unaccountable Movements</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The terrain of the Internet is unusually well-suited to decentralized ideologies where people are never responsible for anything.</p>
      <p>What is a good atheist? Well, as everyone's been saying ad nauseum: "aThEiSm IsN't A wOrLdViEw It'S tHe LaCk Of OnE" and therefore any one atheist, however public, who does something bad by whatever standard you currently endorse is just not part of your own movement/worldview. If that person is you, you can delete your pseudonymous account and create a new one. The only accountability there is, is the one you accept to take on.</p>
      <p>There isn't a better example of this than the recent exchange/callout/debate between Rationality Rules and Sargon of Akkad where Rationality uses that same line of thinking wrt the phrase "the Left". Even the leader of the UK's Labour Party is a "nut" according to him and not representative of "the Left".</p>
      <p>It's not so much that Atheism and other such decentralized movements won, as much as it is that they can only lose on the Internet if they literally accept to.</p>
      <p>Accountable movements are well-suited to the real world where unity is key to defending the real-world terrain from invading movements and where it's useful to have a well-run and trustworthy community so people will want to join and contribute to it.</p>
      <p>But the real-world is fully conquered to the point where we've mostly solved international invasions (until the end of pax americana at least) so the winning strategy is subversion: choose a valuable target, infiltrate it and take it over then ride the wave until it breaks.</p>
      <p>The people you take over can't leave: there's nowhere else to go. So they lose. Not because you beat them but simply because they were suckers who were happily contributing to the organization that would ultimately oppose them. In a way, they unknowingly beat themselves.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>