<post>
  <author>georgemonck</author>
  <date>2020-08-12T17:32:03Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i6yuis/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_10_2020/g18gvpd/</link>
  <title>Contra Keith Woods on Moldbug</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>As a Moldbug completionist myself, I think Woods is mistaken in a number of his critiques of Moldbug. Of course, I don't entirely blame him -- Moldbug clarifies a lot of things in comments or later posts that are hard to miss if you only have time to read a bit of him.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And his own liberal priors are evident when he identifies Thatcher and Reagan, the face of neoliberalism, as his examples of reactionary anti-establishment forces that revolted against the system.” </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>False. <a href="https://foseti.wordpress.com/2011/08/03/eisenhower/">Moldbug recommended</a> biography of Reagan <em>Here’s the Rest of Him</em> which talks about how Reagan, while talking anti-establishment, was actually a sell-out to liberalism:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Obviously you’ve never read Kent Steffgen’s book on Reagan. Political rhetoric is a matter of where you’re getting your votes, not what you do with them. Both Reagan and Nixon could say great things about liberalism – neither did much.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Moving on:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The book by Robert DiAngelo has become very popular. Now, you could see this in the NRx fashion of just another step on the ladder of progressivism and the utter expansion of the Cathedral, self directed, but there are ways to analyse this that show this is clearly directed by certain groups and actors with individual interest. And this obviously gives us a better way of understanding it if it is indeed directed by certain actors.” Andrew Joyce wrote an article on DiAngelo’s book. He found its bibliography was like a family reunion....This analysis is one like the analysis of group behavior that was done by MacDonald in his book, that Moldbug excludes with his Cathedral concept. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>False, Moldbug did exactly this kind of analysis of power networks when he analyzed the Climategate emails: <a href="https://www.unqualified-reservations.org/2009/12/climategate-historys-message/">https://www.unqualified-reservations.org/2009/12/climategate-historys-message/</a>  Moldbug understood and explained that were conspiracies pushing various agendas. But he was explaining that the Cathedral as a whole was not a top-down, 1984 or Star Wars Empire or Stalinist style structure. But it's not exactly a grassroots phenomena either (which is explicitly why he calls it a "Cathedral" as opposed to the "Bazaar"). It's dozens or hundreds of micro-conspiracies all figuring out how to "manipulate procedural outcomes" in order to capture institutions, leverage power, and advance certain agendas.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In the end I believe reactionary thought is limited because it ignores the explanations I’ve laid out: essentially, capital incentives and ethnic interests. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>He doesn't exactly ignore "capital incentives", he basically explains the entire point of his blog is too reject this thesis:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Since we provide the genuine article, UR is pretty much the anti-Chomsky. (As a broad generalization, UR’s stance in any controversy will be the opposite of Chomsky’s.) ...</p>
        <p>...After completing the UR treatment, it is interesting to go back and read your Chomsky. What you’ll see is that Chomsky is, in every case, demanding that all political power be in the hands of the Cathedral. The American system is very large and complex, and this is certainly not the case. The least exception or (God forbid) reversal, and Chomsky is in on the case, deploying the old principle of “this animal is very dangerous; when attacked, it defends itself.”6 The progressive is always the underdog in his own mind. Yet, in objective reality, he always seems to win in the end....</p>
        <p>In other words, the Chomskian transformation is to interpret any resistance, by a party which is inherently much weaker, as oppression by a magic force of overwhelming strength. For example, we can ask: which set of individuals exerts more influence over American journalists? American professors, or American CEOs? American diplomats, or American generals? In both cases, the answer is clearly the former. Yet any hint of corporate or military influence over the press is, of course, anathema.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>And Moldbug is right -- look at how things like Me Too, gay liberation, Black Lives Matter, anti-racism, global warming, etc, enter society. It starts with the academia and activist complex, then gets established in the prestige press and blue city governments, and then corporations start playing along with the themes, once they have already been established in the Zeitgeist. Sure, sometimes particular corporations or particular rich people are involved in pushing these agendas -- eg, drug companies pushing transexual agenda. Moldbug talks about how "clean energy" is a grift with the people pushing it also making money from government grants and subsidies and such. But "capital" overall is not pushing these things.</p>
      <p>Personally, I buy that "powerful people wanting to get rich" did drive the push for market liberalism. I don't buy that they push general wokeness on matters of sex and race. Here is the Rockefeller Foundation on racism in America:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>As I said earlier this week, the recent murders of Ahmaud Arbery, George Floyd, Tony McDade, Sean Reed, and Breonna Taylor leave me angry and heartbroken. These acts of violence and police brutality are despicable. Yet again, innocent men and women were killed for no other reason than the color of their skin....It’s painful to see police vehicles charging into groups of unarmed protestors in broad daylight just a few minutes’ walk from the homes and neighborhoods where our colleagues live and raise their families.....Not enough can ever be said of the unique pain, suffering, and injustice that African Americans have experienced and continue to experience in this country. Not enough has ever been done to end this oppression in all its forms, and truly heal the wounds of centuries of racism and bigotry....The racist inequities in America are baked deep into the fabric of our society, public policies, and power structures. They permeate our health system, and our food system, and more than 150 years after the end of slavery they still define so much of the inequality in our economy. <a href="https://www.rockefellerfoundation.org/blog/reflecting-on-violence-against-african-americans/">https://www.rockefellerfoundation.org/blog/reflecting-on-violence-against-african-americans/</a></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>How do the Rockefeller's profit from pushing this message? I think they push these messages -- and so many rich people and rich corporations are pushing this message -- because 1) there is a mob out there, and people who are not going along with the mob are getting crushed and/or 2) they believe in the message and once you have a lot of money, feeling like you are doing good for the world is a higher priority than making a little bit more money.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>