<post>
  <author>HavelsOnly</author>
  <date>2020-08-07T17:16:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0p7pkq/</link>
  <title>Should You Vote, Though?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is an argument I bring up every once in a while, so just wanting to test it out on The Motte. I think the probability of your vote influencing the national presidential election is so small as to be indistinguishable from zero. So I don't vote. There's a lot of annoying rejoinders to this, like "what if no one voted" (then I would vote, duh, cus my vote would make a difference), or that voting is my civic duty or voting for third party candidates is a protest vote yada yada. Vote if you want - this post is merely about the estimated probability and value of your vote.</p>
      <p>The electoral college makes things tricky and forces most forecasters to use simulation. It's more transparent if I just argue about the popular vote. If you really wanted, you could calculate the probability of your vote mattering in your state and then multiply that by what some model estimates is the chance your state will determine the national election.</p>
      <p>Typical <a href="http://www.stat.columbia.edu/%7Egelman/research/published/probdecisive2.pdf">literature estimates</a> I see have the probability of a vote swinging the national election are on the order of 1/1e7.  That seems small, but if your candidate is $1e12 better (that's like 5% of GDP), then voting for the right candidate has an EV for society of $1e5. Not too shabby for whatever 5 mins or 2 hours people say it takes to vote!</p>
      <p>Unfortunately, I think the method those authors use is pure jank. Someone correct me if I'm wrong (mea culpa, but their article is sparse on equations...) but it looks like they take a sample of state-level polls, fit a probability density function to them, and then calculate the "probability of an exact tie at density at 0". Also note they use Student's T distribution because presumably they are working with a small enough sample size of polls that degrees of freedom matter. Haah.</p>
      <p>Anyway, it's not clear at all that your poll conversion rates capture variability in election conversion rates. They are merely a point estimate of overall conversion rate. I.e., if a well-designed poll tells you 46% are voting for candidate A, your estimate for the real election is also 46%. But by itself "46%" doesn't tell you anything about what kind of variation to expect. And in fact if you only had a single poll using the above method, your variation is 0, which obviously we know it's not. We know it's not because we didn't collect a lump-value of 46%, we actually sampled thousands of people and aggregated them.</p>
      <p>So my preferred method is to think about exactly what a poll is. Ideally, a poll is a random sample of votes from the voting population. If you had such a poll, you would probably only need a few thousand samples to predict the election margin within a 0.1 percentage points. The collection framework assumes each voter's behaviour is probabilistic until they are sampled and take on a discrete value. So if you sample 5000 people, your model for the rest of the population is each voter decides with p to vote for candidate A and (1-p) for candidate B. You estimate p from your 5000 sample. No there is no candidate C.</p>
      <p>So let's say we have a p and we're really confident in it. Now if we know total voter turnout N we can estimate the probability of a tie. And then we're going to double this because the probability of a tie and probability of a tie-minus-one are about the same for large N and p ~0.5. So this will give us the probability that you swing the election for your candidate, or you tie the election away from your candidate losing. In both of those cases, your vote matters very much.</p>
      <p>Easy math time - God tells us that p = 0.5 and there are 10 other people on the island. The probability of a 5/5 vote split is... (and I am going to avoid signaling my intelligence by doing basic math and just point y'all at a <a href="https://stattrek.com/online-calculator/binomial.aspx">calculator</a>) 24.6%. The probability of a 4/6 split in favor of the Bad Candidate is 20.5%, which I said should be close to the probability of an exact tie as our numbers get larger. So in this case, your vote makes a difference about 50% of the time.</p>
      <p>Okay 100 other people on the island. p = 0.5. p(vote matters) ~ 16%. 1000 people, p(vote matters) = 5%. 10k people, 1.6%. Tentatively, this seems pretty favorable. We increase population by a factor of 10 each time but our probability doesn't decrease by a factor of 10. It looks like it actually shrinks by about a factor of 3 each time. Unfortunately we can't keep going forever because the binomial distribution uses factorials, which are difficult to compute for large values. Fortunately, the normal distribution is a good approximation to the binomial distribution with large N.</p>
      <p>Wikipedia wants us to use a normal approximation with mean = N*p and stdev = sqrt(n*p*(1-p)). <a href="https://stattrek.com/online-calculator/binomial.aspx">Calculator</a>. For N = 1000, p = 0.5. So mean = 500 and stdev = 15.8. The probability of being greater than 498 and less than 50 votes is 5.04%. Really close to our exact binomial estimate.</p>
      <p>Let's also take with maximum charity the argument that we care deeply about distributed benefits to our fellow citizens. So if we could make everyone's life better by $5, that is a *really big deal* because it scales with 100s of millions of people. It seems plausible that a good candidate's value would scale linearly with population. I.e., the leader of 1000 people can have 10x the impact as the leader of 100 people. So your EV is proportionate to p(decisive_vote)*population_size. (If we assume voter turnout fraction is also independent of pop size, this relation continues to hold even though only about 1/3rd of U.S. people vote)</p>
      <p>It turns out that for p = 0.5, when plotted on a log-log scale, your decisive-vote-odds decrease linearly with population size. <a href="https://imgur.com/a12Gq3d">https://imgur.com/a12Gq3d</a> However, your EV also increases linearly on the log-log plot. Which means that the larger your population is, the *better* it is to vote. This is really counter intuitive, since you'd think in an infinitely large society your vote would have the least impact. But because that impact is scaled by population size as well, your impact decreases more slowly than the benefits increase, so actually it's more important to vote in large elections.</p>
      <p>This is true when p = 0.5. Exactly 0.5. Not 0.499999. Not 0.50001. Exactly 0.5. Your EV tanks HARD once you are no longer balancing on a needle. Here's the charts for 0.49. <a href="https://imgur.com/PndgpyR">https://imgur.com/PndgpyR</a></p>
      <p>Yes, they crash on me between 1e6 and 1e7 voter pop. This is because they go way below machine precision. The last value I am able to record is on the order of e-237, and the EV is e-230. Note that there are at most 10e82 atoms in the universe. So let's be real here. For 0.499 I am able to get out to about 3e8 population size before p_decisive and EV crash below precision. <a href="https://imgur.com/gp45I2K">https://imgur.com/gp45I2K</a></p>
      <p>For 0.4999, we see something interesting, which is that EV increases up until 1e8 population size, and then craters below precision within an order of magnitude.  <a href="https://imgur.com/k4wmDbR">https://imgur.com/k4wmDbR</a></p>
      <p>This whole thing is counter intuitive because a very large number is fighting a very small number in exponential space. So my tentative conclusion is that if your estimate for the popular vote margin is more than 0.01 percentage points and there are about 100 million other voters, the EV of your vote is 0. Technically, it is approximately zero, but that makes it sound like it still has value. Let me be clear that picking up a piece of litter at the beach has a billion quintillion bazillion times more impact.</p>
      <p>If you think the vote is *very very* close to exactly tied... then it's time to do some math. And I assure you, that math is a lot harder both conceptually and estimation-wise than any of the above. Thankfully, it doesn't look like we'll have a close election any time soon, so the math is easy and I don't think any individual vote makes a difference at all!!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>