<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-08-10T00:01:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0xzaux/</link>
  <title>Defending Utopian Speech-Restricting Overlords</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Since your post is not yet the promised argument for free speech, I'll haphazardly defend the not-quite-free consequentialist society from your parable, by showing that it's a reasonable and arguably unavoidable arrangement.   </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Zeroth, Land.</strong> Consequentialism has the unbeatable Darwinian advantage, in that the principal consequence is survival. You're speaking from a "Thrive" pole, as an entitled consumer of public goods in an abundantly rich society where politics are concerned with negotiation of rank order of projects producing various public goods – not from one where the entire system is trying to perpetuate itself. 25CNAM didn't die out, it <em>lost</em> to some specific competitor like 37CBAIO, and because it wasn't good enough at memetic defense, not for its excessive evil. Humanity got unimaginably lucky that the winner was both utilitarian and friendly (<em>if, indeed, he was</em>); and should feel gratitude for the utopia he has chosen to share with them.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>any reasonable ethical or political philosophy for the governance of human being has to start from the principle that we're all on our own journeys, our own missions to make sense of the world, and none of us is exempt from the game or qualified to serve as its ultimate arbiter</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The preferences here are axiomatic, irrational, the justification being downstream from an effectively aesthetic outlook; I'll spare you another sermon on darn Westerners being molded by their selection pressures, but only because a serious AI would do it better and you can imagine that yourself.   </p>
      <p>
        <strong>First, More.</strong> It merits repeating that 12K AD is a legitimate Utopia. Not just in the sense that its rulers bothered to ressurrect an Early Woke Age monkey riddled with dangerous mind viruses (while in our enlightened age deathism rules supreme, and Robin Hanson's wife may ensure his brain rots, despite express attempts to avoid this), but <em>precisely because it's an illiberal hierarchical technocracy</em>. That's the whole point since Plato. "Abundance, egalitariansism and complete free speech" is not Utopia, it's American-pie-in-the-sky, a rather novel reading. Literally More's <em>Utopia</em>, often touted as early Communist manifesto, and the gentlest of the bunch, has the following provisions: «The same trade generally passes down from father to son, inclinations often following descent ... those who, being recommended to the people by the priests, are, by the secret suffrages of the Syphogrants, privileged from labour, that they may apply themselves wholly to study ... Out of these they choose their ambassadors, their priests, their Tranibors, and the Prince himself ... the generality of mankind are both so dull, and so much employed in their several trades, that they have neither the leisure <em>nor the capacity</em> requisite for such an inquiry [into complex laws]».  Oh, also: «...he therefore left men wholly to their liberty, that they might be free to believe as they should see cause; only he made a solemn and severe law against such as should so far degenerate from the dignity of human nature, as to think that our souls died with our bodies, or that the world was governed by chance, without a wise overruling Providence [...] They never raise any that [think otherwise], either to honours or offices, nor employ them in any public trust, but despise them, as men of base and sordid minds».<br />
The general spirit and the tone of the rest of the book nonwithstanding, we can see that this happy society is more or less ruled by a superior caste and has criminalized a category of wrongthink. How could it be otherwise? It also means that there must be some decisions the upper caste will be unable to honestly justify to the populace (indeed the argument against atheism is not watertight); at best, they'll have to make do with a simplified, imprecise, patronizing analogy, to get the "correct" vote (if for some reason this system still LARPs as a democracy). It is not the case that any higher-level decision can be condensed into a simple verifiable proof; and any inclusive democratic decision-making would depend on there being such asymmetry.  </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Second, Banks.</strong> Indeed, this inequality is only exacerbated with our knowledge expanding, with the notion of superhuman intelligence being appreciated to the full extent of its implications. One of the brightest visions for humanity's future, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Culture#Biological"><em>Culture</em> series by Banks</a>, is explicit in showing that humans will accept their role of pets, protected and guided and sometimes gently deceived by machine Gods, "Minds". Was that your inspiration? </p>
      <p>In 12K AD, after being denied access to any data, I'd immediately ask if they allow uplifting, to get the ability qualifying me for learning the truth. Incidentally, Culture Minds do not welcome it.  </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Third and finally getting to the point, Egan.</strong>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"That’s it? Good luck and bon voyage?" Yatima tried to read vis face, but Inoshiro just gazed back with a psychoblast’s innocence. "What’s happened to you? What have you done to yourself?"<br />
Inoshiro smiled beatifically and held out vis hands. A white lotus flower blossomed from the center of each palm, both emitting identical reference tags. Yatima hesitated, then followed their scent.<br />
It was an old outlook, buried in the Ashton-Laval library, copied nine centuries before from one of the ancient memetic replicators that had infested the fleshers. It imposed a hermetically sealed package of beliefs about the nature of the self, and the futility of striving… including explicit renunciations of every mode of reasoning able to illuminate the core beliefs' failings.<br />
Analysis with a standard tool confirmed that the outlook was universally self-affirming. Once you ran it, you could not change your mind. Once you ran it, you could not be talked out of it. Yatima said numbly, "You were smarter than that. Stronger than that."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You object to the AI overlord denying your equality of agency. You admit really being a lesser mind, but... "But" what? You mean to say that you both are active beings, that is, agents, both entitled to make decisions based on some <em>knowledge</em>. In other words, you perceive knowledge as <em>inert landscape</em> that you [in your colonial cisheteropatriarchical Anglo curiosity] get to travel; how dare a fellow traveler, even if incomparably swifter-footed, bar you from entry?  It's unfair! It's tyranny! It's bullying! Nooo, you can't!   </p>
      <p>None of this tantrum makes any sense from the superintelligent decision-maker's vantage point, and not only for reasons of relative aptitude. He truly is inhuman, you're right about that. He sees all <a href="http://www.ribbonfarm.com/2012/11/27/patterns-of-refactored-agency/">patterns of refactored agency</a> at once. You, the 21st century fossil, and NAM, the 25th century info-hazard, <em>are both data</em>; the distinction of agent and self-unpacking ideas is immaterial for AI. You both have been frozen in time, and his culture deemed only one of you worthy of being revived. In a sense, it is not an issue of your right to explore, but an issue of rights to participation in their society; incomparably more so if it is somehow <em>truly</em> democratic. Just like you have certain ideas and values and will try to persuade others of their importance, so too will 25CNAM. You are asking not for mere "information" but for an esoteric tome freeing <a href="https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/main/sealedevilinacan">the sealed Devil</a>; you are venturing not into Amazon jungle but into a BSL-4 faculty, and without hazmat suit; unthawing not just <em>Mein Kampf</em> but a 300 IQ psionic Hitler... I could go on with analogies, but better stop here, also it brings us back to the modern arguments against free speech. You are asking to be allowed to enable an entity you don't comprehend and won't be able to bear responsibility for. Now, you may claim to be a responsible adult, but how can you back up this ambition? How will you compensate them, should they be proven right about the consequences?    </p>
      <p>Well. If you object so much to their priorities at reviving relics of past age, and are unable to bear costs for your actions upon being invited in, and unwilling to consider those costs, maybe it was a mistake. Would you rather be put back into that crevasse?</p>
      <p>
        <strong>P.S.</strong> There is, however, one small issue with censorship here and now in 2K AD: its proponents are not friendly superintelligent Gods. In fact it can be argued that they're at best statistically illiterate or insane or deluded, and at worst, psychopaths. Their greatest claim to authority is monopoly over some poorly replicating or wholly unempirical academic fields. Modelling the consequences of their reign and its enforcement, specifically, is something they either don't do or won't share. And the outcomes have been... uninspiring, far as we can tell.<br />
If they simply admitted considering themselves superhuman, the negotiations would go much smoother.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>