<post>
  <author>Impossible_Campaign</author>
  <date>2020-08-09T04:29:04Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0v164w/</link>
  <title>Executive Overreach, Norms, and American Collapse</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's interesting how Trump is knowingly and conspicuously exceeding his formal authority in issuing this order. Money is clearly the purview of the legislature, not the executive, but that doesn't seem to matter anymore. Trump will probably away with this set of orders: what he's doing is necessary, popular, and impossible to oppose while retaining the public's trust. And when Trump does get away with these orders, that's a real transfer of power from the legislature to the executive --- one that rises, perhaps, to a constitutional dislocation.</p>
      <p>Not that I mind: whatever we're doing now isn't working, and the American republic is dead anyway. Rome eventually solved its chronic governmental dysfunction (arising from the Optimates and the Populares utterly hating each other) via a strongman (Augustus Caesar) coming to power, neutering the old legislative bodies (while preserving their forms), and governing by edict. Rome replaced a broken republic with a functional autocracy. Of course the latter also became dysfunctional after a few centuries, but the shift in governmental style gave Rome a few hundred extra years of peace, prosperity, and happiness. I think we're traveling the same road that Rome did.</p>
      <p>There's a country out there to govern. There are real problems to be solved. If the legislature simply refuses to govern --- because it's divided into two halves that hate each other --- the executive is going to step in and <em>do something</em> whether or not it's formally legal. Just like Rome, we'll maintain the forms of republican government for a long time --- we'll continue to have congressional elections, hearings broadcast on C-SPAN, and bills passed by both houses --- but real power to decide what happens will shift to the executive, which will inevitably become a lifetime office at some point, probably as a solidification of a temporary measure against some future emergency.</p>
      <p>I wouldn't put too much stock in constitutional norms preventing this transition. Rome had equally strong norms that it had maintained for over 400 years, and during the last first century BC, it all went to hell anyway, the power of norms be damned.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>