<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2020-08-07T23:18:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0qgffv/</link>
  <title>Democracy: Join a Gang and Fight Back</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>What we are looking at here is the clash between democracy as an ancient concept, and the modern atomization of humanity.</p>
      <p>
        <em>Your</em> vote is a drop in the bucket, sure. But until relatively recently, you were proud of your bucket and came to a consensus within the bucket about which candidate to spill over (so to speak).</p>
      <p>“One man, one vote” is a deceptively phrased slogan. You think it means “each individual must cast a vote according their personal preferences”, but it <em>actually</em> means “no demographic can be excluded from the franchise.”</p>
      <p>No democracy in history has been a collection of free spirited, libertarian, rational loners who vote randomly every year depending on what variables in their calculations have shifted. The vote has always been by canton, or by town, or by congregation, or by neighborhood. It has always been collectives moving as one, speaking in one voice, voting as a bloc, much as the Romans would attack in a formation. In fact, when Rome was co-ruled by her small farmers and urban workers before oligarchs strangled the Republic, their version of the electoral college was literally their military unit the marches with.</p>
      <p>That’s the reason why people talk about “the black vote”, or “the Evangelicals”, or the “appealing to suburban moms.” The time for rational decision making to figure out who to vote for is when you’re with your clique figuring out who among you is best suited to represent you. If you missed out on this debate because you were off living your best life instead of coming to the meetings, none of them will.</p>
      <p>You can’t figure out why you should vote, because you are a single dude standing around in a rumble trying to figure out whether it is the Greasers or the Socs who have the best policy, or whether maybe you should go third party with the Jets or the Sharks. The answer is that you are not in a gang, and have no input to either faction’s stance and no obligation to show up and cover your brother’s back.</p>
      <p>That’s why rural republicans who show up and vote as a unit get more power than their numbers allow for- they see a guy wearing their gang colors and they go out of their way to vote for them as a prerequisite for in group membership. If you don’t care who’s in charge, you cede power to the largest bloc standing and you get what you get. If you hate what the largest bloc does, or think that they’ll abuse you with the state power they seized, do what every other scared individual does when the local hoppers target them- join a gang and fight back.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>