<post>
  <author>Verda-Fiemulo</author>
  <date>2020-08-11T06:21:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i6yuis/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_10_2020/g12si43/</link>
  <title>Do Memes Exist? Can They Kill?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>What's more interesting is why you believe in something which is physically impossible.Maybe it's nice to think your words can change the world.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't know why you think it's physically impossible.</p>
      <p>Have you ever seen the Donkey Kong ROM for the Atari 2600 printed out as 0's and 1's? If each row is a byte and you flip to the right page of the ROM, you can see "Mario", it looks like just the pixels that show up on the screen when you play the game (without color information, which is stored elsewhere.)</p>
      <p>Now, when you play your Atari 2600, where is "Mario"? Is he the LEDs in your TV lighting up? Is he some of the electricity traveling through the wires of your computer? Is he the place in computer memory where some physical objects are in one of two states? Is he the mental sensation produced by the concert of all these things?</p>
      <p>He's kind of all these things, but the one thing he definitely is, is physical. And here's the interesting thing - my behavior changes based on what "Mario" is doing. I do different actions, depending on what I see happening on screen, and "his actions" change based on what I do to the joystick. A few switches in an off or on position that correspond to "Mario" cause a chain of effects that causes my behavior to change, and my behavior causes a chain of effects that causes "Mario" to change.</p>
      <p>Now, if information can exist physically in the world, and can even have a causal interaction in the world, why is it at all strange that my ideas, which are just another form of physical information in the world, could have a causal relationship with the world?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Memes can't kill their host because they don't exist. All there is is behavior, and this is explained by genetics and environment. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Right, and technically 1's and 0's in computer science don't exist either.</p>
      <p>They're just a useful notation or abstraction that correspond to states that you can put electrical switches in. However, if we pick out a "meme" as a bit of information stored in my brain in a particular way, which affects my behavior when certain neural passages are stimulated - then I think you can begin to build a theory of memes as the interaction of proteins in one brain, which tend to reliably produce interactions of proteins in other brains.</p>
      <p>I'm curious what your case is that memes are physically impossible.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>