<Post>
  <author>ChevalMalFet</author>
  <date>2019-11-08T10:43:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/drd1uu/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_04/f6vzs7n/</link>
  <title>An Opus on Korean Education: Part 1</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is a top-level reply to a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/drd1uu/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_04/f6jqjn4/">comment</a> made a few days ago, comparing Korean and American test scores. I noted that the Korean school system does a good job getting good test scores, but my own experience with that same system also suggests it comes with a lot of costs and can't be taken as a model for the US. This is my effort post on the same subject. Maybe this should be its own post, but, eh, what the hell.   </p>
      <p>
        <strong>WHY KOREAN SCHOOLS ARE NOT AMERICAN SCHOOLS</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The Korean education system is widely touted as one of the best in the world. Korean students’ high achievement scores in math and literacy are often cited as showing the superiority of the Korean way, and as an indictment of countries with lower average scores (most often the USA). </p>
      <p>I myself am an educator, working for 7 years teaching history and English at American middle schools and in Korean high schools. I have a Master’s in education, but that is just about all my credentials. Everything that follows is based on my own personal observations and opinions and should be in no way treated as authoritative - but if you want a view from the Korean trenches it may serve. </p>
      <p>The bottom line is I think there’s something to the stereotypical view - Korea has certain cultural and institutional advantages, and its education system is practically designed to achieve good test scores. However, I also think that a focus on test scores alone masks a lot of serious problems with Korean education, and I am not at all convinced that the system is the best means of preparing Korea’s young citizens to face the future. </p>
      <p>——-</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Korea’s Cultural Advantages</strong>
      </p>
      <p>It’s very important to understand that Korea is not like the US. I have no doubt that many of you are reading this now and either snorting or rolling your eyes at an obvious assertion, but I just want you to pause and appreciate it for a moment: <em>Korea is not the US.</em> We understand that intellectually, but that has important consequences on the cultural level.</p>
      <p>The main thing is Korea’s Confucian culture. Confucian ethics heavily emphasize duty, responsibility, and hierarchy. Sons have a duty to respect, honor, and obey their fathers. Fathers in turn have a duty to defend and provide for their sons. The Korean worldview (which is shifting somewhat as Korea integrates with the modern, largely-Western world) neatly places everyone into their place into the hierarchy: Parents over children, elders over the young, men over women, etc. Now, individualist Western sensibilities chafe at this, but it’s important to note that Koreans are fully aware that the West does things differently, but they don’t really care. The way they do things is perfectly natural and works well for them. They view us the same way we view them. </p>
      <p>So, most people (not all - just as there are Westerners that want to promote more communal ethics over our own individualist ethos, there are Koreans who want to make their own society less communal) are perfectly comfortable in this system. This sense of heirarchy is everywhere. Young people I’ve never met before are unfailingly polite and respectful, both from my status as an elder (I’m only 30! I’m not <em>old</em>) and as a teacher (when they know I’m a teacher, which is a fair guess when you see a Westerner here - probably an English teacher). Young people are socialized their entire lives to obey their parents and their teachers.</p>
      <p>Now, what do those parents and teachers want them to do? To learn. Education is almost holy to Koreans. Everyone here respects and honors getting a good education. Top to bottom, from the President all the way down, the message is universal: <em>you must get a good education and go to a good university.</em> Korea is an extremely proud and patriotic nation, and one of their badges of honor is their educational attainment. It is every students’ duty to uphold that and contribute to Korea’s continuing dominance in the world rankings (they especially need to keep ahead of the hated Japanese). </p>
      <p>These two factors - Koreans’ respect for elders/teachers, and the society-wide veneration of education - means Korean schools have an influence over Korean students to a degree Western teachers can only dream about. Seriously, I used to teach middle school in the USA, and the difference is night and day. Student behavior here is an absolute <em>dream</em> and it’ll be hard for me to go back to the, uh, livelier environment of an American middle school. The result of this school power is that schools can ask a lot more of Korean students than American schools do. If Americans tried some of the things I’m about to tell you, well, they’d not only have students but parents also revolting. They’d never get away with it. But in Korea, parents will - almost - always support the teachers over the students. </p>
      <p>
        <strong>The Korean school system - an overview</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Korean schools are modelled after the US system, due to the long-standing presence of American troops and the accompanying bleed-through of US culture in the country. Students attend 6 mandatory years of elementary school and 6 years of secondary, split between 3 years of mandatory middle school and 3 years of “optional” high school. High school, while neither mandatory nor free, is basically universal among Koreans due to the society’s intense focus on educational achievement. </p>
      <p>Students learn math, science, “life skills” like pro-social behavior, and, starting in 3rd grade, English, history, and other “soft” subjects in elementary school. Middle school is more of the same, with an increasing focus on English, math, and science. High schools are split into general academic subjects (about ¾ of students), “vocational” schools (about ⅕), and specialized private prep schools (like the one I teach at). </p>
      <p>English proficiency is an obsession with the country. The language is mandatory starting in 3rd grade, and the Korean government is heavily focused on promoting competent English education, including paying its own teachers to live for extended periods of time in English-speaking countries and offering native English speakers very generous contracts indeed to come over and teach their own students (now you know why I’m here). Many high schools and universities are taught exclusively in English. In addition, there are possibly thousands of private English academies in the country - I pass posters and ads for them all the time. </p>
      <p>All of this is aimed at the big event: the CSAT. This event, held in November every year, is THE college admission test in Korea. The results of this single test is the highest of high stakes for Korean students - just short of life or death (actually, given the suicide rate, for many students it IS literally life or death). Traffic shuts down and the government runs extra busses and subways to make sure students make it to the test on time. Air traffic over Korea is shut down for the 8 hours the listening portion of the test takes place in. </p>
      <p>The baseline for admission to Korea’s top three universities (Seoul University, Korea University, and Yonsei University, “SKY”) is a near-perfect score.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</Post>