<post>
  <author>Beerwulf42</author>
  <date>2020-07-06T20:13:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fx4tj2b/</link>
  <title>Analyzing The Music in Hamilton</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Are any of the actual songs from Hamilton any good?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Two things. Firstly Hamilton's songs are songs within the genre <em>Broadway musical</em> that use hip-hop elements, rather than songs within the genre <em>hip-hop</em>. Secondly, the Hamilton soundtrack is far greater than the sum of its songs.</p>
      <p>Therefore, instead of Eminem, the benchmark for comparison would be something like West Side Story. Are any of the songs as good as <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j3d1wrj4riQ">the balcony scene</a>? No, there's probably nothing as good as the last 70 seconds of the Balcony scene, to be honest. The most comparable would be <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rn90wjBmtuY">Helpless</a>, which at least doesn't have much LMM, who's not half the singer of the chap in the first link. In Hamilton's defence, I can't recall any West Side Story lyrics as cute as "We were at a revel with some rebels on a hot night.". Hamilton's rhymes are dense and rather clever.</p>
      <p>For example, there are a lot of songs that follow a Broadway convention of introducing one theme, then another, and then singing both at the finale. There's the classic trope of ending the first act with everyone singing all the songs from the act at the same time.  Is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_YHVPNOHySk">Non-Stop</a> as good as the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MyUV3hIL-G0">Tonight Quintet</a>? No.</p>
      <p>So does Hamilton do anything well musically? It's the most musically coherent and integrated musical I know - the exact opposite of a jukebox musical. It has many repeating motifs that run thoughout the show. </p>
      <p>For example <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kK9c41WgNpc">That Would Be Enough</a>, introduces the "That would Be Enough" motif, but also uses the "Look Around" motif, first heard (I think) in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UqqJO0nTBbQ">The Schuyler Sisters</a> (which has a good example of the two themes at once at 2:20). That would Be Enough also ends on with descending piano part.</p>
      <p>At the start act two, specifically the end of <a href="https://youtu.be/gFCM7k5-8_k?t=218">Take a Break</a> the "Look Around" motif appears again. He doesn't take a break and ends up with the Reynolds affair. Finally, (for my post), after trashing his marriage and the death of his son, we have the song <a href="https://youtu.be/D2DL0-UcaRU">It's Quiet Uptown</a>. It starts with that descending piano part again.  "That would Be Enough" motif occurs at 1:57,  2:10 and 2:43. Particularly since it's been Eliza's line so far, and here it's sung by Alexander.  "Look Around" motif occurs at 3:10.  Given I was critical earlier, I should also say that LMM's delivery is really works for this song. In "Best of Wives..." The descending piano part is now more playful, "That would be enough" returns.</p>
      <p>This is just one example and there are so many more. These motifs run through the show and form the skeleton that turns a collection of songs into an integrated,  coherent whole.  If you listen to songs individually, you don't get that. </p>
      <p>(Edit: Severely Revised below.)</p>
      <p>These turn a collection of songs into a unified work of 2h30. This is not someything you get in pop music at all. I don't know of any other musical that's written with such dense motifs, but I'm not really <em>that</em> knowledgeable about musicals. Star Wars does it. Wagner's Ring Cycle does it better - it has about a hundred different motifs.</p>
      <p>Do these have any good songs, as you request? Star Wars has the Imperial March, the Main Theme, and that's about it - though I've a soft spot for the Cantina Band I wouldn't call it a good song. So, maybe motif based works aren't really compatible with good songs, and that would be why there's basically no motif-based albums.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, there's "bleeding chunks" from The Ring which stand alone as legitimately great music (available on request - but it will get a standalone post...), but he's one of the greatest composers ever (top 5 at worst), and the Ring is the single greatest piece of art ever produced.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, to ask, as you did, whether any of the Hamilton songs are good is to ignore a major part of what makes Hamilton work as a musical.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>