<post>
  <author>Belisaurus_Rex</author>
  <date>2020-07-07T01:04:02Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fx5ql12/</link>
  <title>The History of The Bastille</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The Bastille. The very name inspired dread in the French population. This imposing fortress, near the center of Paris, was a visible reminder of Louis XVI’s tyranny. According to contemporary writers, it was a physical embodiment of everything wrong with the government. When the French Revolution began, the Bastille became a target of the revolutionaries—they knew that if they captured the Bastille, in one stroke they would have achieved a tremendous symbolic victory and would also capture the stores of weapons and gunpowder needed to arm their revolution. </p>
      <p>On July 14, 1789, the revolutionaries attacked the fortress. Bernard-Rene Jordan de Launay, the military governor of the Bastille, was besieged inside along with about 110 men. There were small skirmishes between the defenders and the revolutionaries, but de Launay knew he could not hold out for long because there was only a few days’ worth of supplies in the fortress. When the revolutionaries began hauling up cannons for a final assault, de Launay surrendered and lowered the drawbridge.</p>
      <p>Inside, the revolutionaries were shocked at what they found. This towering, dark fortress contained only seven prisoners (four forgers, one would-be regicide, one insane man who believed that he was Julius Caesar, and one aristocrat who was imprisoned by request from his family). The revolutionaries searched the Bastille for implements of torture, for skeletons chained to the walls, and for starving prisoners, but found none. Stories of torture, of squalid conditions, and of deprivation were mere fabrications. Had they come so far to set so few free? How could they have been so wrong about the terror of the Bastille? And yet, it was too far to go back—dozens of revolutionaries had already been killed in the fighting. Instead of backing down, the revolutionaries doubled down. They killed de Launay, placed his head on a pike, and paraded it throughout the city. Surrender had not brought him any mercy, and the revolution would continue down its bloody path. The revolutionaries continued to call the Bastille a place of horror where prisoners were left to rot.</p>
      <p>So how bad was the Bastille in truth? It was used as a place to house political prisoners, and these prisoners could be sentenced without a trial by a royal <em>lettres de cachet</em>. But these political prisoners were not treated harshly. They were given a stipend throughout their imprisonment that came out to more than the pay given to an average Parisian, and many prisoners were able to use their time productively. Voltaire, for example, wrote his first play while imprisoned. Furthermore, nobles would often obtain <em>lettres de cachet</em> to imprison their own family members without the public attention and embarrassment of a trial (such as the Comte de Solages, the aforementioned aristocrat). In short, it was not a horrible place to be. </p>
      <p>In the hundred years before the Bastille fell, it had held a total of 5,279 prisoners, many of them living comfortably. In the space of about one year, during the reign of terror, the Revolution arrested 300,000 people, guillotined over 17,000, and left 10,000 to die in their cells.</p>
      <p>In the French Revolution, not only were the offenses imagined, but the horrors perpetrated by the revolutionaries themselves dwarfed anything that the monarchy ever did. What can we take away from this example?</p>
      <p>I hesitate to say it, but the number of people shot by the police is not very large. While America’s numbers do not compare favorably to Europe in a relative sense, in an absolute sense, police brutality is not a problem in America. The Washington Post’s prize-winning police shooting <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/investigations/police-shootings-database/">database</a> records about 1000 shootings each year from 2015 to the present, and in only a tiny fraction of those was the person shot unarmed, and unarmed does not necessarily mean incapable of using lethal force. If you accept that armed criminals in the act of committing a crime need to be shot (perhaps necessitated by our higher percentage of gun ownership compared to European countries), then most of these shootings were necessary and not police brutality. It would not be unfair to characterize the nationwide protests at these handful of unconnected deaths (manslaughters and murders) as disproportionate. It is on the level of the French Revolutionaries tearing down the Bastille and executing the king when the Bastille contained only 7 prisoners, some of whom the Revolution itself would shortly reimprison. Coincidentally, in 2020 so far, the number of unarmed black men shot by the police is also 7. You probably know each one of their names. They all make front page news.</p>
      <p>I’m not here to harp on whether the increased deaths due to transmission of COVID-19 will outweigh the benefits of these protests (they won’t, even assuming a reduction of police shootings of unarmed men to zero, it will take decades before the lives saved outweigh the additional deaths due to COVID). I think that the prisoners in the Bastille were a justification, but what the revolutionaries really wanted was the weapons inside the fortress. Similarly, I believe that there are organizational leaders today who know that police brutality, in quantitative terms, is close to a non-issue (sure it’s intentional, but you’re more likely to be struck by lightning, eaten by a shark, etc.). Eliminating these deaths is their stated goal, but it is only a justification, not the actual purpose of the movement. The actual purpose is of course power for the leadership. I wouldn’t advocate for Louis XVI to have been so harsh that the revolutionaries feared to resist, but instead for him to defuse or deflate their justification by explaining to the masses that the revolutionary leaders were misleading them. How much public support would there have been for the Revolution if the masses had known what the Bastille really held?</p>
      <p>Why did I write this? I genuinely believe that most people do not know the true statistics, and that many would change their mind about contemporary issues if they did. In politically charged situations, it helps to guide your audience in gently, like the old myth about placing a frog in a pot of water and heating it so slowly that the frog does not realize it is being boiled alive. An audience who agrees that the justification for the French Revolution was flimsy might find themselves going along with you on other issues without the usual knee-jerk reactions.</p>
      <p>P.S. (Thought this was relevant even though it does not follow 1:1 the point I was making). Tsarist Russia had a reputation as the harshest monarchy in Europe. But how crushing exactly was it? How persecuted were the revolutionaries before 1917? Well, in the Gulag Archipelago, Solzhenitsyn uses Lenin as an example. Lenin’s brother attempted to assassinate Tsar Alexander III, and, uncontroversially, was executed for it. Attempted regicide is a hard crime to forgive. But what happened to Lenin, the brother of the attempted regicide? Far from being punished, he was admitted to the Imperial University at Kazan. Although he stirred up anti-government student protests, he was only punished by expulsion. Although he continued subversive correspondence with other Russian intelligentsia, his rights to communicate were never curtailed. When finally, Lenin was exiled to a remote village in Siberia. His exile was on his own honor, since he bought his train ticket out there himself and traveled as a free man, and once there, he asked for—and received—a stipend from the government that was overgenerous and allowed him to live very comfortably in the village. As Solzhenitsyn explains “He had no obligations, no work to do, no duties, nor did his womenfolk exert themselves; for two and a half rubles a month, a fifteen-year-old peasant girl did all the rough work around the house. Lenin had no need to write for money, turned down offers of paid work from Petersburg, and wrote only things which could bring him literary fame.” “[The Tsars] persecuted revolutionaries just sufficiently to broaden their circle of acquaintances in prisons, to toughen them, and ring their heads with haloes.”</p>
      <p>Where did this clemency get Tsar Nicholas II? It brought him to an early death as the Russian Revolution killed him and his family. The Soviet Union that took Tsarist Russia’s place would imprison at least 18 million in the Gulags (some give numbers closer to 50 million), a large fraction of which would perish (though more left the Gulags alive than died there). This was far worse than katorga, Tsarist Russia’s penal program which each year sentenced a few thousand convicts who had committed heinous crimes such as murder, robbery, or rape to Siberia for hard labor. Not only was the number of those passing through the Gulags orders of magnitude larger, but also, they had committed no crime.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>