<post>
  <author>ChevalMalFet</author>
  <date>2020-07-06T22:26:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hl3tgi/welcome_to_gettysburg_day_three/fx59npn/</link>
  <title>Differing Views in 1865 About What to Do With The South</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Short answer, yes. </p>
      <p>There was a very strong faction in the North that wanted the South reduced to total vassal status, for trials and executions of Confederate politicians, and generals, and a general <em>Carthago delenda est</em> attitude towards the whole affair. Understandable, given that the Civil War was the most destructive conflict in American history to that point. 650,000 dead from a prewar population of 31,000,000, or nearly 2% casualties. An equivalent war fought today would result in the deaths of 6,600,000 Americans, which would be the most devastating event in American history. Hundreds of millions of dollars of wealth was destroyed, from cities burned to railroads wrecked to vast reserves of cotton (one of the most valuable substances in the world in 1865) burned, to say nothing of the 4,000,000 slaves that were now free. The war was fought mostly in the South, so that helped keep the entire country from being devastated, but it took the South more than a century to recover from the war.</p>
      <p>So lots of radical Republicans and a few War Democrats like Vice President Andrew Johnson wanted revenge. Johnson hated blacks, loved poor Southern whites, and despised the rich planter class that started a war to defend slavery and exploit poor Southerners. He was for savage retaliation. Most minor Confederates were quickly pardoned, but the higherups were stripped of most wealth and civil rights for a few years and denied the same pardon.</p>
      <p>What made the difference was Lincoln. Lincoln was all for full reconciliation and a generous peace. He wanted peace (and Union) above all else, so as soon as the Southern states would lay down their arms and rejoin the Union he would welcome them with open arms. His second inaugural lays out his program:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>With malice toward none; with charity for all; with firmness in the right, as God gives us to see the right, let us strive on to finish the work we are in; to bind up the nation's wounds...</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Lincoln was assassinated, and Johnson led Reconstruction for 4 years, but Grant became President in 1868 in the first election following the war. Grant had always understood that being generous towards defeated enemies made them not your enemy anymore. He alone among <em>all</em> generals in the Civil War had not just defeated his enemies, but <em>destroyed</em> them - at Donelson, at Vicksburg, at Chattanooga, and at Appomattox Grant had ended campaigns with either the surrender or the total rout of the entire opposing army. In the 3 instances where the campaign ended in surrender, Grant let the men and officers return to their homes, rather than a prison camp, after signing a parole, with arms and horses. And instead of guerrillas, most men <em>did</em> go home until properly exchanged. </p>
      <p>Grant didn't like Lincoln at first - didn't vote for him - but after meeting him, and after his assassination, Grant became his protege, and vowed to carry on Lincoln's legacy. That meant generous, kind Reconstruction, and it was in his term that the defeated rebels were finally fully accepted back into the fold. However, the rebellious States were still occupied until they passed new constitutions and ratified the 13th Amendment banning slavery, and he was ruthless in defending the rights of freedman and in hunting down the new KKK (the first iteration of the KKK was more or less destroyed by Grant using federal troops in the South; the current version is a resurrected one from the 1910s cosplaying as the original Klan). </p>
      <p>That's all the detail I can really provide right now without doing any research, but I hope it answers your question!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>