<post>
  <author>ChrisPrattAlphaRaptr</author>
  <date>2020-07-09T04:07:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fxe130b/</link>
  <title>Tearing into the Inadequacies of Black Genetic Criminality Studies</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I've tried to stay agnostic on the HBD thing (or whatever you want to call it if we're talking about criminality rather than IQ) because I've barely read anything on the subject, and it's something I've literally never seen discussed in an academic setting. For what it's worth given the local opinion on 'experts' and degrees, I have a phd in a field adjacent to genetics, and my thesis lab focused on the intersection of that field with human genetics. My background in statistics is relatively weak compared to some folks here I would guess, my field generally calculates a p-value or ANOVA and calls it a day.</p>
      <p>The wikipedia article you're quoting from gives three articles in support of those statements: study <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2922855/">1</a>, study <a href="http://www.antoniocasella.eu/dnlaw/GUO_2008.pdf">2</a>, and study <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0191886912004047">3</a>. For study 3 you'll find to find an...alternative method to access it.</p>
      <p>Remarkably, <em>all three papers referenced for this section use the same dataset.</em> Even more remarkably, study 1 and study 2 (by the same authors) use the exact same data to do the exact same analysis, but study 2 has a few additional genes thrown in as well as many more dimensions to the regression analysis. Both only have 11 (and 10 later on, as one 2R individual dropped out for wave II and wave III) individuals with the 2R allele. </p>
      <p>The dataset is what they call the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Health (Add Health), funded by the NIH. It's an analysis of 20,000 teenagers, with 3,000 twins - either monozygotic (MZ, what you call paternal, very very high genetic identity) or dizygotic (DZ, what you call maternal). The teenagers provide DNA for genotyping purposes, and answer questionnaires at 3 periods in their lives, which is what the authors refer to as Wave I, II and III. There's a 12 question survey given for propensity to violence/delinquency as they frame it, and then the answers to the questionnaire are tested for associations to the various alleles of MAOA. I can go into more detail about the genetic polymorphisms if people are having trouble understanding. The authors use a subset of 2524 samples from this larger dataset.</p>
      <p>The 2R variant you're referencing refers to a 30bp repeat present in the promoter region of the MAOA gene, while the 3R/4R variants have 3 and 4 repeats respectively. These are thought to influence levels of MAOA expression, although I haven't dug into that literature to see the evidence for it beyond the luciferase assay in study 1 which is pretty reasonable at face value. In their sample of 2524 individuals, <strong>11 Black males</strong> had the 2R allele. The authors could not compare to white subjects because there were too few. So, they compare these 11 individuals to 508 individuals with the 3R or 5R alleles. and find the mean delinquency scores (just the scores from their questionnaire) to be 5.6 versus 2.3, or twice as high with the 2R allele. But, their respective standard deviations were <strong>9.05 and 4.27</strong> respectively, which is <strong>absolutely atrocious</strong>. The difference is absolutely not even close to being statistically significant.</p>
      <p>They next build a regression model to correct for age and ethnicity of participants. It's harder for me to evaluate considering I don't know what data they actually plugged into the analysis or a plot to look at, but they claim statistical significance after adjusting for age and race of their 11 individuals with the 2R allele. I don't know how this is possible, but maybe someone with more statistical knowledge can chime in.</p>
      <p>It's getting very late for me, so I will summarize the other two studies very rapidly and make a brief closing note I think is important. The second study includes the same 11 individuals (in what I'm sure was an oversight, the authors just left the standard deviation out for their delinquency table (table 2)), but significantly more dimensions for their regression analysis. The third study doesn't detail the statistical model/analyses they're doing as far as I can tell, which makes it very difficult for me to assess. They look at 4 additional measures (psychopathy scale, arrest, incarceration and antisocial phenotype index), and claim to see a significant association of the 2R allele with the last 3. </p>
      <p>Based on their data (of 11 subjects!) they claim that the 2R allele increases the odds of black men being incarcerated by ~3x. So best case scenario, 5% of the Black population has a 3x increased risk of being incarcerated <em>relative to their peers.</em> Note that the allele is too rare to compare it to white people with the same allele, but let's pretend it's just a flat 3x across the board independent of race. Not an expert, but based <a href="https://bjs.gov/content/pub/pdf/Llgsfp.pdf">on this</a> it looks like a 3x increase in incarceration rates for Black individuals across the board. So you've explained 5% of the difference between white and Black Americans. </p>
      <p>Let me hop on a soapbox about genome association studies for a second. We use these studies for complex traits, of which criminality is most definitely one. Here's <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-13690-5">one of our best</a> for Heart Disease (HD). This study has nearly <strong>50,000 cases and 930,000 controls</strong>. Moreover, they estimate the heritability of HD at 26%, and can still only explain a fraction of the heritability of this disease. The unexplained heritability of complex traits is a major outstanding question in human genetics, and I'm sure even if you find estimates of the heritability of criminality extremely highly powered association studies would still only explain a fraction of that. </p>
      <p>I got kind of jargony and ran out steam as I'm getting really tired. Feel free to ask questions, or if I just happened across three shitty wikipedia papers, send me others.</p>
      <p>edit: I should also say the comparison with the GWAS paper is slightly unfair as a monogenic association study obviously needs less power than genome-wide, but 11 cases is still absurdly low.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>