<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-07-06T16:30:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fx42bhz/</link>
  <title>Does Therapy Work?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>In <a href="/u/SayingAndUnsaying">u/SayingAndUnsaying</a>'s <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/hkesjh/le_bon_motte/">excellent post about the Motte's future</a>, it's suggested that we make a greater effort in the community to do big picture exploratory posts to help people refine ideas rather than push an agenda. With that in mind, here's an issue that I'd really like the sub's thoughts and citations on.</p>
      <p>In short, I want to know <strong>if therapy works</strong>. A bit more specifically, I'm interested in (i) which therapies if any are actually effective, (ii) who therapy really helps and to what extent, (iii) the extent to which therapy offers reasonable 'value for money' in terms of QALYs as a public healthcare product, and (iv) whether it's under- or over-prescribed in these terms in the US.</p>
      <p>I'm genuinely open to changing my view on this, but right now, I'm pretty skeptical of the efficacy of therapy; at the very least, I think its capacity to help people is likely wildly overstated, for the following reasons -</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(1) It's a convenient pseudosolution to impossible problem.</strong> When things are going badly for you, or you have a really tough problem or you're distraught, a Christian will tell you to try praying, a /f/itizen will tell you to lift moar, a suburban soccer mom will tell you to try yoga, and most urbane secular young people will tell you to see a therapist. The human brain is basically a problem solving device, and when it runs into a problem that it can't solve, it's immensely stressful. This is true both in our own case and when we're dealing with others. When I'm chatting with my parents about some issue that I'm having, they immediately go into problem-solving mode, and while this can sometimes be helpful, sometimes it's simply not a problem that's easy to fix, and it makes them immensely stressed out when I explain that there are no easy answers. Likewise, one of the most painful realisations that can occur when you've been trying to help someone in trouble (with drugs, an eating disorder, a history of abusive relationships) is that having tried all other options <em>there is nothing left that anyone can do</em>. I think we encounter situations like this a lot, but as long as therapy is an option, it's very easy to stay in problem-solving mode forever. Someone keeps getting fired from their job for behavioral issues? See a therapist. You're already seeing a therapist? Try a different one. This way, we can indefinitely avoid having to grapple with the possibility of problems beyond the ability of human agency to solve</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(2) Mutability bias.</strong> This is related to (1), but I think a lot of people - especially younger people and progressives - have a vision of human nature according to which our behaviour is profoundly mutable. If your relationship is in jeopardy, try couple's counselling. If someone's a racist, they just need debiasing. If someone has anger issues, they need anger management. If someone is a violent criminal, they need empathy and understanding to help them break out of the cycle of violence. This is why <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rat_Park">Rat Park</a> was such a huge hit with academics and the broader public: it suggests that drug addiction isn't a function of the fact that the human brain is a chaotic biochemical system susceptible to <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Wireheading">wireheading</a>, but rather a function of a mindset emerging from social neglect and poverty - in other words, <em>fixable problems.</em> A large part of my social and intellectual development over the last decade has been seeing this plastic view of human nature collapse. Learning about, e.g., the <a href="https://archive.is/jnWNE">relative inefficacy of most drug and alcohol addiction programs</a>, the <a href="https://archive.is/BLDVV">relatively small impact of shared environment and the large impact of heritable factors on behaviour</a>, the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/02/health/biggest-loser-weight-loss.html">pisspoor record of most nutritional interventions in actually changing people's long-term BMI</a> - all of this has made me much more fatalistic. It's not a happy realisation, and it's certainly not a politically trendy one. But insofar as a lot of the injunctions to try therapy implicitly lean on the assumption of mutability, it suggests another reason why we might overestimate the ability of therapy to actually achieve serious positive impacts.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(3) Hard to measure efficacy.</strong> How could we tell if therapy was effective or not? Obviously there's a copious amount of data on this, of which I've already seen quite a lot, both from my own research and from Scott's many posts on the issue, and I'm eager to see the best studies that people want to suggest. But my priors on the average study in this domain being well designed are pretty low - I know from my own line of work that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Replication_crisis#In_psychology">most studies in psychology are a complete mess</a>, and I think <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/medical-nihilism-9780198747048?cc=gb&amp;lang=en&amp;">there's at least some reasons to think that a huge swathe of modern medical research is misleading</a>. Of course, most competent people running studies know about issues like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regression_toward_the_mean">regression to the mean</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Placebo#Effects">placebo effects</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demand_characteristics">demand characteristics</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawthorne_effect">the Hawthorne effect</a>, and so on, but actually controlling for this stuff is incredibly hard. I guess a more fundamental issue that I have is that I think humans are really bad judges of our own well-being. Someone who's on a diet can believe it's going brilliantly until the moment they step on the scales - but in positive psychology, we don't really have any uncontroversial equivalent of a weighing scale. Mostly what we have is subjective measures like random spot-checks ("how are you feeling right now?"), electronic diaries, life satisfaction questionnaires, and so on. "But doglatine, surely there's a difference here? Weight is an objective measurement, but happiness is just a matter of how people feel. Isn't that something we can reliably ascertain by just asking them?" I don't know about that. There have been times in my life where I sincerely believed things were going great but in retrospect I was deeply unhappy, though I didn't realise it at the time. Likewise, there have been times when I've been acting curmudgeonly and cynical, but in retrospect was really thriving, something I realised only months or years down the line. So insofar as well-being is something I care about, I don't think it's something we have some kind of guaranteed subjective epistemological access to. This is related to a persistent bugbear of mine, namely that I <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fw4y16v?context=3">think our knowledge of our own minds is terrible and we massively underestimate the extent to which we're routinely in error about our emotions and our attitudes</a>. Add to this the fact that I've frequently seen friends announce "breakthroughs" in therapy, only to witness them continue to be just as self-destructive, unhappy, and otherwise fucked-up as ever.</p>
      <p>Finally, I'll add that I have tried therapy once myself (I got some free sessions during grad school) and I found it quite pleasant: getting to sit and talk purely about myself for an hour with a highly trained professional was quite fun, especially given that I'm a mild narcissist. I even felt at the time that it was making me a better person, but in retrospect I think that was just a temporarily constructive story I was telling myself. But as I say, this was free - would I have thought it worthwhile to pay $100/hour for the privilege? Only if I earned ten times what I do currently. Likewise, given the number of people in need of life-saving medical treatments out there, I wouldn't have expected the state to pay even half that much on my behalf just so I could sit on a comfy couch and speculate about where my sexual fantasies came from. And then I look around at some of my friends who've been seeing therapists weekly for a decade or more and I think, fuck, at least some of this may be a huge waste of money.</p>
      <p>But as I say, this is a genuine CMV post - I'd be very interested to hear more evidence on the issue, especially evidence that engages with priors like those I've listed above!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>