<post>
  <author>long-walk-short-pier</author>
  <date>2020-07-07T23:46:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fx9ddy8/</link>
  <title>Little Interminable Indiginities</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Here's my perspective (right of Republicans) :</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Reid">Richard Reid</a> tried to light his shoes on fire on a flight in December 2001. Nineteen years later, we still remove our shoes before every flight. Is the threat of shoe bombs so great that this practice is a sensible precaution? There's almost consensus that this and much of what the TSA does is theater, but hey, it's a minor inconvenience, you say, just suck it up. Besides it's basically a job's program, so it and it's busy work will never leave us - it's original intent is irrelevant now. Our experience with little, interminable indignities inform my own perspective on masks. </p>
      <p>Now, this may seem like a reach, but the point is if masks are mandated to be worn as a preventative measure against a threat, what is the criteria for the mask requirement to drop? When the threat becomes zero? Realistically when does that happen? Those who advocate for mask relaxation will be hit with the 'just suck it up it's a minor inconvenience.' and the same way flying changed post 9/11, grocery shopping will too. Again, this may sound hyperbolic but when do you think you'll be able to go into a big name grocer and not wear a required mask? I mean, flu comes around every winter, wouldn't it be sound to demand masks at certain times of year? Why not all of them? Mission creep is assured. The new 'normal' means this is just how it is now, tough shit. Once rules are in place, they are very sticky and hard to remove. I fear this will continue far beyond necessity and then be persistent because they'll find a new justification. </p>
      <p>Maybe I'm wrong - after all, everyone goes to the grocery store (or out in public period) far more frequently than most people fly, so the groundswell for mask getting removed will be louder - but I have my doubts. </p>
      <p>Perhaps this stance is pure selfishness, but the people who are almost assuredly not living the downsides of it's continued practice. It's antisocial, increases the cover for opportunistic crime, and frankly contributes to the already rampant anomie of modern society. I absolutely loathe the mask-as-a-virtue crowd so I'm actually glad it's getting significant pushback. </p>
      <p>Now, having said all that, I currently abide by the prescribed mask rules, because I know I'd fly off the handle at a stranger who had the temerity to say something to me if I was not wearing one. Over the past weekend I went to several restaurants - in the car, no mask, arrive in a parking lot, put the mask on for five minutes as you approach the host, get seated, mask off. It's theater.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>