<post>
  <author>roystgnr</author>
  <date>2020-07-07T18:57:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fx8eovy/</link>
  <title>Cultural Appropriations as Trademark Infringement</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Don't think of cultural appropriation as copyright infringement, think of it as trademark infringement.  When an aspect of someone's culture gets appropriated, it's not likely to be a carefully preserved copy of the original, it's going to be changed.  The details of the change can be completely different depending on context: maybe it'll be made cheaper to mass-produce or upscaled to be more fashionable; maybe what's unique about it will be diminished to better suit a new audience's tastes or be exaggerated to seem more exotic.  But <em>something</em> about the original won't be perfectly suited to making it popular in its new environment, and so whoever changes those things will have the most popular new version.</p>
      <p>And perhaps they will call their new version "fusion" or some other rebranding that makes it clearly distinct from the one you knew and loved, but what if they don't?  Trademark lawyers turned "Peppo" into "Mr. Pibb", but your culture's names probably don't have a trademark attached, and in cases where they do those names are probably owned by the highest bidder, not shared by the culture's current fans.</p>
      <p>So this new version of your culture still has your names attached, and has been changed to make it more popular ... so eventually it is more popular, and your version is an afterthought.  Even in the best case, for the rest of your life you get to explain that no, that thing everybody knows by X isn't <em>your</em> X, it's a knockoff.  Perhaps New X siphons off people who would otherwise have become fans of X, and now your culture is dying.  Perhaps New X gains a bad reputation and that spills over on you.  Whatever happens, you're out of the loop for it.</p>
      <p>The phrase "cultural appropriation" has connotations of centuries-old ethnic traditions, but you can see it in geek culture too.  Does "Star Trek" evoke thoughts of diplomats negotiating a brokered peace, or lots of stuff blowing up to a Beastie Boys tune?  Are "Starship Troopers" an exemplar of how people can learn to volunteer their lives to protect humanity and make peace among aliens, or a bunch of cannon fodder who got tricked by Nazi Doogie Howser?  Cultural appropriation is the mechanism by which "popularity causes death" when you mix <a href="https://meaningness.com/geeks-mops-sociopaths">geeks, MOPs, and sociopaths</a>.</p>
      <p>You can see it in politics.  Iowahawk's classic description of entryism, "1. Identify a respected institution. 2. kill it. 3. gut it. 4. wear its carcass as a skin suit, while demanding respect.", is a form of cultural appropriation in this sense.  Woke people don't start the Woke Scouts, they try to make existing Scouts become woke, because they know cultural appropriation works.  Trump didn't start a third party, he turned the Republican party and conservatism into referenda on and apologetics for Trumpism.  </p>
      <p>I'm not sure all this counts as an "against" position, because I'm not convinced any of this outweighs the <em>benefits</em> of cultural appropriation, but hopefully it at least elicits more sympathy for the targets.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>