<post>
  <author>thirdtimesthecharm</author>
  <date>2020-07-08T13:01:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hn6gbx/the_reason_it_pays_off_to_entertain_weird_beliefs/fxb4hyx/</link>
  <title>Living On A Narrowboat</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I've been living aboard what's called a project boat (very much unloved for years)
Here's a few off the top of my head.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Pros</strong>
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>Slower pace of life. I spent my time as I see fit.</li>
        <li>Beautiful countryside, canalside pubs</li>
        <li>Cheaper way to live (I get by on a few hours of online tuition a week)</li>
        <li>I've learnt a great deal of DIY. Two weeks ago I rewired my 1970s engine and control panel.</li>
        <li>You own your home. I cannot stress how wonderful it is to be able to live like a human being. I've never had a great experience renting in the UK. I can decorate and get nicer furniture than ikeas budget range.</li>
        <li>Low cost of entry. A 30ft NB can be got for 15 to 20 thousand. A yoghurt pot is cheaper. Certainly possible on 5 k. I'd recommend looking into buying a ex-lifeboat if you're after space and low price. Mine was 22 k for a 45ft (14 m) NB.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <strong>Cons</strong>
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>You can get only get one or two out of available, competent or cheap when it comes to marine engineers of all flavours.</li>
        <li>Things break, leak or burn with a regularity that used to worry me.</li>
        <li>You need to empty your own loo. Everything you bring in you'll need to bring out.</li>
        <li>You're essentially living in the UK's only shanty town. It's certainly going to make an interesting book in a few decades times (a la the hippies who squatted in empty East Berlin homes at the end of the cold war) but that does mean crime and danger are more common. Theft and muggings are the most common. This does depend on where you are. Most places are fine. Most places in central London are not.</li>
        <li>Safety standards are essentially optional on the water. Just get a corrupt examiner to sign of the boat safety certificate (BSS) every few years. The fact you have to choose to ethical about this definitely worries me.</li>
        <li>It does feel like it's a secret way of living that one day probably far too soon will be killed off. There's only about 5,000 boats doing what we do in the whole country. A large portion of those are in London.</li>
        <li>The canals and rivers were given to a brand new organisation (Canal and river trust) a few years back. Nice enough people but not competent and certainly not in favour of boaters. Costs are soaring as CRT seeks to turn a public resource into jobs for the boys rather than doing actual maintenance. There's signs of damage everywhere.</li>
        <li>Locks are dangerous. Boating is dangerous. I've got new scars since starting this.</li>
        <li>In winter if you cannot keep your stove lit and you come back after a few days your home is essentially a floating caravan/shed. It is damp and exceedingly cold. However if you can keep your fire on,  winter is my favourite time of the year.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>I'm sure there's plenty more, feel free to ask me anything.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>