<post>
  <author>4570_throwaway</author>
  <date>2020-11-28T06:24:16Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jzbis2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_23/gducmqt/</link>
  <title>The Incomparable Joy of Child-Rearing</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>tl;dr: do any of you have children? Did you try to think rationally about the decision to have children? Do you think you made the right choice?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Yes, yes, and yes.  </p>
      <p>I grew up the eldest brother of four.  My youngest sister was born when I was 14.  My siblings and I grew up helping take care of her, bathing, feeding solid food, diapers, etc.  The only thing I didn't do was calm her at night.  I didn't realize how much this had affected me until I had to show my wife how to properly hold, bathe, and change our firstborn--she was wondering how I knew how to do all that stuff as a dude in my mind 20s.  Helping raise my sister left me under no illusions that having kids was easy or fun, but it also dispelled the illusion that it was nothing but a boring grind.  Even as a moody teen it was fun to roughhouse with a toddler or blow her mind with some trivial slight of hand.  Her happiness was infectious and brightened the entire household at a time when the three other siblings were hormonal teenagers and my parents were going through a divorce.  </p>
      <p>I don't have much to add to this thread, but I do want to emphasize a few things other have already said:  </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <strong>It's an incomparable experience and emotion</strong> - you will indeed discover whole new categories of love and joy, the likes of which you've never experienced and can't even approach otherwise</li>
        <li>
          <strong>It's exhausting and all-consuming, but worth it</strong> --  I like the exercise analogy someone else used -- the hours you spend at the gym may not be fun, but man, when you are the most ripped dude at the pool, or you hit a new PR, or you score that goal, it makes all the blood sweat and tears worth it.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Most people don't/can't do anything meaningful with their time</strong> -- Controversial opinion time! Unless you're in Doctors without Borders vaccinating kids in the third world or have a calling to the priesthood, the extra time you have is probably going to be pissed away on frivolous nonsense. Not just TV and video games, but IMO even building a career, picking up girls, making a bunch of money to buy cool shit, traveling to dozens of foreign countries, writing a substack blog for culture war nerds... none of them will provide the same satisfaction for the craving of purpose for which so many people, at root, engage the aforementioned activities.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>It's a huge investment, so have multiple kids</strong> -- someone said something like this offhand in one of the replies and they're dead right IMO.  Having kids is definitely an "in for a penny, in for a pound" affair.  I really don't get people who want only 1 or 2 -- if you're going to completely and irreversibly alter your life, why not go all in?  We currently expecting our third, and its really not that bad.  Going from 0 to 1 was an infinite difference, but going from 1 to 2 is maybe 20% more work (they eat the same food, wear the aame clothes, etc etc).  I've heard number of kids vs parenting effort increases logarithmically until the eldest kid is around 9 or 10, by which time if actually starts to decrease as you can enlist them for doing chores (actually, I've already got my 4 yr old picking up her room, clearing her own dishes, taking off and throwing away her overnight pull-up, etc so it doesn't even take that long)</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Most young people don't know what it's like to be old and alone</strong> -- Here's controversial opinion number two. When I was 13, if someone had asked me what I would do if I were 25, I probably would've said something about owning the latest consoles, eating as much junk food as I wanted, and (maybe I wouldn't have admitted this) watching as much pornography as possible.  If someone asked me at 20 what I would do if I were 35 and had a stable career and a bunch of savings, I probably would've said something about buying a badass car, a sick bachelor pad, hooking up with hot girls, and definitely not being married with children and living in suburbia.  As we gain life experience and our bodies age and novelties wear off, what we want out of life changes.  For some reason people seem to think that this process of development slows or stops after age 25 or 30, but my experience dealing with the middle aged and elderly members of my family have shown otherwise.  Being alone and lonely at ages 12, 22, 42, and 62 are not identical experiences.  The experiences in life from which you can derive pleasure seem to diminish both in number and intensity as time goes by.  Careers lose their savor, possessions become deadweight, physical attractiveness gives way to wrinkles and soft muscles.  Family doesn't, though.  Think about happy many grandparents are to see their grandkids.  I can't think of many other things that draw out as much joy in the elderly.  And one day, God willing, we'll all be elderly. </li>
      </ol>
      <p>EDIT: terrible grammar and missing words</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>