<post>
  <author>Catbyself</author>
  <date>2020-11-30T15:15:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k3pgku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_30/ge5jr38/</link>
  <title>Imagining a Rationalist Hellscape</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Well..... this is exactly the modern worlds problem.</p>
      <p>No one agrees on the basics. They know just enough rationality and science to be able to destroy their opponents worldview as being based on fiction but lack the self discipline to also destroy their own for the same reason.</p>
      <p>Can you imagine what a genuine rationalist/empircalist reaction to Idpol would entail?</p>
      <p>It would be a complete disaster socially. Fat? Stop that it's a health risk. Black? x % more likely to commit a crime we had better monitor you more harshly than everyone else as a precaution. Low IQ white working class? Literally worth less to the world than high IQ asians and Jews, we know, we measured it in dollars -  be grateful for what your betters let you have. Take your oxy and listen to Springsteen, your jobs aren't coming back.</p>
      <p>Single parent? You suck, it's hurting your kids. Check the stats. Do you like recreational drugs? Moron. Stop doing them. Want to sleep around? Destroying your own mental health and future. Think you've married the wrong person and want a divorce? You have bad judgement and no consistency and are therefore to be shunned socially. Also we are going to tax you more for any of the above because it costs us a fortune cleaning all the secondary effects up.</p>
      <p>You are a nationalist? Maps aren't territories bub. Religious? No son, god is dead and your books are nonsense. We know, we tested. Lesbian/gay/trans - you know you are just making a reification error, right? Sex is an activity not an identity. </p>
      <p>And we could do this for pretty much everything. This may we why rationalists are this tiny community that can only exist due to the internet....</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>