<post>
  <author>crazycattime</author>
  <date>2020-11-27T21:49:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jzbis2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_23/gdt0jb3/</link>
  <title>Lawyering and Bizarre Errors: All Part of the Show</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I can't imagine how any lawyer would showcase a sloppy product like this</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Wholly unrelated to the particular case at hand, this sentiment is a function of your time as a lawyer.  I went through something like this around three years after starting practice.  I think that in the beginning, I was too new to understand what was good and bad lawyering and the bulk of my mental energy was split between "don't fuck up" and trying to figure out what was going on.  In other words, the time between law school graduation / bar admittance and actually getting trained up as a lawyer, working on live cases, is terrifying, stressful, and nightmare fodder for impostor syndrome.  </p>
      <p>But once you have a modicum of competence and experience, the illusion that everyone (but you) is a highly-skilled, whip-smart, legal eagle starts to slip.  At that point, you begin to notice the cracks in everything.  Some lawyers, consistently but not always, turn out work that is truly superb.  Most lawyers turn out work that is adequate and "not malpractice."  As you are by now aware, a ton of legal work is yeoman's work--building an economy-class chair for sitting in, not for display in the Louvre.  </p>
      <p>Over time, I have run into colleagues who have presented work that should earn a C- when compared to the platonic ideal of good lawyering.  Their clients loved them.  The better you are at legal analysis and writing the more this will grate on your nerves.  I have had clients choose the dumbest of several options, forgoing the prize stallion in favor of putting a really pretty ribbon on a mule.  As an artisan, that sucks.  As someone with a mortgage, that's what pays the bills.  </p>
      <p>And at the end of the day, we're not artists.  Our work is judged by two wholly separate metrics: professional standards and client satisfaction.  The Greatest Brief in History won't get filed if the client doesn't like it.  What the client actually wants you to file will almost never pass muster at a professional responsibility review board or malpractice defense hearing.  The lawyers who stay in business know how to produce work that 1) makes the client very happy; 2) meets the bare minimum of professional standards; and 3) doesn't cost more to produce than the attorney's fees.   The most successful lawyers know how to do all that and win their cases more often than not.  </p>
      <p>Turning back to Sidney Powell, you write:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I believe she's just working backwards from "What relief would flip Georgia in favor of Trump?" instead of actually following where the evidence takes her.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Well, yeah.  In terms of her public-facing comments and court filings, that's exactly what she's doing.  Looking at the evidence objectively is something you do behind closed doors and heavily papered-over with "attorney work product" and other privilege markings.  If you're smart, you do that as part of the process of deciding whether to take the case.  That is, you listen to what the client wants to achieve (e.g., get my medical bills paid off) and look at what evidence they have (or you think you can get) to determine whether there is any chance of success.  Federal Rule 11 makes this an ethical requirement if you actually file suit, but it's also mandatory if you want to stay in business.  </p>
      <p>After you take the case, you've made your bet and you play the best hand you can with the cards you're dealt.  It's good practice to acknowledge and head off your opponents strongest or most-likely arguments, sure.  It's terrible practice to make those arguments for them.  "Following where the evidence takes you" is the job of the fact-finder/trial court.  "Leading the court through the evidence to the conclusion you want" is exactly what each side is supposed to be doing as zealous advocates for their clients.  </p>
      <p>I can't be sure from your post, but it sounds like you do at least a little litigation and actual trial work.  As best I can tell, anyone involved in litigation will run into an obnoxious opposing counsel within their first three cases.  The drama queens alleging with a straight face that a fifteen minute delay in receiving an email was a "catastrophic" highly-prejudicial injustice.  The outraged crusader arguing that your client's outrageous practices caused an outrageous injustice to be visited on their saintly, outraged victim/client.  The deposition character actor who prefaces every question with "As someone who has intimate and deep knowledge of EvilCorp's daily business practices, were you aware that. . ."  </p>
      <p>In short, you have by now observed a portion of the (ethically questionable) performative aspect of lawyering.  Some lawyers will pound the table even when they have the facts or the law on their side.  Some have mastered the passive-aggressive, pretend-to-show-your-belly style of appearing harried and overworked but good-hearted and trying-their-best.  One lawful evil tactic is to deliberately include plainly incorrect (but not misleading!) sections of a brief in order to justify asking for leave to amend, thereby gaining more time to prepare a proper response.  It's lawful lazy cousin is assuming leave to amend will be granted and just getting something on file in order to meet a deadline.  (Neutral lazy is knowing exactly how long it takes to drive to the 24-hour post office to get that day's postmark.)  </p>
      <p>At the highest level, these personalities develop more complex tactics.  You've seen the TV-trope tier prejudicial-question -&gt; objection -&gt; withdrawn cycle.  You've probably also seen the overbroad-complaint -&gt; answer -&gt; amendment cycle, too.  I see a 50/50 chance in this "Kraken" filing a performative retention of all those typographical errors as a strategic move.  Force the judge's brain to focus on reading around the spelling errors and it's that much easier to slip some shaky logic past him.  Assuming the chance to amend, you can fix the typos at the same time you cull any losing claims.  Sidney Powell didn't get to where she is by filing something like this on accident.  She may not be able to put together a top-tier complaint, but she would at least be able to get to something the client likes and is adequate and not-malpractice.  Errors even the client can spot aren't likely to be left in by accident.  </p>
      <p>tl;dr: At Powell's level, it's not unreasonable to assume that all of this, including the very strange typos, are intentional and part of the show.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>