<post>
  <author>iprayiam2</author>
  <date>2020-11-26T14:48:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jzbis2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_23/gdo0asc/</link>
  <title>Examining Bigotry and Kindness</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The thing is, she is a genuinely nice person. She works as a teacher, and has always treated people equally, regardless of race.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is really hard to accept at face value, just because you throw it in. I live in the American deep south, Im red tribe enough that folks dont hold back around me, and Ive never encountered a racist with as pervasive and uniformly negative views about another group of people as you described in your sister.</p>
      <p>You have to either be exaggerating about her hostile views or her genuinely treating people equally regardless of all that contempt. I have encountered no evidence in my life that folks can hold such emotionally contradictory capacity. Loving your neighbor and treating your neighbor well covary.</p>
      <p>If, on the other hand, I am wrong and she has no problem feeling this way but treating everyone equally, then why are we worried about racism at all? Why cant we apply that charity back to KKK and Nazi caracatures and assume they have the good will and capacity to treat everyone well despite their bigoted hostile views? And if they dont act kindly, why assume it is <em>because</em> of those views?</p>
      <p>Look I respect your post and your honestly and your love for your sister. In reality, I suspect you are exaggerating a bit on both sides. But I think this kind of bigotry apologetics from leftists who want to distance themselves from idPol, while defending the integrity of their idPol co-travelers is just as bad if not worse than the same thing coming from the right because it actually has institutional license. </p>
      <p>Imagine your post in reverse. What if Johhny Southern says:</p>
      <p>
        <em>"I'm white but my family has never owned slaves and we emigrated to America post-Civil Rights era. I am as far from leftwing as possible, but Im NOT a racist. But my brother is a straight white supremacists. He thinks all black people are lazy with no exceptions, and any black person who has succeeded got there through handouts and white support, NOT through any merit of their own. But my brother is a really nice guy! And he treats all people equally!!"</em>
      </p>
      <p>Do you believe that about his brother? Do you believe thay Johnny is not enabling racism through his brotherly apologetics? And if yes, and yes, help me understand who the <em>actual</em> racists are who actually act on their bigotry, if not Johnny's brother?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>