<post>
  <author>mangosail</author>
  <date>2020-11-27T12:48:47Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jzbis2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_23/gdre4ql/</link>
  <title>Voting Fraud Claims and Gish Gallops: When “Judge the Contents, Not the Wrapper” Falls Short</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think that while you and others making this point are intellectually correct (i.e. “judge the contents, not the wrapper”) I think you might consider that the above poster is actually using a good heuristic which will prove out well. The document appears to be put together by someone who is sloppy and insane. That doesn’t guarantee it’s wrong! But personally, I myself would struggle to read a legal document and judge its legal merit. There is probably a lot in a legal document that would look weird to me, a layman, and yet be legally clever or justified. A blog post or a Reddit comment, sure, tee me off. But for me, the only thing that I can judge this document based on is (1) in the short term, analyses from smart lawyers which I can engage with, and then (2) in the long term, the treatment in the courts.</p>
      <p>You’re right that a useful legal analysis from a lawyer might lay out the claims and soberly explain whether they have merit and whether they’re argued well. While I’m waiting for this though, my heuristic that sloppy writing, missing evidence, redacted witnesses, and etc. appear to suggest that Biden doesn’t have much to worry about here. They are certainly the standard I would judge the veracity and intellectual consistency of a Reddit comment or blog post by, and that’s closer to my own expertise.</p>
      <p>Beyond this heuristic as well I am feeling a little fatigue with the raw volume of low quality allegations. I feel like the specific allegations from 2 weeks ago have all but completely disappeared and been replaced by new allegations. There’s a bit of a reducto ad absurdium happening here - I want to take meaningful allegations seriously and engage with people on the merits, assuming good faith. But I’m feeling a little worn down by the pace of low quality stuff here - we had <a href="https://www.gl-li.com/2020/11/11/benford-s-law-and-census-data/">Benford’s law</a> not pan out and get memory-holed, we had <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/election-us-2020-54874120">dead voters</a> in Michigan not pan out, we had the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2020/11/05/video-claiming-detroit-ballot-fraud-debunked/">ballot van</a> that turned out to be a camera van, we had <a href="https://www.azcentral.com/story/news/politics/elections/2020/11/11/sharpiegate-could-arizona-election-officials-have-prevented-it/6229217002/">Sharpie-gate</a>, we had <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/uk-factcheck-wisconsin-more-votes-regist-idUSKBN27K2WU">Milwaukee’s suspiciously high turnout</a> which turned out to just be using the wrong denominator, we had the accusations that Georgia had a lower rate of ballot rejections this year when it turned out <a href="https://sos.ga.gov/index.php/elections/number_of_absentee_ballots_rejected_for_signature_issues_in_the_2020_election_increased_350_from_2018">the opposite was the case</a>, and the confusion came from comparing this year’s signature rejections to last election’s signature + late arriving rejections, we had the alleged video of the guy submitting fake ballots <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/factcheck/2020/11/06/fact-check-video-shows-pennsylvania-poll-workers-fixing-damaged-ballots/6185589002/">even though he was just duplicating them for the machine</a>. Maybe I’ll come back to this later and add some more, or others can add more below. These were core mainstream theories, brought up by key members of the President’s team in public or in court (and most of which were discussed here as well, maybe with the exception of Sharpiegate).</p>
      <p>To come back again with a 100 page report with a new set of accusations, one made by someone recently fired from the President’s team and seemingly without much attention to detail, and to ask for a good faith, detailed response to the content without using any heuristics - this is actually a bit of a frustrating ask. It certainly is starting to feel more and more like the expectation of good faith is a bit one sided. Although it’s certainly reasonable to say “engage with the best form of Powell’s argument and don’t get distracted by the wrapper it comes in,” I feel like it’s equally reasonable to say “we just did this a bunch of times, and this set of accusations seems to have even less care put into them than the previous ones, so do we really need to do this again?”</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>