<post>
  <author>Shakesneer</author>
  <date>2020-11-30T18:32:57Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k3pgku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_30/ge67yjr/</link>
  <title>Election Fraud Allegations: What Trump Supporters Are Thinking</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <blockquote>
          <p>The contrast to 2020 is striking. Kerry put country over party and personal interest. Trump has not. Instead, the President has refused to concede and party officials (encouraged and magnified by online grifters and media personalities) have stoked and spread bogus election fraud claims and pretended as if there is a way to overturn the election results in court.</p>
        </blockquote>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Well, since you asked what Trump supporters are thinking...</p>
      <p>Personally, I get tired of every legal maneuver becoming a headline and thus an opportunity to examine What President Trump and His Supporters Are Doing to America. (It's highly revealing, on a number of levels, that more attention is still paid to Trump's tweets than Joe Biden.) It puts me in the mind of the breathless TV news stock coverage: "Its 9 o'clock and the Dow Jones Industrial Market is down 5 points, signaling what might be the beginning of a day of losses in wake of the news that..." Yes, and tomorrow it may be up 5 points. Are we really out of things to discuss that we are back to augury and reading entrails?</p>
      <p>Because from what I have quoted above it is clear to me that the author -- and thus you in your response -- are missing the forest for the trees.</p>
      <p>The issue is framed as though Trump "refuses to concede," is trying to "overturn the election," and the only people "enabling" this "assault" are Trump's supporters who believe in "bogus" or "debunked" claims. Do I need to explain why, as a Trump supporter, I don't accept this frame at all? Do I need to explain that I am not sitting here fingers-in-ears head-in-sand crying "lalalalala fake news truth is whatever I say it is lalalalalala" -- ?</p>
      <p>I don't really want to rehash all the claims and counter-claims of election fraud -- it gets quite repetitive. (At this point if I could fit "Lyndon Johnson stole hundreds of thousands of votes in his 1948 Senate race" into my flair, it would save a lot of people the bother of hearing me explain over again why I dont think election fraud is <em>prima facie</em> implausible.) But is it really so hard to understand why I (we) feel the election was stolen?</p>
      <p>At least, from the polls I'm looking at, about half of the country now thinks that there was enough election fraud to have stolen the election. If thats not proof of fraud, maybe it's at least proof of a position worth taking more seriously than <em>crazed conspiracists who want to coup the government and are eroding our democratic way of life because they're part of a Trump cult</em>. (Which is something like the aggregate of what I see from Trump-supporter-as-zoo-animal exposés on twitter.)</p>
      <p>Because when I read sentences like this:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I suspect that there's a deep belief in the hearts of Trump voters that they are oppressed, conspired against, and that as such, they should not be expected to speak reasonably about it. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think something like, "This uncharitable strawman does not represent me at all, and it's also obviously true."</p>
      <p>That is -- I do believe many of the things you accuse me of believing, but the frame that uses such words as "refuses to concede" undermines that very accusation. It's not as though there is some objective debate fairy who proves that "red is the best color" which I stubbornly refuse to acknowledge -- that is the entire issue on debate.</p>
      <p>To summarize: I believe the 2020 election was stolen, that cheating occurred to the tune of hundreds of thousands of ballots, I think that this steal undermines democracy more than Trump's "refusal" to "concede" -- and I didn't arrive there by starting with some new definition of truth being whatever I say it is.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>