<post>
  <author>withmymindsheruns</author>
  <date>2020-11-24T10:06:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jzbis2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_23/gdfe7ut/</link>
  <title>The Male Environment, Childhood, and Imitation Learning</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I reckon the farmers took the survey as a joke. 'Yep, I have sex every day and my performance is incredible!'</p>
      <p>I'm a builder, but I used to be a schoolteacher. I can say that the guys I work with now seem to be less neurotic generally, I can't imagine many of them agonising over stuff like this, whereas quite a few of the teachers I worked with really seemed to have a tendency toward over-thinking things.</p>
      <p>I guess a lot of it has to do with personality traits sorting themselves into different jobs but I like to think being outside, working with your hands on concrete projects in a team of other men has a bit of a tendency to let you get over yourself in a way that being sat behind a desk doesn't. Maybe I'm just romanticising it though. Possibly it's also the differences between being in a workplace that has women in it and one that doesn't. Maybe the (pretty much) male-only work environment provides a good refuge for men's development of themselves free from the pressure of women's presence. Especially for the development of mentor/role model type relationships</p>
      <p>Actually, now that I've said it, I think that really is a big part of it. The male only environment seems to me to provide a much easier atmosphere of interaction that males can relax into. That can get corrupted by dysfunctional arseholes where it turns into sociopathic bullying or gross 'locker room talk' sex stuff, but that almost never happens on any of the building sites I'm on, possibly because the professional network of guys I've built up would exclude that because of my preferences, but I find that even guys who do edge into those areas almost seem relieved to not go there when I signal my preference not to engage in that kind of thing.</p>
      <p>Yeah, I do think the uncorrupted, relaxed male environment is a source of strength and simplicity to men who have access to it. I think one of the other big enemies of that mileu has been alcohol, as the male culture has been hijacked in a lot of places by drinking culture where (IMO) very little self-development or maturation occurs and male interaction can just become a hazy mess of stupidity that does more harm than good.</p>
      <p>So it might be possible that men just aren't developing good solid friendship groups and ending up feeling all ill-at-ease in the world.</p>
      <p>Physicality also ups testosterone production, being outside in the sun ups vitamin d production, physical work makes you feel tired but relaxed etc. there's probably a hundred other factors involved.</p>
      <p>Possibly men that come from blue-collar backgrounds see more of their dads too. I finish work at 4pm, my dad was an engineer and he never used to be home before 7pm. Also the kids of blue collar workers that I know seem a lot less worried about the world than their white collar peers. They see and understand the jobs their dads do, a lot of them have been on building sites/ the farm etc. helping out in the holidays and things like that. The future and the working world isn't some far off mystery that they have to pass through the opaque curtain of university to gain access to, it's something they can see and touch and understand. It's a much less anxiety provoking mindset to grow up with. </p>
      <p>Incidentally, I think this is the reason a lot of first-born siblings turn out much more neurotic than the following ones, the future is opaque to them because they don't have anyone demonstrating the next step in their development. For them, every stage of development is a step into the unknown is often experienced as (appropriately IMO) terrifying. </p>
      <p>I don't think children have evolved to develop in this way. I don't think they are equipped to deal with it, at least not as a constant state.</p>
      <p>The ancestral environment for childhood development must have been the tribe, the small community, the village, where there will be children and young adults at every stage in the continuum of development at all times, so every child has an example, a role model to imitate, so development becomes a joyous movement forward where the child is eager to aquire the skills and understanding displayed by the bigger kids who are only a small jump ahead of them. They can see the path forward.</p>
      <p>Compare that to the kids of today, especially first-born kids who are either segregated with kids at the same developmental level, or with adults. I know a lot of my own childhood vision of the future was stress over 'how the fuck am I ever going to be able to do (X)?' </p>
      <p>Maybe that was just my own anxious nature, or maybe it was the environment. It seems to play out in a lot of first-born children though.</p>
      <p>The other blatantly obvious fact (at least to anyone who has kids) is that little kids get absolutely and completely enamoured with slightly older kids. There is some very strong innate mechanism at work there, and I think it's pretty safe to say that it's (at least partly) that this is the mechanism by which kids develop. </p>
      <p>Learning only occurs when the gap between the presently mastered behaviour/ knowledge and the next level is bridgeable. When the conceptual/behavioural gap is small enough that the student can make the leap and land on the other side. This is what we get from imitating a slightly more developed peer. This is what kids are tapping into when they get into that hero-worship mode.</p>
      <p>So I think this where we come full circle, back to the male environment. I think the same principle applies. We learn through imitation of our slightly more advanced peers that lay out a future path ahead of us through their present actions. I think there may be some way in which a mixed gender environment upsets this mechanism for young men. Possibly because they aren't paying attention to the older men when young women are around, or simply because the dynamic which allows for that subliminal transfer of information is disrupted by the presence of sexual selection pressures, male hierarchy displays and stuff like that.</p>
      <p>Or it might just be that those types of work environments are so much more structured (or hierarchically segregated, or atomised, or opaque, or mediated)  that establishing those types of relationships just isn't possible and it's nothing to do with the presence of women, or maybe it's a bit of both. </p>
      <p>The upshot of it would be that for children of professionals, (i think especially boys) you have an environment that is continually inducing anxiety around the next developmental step because there is nothing to obvious available to imitate. And because the path of development is generally one of imitation, we have all these young men who have stalled out in a state of terrible anxiety because they just have no idea what the fuck they are supposed to do now.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>