<post>
  <author>cjet79</author>
  <date>2020-08-04T18:27:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0cul6c/</link>
  <title>Adversarial Establishment of Religion</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Adversarial Establishment of Religion</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I've had an idea bouncing around in my mind. I mostly think the idea would be terrible, but the thought exercise was pretty interesting. The US bill of rights has the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Establishment_Clause">Establishment Clause</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion, or prohibiting the free exercise thereof...</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>And for most of US history if some group wants to establish a new religion they have worked very hard to get recognition of their new religion as a religion. Mormonism and Scientology are the two big examples that spring to my mind, but there are also cult offshoots of Christianity have often gotten a default presumption of religious protection.</p>
      <p>Anyways, what happens if someone wants to establish a new religion, but they never call it a religion? They wouldn't get any of the protections that the establishment clause creates, but they also wouldn't get any of the restrictions. <em>In theory,</em> they could nationally require any aspect of that religion as long as that aspect does not conflict with other parts of the bill of rights.</p>
      <p>
        <em>In practice</em> Christian politicians have been testing the limits of the establishment clause for quite a while. Religious iconography, school prayer, the 'under God' part in the pledge of allegiance, etc. Courts have generally been forgiving as long as there is a good secular purpose mixed in, or at least some secular iconography.</p>
      <p>But it has generally been easy-mode for these cases. There is a clear Christian bible, there is a clear Christian faith, there are clear Christian symbols and iconography, and the politicians that make these overt displays are often being quite clear about their intentions to promote the Christian faith.</p>
      <p>Would it be necessary in certain circumstances to label a certain set of beliefs as religious? Even if the proponents of that belief did not want to be labeled as religious?</p>
      <p>
        <strong>The Big Problem</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Scott had a good article <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/03/25/is-everything-a-religion/">Is Everything A Religion</a> that shows just how such a policy could go horribly wrong. Establishing your opponents' political beliefs as a religion could become a superweapon. </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Scientology Case Study</strong>
      </p>
      <p>For a minute I want to ignore the problems of 'what is a religion'. So let's just look at Scientology and think about how history might have been different if they had taken a different path. Scientology's status as a religion isn't devoid of controversy, but its got more support for being labeled a religion compared to environmentalism or transhumanism (Scott's first two examples).</p>
      <p>So let's just imagine that Scientology never tried to officially establish itself as a religion. But its organizers still had the goal of expanding its beliefs to as many people as possible.</p>
      <p>Let's say they become big enough in a city or state to get majority control of the government. Here are their <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientology_beliefs_and_practices#Core_beliefs_and_practices">core beliefs</a>. Aside from their afterlife beliefs they could probably easily and permanently establish themselves in a government after gaining control:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Mandatory 'Auditing'. Scientology has a process of auditing people that seems a bit like a bastardized form of psychology. It involves bringing up painful and traumatic memories. Good blackmail material, and no doctor-patient privilege.</li>
        <li>Ban psychology/psychiatry. Psychology and psychiatry are viewed very negatively by Scientology. They may not be able to completely ban the practice, but they can heavily restrict it, tax it, and make it difficult to practice. For how this could be done, see abortion. Abortion isn't officially banned in most places, however, it is practically banned with how difficult it is to operate a family planning clinic.</li>
        <li>Establish local schooling lessons and college subjects related to Scientology. Capture the next generation while their minds are still pliable.</li>
        <li>Increased funding from taxpayers. They could fund new Scientology centers, provide scholarships to Scientology courses in college, hire new Scientology teachers at schools, etc.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>
        <strong>Memetic defenses</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I've often viewed the bill of rights as a sort of memetic mental defense against typical forms of government oppression. Religion and government is viewed as a bad and dangerous mix for good reasons. Europe tore itself apart for a few centuries due to religious conflict. The middle east has recently seen its fair share of religious violence mixed with governments. Central America had empires that engaged in human sacrifice for religious purposes. The examples in human history are endless, pretty much every people or country has had a run-in with this issue.</p>
      <p>The founding fathers of America were smart people. Not infallible, and not seers, but they still had some good insights. But I'm starting to wonder if the establishment clause is going to quickly become useless due to the fact that <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/01/13/evil-is-anti-inductive/">Evil is anti-inductive</a>. The establishment clause was meant to stop a known bad combination of super-strong beliefs mixed with government power. But it really only stops those super strong beliefs if the super-strong beliefs agree to be identified as a super-strong belief of a certain flavor.</p>
      <p>I don't really have a solution, I think the adversarial establishment of religion is maybe a solution, but I could easily see that sort of thing being abused. I'd like to hear other people's thoughts.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>