<post>
  <author>HlynkaCG</author>
  <date>2020-08-05T22:59:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0hyzgx/</link>
  <title>The Red Pill, the System, and Structural Power</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The key point has always been: Why? Why is there a structural power disparity? (No serious person disputes that there is one.) If the leftist theory is correct, it's merely a contingent fact of historical oppression, and can be remedied by removing the straight white male boot from everyone else's face.</p>
        <p>If the leftist theory is incorrect... well. That's why it is now completely verboten even to intimate vaguely that it might be.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is going to seem a little off topic at first but please bear with me. I'm a big fan of the Wachowskis. After Michael Mann and the Cohen Brothers they're probably my favorite contemporary film-makers. At first blush this might seem absurd because I'm socially conservative Christian from the rust belt and they are a pair of woke pink-haired Hollywood trannies. But moving past the surface level details, these two people seem to have a better better grasp of (for lack of a better term) "the old ways" than anyone else working in Hollywood today. Perhaps thier most prominent contributions to internet culture is the concept of the "red pill". I think it's an important and useful analogy, but much like the film <em>The Matrix</em> itself there's both a clear surface level reading that and a more nuanced lower level reading that doesn't really become apparent until you put it through the wringer.  For those who haven't seen the movie, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RglbAT0Cl-A">this scene</a> lays out the basic idea. Do you want to be safe/comfortable, or do you want to see what's going on behind the curtains. Naturally our protagonist [Reeves] picks the latter, as there wouldn't be much of a movie otherwise. </p>
      <p>Since then the image of the red pill has been used to illustrate having one's fundamental truths and assumptions called into question. People describe personal political shifts as "getting red-pilled", "black-pilled", or "woke", and most people understand what they mean. It flatters the ego to think of ones self, as being awake and "in the know" rather than one of those poor saps/NPCs who chose the blue pill. Thing is that there is an element to the whole thing that this reading misses. The pill is not "the Truth", it's a choice. And this is where we roll back around to your comment above. Even after having the true nature of his world revealed to him, Neo still struggles to free his mind. Recognizing that "the system" is a social construct, or that the life you were "sold" isn't what was actually in the offing is not the same thing as knowing the truth or having an actionable response.</p>
      <p>I find myself thinking of a bit of fan-fiction that I encountered in a forum/comment section years back where in some smart nerdy kid takes the red pill and after being shown what what the Matrix is, immediately starts explaining to the Morpheus analog why the whole premise is absurd. Morpheus, asks "...and you figured this out using facts and logic?", "yes" the kid replies. "Ok, and where did you learn logic?", "in school". "Ah yes, a school within the Matrix. Do you see the problem?" </p>
      <p>This isn't just on you. Frankly, I feel like I've been seeing it all over the place lately. Where was the concept of "structural power disparities" first explained to you? Who told you that there was one? Where did you first hear that this was a problem that required government intervention. Where did you get the idea that the criteria by which you have chosen to measure these disparities, be they racial, cultural, or economic were the correct ones? I'm going to guess that the answer to all of the above is "In a broadly secular progressive upper-middle class academic setting". Do you see the problem?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>