<post>
  <author>HuskyCriminologist</author>
  <date>2020-08-03T16:25:02Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g08271i/</link>
  <title>Why We Are Underestimating Trump's Chances</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Motte: We are all vastly underestimating the likelihood of a Trump 2020 victory because pollsters (excluding some individuals) learned <em>nothing</em> from 2016</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I recently got into a (brief) discussion about the likelihood of Trump winning in 2020 with another redditor. I held that it was extremely unlikely, given that Trump is polling very poorly in states that he won handily in 2016 and he badly needs to win in 2020. I held this view (note the past tense), because I had read several articles to this effect. <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/trump-trailing-biden-in-6-key-battleground-states-according-to-new-polling">Trump trailing Biden in 6 key battleground states</a>, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/07/26/trump-behind-biden-key-states-2020-election-381518">Poll: Trump trailing in battleground states 100 days out from the election
</a>. These articles and others like them emphasize things like:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Trump trails Biden by 51 percent to 46 percent in Florida; by 49 percent to 45 percent in Arizona; and by 52 percent to 40 percent in Michigan.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>NBC has <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/meet-the-press/poll-trump-loses-ground-key-2016-voters-n1226971">mentioned</a> that:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Comparing the new survey data to the numbers from the 2016 election exit poll shows Trump has lost ground with a wide range of demographic groups measured by educational attainment, gender and race. These are numbers he’ll need to address if he wants to be re-elected.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The key issue that I have seen, and why I think it's very likely that Trump is doing much better than one would otherwise think, is comparing 2020 <em>polls</em> with 2016 <em>results</em>. This comparison is why I no longer believe that Biden, barring a resounding upset, will cinch the election.</p>
      <p>To illustrate, let's use my favorite tool. Maps.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.270towin.com">Here</a> is the current 2020 predictions from 270towin, which creates a "consensus" model the details of which can be found <a href="https://www.270towin.com/content/forecasts-in-the-2020-consensus-map">here</a>. The gist of it is that 270towin's map is a composite of full time analysts, statistical models, media analysis, and a betting market (predictit). As things stand it looks pretty grim for Trump. Biden has more than 270 electoral votes in states that are safe/likely/lean Democrat, meaning Trump would have to win every battleground state <em>and</em> flip several "lean democrat" states to win. That'd be a difficult proposition. Especially when you compare that map to <a href="https://www.270towin.com/2016_Election/">these maps</a> showing the 2016 election results. States like Pennsylvania, North Carolina, Georgia, Ohio, Michigan, Wisconsin and Florida that Trump won in 2016 (some by very healthy margins) are now either leans-Democrat or battleground states.</p>
      <p>But. What if we look at the 2016 <em>prediction</em> map? <a href="https://www.270towin.com/maps/consensus-pundit-electoral-map">This map</a>. This map looks a lot closer to the 2020 prediction map than the 2016 results map doesn't it? There's some important distinctions certainly, in 2016 Georgia and Arizona were safer bets for Trump with their collective 27 electors. But if Trump wins every state he won in 2016 with the exception of Georgia and Arizona, he's left with 277 electoral votes. Victory Trump. </p>
      <p>What if Trump flips Minnesota? It's not outside the realm of possibility, the most recent poll shows Biden only leading by 5%. The recent instability in major cities across the US hasn't shown itself as being a boon or a curse for either candidate just yet, but if it <em>does</em> end up being a boon for one candidate, that candidate is likely to be Trump. Which could turn that last 5% and give Trump Minnesota. If Trump flips Minnesota he can lose Georgia and Arizona and even Winsconsin or Michigan. </p>
      <p>I'm not going to make a prediction here as to who is going to win in November yet. I will do so on Monday November 2nd, and not before. But in the mean time, I think Trump's chances have been underestimated.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>