<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-08-04T23:54:09Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0e3m1f/</link>
  <title>Examining Ethnic Hatred</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Why shouldn't I hate Germans / Russians / Americans for what happened to Poland during WWII and the decades of communism after?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Why indeed?  </p>
      <p>I do not hate Poles for their condescending attitude and casual racism, for their abuse of what is known today as Western Ukrainians, for the hijacking of our monarchy and occupation of Moscow <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_of_Troubles">in our darkest hour</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_armed_conflicts_involving_Poland_against_Russia">for every single time they were fucking with us throughout centuries</a>. Still, these are immutable facts, as is the fact that Polish patriotism is founded, in part, on feeling no shame for any of it.<br />
It helps that I know how after growing into its power Russia did much worse to Poland. While it would be nice to have a less blemished history and belong to some hypothetical more magnanimous nation, I do not condemn my ancestors for their brutality; and so I can easily forgive modern Poles, as well as even the Germans, for their own patriotism (yes, Russians have no hate for Germans, despite 27 million dead: we won, after all; and it’s a travesty how they were broken). It’s only fair. And I can admire the unyielding Polish will to national independence, and congratulate them on their success at getting out of our grasp in the end – it’s only sportsmanlike. They would never have succeeded without their hate, would have simply assimilated like weaker people. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J%C3%B3zef_Pi%C5%82sudski">This titan of a man</a>, too, would have had no fire in his chest. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tadeusz_Ko%C5%9Bciuszko">And this one.</a> Wouldn’t that have been a pity? For you as an American and a Pole alike?</p>
      <p>But mature, serious nations tend to overcome historical animosity once they secure their statehood and learn to appreciate peace. Americans do not hate the Brits; the Brits do not malign the French. It’s not exactly all water under the bridge for those who feel strongly as part of the collective body of their people; but history of rivers of blood is treated as a cause for silly jokes. (Cue angry Brit or Frenchman in denial).   </p>
      <p>The hate is there, sleeping alongside fallen soldiers. Just like them, not forgotten, no – just covered with grass. It doesn’t ask to be woken up. It’s all part of the solid ground on which new generations proudly stand.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>