<post>
  <author>is_not_strained</author>
  <date>2020-08-07T00:16:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0mfzgl/</link>
  <title>Philosophy: The Decline of an Academic Tradition</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="https://kieranhealy.org/blog/archives/2013/06/18/a-co-citation-network-for-philosophy/">Kieran Healy</a> gives some analysis of who cited who in four of the top philosophy journals.  This is not an exact metric of what counts as good philosophy, but it does measure what philosophers thought was interesting.</p>
      <p>He finds that the top ten articles are: (first number rank, second number of citations in Nous, Mind, Philosophical Review, Journal of Philosophy)
1   180 Kripke S 1980 Naming Necessity<br />
2   131 Lewis D 1986 Plurality Worlds<br />
3   97  Quine W 1960 Word Object<br />
4   83  Williamson T 2000 Knowledge Limits<br />
5   82  Lewis D 1973 Counterfactuals<br />
6   78  Evans G 1982 Varieties Reference<br />
7   77  Chalmers D 1996 Conscious<br />
7   77  Davidson D 1980 Essays Actions Event<br />
9   73  Lewis D 1986 Philos Papers
10  64  Parfit D 1984 Reasons Persons<br />
10  64  Davidson D 1984 Inquiries Truth Inte     </p>
      <p>Some of these titles are greatly shortened, but I imagine most people who have read them can complete the titles.  I think it obvious that this has general agreement with what people consider good philosophy.</p>
      <p>The articles published by year are interesting.  The titles from the 2000s (the list was made in 2013 so is limited to before then and skews old, as all reference counting does) are:</p>
      <p>4   83  Williamson T 2000 Knowledge Limits<br />
30  42  Sider T 2001 4 Dimensionalism Ont<br />
41  36  Hawthorne J 2004 Knowledge I Ottenes<br />
82  27  Tye M 2000 Consciousness Colro<br />
86  26  Stanley J 2005 Knowledge Practical<br />
86  26  Pryor J 2000 Nous  </p>
      <p>I will stop at 200.  The list from the 90s seems higher quality to me:</p>
      <p>7   77  Chalmers D 1996 Conscious<br />
13  58  Scanlon T 1998 What We Owe Each Oth<br />
17  49  Williamson T 1994 Vagueness<br />
19  45  Jackson F 1998 Metaphysics Ethics<br />
20  44  Lewis D 1996 Australas J Philos<br />
20  44  Vaninwagen P 1990 Material Beings<br />
25  43  Gibbard A 1990 Wise Choices Apt Fee   </p>
      <p>The 80s look even better to me.</p>
      <p>1   180 Kripke S 1980 Naming Necessity<br />
2   131 Lewis D 1986 Plurality Worlds<br />
6   78  Evans G 1982 Varieties Reference<br />
7   77  Davidson D 1980 Essays Actions Event<br />
9   73  Lewis D 1986 Philos Papers<br />
10  64  Parfit D 1984 Reasons Persons<br />
10  64  Davidson D 1984 Inquiries Truth Inte<br />
12  60  Nozick R 1981 Philos Explanations<br />
14  57  Kaplan D 1989 Themes Kaplan<br />
16  50  Lewis D 1983 Philos Papers<br />
18  48  Lewis D 1983 Australas J Philos<br />
20  44  Fodor J 1987 Psychosemantics Prob<br />
20  44  Harman G 1986 Change View<br />
20  44  Searle J 1983 Intentionality Essay<br />
25  43  Putnam H 1981 Reason Truth Hist<br />
25  43  Stalnaker R 1984 Inquiry<br />
25  43  Salmon N 1986 Freges Puzzle  </p>
      <p>Consider the top 6 from the 70s:</p>
      <p>5   82  Lewis D 1973 Counterfactuals<br />
15  53  Rawls J 1971 Theory Justice<br />
32  40  Burge T 1979 Midwest Stud Philos<br />
35  38  Putnam H 1975 Mind Language Realit<br />
41  36  Lewis D 1979 J Philos Logic<br />
47  34  Fine K 1975 Synthese  </p>
      <p>Are these better than the top 6 from the 80s? Then again, the top 6 from the 60s seem good too.</p>
      <p>3   97  Quine W 1960 Word Object<br />
41  36  Frankfurt H 1969 J Philos<br />
53  33  Quine W 1969 Ontological Realitiv<br />
67  29  Lewis D 1969 Convention Philos St<br />
86  26  Donnellan K 1966 Philos Rev<br />
96  25  Gettier E 1963 Analysis  </p>
      <p>The 50s are good, though Chisholm has not aged well.</p>
      <p>57  32  Wittgenstein L 1953 Philos Investigation<br />
96  25  Quine W 1953 Logical Point View<br />
109 23  Strawson P 1959 Individualy<br />
130 21  Williams D 1953 Rev Metaphys<br />
141 20  Carnap R 1956 Meaning Necessity<br />
141 20  Chisholm R 1957 Perceiving Philos St  </p>
      <p>Philosophy seems, from this list, to have been very strong from the 60s to the 80s, and started to decline in the 90s.  There are a few solid contributions, but even the very best work of the last 30 years, Chalmers, Scanlon, Williamson, and Jackson don't seem to have the rigor or breadth of the earlier work.  Chalmers is very squishy, Scanlon's contractionalism is about ethics, which I hate, and Jackson's whole thesis seems to be preferring squishyness.  I suppose, ironically, the most precise and formal work is Williamson's.</p>
      <p>I like my philosophy precise, and things have gotten much worse since the 80s.  I blame the rise of computer science, which has taken a lot of detail and precise thinkers and given then something else to do.  As a result, philosophy departments have become hopelessly handwavy.  Church, almost single handily made symbolic logic a respectable discipline, and his peers and students were the golden age.  Their students kept the faith, but were unable to pass it on.  The philosophers I knew who were close to retirement age in the 80s and 90s would claim they were much worse than Von Neumann, Church, Tarski, etc. but they saw the students that were available we much worse again.  A tradition was lost, somewhere in the 80s, and is not unrecoverable.</p>
      <p>As an aside, a similar thing happened in nuclear weapons.  I worked on a weird project in the 90s, where, because all the competent people had retired, the US nuclear stockpile stopped working.  The people who were hired post 1960 were incompetent, compared to the earlier crowd, so the experts just did not explain how things actually worked, as everything was on a need to know basis, and the new hires were not smart enough to understand.  </p>
      <p>It took weeks of interviews to break down these retired guys attitude and to get the to internalize that they had to tell everything they knew to the current hires, even though they were idiots, as everyone competent was gone.  The last I heard, the project worked, and America could make nuclear weapons again.  Hopefully they have a plan for next time.  </p>
      <p>It is strange that entire fields can die, just because the new students are dumber than they used to be, but it happens.  Tastes change, everyone goes off to investment banking, and suddenly an academic tradition is lost.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>