<post>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2020-08-05T04:41:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0evhqf/</link>
  <title>Contra Scott Alexander on Mencius Moldbug and Protests</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Long ago - back when 'President Trump' was still a Comedy Central Roast gag - Scott Alexander <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140708072622/http://squid314.livejournal.com/354385.html">wrote a response</a> to Mencius Moldbug premised on a protracted metaphor of the The Donald getting into a bar fight with briefly viral YouTuber Rebecca Black. Scott opined that Moldbug's famous 'Cthulhu only swims left' was narrowly focused because the left only actually holds social power whereas the right holds structural power, and the former is only weakly able to influence the latter. Please give it a brief read before continuing</p>
      <p>Looking back at this 7 years later, several things jump out at me. Firstly, just how decisively <em>wrong</em> Scott was: for starters, you're reading an archive link of a now private post that you were linked to from a disavowed spin-off of a quarantine thread of his sub-reddit even as the blog has <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/10/23/kolmogorov-complicity-and-the-parable-of-lightning/">scurried away from social issues</a> and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/i3rvzw/update_nyt_still_at_it_reopening_on_hold/">still faces existential threats</a>, because it turns out that social power is actually pretty impactful after all (as <a href="https://slate.com/technology/2015/06/curtis-yarvin-booted-from-strange-loop-its-a-big-big-problem.html">Moldbug</a> can corroborate). Secondly, an example he gives:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The first is that it's outright false. Moldbug <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140708072622/http://unqualified-reservations.blogspot.com/2013/01/christians-have-right-to-vandalize.html">later uses</a> the example of pro-lifers protesting abortion as an example of an unsympathetic and genuinely powerless cause. Yet as far as I can tell abortion protesters and Exxon Mobile protesters are treated more or less the same. In both cases, polite protesters who stick to the law are allowed to keep doing their thing, or occasionally get arrested and then immediately released, but those who actually hurt people or damage property <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140708072622/http://saltyeggs.com/will-the-real-eco-terrorists-please-stand-up/">are punished</a>.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>...is fairly hilarious in retrospect, as mobs <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/george-floyd-protests-expensive-civil-disturbance-us-history">torch cities</a> in the name of social justice and face <a href="https://www.insider.com/manhattan-da-says-city-wont-prosecute-arrested-protesters-2020-6">no charges</a> or <a href="https://www.kgw.com/article/news/local/protests/criminal-charges-against-dozens-of-portland-protesters-dropped/283-0571774d-43e4-4750-903a-db8e686a7a51">sanction</a>, while <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/two-protesters-arrested-for-chalking-black-pre-born-lives-matter-on-sidewalk/2020/08/01/6d966d90-d41f-11ea-9038-af089b63ac21_story.html">two pro-life activists were arrested</a> the other day for writing 'Black Pre-Born Lives Matter' on the sidewalk in chalk. Likewise, De Blasio admitted today he <a href="https://nypost.com/2020/08/03/de-blasio-admits-city-skipped-permit-process-to-paint-blm-murals/">skipped the permit process</a> everyone else has to go to for his BLM mural on 5th Ave, but still feels comfortable arresting and charging <a href="https://www.silive.com/news/2020/07/two-staten-island-women-charged-with-defacing-black-lives-matter-mural-outside-trump-tower.html">anyone painting over it</a></p>
      <p>Meanwhile, Moldbug's formulation of "<em>'Civil disobedience' is no more than a way for the overdog to say to the underdog: I am so strong that you cannot enforce your 'laws' upon me. I am strong and might makes right - I give you the law, not you me"</em> seems to have found a living metaphor with <a href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-8540579/Naked-Athena-protester-confronts-Portland-police.html">ratchet Portland hipsters stripping naked</a> in front of lines of police they know will not engage them</p>
      <p>In my estimation, where Scott went wrong was failing to consider that social power would be boosted and augmented by the social networking effects of the internet. Shaming tactics that were largely impotent mere decades ago can now cause ruinous harms to all those subject to their glare. A recent tweet sums this up nicely:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <a href="https://twitter.com/zermatist/status/1290451067600277504?s=20">Political correctness needed the internet to really get going, in the same way that protestant theology needed the printing press. The PC scolds of the early 90s were like the Lollards of the 14th century</a>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This only seems to be accelerating as i) shaming / activist networks formalize and grow; ii) their influence becomes accepted as a given; iii) bandwagoners see the opportunity for clout; iv) corporations, celebrities, institutions defer to their influence and predilections; and v) rhetoric like 'silence is violence' shakes loose fence sitters and makes participation a social imperative</p>
      <p>Finally, the dichotomy Scott once drew is a bit naïve. As he tells it, "the things people actually care about, like money, success, influence, and psychological health, come entirely from structural/unconscious power". Well, what happens <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Fragility">when the best selling book in America</a> is a paean to the dominant social/conscious power, the industry <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2019/jun/15/torn-apart-the-vicious-war-over-young-adult-books">demands conformity</a> to its values, and its <a href="https://www.indy100.com/article/george-rr-martin-game-of-thrones-hugo-awards-racism-transphobia-9651451">award ceremonies</a> become rituals to its sacraments? What happens when <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/money/2020/06/18/boycotts-people-plan-stop-spending-stores-dont-support-blm/3208170001/">money</a> and <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jemimamcevoy/2020/07/01/every-ceo-and-leader-that-stepped-down-since-black-lives-matter-protests-began/#1f54d4f65593">success</a> and <a href="https://theunionjournal.com/stefan-molyneux-suspended-from-twitter-just-days-after-receiving-youtube-ban-rt-world-news/">influence</a> and <a href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/video/2020/07/27/activists_protest_outside_home_of_acting_dhs_secretary_chad_wolf.html">psychological health</a> became contingent on <a href="https://thegrio.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/Democrats.jpg">kneeling</a> to the dominant social power structure and its anarchotyrannical enforcement of its ever shifting  mores?</p>
      <p>I guess we'll see. But given that Scott's money and success are hostages of the same social forces that have stymied his influence and psychological health, it seems increasingly unlikely we'll ever get a follow-up</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>