<post>
  <author>Viva_La_Muerte</author>
  <date>2020-08-03T22:52:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g09mhus/</link>
  <title>Life as a Jehovah's Witness</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Some here may be interested to learn some about a group in American society that you are probably are familiar with, but likely don’t know much about. More specifically, that group's position (or lack of position) in what seems like an all-consuming culture war: the Jehovah’s Witnesses.</p>
      <p>I was semi-raised as a JW. Neither of my parents were actually baptized (my father was actively hostile to the Watchtower Society), nor was I. But many of my aunts and uncles were, and I was largely raised by them as a kid because my mother and father were gone a lot.</p>
      <p>Everyone knows the image of Jehovah’s Witnesses going door to door annoying the neighborhood and asking if “you have a moment to talk about our Lord and Savior” (though they never use that actual language), and might know they don’t celebrate holidays or accept blood transfusions, but a lot of their beliefs are unknown to most Americans. </p>
      <p>Like Mormons, they have a lot of bizarre theology that really sets them apart from most of mainstream Christianity and leads to most other Christians not actually counting JWs as fellow Christians.</p>
      <p>They don’t believe in the Trinity. They believe Jesus is not God, but God’s first creation, identical to the Archangel Michael, and also the agent through which Jehovah created everything else. They also don’t believe the Holy Spirit is God, or even a person, but rather simply a term for Jehovah's ‘active force’ working in the world. </p>
      <p>They don’t believe in heaven or hell (they believe Heaven exists, but it is the abode of Jehovah and the angels, not a destination for humans--with some caveats). The soul does not persist apart from the body. Unbelievers (i.e, non-JWs) will be destroyed at Armageddon, and simply cease to exist. The righteous (i.e, JWs) ‘fall asleep’ upon death, and are resurrected on the last day to live forever on a renewed paradise earth. </p>
      <p>Where I think the JWs are especially interesting is in the realm of political and social issues.</p>
      <p>On first glance, they map pretty neatly to the conservative, right-wing value system. They believe marriage is between one man and one woman, wives and children are to submit to the 'headship' of the man of the house, smoking, drinking (‘to excess’), and premarital sex are sinful, divorce is not allowed, etc. Racy media and media with occult themes are to be avoided. They are certainly not religious pluralists or ‘all paths lead to God’ types, and firmly believe their belief system is the only way to eternal life. They frequently bemoan the (as they see it) increasingly corrupt, perverse, and godless state of the world.</p>
      <p>In those respects, they strongly resemble Evangelicals, the group I would say they have the most commonality with (except maybe Mormons in other ways).</p>
      <p>But that’s about where they part ways with the mainstream religious right.</p>
      <p>The first big difference is their attitude towards patriotism. Evangelicals are notoriously patriotic, and of course one of the GOP’s most solid bases. I think they've been found to have the highest reported rates of patriotism of any religious group in the US. </p>
      <p>JWs on the other hand have more disdain for patriotism than the most hardcore cosmopolitan liberals. For them, the ‘Kingdom of Heaven’ isn’t a nice phrase for the fellowship of all Christians or anything—it’s a literal supernatural polity and they are its subjects. On the other hand, all <em>human</em> governments are tools of Satan in his capacity as ‘god of this world,’ and will be destroyed by Christ at his second coming. Consequently, serving in the military, running for office, endorsing a candidate, voting, political lobbying, or even pledging allegiance to the flag are tantamount to swearing fealty to Lucifer. You will never hear a JW say anything like 'we need to turn the country back to God' or 'bring prayer back to schools', and you will <em>never</em> hear one say, ‘God bless America.’ </p>
      <p>They would consider a conservative Evangelical claiming that God is working through Trump, or a liberal Christian claiming that Jesus would support modern notions of racial and social justice, to both be uttering blasphemies.  </p>
      <p>Which leads to the next point—their racial/ethnic diversity. Evangelicals and the American religious right in general are notoriously white. Ditto for Mormons and probably most other small Christian denominations (many of which, like the Amish, are ethnic groups as much as denominations), save perhaps some which are instead overwhelmingly black. JWs on the other hand have no majority race/ethnicity and are quite remarkably diverse. I can testify to that from personal experience. Kingdom Hall meetings are mind-numbingly boring, so when I was little, I often counted faces to pass the time. Those faces were very multichromatic.  </p>
      <p>Statistics bear this out. JWs have no majority race/ethnicity. They have very a slim white plurality, followed by Hispanics, and then blacks. I have also, personally, noted a very high rate of interracial marriage among JWs, though I can’t back that up with stats. I suspect if you gave the average JW one of those racial in-group bias tests, they would score as low or even lower than your average white liberal. </p>
      <p>Something you might not grasp if you just look up ‘what do Jehovah’s Witnesses believe’ is that they really, truly believe in Satan and demons. Not just in a ‘oh Satan is tempting me’ way or even in a 'yeah demonic possession can happen' way, but as in they deeply believe there are hordes of evil spirits wandering the earth right now that can and will fuck with you, personally and this is something you, personally, need to be worried about. Even the more religious conservative Christians I’ve known may say things like ‘demons are very real’ or ‘Satan is not a metaphor,’ but by and large (obligatory <em>in my experience</em>) they don’t really <em>act</em> like it. If you tell an evangelical or a traditionalist Catholic that you’re pretty sure you were attacked by a demon last night they’re probably only a little less likely than anyone else to give you a weird look. </p>
      <p>JWs absolutely walk the walk in this respect. If you are a JW you almost certainly know someone who claims firsthand experience with demonic possession, cursed dolls, witchcraft, etc. I personally have several family members who will swear they’ve been personally assaulted by the forces of the evil one. My uncle believed he had nearly been killed by a clown doll, and my aunt insisted upon covering up the Catholic iconography in a house we once stayed in for fear it would draw demons to us, something she said had happened to her before. I also knew some people who believed Criss Angel had actual supernatural powers. Go search ‘demons’ or ‘demonic’ on <a href="/r/exJW">/r/exJW</a> if you want some fun stories. </p>
      <p>So, in summation you have highly socially conservative people that also despise patriotism and ethnic and tribal loyalties, consider government and political participation to be literally Satanic by default, and live in a 24/7 <em>Conjuring</em> movie. </p>
      <p>JWs are quite strict and serious about their religion. They will certainly kick you out if you insist on violating their teachings and will coerce your friends and family still in the faith into shunning you or else suffering the same penalty. They have often been labelled a cult, especially by ex-JWs understandably upset about such treatment. They certainly have cult-like aspects, like the aforementioned habit of 'disfellowshipping'. The Watchtower Society also has a bad habit of predicting the end of the world and being wrong. They finally stopped setting dates after the last embarrassment in 1975, but Armageddon is still perpetually <em>just around the corner</em>. The WTS also has an impressive ability to pull absurd teachings out of thin air that all but flatly contradict previous teachings, and pretend they never taught differently. But personally, I would not say they are a cult any more than Mormons or Evangelicals (though that's not necessarily a great compliment IMO). And I believe the only real distinction between 'cult' and 'religion' is size.</p>
      <p>What I find so fascinating about the JWs is that as a religious group they seem to have succeeded as far as it is possible in charting a truly neutral course and abstracting themselves from the world, and really do live in another reality wherein the political and social battles that are so dear to most everyone else just don’t matter. How could you care about wealth inequality, or woke corporations, or whether progressivism is destroying the country or Trump has dictatorial ambitions when you’re fighting literal demons? There’s no side to take because, top to bottom, left to right, liberal to conservative, it’s all the same side: the devil’s side. It's a waste of time trying to change it, and the only good thing that will ever happen to 'this system of things,' as they call it, is its imminent destruction by an army of angels.</p>
      <p>That's more or less how I grew up, and even though I haven't believed in anything the WTS teaches in a long time, it's had a real impact on my ideals and character to this day. Certainly, I'm still instinctively leery about things like tarot cards or fortune telling, even though I don't believe in demons or witchcraft. I have a lot of gut conservative instincts probably traceable to the WTS, but notably I have never had the least patriotic sentiment. I tend to find myself regularly thinking along the lines of 'the whole system is evil to the core anyways, what's the point?' and am quite politically disengaged (beyond online intellectual masturbation) because engaging in real life politics still makes me feel rather dirty.  </p>
      <p>I guess I may still be a Jehovah's Witness at heart.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>