<post>
  <author>ChevalMalFet</author>
  <date>2019-11-08T10:44:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/drd1uu/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_04/f6vzu2q/</link>
  <title>An Opus on Korean Education: Part 3</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>​</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Costs</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Let’s talk about my own personal experience. I teach English at a gifted high school - and right there was my first cultural shock. A gifted high school would never fly in the United States. Why not is left as an exercise for the reader. For my part, it’s a dream job. I only have 3 or 4 total preps a week (barely 20% of my middle school preps), the administration is supportive, and the students not only are imbued the Korean spirit of subordination and respect, but also are motivated, talented, and proud of earning their place at the school. That makes instruction a breeze - behavior problems are totally absent from the school and I can focus solely on providing content. I’m not a babysitter here. In fact, the only trouble I ever have with students is one common problem: They sleep in class.</p>
      <p>Big deal, you think. They’re teenagers. Teenagers sleep in class all the time. And you’re right! They do! In this way they are no dfferent than American teenagers. </p>
      <p>But the way Korean students sleep is different than American students. The students shuffle in at the start of class, take their seats while waiting for the bell to ring, and immediately nod off. Some will sleep until the bell rings, then do their best to stay attentive through the lesson. Others - well, not so much. They remind me of nothing so much of stories I’ve read of soldiers in combat zones, who quickly master the art of sleeping whenever they have a spare moment. They resemble veterans in other ways - Korea’s suicide rate is the highest in the OECD, and suicide is the leading cause of death among Korean teenagers. The most commonly cited reason? Academic stress. </p>
      <p>No wonder, either. Here’s my students’ biweekly schedule.</p>
      <p>At 7:30, wake-up music blasts through the dormitory (I was allowed to set the playlist during Halloween week, and you bet your ass I scheduled all the spooky music I could. Halloween isn’t really a thing here, but it’s my favorite holiday so by God I’m making it a thing). The students must all rise from their beds and report to a check-in desk, which will note that all students are awake and up. If a student fails to check in, a teacher will be sent to investigate.</p>
      <p>By 8:00, all students are out of the dorms. They can go to the mess hall for breakfast, if they like. Breakfast is typical fare - rice, some sort of fish soup, kimchi. The same food they’ll eat for lunch, and for dinner.</p>
      <p>8:20, and they need to report to home room. Many students have opted to skip breakfast so they have more free time, so they will straggle in from all over campus. Following 20 minutes of home room, the school day begins - 50 minute classes with 10 minute passing periods, plus a lunch period. No individualized classes here - they move with the same group all day. The ~16 people in their home room will be their main companions for the entire academic year. </p>
      <p>At 4:20, the final class ends and it’s time to clean the school. They scatter to the various rooms, dig out cleaning implements from various cupboards built for the purpose, and swiftly sweep, take out the trash, dust, etc. </p>
      <p>4:40 and their “special after school club” begins. Basically this is another class - math, physics, chemistry, some subject that they selected. You choose at the beginning of the year and, of course, cannot switch. Many have said that their biggest regret at school was choosing the wrong club.</p>
      <p>At 6:00, it’s time for dinner. Same stuff as lunch - rice, fish soup, kimchi, some form of meat dish usually. Same as breakfast will be in the morning. </p>
      <p>At 7:00, it is time for “self-study.” Self-study consists of the students gathering in a large study hall filled with individual study cubicles. They will set up, each in their own cubicle, and spend the next two hours hitting the books. </p>
      <p>At 9:00, they get a break.</p>
      <p>At 9:20, self-study resumes. Another two hours. Same as the first. Some admit they have difficulty concentrating at this time.</p>
      <p>At midnight, the dorms are at last unlocked. The students are allowed to return to their rooms and to sleep. Most don’t, of course. They have been unable to socialize outside of mealtimes literally all day, so most stay up for one to three hours talking with their friends and visiting. It is their only free time during the day. Most go to bed around three am.</p>
      <p>Four and a half hours later, the morning music blasts again and it resumes. </p>
      <p>Saturdays, there are no classes. Instead, students spend the morning at a special club - maybe sports, if they were smart enough to sign up for baseball or badminton or soccer - or else writing, art, music, one of the finer arts. In the afternoon, after lunch, self-study time resumes. This will last in 4-hour sessions, with breaks and a meal, until bedtime. </p>
      <p>Sunday, they have self-study in the morning, and then the afternoon is free. </p>
      <p>Every other weekend, they are allowed to visit home. </p>
      <p>Now, my high school is an intensive, elite high school dedicated to training Korea’s gifted and talented children in the ways of science. Surely normal high schoolers don’t have it so bad, you’d think? And you’d be right! ...sort of.</p>
      <p>Not all high schools are boarding schools (although many are). And no elementary or middle schools are. However, such is Korea’s intense focus on education, and such is parents’ obsessive competition to get their children into a top university, that letting your kid only study at school is for fools and beggars. Everyone else ponies up for private tutoring, most commonly hagwons.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>