<post>
  <author>ChevalMalFet</author>
  <date>2019-11-08T10:43:58Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/drd1uu/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_04/f6vzt1u/</link>
  <title>An Opus on Korean Education: Part 2</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Tailor-made for tests</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The result of all this is <em>intense,</em> even <em>insane</em> competition amongst Korean students. No reputable job will look twice at them if they fail to have a degree from a top university. Worse, their friends, their family - everyone will be disappointed in them if they fail. In the heavily Confucian culture of the country, this is an almost unbearable shame. It’s difficult for Westerners, at least those of us from guilt cultures like America, to empathize, but imagine how your family would look at you if they knew you, I don’t know, hosted dog-fighting rings for fun or had a huge stash of kiddy porn. Well, maybe not that extreme, but you get the idea. Failure is <em>unthinkable.</em></p>
      <p>But for many students, failure is <em>inevitable.</em> There are millions of students jostling for a very limited selection of spots. There’s no way for all of them to get in. The result, then, is an arms race. Private schools, tutors, hours upon hours of study - any edge students, and especially parents, can find for their kids, they take, starting as early as elementary school. Anything less results in your child falling behind, and that is doom. </p>
      <p>Most schools know this, and respond. Korean education is very grade-focused, and the reputation of drill-drill-drill, rote-memorization is, while a bit exaggerated, not entirely inaccurate. Schools demand perfection in memorization and recital, whether of math facts, of complicate chemical equations, or a massive list of English idioms for some goddamn reason (I still don’t get that last one). I once was called in and chastised by my principal because my students were averaging scores of 90 on my tests and I needed to get that down to 80. </p>
      <p>So, all of Korean education is optimized around students delivering the best score they possibly can on a single standardized test at the culmination of their academic career. Their entire culture, society - the whole support network students have access to is dedicated to this one goal. Thus, <em>of course</em> you get a system that is very, very good at churning out students that will score well on standardized tests!</p>
      <p>But all that optimization comes at a high price.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>