<post>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2021-04-02T22:21:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mfj47c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_29_2021/gt6qr4b/</link>
  <title>"Every ideology and cult has a common-sense packaging around it that lures people in. You can't start with the crazy stuff outright."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Interesting article. However, even if it's true about the academic woke ideology, I'm not so sure that the bulk of those who are generally described as "woke", e.g. on Twitter, follow the literature that closely. I don't think they all do this consciously or following some script, rather they instinctively feel out their incentive landscape and follow it from their own local point of view.</p>
      <p>Indeed, I think the core ideology relies on these people for spreading. On people who only see bits and pieces of its argument structure and simply think it's mere common sense decency. They'd say all this talk about an underlying ideology or "agenda" is bogus like a conspiracy theory about Jewish control, while it's actually all just about equality and human rights.</p>
      <p>Every ideology and cult has a common-sense packaging around it that lures people in. You can't start with the crazy stuff outright.</p>
      <p>Woke starts with "surely you agree black people and women deserve human rights too!" and leads to "every white person is always racist by nature, it can never be overcome, but must be 'worked' on every second of the day, the concept of objective truth is white supremacy etc." That society must be wholesale dismantled as we know it and rebuilt from the ground up based on fundamentally different ways of knowing, different ways of organizing, different ways of thinking, speaking and existing. So different that we can't even formulate how the end state will look like using our currently available concepts.</p>
      <p>Scientology starts with techniques to manage your life, get organized, find structure, basic psychology therapy stuff. On another front it runs anti-drug campaigns to save the youth from destroying their lives; what decent person would have an issue with that? Then it gets into how psychiatry is the big evil of the world, how we must work constantly to "clean up" the Earth of various entities by moving along "the bridge" to acquire supernatural powers. Because we are all part of a cosmic battle of aliens spanning billions of years and zillions of aliens are within you right now and are controlling you and other pants-on-head crazy stuff.</p>
      <p>"Rationalism" starts with Kahnemann-style basic logical thinking patterns, appealing to analytical minds (Sequences). It also explains all the weird stuff socially more "normal" people do in mechanistic terms, it gives you a new terminology to understand your place in society, through which you can finally see yourself as above the normal everyday people who are not aware of the counterintuitive signaling games that happen all the time, they think education is to educate, healthcare is for improving health, while you know it's all just signaling (from Robin Hanson). Nothing is really what it seems. Academic science is also bullshit signaling and credentials don't mean anything. There's not much use in tapping into prior literature, first-principles thinking will get you further, by following the rationalist leaders' example. Then as you get deeper it starts to be about acausally trading with superintelligent AIs from the future and specks of dust in trillions of people's eyes and the imperative to throw away moral intuitions in favor of rationalist dogma since it's underpinned by hardcore math, like Bayes theorem, and equipped with that you will be a winner. And of course following this imperative must lead you to the conclusion that you have to donate a serious chunk of your income as charity to Yudkowskian "research institutes". Afaict it slowly fizzled out and lost its fangs as the members were self-aware enough to constantly meta-discuss whether this was happening.</p>
      <p>A similar one could be written about neo-Nazi far-right nationalism. Or for PUA/Redpill. Or communism, etc.</p>
      <p>The common elements are: first, we give you some stuff that obviously works and is reasonable. Second, you learn that <em>nothing is what it seems</em>. That <em>you've been lied to your whole life</em>. We know how things really are, your family, friends etc. should be relatively discounted. That there's a Matrix-like background existence that you've been blind to, but the techniques you've started to gain access to will allow you to escape this mental prison and be enlightened. Oh and by the way here is some psychologically pretty disturbing stuff that will guilt trip you into giving us money, plus some crazy beliefs that you would never have accepted at the outset if we had started with those, but now you're far enough along that you will accept them like a slow boiling frog, due to sunk cost fallacy and other stuff.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>