<post>
  <author>JuliusBranson</author>
  <date>2021-04-06T04:27:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mke4zb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_05_2021/gtjb4om/</link>
  <title>"Do anti-HBD leaders genuinely believe in their position, or are they motivated by something else?"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Why the Woke Won't Argue: A look at Turkheimer and HBD research</strong>
      </p>
      <p>1/2</p>
      <p>Recently there has been discussion about the discussion about why the woke aren't here debating with us in large numbers, particularly with regards to the topic of HBD. This has so far culminated in an <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/mfj47c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_29_2021/gtac5zi/">AMA</a> by a self-prolaimed wokie which was quickly posted to the sub where the haters gather by the same account who started the AMA. The poster wanted to discuss many topics but I am going to focus on what he said about HBD as I feel that that is really what people are referring to when they bemoan the lack of woke in this subreddit. In other words, I think we have a healthy diversity, or at least a healthy amount of people who lean left, on topics such as sex, gender, class, economics, epistemology, ethics and so on. <a href="/u/Inconvenientprequel">/u/Inconvenientprequel</a> didn't directly mention HBD in his top post, instead opting to make statements like "Equality is good, actually" and "I think suffering is bad, compassion is good." I view these statements as utilitarian and I code that as left; I for one essentially do not agree with either of them and I feel like I am outnumbered in that sentiment here. Consequently I believe that we have a healthy amount of representation for that viewpoint here. I could go on but my point is that almost everyone here believes HBD, but a large chunk of those people see themselves as "blue tribe outcasts." Feel free to hash this out below if you think I'm wrong, but AFAIK those who want more wokists here agree with this, as I have seen it said here and there multiple times. The point I am making is when people say they want more woke here, that can more or less be boiled down to them wanted more people who don't agree with HBD. This is important because I'm going to look at why I think those who don't agree with HBD don't argue, and by extension if this past paragraph is correct it should help inform as to why the woke don't want to come here and argue. </p>
      <p>Now I want to consider HBD as a simple, binary ideology: in general there are those who agree with it and those who do not. This is a simplification of a bimodal continuous distribution, but I don't think a lot of relevant nuance is lost as in practice those who believe it to some degree are lumped in with those who believe it to a larger degree by those who more or less believe it to no degree. This is what we see in <a href="https://www.vox.com/the-big-idea/2017/6/15/15797120/race-black-white-iq-response-critics">this article, which I will be coming back to, by Turkheimer &amp; co.</a> Turkheimer et al argue that there is no evidence that there is any genetic component of the black-white IQ gap, and lumps Murray's hesitant statements in The Bell Curve in with people who believe the gap is totally heritable (such as myself). I don't think it's much of a leap to just note that this is generally how it works in real life as well, or in other words, that this lumping phenomenon is very common. </p>
      <p>I for one am pretty sure that we have a sub with a nice diversity of pro-HBD viewpoints. Maybe this can be evidenced in the comment section. What I mean is that I would be surprised to find out that I am not outnumbered; that for every person who thinks the black-white IQ gap is 100% genetic there is a person who frequents this place who will say "wait a minute, it could be 50%" and another who will say maybe 80% and maybe even one who thinks it could be as low as 30%. What we are missing is people who think it's essentially 0%. People who might reasonably interpret the previous imagined discussion in such a way that you have surely read here and there, perhaps as "merely a discussion on how inferior black people are." Again, given a prior that HBD is totally false, this is totally reasonable. And of course this has been discussed in the meta-discussion: people who don't believe in HBD are probably scared off by HBD discussion because it's mean. </p>
      <p>But why would that be so many people that we have essentially no one here who doesn't agree with HBD to some meaningful degree? I believe that the two different views select for temperamental differences. In other words, it's not random how people come to pro and anti-HBD views. It's not an equal pool of people on each side. It's not that some pro-HBD people are scared off by discussion of anti-HBD and vice versa. I in fact believe that anti-HBD people are much more likely to be "scared off" by discussion for one reason or another relative to pro-HBD people. </p>
      <p>And specifically I think there are roughly two reasons why an anti-HBD person might be "scared off", and that these two reasons are analogous with why said person is anti-HBD. These two possible reasons are in turn analogous with <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/lv2rb7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_01_2021/gq2i62h/">my post on the Leader/Follower dichotomy for ideologies.</a> My observation is that there are members of any ideology which are followers of other figures, and there are independent leaders of ideologies. The leader's psychology are what really explain the ideology, especially when it is dominant, since I believe most people will then follow said ideology because it is egoistically rational. Only weirdos (I jest) like us will irrationally dissent based on notions of "truth" or whatever else. </p>
      <p>I observe that anti-HBD is the dominant ideology -- hopefully people can agree with this as most people here who work would probably lose their job if it were discovered that they believe that the black-white IQ gap is even partially due to genetics. Examples of HBD related cancellations come to mind: Hsu is one and Scott Alexander could also be considered one. It follows then that there will be a lot of followers who are anti-HBD because it is the expert and the social consensus. Indeed, when I listen to people I often here this. Many will explicitly refer to "consensus." Our friendly AMAer did this implicitly; instead of independently discussing systemic racism, <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/mfj47c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_29_2021/gterbfh/">here</a> he merely linked a wikipedia article, and here he "just thinks <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/mfj47c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_29_2021/gtdhctl/">HBD is false,"</a> linking two articles instead of generating his own argument. In contrast, he writes loads on socialism, citing specific facts, organizing them into arguments, etc. What we see here is none other than the leader/follower distinction: intellectually speaking, we may class our friendly AMAer as a 'leader' of Marxism and a follower of anti-HBD. He has thought independently about Marxism, but with regards to HBD he is simply going with expert consensus. On Marxism he has dug into the facts and can have an argument; he either knows it to be true or false but is otherwise sticking with it for personal reasons. But for HBD he knows only the expert consensus. He could not say first hand if it were true or false. In consequence there is no real discussion to be had about HBD with this poster. By definition, people are only equipped to defend ideologies which they may be classed as 'leaders' of. Linking a Vox or a Wikipedia article is just not an informed discussion. Those articles are not necessarily wrong, but by definition it isn't a discussion. People who are uninformed on HBD except for what the experts say about it are just not going to have a discussion about it because they obviously don't care enough about it to become capable of having an independent discussion about it. I for one am like this with many topics, for instance climate change. I know nothing about it either way and so I don't discuss it. This does lead to me being agnostic on the topic and staying completely silent; this is what people are complaining that most people who are nominally anti-HBD do. But it makes perfect sense to me: they don't care enough to debate the topic online, and since it's a dangerous topic, it obviously makes sense to give the socially expected answer if pressed. Such a person furthermore is unlikely to have many experiences that devalue "consensus," so instead of agnosticism they'll have slight agreement with anti-HBD because it's consensus. This is what I see in main subs a lot -- people who don't really care but kind of think it's mean to say IQ heritable and besides it's expert consensus that it isn't so just shut up and stop being racist okay? My point is that it's not really a mystery why they aren't here passionately debating with us. </p>
      <p>What about anti-HBD 'leaders' and those more active followers who would swear their life on anti-HBD yet seem to never debate it beyond perhaps an article or an tangential argument that race is a social construct? Well, tautologically speaking, if we have a 'follower' who is uninformed on HBD yet swears by it or against it, they are obviously dogmatically motivated to begin with. Of course they're not going to show up and have a hearty debate. This leaves the 'leaders.' What about the 'leaders?' This is where Turkheimer comes in. I see two possible answers: the leaders should be informed enough to know if HBD is true or not. Do anti-HBD leaders genuinely believe in their position, or are they motivated by something else? If the former, we can theorize that there may be less of them for some reason, or they may just be too bored to debate since they're in power (how often do you debate flat earthers? To someone who is highly informed and genuinely believes HBD is false, pro-HBD people are flat earthers). If the latter, then it's obvious that not debating is a tactic of sorts.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>