<post>
  <author>JuliusBranson</author>
  <date>2021-04-06T05:02:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mke4zb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_05_2021/gtje137/</link>
  <title>"I conclude that Turkheimer does not genuinely, descriptively believe in anti-HBD. He is motivated by something other than hard data."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>2/2</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Now I can go back to the Vox article that the AMAer linked. I want to understand Turkheimer, and reveal whether a forum frequenting amateur would love debating the topic if they knew what Turkheimer knew.</p>
      <p>Long story short, I don't want to reinvent the wheel. Someone already wrote an excellent <a href="https://cremieux.medium.com/is-eric-turkheimer-a-scientist-ed5850b028d1">analysis of this question</a> and concluded: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>He has committed himself to the misrepresentation of science, its history, and the actors within it, for clearly ideological reasons. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I urge you to read this whole article, for it is magnificent, but I will provide highlights: </p>
      <p>First Turkheimer has stated twice that he has the motive to obscure the truth regarding HBD: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>If it is ever documented conclusively, <strong>the genetic inferiority of a race on a trait as important as intelligence will rank with the atomic bomb as the most destructive scientific discovery in human history. The correct conclusion is to withhold judgment.</strong></p>
        <p>I should be clear that I am not making a “both sides do it” argument. <strong>It is the hereditarians who are trying to reach a strong and potentially destructive conclusion, and the burden is absolutely on them to demonstrate that they have a well-grounded empirical and quantitative theory to work with.</strong> So, if you are out there and think that group differences t [sic] are at least partially genetic, please explain exactly what you mean, in empirical terms.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Next, the Scarr-Rowe effect. Turkheimer likes to argue (this is in the Vox article) that the heritability of IQ correlates with SES positively, and that this implies that the black-white IQ gap is not caused by genetic differences. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The size of this effect is usually small and this literature is plagued by faulty methods and bad statistical reporting (most interactions, as in all fields, fail or are absurdly weak). Turkheimer (with Richard Nisbett and Paige Harden) implies that the Scarr-Rowe effect can explain some part of the racial gap in ability:</p>
        <blockquote>
          <p>The heritability of intelligence, although never zero, is markedly lower among American children raised in poverty. Several interpretations of this fact are possible. The one we find most persuasive is that children raised in those circumstances are unable to take full advantage of their genetic potential because they do not have access to the high-quality environments that could support it.</p>
        </blockquote>
        <p>It is implied that blacks show lower heritabilities because they are generally poorer than white Americans. However, the heritability of cognitive ability has been found to be essentially the same regardless of race in the US. This is an instance where Turkheimer is verifiably promoting fraud. He has done this more than once. In the article where he makes that quote — an article discussing racial differences — , he links to his 2003 Scarr-Rowe finding from the NCPP study. This finding has never replicated at this magnitude and is, in fact, by far the largest effect size in the literature on this subject. More importantly, however, is that this study did not find a Race x SES interaction and that Turkheimer knew this. Turkheimer also knows that the heritability of IQ, like many traits, increases with age — this is one confound he is confident in ignoring. Here’s the relevant table omitted from the cited study:</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The table is one that shows a) Turkheimer's data is from 4 and 7 year olds (this is totally unacceptable) and more importantly b) while he found a difference in heritability by SES (which never replicated to the degree he reported it), he found that there were no heritability differences by race. He is quoted showing that he knew this yet he never states this in his articles. In fact he generally just ignores data that contradicts his reasoning (which is fallacious), like that in The Bell Curve which shows that the IQ gap between blacks and whites persists at the highest SES levels. Turkheimer's reasoning is fallacious because he is essentially arguing that within group heritability implies something about between group heritability. He himself states that it is improper to do this, because heritability is typically reported to be high and so doing this typically results in claims that the between groups heritability is equally high. But his arguments are essentially obscure extensions of this fallacy. He argues that heritability is lower among the poor, more black people are poor, so the heritability of IQ among black people is on average lower than among white people (when directly tested this isn't even true, because the Scarr-Rowe effect is too weak and apparently not universal enough, but that's besides the point), so the heritability of the black-white IQ gap must be low, or even 0 as he attempts to argue in the Vox article. His statements on the Flynn effect, prominently featured in the Vox article, are also an obscured form of this fallacy. Nevermind the fact that the Flynn effect has nothing to do with the gap as it impacts both races equally: Turkheimer argues that since IQ has "risen" via the Flynn effect, heritability must be low, and so the black-white IQ gap must be low. Both implication steps here are non-sequiters. It makes no sense at all. </p>
      <p>He also just totally ... ignores the Minnesota Transracial Adoption Study. He ignores this while talking about within groups adoption studies showing poor people have lower IQ heritability, leaping from this fallaciously to predicting the opposite of what the MTRAS results were. Let me remind that this is in addition to ignoring the data in The Bell Curve on the black-white IQ gap at different SES's. Also in that Vox article they try to say the gap closed a bit, ignoring data <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22963424/">from 2012</a> stating otherwise, saying they are only aware of data from 2009, even though the article was written in 2017. </p>
      <p>Based on his biased comments and his non-sequiturs, I conclude that Turkheimer does not genuinely, descriptively believe in anti-HBD. He is motivated by something other than hard data. Since he is well informed, this suggests to me that <a href="/u/Ilforte">/u/Ilforte</a> is essentially correct: there is evaporative cooling. There are those who are uninformed and therefore cannot debate HBD, and there are those who become informed. Frankly, this analysis of Turkheimer and my own beliefs suggest that those become informed will become pro-HBD to some degree, because it is the side the evidence is more for. Those who do otherwise are biased against truth in some way -- of course they don't want to come on the forum of light and not heat and have their ideas be open for public scrutiny and so on. <a href="https://twitter.com/ent3c/status/1100396433453314049">It is more characteristic of such a mind to worry about giving pro-HBDers too much attention, anyway.</a></p>
      <p>I conclude that we have no "woke"/anti-HBD people here because pretty much no one interested in arguing for truth on an inconsequential internet forum is anti-HBD. Those who are anti-HBD are either informed like Turkheimer or just don't care enough to bother with politics in general. I think this solves the great mystery that has grasped this forum in the last week, and hopefully it is put to rest.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>