<post>
  <author>TheEgosLastStand</author>
  <date>2021-04-05T12:36:09Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mke4zb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_05_2021/gtg42xe/</link>
  <title>Chavin trial notes Week 4</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Derek Chauvin Trial Week 4: First Week of Testimony</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The first week of testimony is finished and it was <em>mostly</em> a boring week, especially the first half. The prosecution’s case-in-chief, thus far, has mostly been civilians who were on scene at the time of the incident and a few higher-level officers who got involved shortly after the incident when it became clear this was a fairly major incident. Some other witnesses included 911 dispatch and George Floyd’s former girlfriend, Courteney Ross, who testified a bit about her relationship with Floyd and their shared opiate addiction. </p>
      <p>But I want to start out briefly by responding to a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/mfj47c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_29_2021/gsuxc9j/">post</a> made in last week’s CW thread:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I find myself feeling sympathetic towards the defense in the Floyd trial. Part of it is that all of the witnesses' testimonies so far have been — in my opinion — useless (and awkward, rude when cross-examined). I feel like anyone who's seen the footage could be on the stand and give just as good information; we all know what happened. These people aren't really saying anything that could sway me one way or the other, and they seem to get easily flustered by defense attorney Nelson.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The witnesses’ testimony thus far has been largely for purposes of admitting evidence. Videos taken by bystanders, security cameras on the street, body-worn cameras from the officers. True that most people who have seen the video could have given a similar description, but they didn’t take the video and cannot testify to its reliability and, thus, they cannot be used to get the evidence admitted.</p>
      <p>I also don’t really understand what about this should be creating sympathy for the defense. These types of witnesses are part and parcel of every trial and witnesses get combative fairly often when cross-examined about, for example, what they don’t know or didn’t see or can’t actually conclude. This is just...run of the mill trial stuff. If anything, the fact that Nelson so easily flusters them (though I disagree he was flustering witnesses often, it was just every once in a while) means the defense is probably doing better than you think. It means he’s poking annoying holes in what some witnesses thought, assumed, or concluded. This may not mean anything ultimately, but clearly the defense had an attack plan.</p>
      <p>Onto the testimony. Here are some of the more fun/awkward/notable, though not necessarily consequential, highlights thus far:</p>
      <p>-One of the first witnesses was Donald Williams, an MMA fighter who happened to be walking by as the Floyd incident occurred. Nothing major really happened with his testimony, though he was granted some leeway to give expert testimony as to the choke Chauvin had Floyd in. Mostly, it was just entertaining to <a href="https://youtu.be/_Td8Wz1C8mQ?t=38">watch him and the defense attorney, Eric Nelson, duke it out</a>.</p>
      <p>-Another on-scene witness was Genevieve Hansen, an off-duty firefighter who also happened to be walking by at the time of the incident. She got into a couple small battles with the defense, leading to the first serious admonishment from the judge to a witness <a href="https://www.courttv.com/news/firefighter-blocked-from-helping-floyd-returns-to-stand/">at about 3:30 in this video</a>.</p>
      <p>-The final moment I’ll list here is from Charles McMillan, another bystander. After a few minutes of mostly foundational questions and normal and even slightly charismatic responses, the prosecution played the beginning of the incident for McMillan <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZsqJJTeA_q8">and he basically fell to pieces</a>. He seems like a sweet man so I felt bad for the guy. You can tell by his actions on scene that he was trying to help, but it was just not to be.</p>
      <p>Now for the more consequential stuff. The witnesses I expect the media are latching onto thus far are Sgt. Ploeger and Lt. Zimmerman, who testified on Thursday and into Friday. Both condemned Chauvin’s actions, though Ploeger’s condemnation was relatively minor imo. The money quote is on re-direct when he said <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2021/apr/01/derek-chauvin-supervisor-testimony-george-floyd">“[w]hen Mr. Floyd was no longer offering up any resistance to the officers they <em>could have</em> ended their restraint,”</a> (emphasis mine), and then he affirmed that “no longer offering up any resistance” meant after Floyd was handcuffed, on the ground, and no longer resisting. A condemnation of a sort, but not the kind of thing that will, on its own, make much of a difference in the outcome imo.</p>
      <p>Lt. Zimmerman was much stronger in his condemnation. <a href="https://www.kare11.com/article/news/local/george-floyd/derek-chauvin-trial-richard-zimmerman-minneapolis-police-lieutenant-george-floyd/89-4d499ddd-5b70-40c0-a654-3fe233b5c2e2">He testified that Chauvin’s placement of the knee on Floyd’s neck for so long after getting him to the ground was “totally unnecessary” and “uncalled for,” and that he saw no reason to believe the officers should have felt they were in danger, and that the restraint should have stopped once Floyd was on the ground and handcuffed.</a> The defense rebutted by challenging how long it’s been since Lt. Zimmerman has had to use force himself, how much use of force training has changed since 1985 when Zimmerman joined the Minneapolis police, and that he does not train individuals in use of force training, but I don’t know if that’s going to help much. Getting a lieutenant with 35 years of experience as an officer to condemn your actions with zero hesitation is going to weigh on the jurors’ minds quite a bit.</p>
      <p>One last thing I want to bring up is the body-worn camera footage from before the bystander footage that went viral—<a href="https://www.fox9.com/video/838956">specifically the footage from Officer Lane</a>. I don’t know if it had been released before the trial but I know I hadn’t seen it, and it’s definitely worth a watch. First, Officer Lane approaches Floyd as he is in a parked car. As Floyd opens the door, he is immediately kinda histrionic (and hardly ceases being histrionic throughout the whole encounter) about the officers and, presumably because he does not comply with the request to show both hands, Officer Lane pulls his gun out (~1:30 in the linked video). </p>
      <p>Lane holsters his gun shortly afterwards, but for the rest of the video the interaction between Floyd and police can only be described as <em>incredibly</em> annoying. Between the constant, fairly easy requests to, say, show his hands that are basically ignored, to Floyd’s almost-incoherent rambling, to the eventual <em>absolute refusal</em> to sit in the squad car (sprinkled with the occasional “I can’t breathe” looong before anyone applied any kind of hold), it’s no wonder this police encounter went horribly wrong. </p>
      <p>I would never say that Floyd deserved what happened, but...jesus fuck man. This encounter was pure insanity/stupidity/drugs. I can’t say I know what would have been the proper thing for police to have done that day with an obviously high and noncompliant George Floyd, but there were <em>plenty</em> of opportunities for this to have never happened. If Floyd had cooperated at any point during the roughly 4 minutes (in the linked video, from about 7 minutes in until 11:20) that police attempted to sit him in the squad car, we would have never heard his name. Floyd would have been charged with forgery or some similar crime, possibly resisting arrest, and maybe a tad more if they found drugs in the vehicle after impounding it, and he would likely have gotten some fairly minor punishment (in the grand scheme of things). Instead, his punishment is eternal. </p>
      <p>Do not resist the police when you are arrested. It sucks, your life may take a huge hit, and it may be unfair, but it isn’t worth what happened on Memorial Day 2020. Live to fight another day. And don’t do drugs. Okay, don’t do the <em>wrong type</em> of drugs. </p>
      <p>I have a lot more I want to write about but this is already getting long, so I’ll try to fit the other stuff in in future posts. Ultimately, it is still way too early to predict what’s going to happen, so hopefully we get more consequential witnesses (i.e., fights about the autopsy and Floyd’s pre-existing health conditions, as well as better experts on police use of force in this type of interaction) this week.</p>
      <p>edit: and to the people who gilded this post or have complimented me below for the effort, much love homies</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>