<post>
  <author>4bpp</author>
  <date>2021-01-24T04:23:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gkhruwr/</link>
  <title>QAnon as a Columbian disease exchange of memes</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Looking at some of the posts and interactions quoted in and linked from that sub, I get the impression that we are really looking at something like a Columbian disease exchange of memes. That is, a bunch of boomers and human-scale communitarians whose memetic immune system was utterly unprepared for it found themselves exposed to a set of seasoned imageboard users whose fabulation skills had evolved in a highly adversarial environment.</p>
      <p>To my eyes, the Q drops read as something very similar to the sort of serial posts that used to get popular on /b/ back in the days, like <a href="https://wiki.bibanon.org/Blindmute_Loli">the tale of anon taking in a blindmute loli</a>. These stories are good enough that Anon is willing to suspend disbelief and let his frozen heart be warmed by them for a while, all while retaining enough skepticism in the back of his head that he would know that it's probably fake if pressed and could not be convinced to donate his time and money to OP. The /pol/ veteran, likewise, probably found the ideas expressed in the Q drops rather heartwarming and was willing to suspend disbelief to bask in the warmth of imagining it to be true for the duration of a few threads, but would know better than to actually go to DC and get shot or arrested for it.</p>
      <p>These people are the memetic equivalent of smelly, pockmarked, plague-ridden conquistadors who just spent a month on a cramped boat, and that they ever made contact with <a href="/r/forwardsfromgrandma">grandma</a>'s virgin lands is a bit of a tragedy. I'd guess that the lockdowns meant that a lot of people who normally never would stray into their colony suddenly found themselves bored and spending a lot of time looking for vaguely sympathetic content on the internet, instead of, I don't know, golfing, hanging out in plastic chairs outside the town diner or going to the sports bar. (A lot of the reports on QAnonCasualties also independently made me think that the lockdowns can't have been good for these people's mental health.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>