<post>
  <author>cheesecakegood</author>
  <date>2021-01-25T15:47:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l4ii8x/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_25/gkptw1d/</link>
  <title>Whether Pax Americana ultimately ends as a result of military conflict, or lack of military conflict, over Taiwan</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>The moment America loses its place on top</strong>
      </p>
      <p>In 2023 or 2024, tensions have long been simmering and growing even more tense between the US and China. The war of words, initially decreasing, ramps up dramatically as the US accuses China of genocide, of brutal repression, of an imperialistic wish. China accuses the US of meddling in foreign affairs, of being a war worshipping evil force trying to keep the boot on the necks of half the world. Economically, sanctions begin to grow larger and larger as both sides are trapped in an ever escalating tit-for-tat, and eventually China begins taking financial actions that threaten the economy. </p>
      <p>But none of that is really so bad. None of that really spells the end. </p>
      <p>What is the tipping point? Taiwan. China has had swagger but nowhere to actually use it for years. Their online netizens have grown increasingly nationalistic and their belligerent opinions are more and more appearing in official state media. Secretary Xi in particular has never quite had a single large undeniable accomplishment to cement his legacy, and his generals are increasingly self confident. China has been amassing ships as a rate three times that of the US, taking months not years to build. Their cyber ops, sharpened by a wealth of practice, are honed. Across the massive size of China, airfields are built and stocked with a huge numerical advantage. All of China’s navy begins to assemble. </p>
      <p>What precipitated this? Who knows. Likely Congress made some move to recognize Taiwan a bit more fully. Perhaps a senior American figure visits the island. Perhaps Xi just figured it was time. Perhaps some false flag attack is staged and used as an excuse. </p>
      <p>For Chinese morale, reunification is an ultimate prize. Strategically, it’s the holy grail. Home to one of only two top chip manufacturers, an area China never could get started. Next to the South China Sea, an area rich in shipping and oil and also nationalistic claims. In fact a majority of the worlds shipping sails right past every day! Not only that, but Taiwan controls sea lanes that literally feed Japan and are crucial to South Korea as well, giving China a massive unequaled regional lever. </p>
      <p>The US actually has no treaty obligating it to defend Taiwan. Partisan bickering still plagues America. The call is made not to try to attack Guam and other US installations, even if it would make strategic sense, because China counts on US apathy. As long as no Americans die, they figure most of the US is war weary and doesn’t see any reason to help. </p>
      <p>The old wisdom was that an attack would be telegraphed in advance, that it would be all difficult amphibious landings, and China is inexperienced. But that’s the old world. </p>
      <p>When Russia took Crimea, they showed off a newer way to do things that leverages confusion, plays up local desire for reunification, and integrates many branches. Although buildup is seen in advance, China pretends it is another training exercise. Politically no one wants to believe it. Congress can’t quite commit to a course of action. Taiwan has a military that has a couple fancy weapons but practically no ammo, logistics are in shambles, and the reservists literally fire one magazine of rifle ammo once a year to “practice”. </p>
      <p>The island is hit by crippling cyber attacks. Communications are almost completely down. News is difficult. Panic sets in. Reservists struggle to go to the right places as leadership goes to the bunkers. Sleeper saboteurs begin to hurt key infrastructure. Air dominance is quickly achieved by China, despite all the AA, by a combo of hacking and massed missiles China stockpiled for years. Turns out mechanics and parts are in short supply and half of Taiwan’s Air Force can’t even get in the air. </p>
      <p>After the first day or two, after air dominance is achieved but before US assets can make a decision or fully deploy to the region, and in some cases before, mass airdrops occur. Reservists struggle to get to their assigned positions as roads are crammed with traffic and panicked civilians. Amphibious landings are attempted but most troops are brought in via helicopter by China’s fleet that has been built for this very purpose over the last seven years. Confusion reigns in Taiwan as units desert, Chinese appear to be everywhere, leaders are assassinated, morale plummets. China gets some puppet, perhaps even a leader in the pro-China political wing to go on air and announce a surrender. And that’s it. It’s over. At the end of the day most European countries never wanted to get involved even from the beginning. Sharply worded condemnations are issued but everyone knows, from Germany to Japan, that trade links are just too important to jeopardize over some people half a world away that cannot be realistically helped. </p>
      <p>And just like that, the Neville Chamberlains of the world allow a robust democracy to fall. China is a nuclear power and can do whatever it wants. Although no more invasions are coming, it’s clear to everyone that the US is no longer the top dog militarily, and that their interest in foreign intervention is at an all time low. The world order since 1945 has collapsed. </p>
      <p>I predict that Taiwan will be forcibly reunified within the next five years, with 80% certainty. Everything is there: the motive, the rhetoric, the means, the political opportunity, the ego of Chinese generals and Xi himself, the complacency of the West, the political unpopularity of truly effective defensive asymmetrical defensive measures by Taiwan, the false outdated assumptions about the way war will be fought. The only thing holding them back is how big a gamble it is! But if their own military feels confident, if the US has stood by while its allies have been bullied for years, the perceived cost drops dramatically and so does the likelihood rise.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>