<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2021-01-26T02:57:33Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l4ii8x/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_25/gks7k0g/</link>
  <title>What "learn to code" looks like on a wetware substrate</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I’m not sure it’s downsizing exactly, but it does reflect the needs of the commercial world. Ask yourself: what kind of jobs do successful English literature graduates from mid-ranking universities go on to do? The vast majority will not become academics or curators or publishers for whom knowledge of Chaucer might be genuinely valuable. Most will go off into careers in HR, law, maybe marketing. In all of these careers, knowledge of the Ways of Woke is genuinely valuable, and vastly more valuable than knowledge of Middle English literature.</p>
      <p>This kind of thing seems to me like an almost inevitable adjustment to the surge in higher education participation over the last forty or so years. If only 10% of the population are doing academic undergraduate degrees, then you can afford to make the relevant course material pure signal, focusing on challenging, erudite, and high status material. That 10% will go on to be the knowledge economy elite, and specific immediate marketable skills won’t be all that important because they’ve demonstrated their smarts simply by attending university in the first place (compare the way management consultancies aggressively recruit upper level students from elite universities today, often with scant consideration of their specific academic background). But in a world where 50% of young people go on to university, the signal of university attendance has limited value in itself, and additionally the teaching of difficult material will typically have been dumbed down to the point that it doesn’t signal all that much. You’re no longer dealing with the knowledge elite, but the knowledge middle class, and actually having marketable skills is critical for them. And they and employers will explicitly or implicitly prompt low- and mid-level universities to tailor their offerings appropriately.</p>
      <p>A common cry - especially among the STEM crowd - is that people who do ‘useless’ degrees shouldn’t be shocked when they find themselves unable to find meaningful employment. Hence the ‘learn to code’ meme. Learning to navigate racially charged topics, familiarising yourself with key buzzwords and concepts, being able to identify problematic phrases or assumptions in a text - <strong>this is just what ‘learn to code’ looks like in the humanities.</strong> These skills have real added value for lots of knowledge workers in the modern world, so it’s not surprising that a mid-level university is choosing to teach courses that will provide these skills. Of course, the specific focus on race is a function of our current political climate, but in previous decades it’d probably be something else - sustainability, environmentalism, American values, or just the complex web of micro-norms proper to a given profession.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>