<post>
  <author>professorgerm</author>
  <date>2021-01-20T15:17:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gjy92jt/</link>
  <title>Why Williamson's comments about the "White American" would not fly in any other context</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>What can a reader that vaguely agrees say that doesn't end up where Williamson is, minus the scorn? What's different between "you're scum you need a uHaul" and "buddy, injecting more cash into a place that isn't doing anything is never going to make it self-sufficient, you need a uHaul".</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <em>Literally anything else than what he said</em>. </p>
      <p>Williamson is cruel, hateful monster who'd be crucified if he talked about any similar community this way, and he only gets a pass out of <em>racism and ignorance</em>. <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xp3n1t">Appalachia is a resource colony.</a></p>
      <p>Would you say "great, accurate read" if someone wrote that about, say, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exploitation_colonialism">British India</a>, or any number of African (ex-)colonies? I think <a href="/u/2cimarafa">/u/2cimarafa</a> might bite that bullet, but would you? Or maybe I'm wrong, and both of you would claim there's something <em>uniquely evil and corrupted</em> about the souls of rural and Rust Belt poor- which, keep in mind despite Williamson's poisoned spewing, are not just white. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The only thing that is going to help people is for them to be part of a productive enterprise that does <em>something</em> that is useful </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Yeah, how's that work out for the inner-city poor? They're all fulfilled and overjoyed working as fry cooks barely able to make rent, or commuting hours to scrub toilets, right? Are hotel maids and customer cashiers known for achieving enlightenment, and I never knew?</p>
      <p>There is also a question of choice, here. About living the life one wants. <strong>I am deeply familiar with how broken rural resource-colony cultures are</strong>, but I also know many people in such cultures that are <em>content</em>, that get to live a life they want. Should they pack up that Uhaul: no more 4-wheeling across mountains; no more hunting; no more shootin' just for the hell of it; no more <em>anything</em> outside the urban steel and glass scape. Before, that was just "the backyard;" once you're in the city it's an expensive effort to do all that.</p>
      <p>Don't underestimate just how much "pack up the Uhaul" sounds good <em>specifically</em> to you because that's the life you want and the life in which you thrive, whereas they, likely as not, would still be lacking the necessary traits and would just be the same suicidal and drug-addicted people, somewhere else.</p>
      <p>I think the <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/av/uk-39293519">Somewhere versus Anywhere</a> distinction is important here. If they are <em>Somewhere people</em>, and that's what ties them to a failed place, you can't just transplant them and expect them to thrive. They are not just in the wrong environment; <em>their environment has died</em> just like the Great Lakes were, for a couple decades, lifeless. The world that could support them is gone; moving them to a city would be like slapping an endangered species in a zoo.</p>
      <p>I assume you are an Anywhere, more or less, and thus a transplant to the city sounds fine. I do think that term is flawed because "Anywhere" isn't quite accurate- such people have a selection of cities that have blurred together in many ways; it's not <em>literally</em> Anywhere like some #vanlife, but rather a type of cosmopolitan.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>without qualification in front of my blue tribe friends </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Would they even care, if you're talking about rednecks?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>