<post>
  <author>Tilting_Gambit</author>
  <date>2021-01-26T06:09:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l4ii8x/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_25/gksqdon/</link>
  <title>An in-depth look at possible military conflict in Taiwan</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Edit: Here we go. The Taiwan conversation I've been waiting for. In short, all the issues raised by <a href="/u/KulakRevolt">/u/KulakRevolt</a> are good considerations, but massively counter-balanced by the appropriate military <a href="https://www.google.com/imgres?imgurl=http%3A%2F%2Fcdn.statcdn.com%2FInfographic%2Fimages%2Fnormal%2F3471.jpeg&amp;imgrefurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.statista.com%2Fchart%2F3471%2Fthe-military-imbalance-in-the-taiwan-strait%2F&amp;tbnid=HojsOt9JX_FzCM&amp;vet=12ahUKEwiL_-qmyLnuAhUMUysKHSYwBjIQMygCegUIARCpAQ..i&amp;docid=nxLN1SeGRsgyiM&amp;w=1200&amp;h=1200&amp;q=size%20of%20chinese%20military%20vs%20taiwan&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiL_-qmyLnuAhUMUysKHSYwBjIQMygCegUIARCpAQ">reference class</a>. If left to their own devices, Taiwan will fall <em>rapidly</em> against a Chinese invasion. The entire defence of Taiwan rests on the ability of the US Navy to contest Chinese air superiority. For the below, I will ignore potential US involvement (that wargame is for a different thread!) I'll try to summarise this as best I can, but there's a LOT more background info that goes into this. </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Geography</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Taiwan’s east coast is mostly comprised of cliffs overlooking the ocean. The west coast is composed of mudflats, some beaches and major population hubs, with less than 20% of the coast accessible by amphibious landing craft.  The island’s interior can be divided roughly into two sections:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>The mountainous Chung-Yang Range which runs from north-south along the centre and east coast of the island (two-thirds of the island’s interior).    </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The flat farmlands that run across the west coast and are home to most of the Taiwanese population (a third of the island’s interior).  </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Rainfall is persistent in Taiwan, with rainstorms and typhoons common. Winters are short, lasting from December to February, and rainfall is less severe than the May - October wet season. In any military engagement, it is likely that the Chinese would opt for a winter military operation to avoid the reductions in ground, air and naval mobility likely to result from wet weather and rainfall.  </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Military</strong>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>China</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The Chinese military is divided into six separate services organised under five theatre commands. The Eastern Theatre Command (ETC) retains control over the geographic area around Taiwan and the East China Sea, and would almost certainly be the main contributor to a military engagement with Taiwan. ETC is composed of three army groups, with a full ORBAT breakdown available <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Theater_Command">here</a>, or a detailed read <a href="https://media.defense.gov/2020/Sep/01/2002488689/-1/-1/1/2020-DOD-CHINA-MILITARY-POWER-REPORT-FINAL.PDF">here</a>.  Chinese Group Armies are <em>corps sized formations</em>, and the ETC retains six full infantry divisions, supported by two armoured divisions and smaller formations.  </p>
      <p>The key components of the ETC’s ground forces are the amphibious units (two independent marine brigades and the amphibious division), who would almost certainly spearhead any military operation against Taiwan. Follow up troops are likely to consist of motorised infantry and armour to quickly expand and break-out of a beachhead, making the 72nd Group Army a likely candidate for first-wave activities. </p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://jamestown.org/program/snapshot-chinas-eastern-theater-command/#:%7E:text=An%20overview%20of%20China's%20Eastern,military's%20current%20capabilities%20against%20Taiwan.&amp;text=Although%20eastern%20China%20is%20one,been%20its%20primary%20strategic%20direction.">ETC’s air assets are composed of four fighter divisions, a bomber division, a UAV brigade and various ground-based defence subunits</a>.  Modernisation of ETC’s air assets has been a high priority for the Chinese, with new J-20s being deployed to this command before any other.  Air force exercises have been heavily emphasised in this theatre, with fighters, bombers and intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance (ISR) assets conducting operations to simulate support for amphibious landings.  <a href="https://www.rand.org/pubs/research_reports/RR392.html">Some analysts</a> now rate the Chinese Air Force  (PLAAF) as maintaining a local “parity” in air superiority and penetration with the USAF.  Additionally, it is assessed that a “frontloading” of air assets will be shifted to ETC in the event of a planned military engagement. This will provide overwhelming air support for Chinese ground troops as they conduct amphibious operations, and conduct air-superiority operations to defend the Chinese mainland (alternatively, these activities will be a key indicator/warning for US/Taiwanese intelligence agencies). </p>
      <p>The PRC now maintains the largest navy in the world (350 ships and submarines, vs the US Navy’s 293) and is <a href="https://media.defense.gov/2020/Sep/01/2002488689/-1/-1/1/2020-DOD-CHINA-MILITARY-POWER-REPORT-FINAL.PDF">rapidly replacing older vessels with modern, multi-role vessels</a>. The East Sea Fleet maintains 11 destroyers, 18 frigates, 10 corvettes and 7 submarines (for comparison, the forward deployed <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Seventh_Fleet">US 7th Fleet maintains 10-14 destroyers and cruisers, 8-12 submarines and an aircraft carrier</a>).  Importantly, the fleet has 15 landing ships, with uplift capacities ranging from 200-800 troops. At full speed in calm seas, these landing ships could reach the Penghu archipelago from Fujian bases in <em>approximately 8-9 hours.</em></p>
      <p>
        <strong>Taiwan</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The ROC Army consists of three corps and five independent commands (approx. brigade to corps sized) responsible for the defence of their respective island locations. <a href="https://www.routledge.com/Defending-Taiwan-The-Future-Vision-of-Taiwans-Defence-Policy-and-Military/Edmonds-Tsai/p/book/9781138879041">The mechanised brigades are equipped with M113 APCs and the armoured brigades are mostly equipped with M60A3 tanks</a>.  Both vehicles are aging, with the M60s unlikely to check Chinese ground troops equipped with basic AT weapons. In addition to these forces, the ROC maintains a Reserve Command, with nine active infantry brigades and 24 reserve brigades that would be activated in wartime. </p>
      <p>If the Chinese launch a military operation, the main Taiwanese defensive strategy calls for a “<a href="https://media.defense.gov/2019/May/02/2002127082/-1/-1/1/2019_CHINA_MILITARY_POWER_REPORT.pdf">decisive battle in littoral zone, and destruction of enemy at landing beach</a>”.  This underlines the <em>entire</em> Taiwanese defensive operation, making responsiveness and readiness the primary focus of training and equipment acquisition programs. The Taiwanese understand that if Chinese troops establish a beachhead, their superior numbers and technological superiority will likely allow for an eventual breakout, whereby Taiwanese defences will unravel rapidly. </p>
      <p>The ROC Air Force (ROCAF) maintains 400 combat aircraft, consisting of F-16s, Mirage 2000s, F-5E/Fs and locally built Indigenous Defense Fighters. Additionally, the ROCAF employ the P-3Cs and E-2 Airborne Early Warning (AEW) / ISR role. <a href="https://project2049.net/2020/09/01/preparing-for-the-nightmare-readiness-and-ad-hoc-coalition-operations-in-the-taiwan-strait/">All of these aircraft have faced considerable logistic, maintenance and budgetary constraints which have reduced the ability for pilots to meet flight hour requirement, as well as reduce the amount of time assets can maintain surveillance over the local seas</a>.  It is likely that the PLAAF will quickly achieve air superiority over the aging ROCAF air fleet. </p>
      <p>The ROC Navy (ROCN) can marshal four destroyers, 20 frigates, 4 submarines and various other vessels. Of note, the ROCN has deferred the mid-life upgrades of the major surface combatants in the fleet, leaving them outdated. Additionally, the four submarines are old and mostly defunct.  The fleet maintains some modern surface-to-air missiles, purchased from the USA, as well as surface-surface missiles. It would not be an exaggeration to assert that the ROC are <em>basically</em> assuming the US will fulfil the naval role in any potential conflict and are redirecting their limited funding elsewhere.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>