<post>
  <author>toegut</author>
  <date>2021-01-24T03:13:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gkhkujl/</link>
  <title>Why the "color-blind" paradigm of federal science grants may be coming to an end</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Biden has appointed to the second-highest science post in his administration a sociologist, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alondra_Nelson">Alondra Nelson</a>, who has a PhD in American studies. This has been praised by <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-00159-z?utm_source=twt_nnc&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_campaign=naturenews&amp;sf242224981=1"><em>Nature</em></a> (which has gone rather woke):</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>During his presidential campaign, Joe Biden pledged that his administration would address inequality and racism. Now that he’s been sworn in as US president, his appointment of a prominent sociologist to the nation’s top science office is raising hopes that the changes will extend to the scientific community.</p>
        <p>“I think that if we want to understand anything about science and technology, we need to begin with the people who have been the most damaged, the most subjugated by it, but who also, out of that history, are often able to be early adopters and innovators,” Nelson told The Believer magazine in a January 2020 interview.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>As <em>Nature</em> points out, Nelson is not the first social scientist in this position: under Obama it was occupied by Thomas Kalil, a political scientist, who published articles on <a href="https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/blog/author/thomas-kalil">"S&amp;T policy, the use of prizes as a tool for stimulating innovation, nanotechnology, [...], the National Information Infrastructure, distributed learning, and electronic commerce"</a>.</p>
      <p>The new appointee, Nelson, started her career as a professor of African American Studies and Sociology at Yale. Subsequently she was a professor of Sociology and Gender Studies at Columbia where she directed the Institute for Research on Women, Gender, and Sexuality, was the founding co-director of the Columbia University Women's, Gender, and Sexuality Council and helped to establish several initiatives, such as the Atlantic Fellows for Racial Equity program at Columbia. In her 23-year academic career she has published <a href="https://www.ias.edu/sites/default/files/sss/pdfs/Nelson/nelson-cv-july-2019.pdf">11 refereed journal articles and 2 books</a> which helped her get the aforementioned appointments at Yale, Columbia, and finally the chair of Social Sciences at Princeton's Institute of Advanced Study.</p>
      <p>Her original appointment at Yale came on the heels of her editing a special 2002 issue of <em>Social Text</em> dedicated to Afrofuturism. <em>Social Text</em> is an academic journal which became infamous for publishing in the 1990s a nonsense article on "the hermeneutics of quantum gravity" which was submitted by a physicist, Alan Sokal, as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sokal_affair">hoax to reveal the vapidity of intellectual discourse in some academic fields</a>. In Nelson's <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/social-text/article/20/2%20(71)/1/32617/IntroductionFUTURE-TEXTS">introduction to the Afrofuturism edition</a>, she writes:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>That  race  (and  gender)  distinctions  would  be  eliminated  with  technology  was  perhaps  the  founding  fiction  of  the  digital  age.  The  raceless future  paradigm,  an  adjunct  of  Marshall  McLuhan’s  “global  village” metaphor,  was  widely  supported  by  (and  made  strange  bedfellows  of ) pop visionaries, scholars, and corporations from Timothy Leary to Allucquère Rosanne Stone to MCI. Spurred by “revolutions” in technoscience,social and cultural theorists looked increasingly to information technology,especially the Internet and the World Wide Web, for new paradigms. We might  call  this  cadre  of  analysts  and  boosters  of  technoculture,  who stressed the unequivocal novelty of identity in the digital age, neocritics. Seemingly  working  in  tandem  with  corporate  advertisers,  neocritics argued that the information age ushered in a new era of subjectivity and insisted that in the future the body wouldn’t bother us any longer. There was a peculiar capitalist logic to these claims, as if writers had taken up the marketing argot of “new and improved.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This may sound familiar to many followers of SSC as technoutopianism is still attacked for its supposed erasure of race and gender identities. Nelson deconstructs "the raceless future  paradigm"  after the collapse of the dot-com bubble. She then outlines the emergence of Afrofuturism, writing:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The AfroFuturism list emerged at a time when it was difficult to find discussions  of  technology  and  African  diasporic  communities  that  went beyond the notion of the digital divide. From the beginning, it was clear that  there  was  much  theoretical  territory  to  be  explored.  Early  discussions included the concept of digital double consciousness; African diasporic  cultural  retentions  in  modern  technoculture;  digital  activism  and issues of access; dreams of designing technology based on African mathematical principles; the futuristic visions of black film, video, and music;the  implications  of  the  then-burgeoning  MP3  revolution;  and  the  relationship between feminism and Afrofuturism.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I am curious what Nelson views as "African mathematical principles" for designing new technology and whether she will be recommending them in her role as a deputy director of the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy. Perhaps an enterprising senator may ask this during her confirmation hearing.</p>
      <p>Now, to be fair, Nelson has seemingly moved on in her career from Afrofuturism to writing a book on <em>"The Social Life of DNA: Race, Reparations, and Reconciliation after the Genome"</em> where she discusses (among other topics) how <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/1468-4446.12607">colleges and universities can exercise "institutional morality" to remedy structural racism by engaging in 'reconciliation projects'</a>. She argues that because of "the inextricable links between edification and bondage" colleges and universities should undergo <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/1468-4446.12612">"a radical shift to the creation of an anti‐racist institution"</a>. She explicitly condemns the "colour‐blind racial paradigm" of the Human Genome Project:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Forgetting and masking are characteristic of this ideology. On the one hand, this paradigm frames racism as ‘a remnant of the past’ and, therefore, something to be forgotten; on the other hand, the colour‐blind paradigm obscures structural discrimination–‘the deeply rooted institutional practices and long‐term disaccumulation that sustains racial inequality’ (Brown et al. 2006:37). The commercialization of genomics activates and reinforces the pernicious dynamics of the genetics of race, privileging essentialist ways of knowing and being classified by Roth such as ascription and phenotype. At the same time, however, other, potentially benevolent ‘dimensions’ of race are also given voice through the practice of genetic genealogy, such as self‐classification and ancestral identity. It is in this heterodox milieu a prevailing racial paradigm and racial multidimensionality, that the logic of using novel applications of genomics to recover, debate and reconcile accounts of the past takes shape. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>So it seems likely to me that the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy will look to dismantle the color-blind paradigm in research very soon. I feel sorry for the mottizens in biological sciences now. I suggest becoming familiar with the lingo of "racial multidimensionality" and avoiding "essentialist ways of knowing" in your grant proposals.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>