<post>
  <author>WestphalianPeace</author>
  <date>2021-01-22T10:07:35Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l2bytu/ethiopias_government_appears_to_be_wielding/gk5uhpo/</link>
  <title>Starvation as a means of war</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>If anyone has an archived link it to share of this it would be greatly appreciated.</p>
      <p>Starvation as a means of war appears to be the low-tech solution to the problem of the power imbalance between rebels with high morale vs government forces with low morale. </p>
      <p>Even after spending the necessary treasure to build an army capable of fighting rebel groups all the money in the world can't buy a willingness to stand a fight. I cannot forget the Iraqi troops fleeing from the dedicated ISIS fighters on a "Blitzkrieg by Technical". But while it can be hard to get low morale troops to fight offensively it is a more reachable goal to get them to at least not abandon their posts Iraqi style. </p>
      <p>And as the government you risk a lot of prestige if you attack and fail. For example it's no exaggeration to say that Saudi Arabia's war in Yemen has been absolutely humiliating for Saudi. There are scores of videos of one of the wealthiest nations on earth using the latest equipment getting their convoys blown up and artillery positions overrun by rebel groups with barely a sliver of their resources. Emaciated khat-chewers with nothing more than small arms and a few RPGs holding against one of the richest nations on earth with an army that's supposedly been preparing for war vs Iran for decades now. And the khat-chewers were winning. For a time there was even a real risk that they would cross over into Saudi Arabia and take Najran. They at least held the mountains overlooking for an uncomfortable amount of time for Saudi. </p>
      <p>So instead of continuing to be humiliated the Saudi's took a different approach. They'd just starve the entire country. Why reveal your weakness to the world and risk potential domestic political backlashes from failed offenses? So they didn't move in troops to fight in the crowded cities. They had the UAE take Aden and they blocked the only remaining port of significance, Hudaydah, and pursued a strategy of starvation and bombing.   </p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2020/05/the-war-nerd-how-many-dead-yemeni-nobodies-does-it-take-to-equal-1-wapo-contributor.html">https://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2020/05/the-war-nerd-how-many-dead-yemeni-nobodies-does-it-take-to-equal-1-wapo-contributor.html</a>
      </p>
      <p>As WarNerd points out, starvation works. It worked in Biafra</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://pando.com/2014/05/17/the-war-nerd-nigerias-inevitable-mess/">https://pando.com/2014/05/17/the-war-nerd-nigerias-inevitable-mess/</a>
      </p>
      <p>where the Nigerians couldn't win a military victory and so starved out the Biafrans. 2 million dead later and Biafra is now a nation forgotten.</p>
      <p>And it's working in Yemen where the Saudi's can just sit back and wait for Yemen to starve for as long as it takes for them to crack. Since implementing a starvation strategy Saudi's bad press has disappeared. No international backlash, no revealed weakness, no domestic consequences from military failures.</p>
      <p>The point of this rambling is that if the Ethiopian government is pursuing a strategy of starvation then we should not be surprised. Starvation works. It's a great means of war to pursue when up against a stubborn enemy when all you have is low quality troops. And no one is going to invade Ethiopia to stop this, so pursuing this strategy basically guarantees the government will succeed so long as it has the political will to follow through to the end. Everyone should expect that this war can only end with a government victory. It's only a question of how much horror innocent people will endure before that inevitable victory arrives.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>