<post>
  <author>xX69Sixty-Nine69Xx</author>
  <date>2021-01-20T22:50:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gjzy4zi/</link>
  <title>Urban development and planning in Houston versus Austin</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The Houston metro (not just COH - I could go into detail on where the blame lies on Houston where the blame lies on Harris/surrounding Counties but frankly I write about this shit all day for work and don't want to spend too much time on it here) is too lax. You generally want pretty lax development laws, but the exceptions to that you do want to make have to do with safety and environmental factors. Houston is built on a swamp and has what is easily the worst weather for any major city in the US, at least in terms of how likely it is to kill you. It floods in Houston often enough that is barely makes the news when it does.</p>
      <p>Part of the reason why it floods so much is that we've basically paved over all the swampland that would normally help soak up a lot of rain when it is storming. So this has made several previously flood-safe neighborhoods prone to destructive flooding. And a lot of the areas in the Houston metro we've paved over were never going to be safe for human development - they regularly got destroyed every few years by a major flood before suburban track development really ramped up. Its even worse now.</p>
      <p>Then there is just the scale to which Houston is spread out. I do think it is smart for governments to subsidize some level of density and public transit. I understand why Houstons suburbs are desirable - they're cheap and the schools are decent - but the city sprawls so much that the tradeoff you make for living out there is an 1hr+ daily commute and 15 minutes minimum of driving to do mundane chores/leisure activities. That is a <em>lot</em> of time spent in a car, especially in a city notorious for bad driving. The combination of stress, sitting on your ass, and injuries from wrecks is surely putting a major dent in QALY. I get the appeal of suburbia and why people want single family housing, but that needs to be done practically and with the consideration of what will build a healthier and happier city as a whole. This means some people will just have to make do with letting their kids play in public parks... which frankly seems like more fun to kids for me, but what do I know.</p>
      <p>Houston's sprawl is a tragedy of the commons that causes regular rounds of billions in flood damage and an unhealthy sedentary lifestyle.</p>
      <p>BUT on the other hand Houston is easy to build in. So unlike other major cities, its managed skyrocketind demand to live in it fairly well. The inner loop is densifying at an astounding rate, which is thankfully keeping supply and demand in line. This is because its pretty easy to just buy up land and do what you want with it here - city officials are historically insensitive to nonsense about neighborhood character.</p>
      <p>We can compare this to Austin. Austin is a slightly different scenario because of geographic factors. It doesnt have functionally unlimited flat land to expand into, but it still has quite a bit of flat land to expand into. And, like Houston, there is still TONS of poorly utilized land 5 minutes from downtown thats developed like a suburban single family neighborhood, not a mixed use city neighborhood. But Austin buys into culture warring hard, so like San Francisco, development gets tied up pretty often by NIMBYs whining about neighborhood character and champagne socialists mad at the prospect of developers making money. Not to mention more basic and mundane problems with its development laws just intentionally making development harder than it needs to be. Thankfully it is not as easy to tie things up in Austin as in SF, and the Austin city government seems to be more inclined towards pro-market reforms. But the difference in Austins policies have clearly done their damage: it is now considerably more expensive than Houston despite Houston being a frankly better city by most metrics (larger economy, better pay on average, pro sports, internationally ranked museums and performing arts, better restaurants, more diversity, basically everything besides being desirable for bachelorette parties).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>