<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-06-06T08:38:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/nowgdg/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_31_2021/h0ryfqs/</link>
  <title>Free Cosmetic Surgery: It'll Improve Everyone's Lives</title>
  <category>
    <li>flux</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Gender dysphoria is a condition that trans activists generally believe is genetic or at least develops early in childhood, and for which the only viable treatment is HRT and (in almost all cases) surgery to alter the dysphoric person's physical appearance in order to correct the problem [by matching their perceived gender expression]. For this reason, trans campaigners have argued (successfully) that HRT, GRS and - increasingly - FFS/FMS (facial surgery) should be funded by state healthcare and/or insurance depending on country. </p>
      <p>Facial ugliness is no less genetic - indeed unlike gender dysphoria it is scientifically <em>proven</em> (except in cases of accidents/injury, in which insurance already does cover surgery) to be purely genetic. Being forced to live, absolutely faultlessly, with an ugly face is a clear injustice, one which the wealthy already do correct. Society<sup>TM</sup> funds many programmes designed to help disadvantaged people become wealthier, old people retire with financial security, and people who suffer from gender dysphoria (in many countries) to transition. It seems strange, then, that medical insurance or national healthcare schemes do not cover facial cosmetic surgery for objectively ugly people, who suffer a cruel injustice in every interaction they have with other people, through no fault of their own. </p>
      <hr />
      <p>One could actually take this one step further. Being ugly, in a wealthy developed country in which there is no fear of starvation/having to prostitute oneself etc.. is probably <em>worse</em> than being poor, except in cases of extreme wealth imbalance (eg. yes, we'd all rather be very very rich and moderately ugly than poor and moderately attractive). </p>
      <p>But compare, say, a lower middle class incredibly attractive person (97th percentile of looks, 35th percentile household income - ie. around $46k) to an upper middle class ugly person (20th percentile looks, 97th percentile household income - ie. around $300k). I actually think the former, who finds it incredibly easy to make friends in all their social circles, who has the natural confidence of genuine beauty, who never worries about rejection, and who glides through life in the way that all truly attractive people do, probably lives a better - or at least richer, fuller - life. The 'Halo Effect' ensures they're viewed as competent and capable; the acceptance of others creates confidence which begets charm and other social skills. And because being part of communities that like and accept us is central to human happiness, they're more likely to be happy, too. 97th percentile looks also afford any even remotely intelligent person an easy way into higher tiers of income, if that's what they want. </p>
      <p>Beauty is central to acceptance of ourselves and the enjoyment of life. And we all want to live in a more aesthetically beautiful society, presumably. Seeing ugly people is a drag. And they themselves are (once again, generally through little fault of their own) damned for no real reason. Offering them free cosmetic surgery won't just improve their lives, it'll improve everyone's.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>