<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-06-08T12:46:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/nu5kvj/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_07_2021/h10tbam/</link>
  <title>He Doesn’t Believe His People Can Be Redeemed at All</title>
  <category>
    <li>flux</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Unz has the characteristic of a lot of smart people on the politically radical fringe who’ve spent a long time there (and he’s spent upwards of 20 or 25 years there now) where they go in thinking that they’re obviously never going to believe the ‘really stupid’ shit, at least not without significantly better evidence, only to eventually find themselves persuaded by the sheer volume of argument, pressed home over decades, made by so many people in their sphere. His ideological evolution was slow but unidirectional, driven as much by his own commenters as the people he hired to write for him. (There was a time he was more liberal than the majority of his writers, in recent years many have begun to distance themselves from him because he’s probably the most extreme writer on the site, or at least in the top couple). </p>
      <p>Unz is Jewish, and so had the same three* ideological positions open to him that all Jews on the dissident (or alt) right have. </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>A kind of often-almost-trolling ethnic chauvinism of the “goys mad lmao” variety that one often sees among legit Israelis on /pol/ and, more seriously, among many Jews active on the dissident right. This may or may not involve ‘acknowledgment’ of some rightist complaints about some Jews (or even agreement since people like Soros often push the same policies in Israel that they do elsewhere) , but essentially counters that yeah, all peoples are out for themselves, no take backs, we won, nuclear armed ethnostate FTW, <em>am Yisrael chai</em> (etc)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Denial and/or deliberate ignorance. This either involves laborious, Nathan Cofnas-esque arguments that attempt to defend Jewry against apparently libelous claims made by various antisemitic reactionaries, or - slightly less often - simply a refusal to discuss “it”, whether for reasons of propriety, alleged perceived or unconscious ethnic self interest, or simply lack of interest in general. Moldbug, for example, refuses to discuss it. Other Jewish online reactionaries who take similar approaches might briefly mention and dismiss it, or might pull a Cofnas and really try to go to battle.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Agreement and resulting descent into self-hatred. Every Jew on the dissident right will eventually (sooner, rather than later) come across long effortposts/collages/lists of actions by Jews allegedly responsible for various things rightists dislike about our present society. We’ve already discussed several possible responses to these - the <em>chauvinist ‘Yes, and’,</em> which requires ethnic loyalty (zionism), a fondness for one’s people, <em>denial/argument</em>, which would hardly endear Unz to his antisemitic audience - who would relentlessly assault his points in the comments section and generally call him all kinds of nasty things, <em>ignorance/lack of interest</em>, which would cause the same thing because antisemitic gentiles tend to demand Jewish reactionary writers discuss it at one point or another, and - lastly - <em>acceptance/embrace</em>, which is what Unz does.</p>
          <p>If you are Jewish and believe, as Unz does, that Jews are responsible for practically every bad thing (in his opinion) that has happened to America over the last century, and (unlike chauvinists/zionists) don’t believe this to be understandable or even reasonable in any way except as evidence of absolute, unjustified hostility towards western civilization / whites, and your own relationship to your Jewish identity is frayed or hostile (Unz was abandoned by his Israeli professor father, while his mother, a leftist anti-war activist, decided to have him out of wedlock and raised him as a poor single mother), then it doesn’t seem too surprising that Unz might just...agree with his commentators that his own people (for whom he clearly has contempt) have the aims which they often attach to them. </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>Unz is a sad case, more radical even than most leftist self-hating whites of the Robin diAngelo school, who at least seem to believe in a future in which whites can/will be ‘redeemed’ by ‘smashing white supremacy’ or whatever. Unz doesn’t believe his people can be redeemed at all.</p>
      <p>* Cole’s position is essentially the first, with a little humor and some mild influence from the second category. He’s an entertainer, though, really.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>