<post>
  <author>a_motte_alt</author>
  <date>2020-10-09T18:01:09Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g88ldd1/</link>
  <title>A Yelp Employee Shares What Actually Goes On With Yelp advertising</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There's quite a lot of misinformation in this thread (not least in credulously accepting the narrative of the hit piece "documentary").  Rather than get into an internet slap-fight about it (something which my employer is rather emphatic that employees shouldn't do anyway) I'm going to make this into an effortpost about what actually goes on re: Yelp advertising (with a small discussion of the instigating topic at the end).  You can feel free to form your own judgments about whether Yelp's practices are ethical -- while I believe Yelp is miles better than most of the competition, I do think there are some things which are dubious -- but at least you'll have some more accurate information.</p>
      <p>Before I start, a few disclaimers:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>I am a software engineer at Yelp, not a Yelp spokesperson.  I don't speak for the company, only for myself.</li>
        <li>I'm not going to discuss any non-public details about the internal operations of Yelp's tools, especially the ones that are used to combat fraud.  While I'm sure people would like to know about them, there is a certain amount of security-through-obscurity here, even at the highest levels (as anyone who knows about the SEO arms race is already aware).   Plus, I don't want to run afoul of issues with disclosing trade secrets or material non-public information or anything like that.</li>
        <li>While I work adjacent to some of the areas I'll discuss, I haven't read every line of code.  There may be some small errors in what follows.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Section 1: Yelp advertising and organic results</p>
      <p>Like most companies that provide free content and make money from advertising, Yelp shows both advertisements and organic (i.e. non-advertisement) content on the same page.  There's two main kind of pages for this yelp content: search, and business pages.  There are multiple ways for a business to spend money to advertise on Yelp, but for now I'll group them all together.</p>
      <p>The following things are NOT affected by advertising (whether the business is an advertiser, how much the business spends on advertising, etc.) or by any actions the business can take: ranking of the business on organic search results; the sample review displayed in organic search results; the reviews displayed on the business page; which reviews on the business page are "recommended" or not recommended.</p>
      <p>Some content can be changed by businesses or affected by advertising.  Some of it is available to all businesses, and others only to advertisers who explicitly pay for the particular feature.   This includes: The appearance of a business in the advertisement results (duh); the review/picture shown with the advertisement (businesses can specify, but usually this is determined automatically); the "verified license" (for licensed service providers) and "business highlights" tags shown on both search results and business pages (these are separate products which businesses pay for, more below); the highlighted review snippets (clearly marked as such) at the top of the business page; auxiliary information such as the about-the-business blurb, featured photos, extra stuff like covid response, hours, and services provided lists.  In addition, Yelp by default shows ads for similar businesses on the sidebar of the business page; the business can pay to get rid of those.</p>
      <p>I believe that a business (of an appropriate type) can sign up to have the "request a quote" button even if they don't advertise (though advertisers can pay to get quote requests if the user opts to send their request more broadly when they submit a quote request), but I'm not 100% sure of that and can't be bothered to check at the moment.</p>
      <p>A word about the "verified license" and "business highlights" features.  These are relatively new products and are separate from the displayed ads (i.e. a business might pay for one or both of these, but not advertising slots; they are typically cheaper).  For verified license, if the business opts to get it, Yelp will have someone check that they are actually a licensed professional/contractor and then put the sticker there as long as the business continues to pay for it.  Business highlights (those icons with things like "woman-owned" or whatever) are similar, though I'm pretty sure that in general they are not verified -- the business can choose whichever ones they want.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>Section 2: Disputes, Fraudulent Reviews, Etc.</p>
      <p>Yelp has systems (both automated and human-involved) to detect and remove fraudulent content.  This includes both negative and positive fake reviews.  As you can imagine, the system is not perfect (though it does seem to be much better than that on e.g. Google reviews), and sometimes fraudulent content will stick around.  Now, I don't know many details about how Yelp does or doesn't handle disputes (e.g. when a business owner claims a negative review is fake, or when they claim a positive review that is flagged as fake was real), but there's a very good reason for Yelp to not wade into these:  they're often extremely difficult or impossible to verify, and unscrupulous business owners have a big incentive to claim that legitimate negative reviews are fake (to try to get them removed).  Yelp categorically will not -- regardless of whether a business is an advertiser -- remove reviews unless it believes they are likely to be fake.  I'm not sure if advertising businesses are more likely to get an ear for dealing with fake review issues or not; I believe that there is a general principle to not play favorites in this way, but Yelp doesn't have perfect control over the behavior of its reps.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>Section 3: Sales rep annoyances</p>
      <p>Yelp has pretty good policies around sales, including that salespeople are not supposed to hound businesses, or call them at all if they ask not to be called back.  Unfortunately, salespeople are gonna salesperson, since commission is a bitch and incentives are what they are, and some salespeople don't follow the rules if they think it will get them a sale.  (Aggressive and misleading salespeople, and/or business owners who have misunderstood what's on offer, are probably the source of the extortion meme.)  Honestly I'm not sure what Yelp can do about it (other than to discipline/fire sales reps if it becomes aware of crossed lines), but that's not my area of expertise anyway.  (Tangentially related: that recent Business Insider article about bad behavior at Yelp sales offices -- the culture in product and engineering is about the polar opposite of what is described there; it is a sales problem, not a general Yelp problem.)</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>Section 4: The "racist business" thing</p>
      <p>First, I've got to say that I think this was a terrible idea.  Nevertheless, it's not as bad as what people here seem to think.</p>
      <p>Basically, when a business is in the news for something controversial, their Yelp page will get brigaded with drive-by one-star reviews (and sometimes five-star reviews from people on the "other side").  Yelp's general practice in this case is to remove the offending reviews and stop all new reviews, with a notice/explanation why, until the controversy dies down.  This happened e.g. with the pizza place in Indiana a few years back (you know the one).  As far as I can tell, this new alert is just that, but with some woke "Yelp is totally against racism" flavor.  I could be proven wrong, but I don't expect this alert to show up just because some people report racism at the business on Yelp, rather, it's for when such complaints make the news otherwise.  The net effect will probably be to stop people mad about alleged racism from brigading the review section, while still very strongly signalling Yelp's opposition to racism.</p>
      <p>I don't like that either (a) it gives Yelp's imprimatur to the accusations, or (b) that it gets a special notice different from the general policy about shutting down reviews in the middle of a controversy.  It also seems more open to possible abuse (e.g. bias in Yelp employees making decisions about whether to put up the "racism!" alert).  But it's not a free-for-all or a way to shake businesses down.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>