<post>
  <author>CanIHaveASong</author>
  <date>2020-10-06T18:54:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g7x9dvg/</link>
  <title>Why do religious people have more children? </title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>For something completely different from our normal posts here:</p>
      <p>Why do religious people have more children?  </p>
      <p>Oh come on!  We've all noticed it:  The fundamentalist family with four kids, and their irreligious siblings with zero to one.  I exaggerate a bit:  There is a significant child difference between the religious and the irreligious, but it's not quite so stark.  According to a <a href="https://www.pewforum.org/2015/05/12/chapter-3-demographic-profiles-of-religious-groups/">pew research study carried out on adults between 40 and 60 in 2014</a>,  Evangelicals and Catholics manage to break the replacement barrier at 2.3 children per individual.  Mormons do even better at 3.4 children per family.  By contrast, religiously unaffiliated adults average a measly 1.7 children.  </p>
      <p>I want to know why.  What is the secret sauce that causes religious people to defy the trend of below replacement fertility?  Sociological research focuses on <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/26347984?seq=4#metadata_info_tab_contents">four different hypotheses</a>:  Pro-natal theology, demographic differences, minority group status, and  socialization.  All four of these play a role.  Pro-natal theology in particular carries a punch.  It goes without saying that banning birth control and abortion raises fertility rates.  However, this doesn't explain all of the fertility increase.  Even denominations that permit birth control and sterilization have fertility rates significantly above secular rates.  This positive fertility effect is seen not only in fertility results, but also <a href="https://www.livescience.com/38743-religious-women-having-more-babies.html">fertility desires</a>.  On average, religious women desire about half a child more than irreligious women.  </p>
      <p>Now is probably a good time to talk about my own interest in this issue.  I grew up in a religious household, and I remain devoutly religious.  As for me, I have three kids, and may have more in the future.  I'm not investigating this topic to try to justify my approach or beliefs, but rather to figure out why it seems so obvious to me to have several kids while my secular friends only desire one or two.  </p>
      <p>One of the most compelling studies I've found says that <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rstb.2019.0428#d403693e1">Religious support networks lower the cost of having more children for participants</a>.  Usually, having more children is associated with reduced child quality, but religious people don't see this effect.  They can have more children without their children's cognitive ability suffering.  In fact, it appears that church aid has a positive effect on children's cognitive ability.  Religious parents also get a great deal of aid from their religious networks, and that aid doesn't decrease over time.  On the other hand, secular support networks are associated with reduced support over time and reduced fertility. </p>
      <p>I find this incredibly satisfying.  This study suggests that religious parents aren't gritting their teeth and obeying God (something I was skeptical of in the first place), but rather making a rational decision to have more children.  Basically, both secular and religious parents are optimizing their fertility outcomes.  However, religious parents have lower costs per child than secular parents have, so they make the rational decision to have more children.  Religious parents can have higher reproductive success for the same cost!</p>
      <p>I know many of you would like secular people to increase their fertility rate.  This study suggests that a significant part of the problem is lack of support.  And  make no mistake!  This is a significant problem.  Part of the reason religious people support eachother so well is because the religion makes so many demands of its adherants.  <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/1069397103037002003">More demands → more group cohesion</a>.  Secular groups have trouble making demands of their adherents, as there is no eternal truth to compel behavior.  See how well Sunday Assembly did!  I suppose the State could step in with support, as they do in Israel, the only country that has a secular fertility rate above replacement.  However, in Israel, the religious fertility rate still outstrips the secular rate by a wide margin.  One might be able to bring secular fertility rate up, but it will still not match religious fertility.   Another way for secular people to gain fertility support may be to live near family, and rely on a genetic support network.  However, it's also thought that <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/2153599X.2016.1249920">religion serves as a signal to family to provide kin care</a>.  Secular parents simply can't catch a break!</p>
      <p>All this considered, it's not surprising to me that people with children are more likely to become religious than people who never reproduce.  Truth claims aside, religion seems to confer very significant evolutionary advantages on its adherents.  It also suggests that secular America's strategy of capturing and converting children who were raised religious is probably their best strategy.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Interesting but unrelated article I came across in my research:
<a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0956797617753606">People trust religious people more not because they're religious, but because they are assuming religious people use a slow reproductive strategy</a>.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>