<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2020-10-07T14:21:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g806jja/</link>
  <title>Worrying about what was done in the name of opposing Russia</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Which Russia scandal?</p>
      <p>There are two main scandals in the American 2016 election cycle- the scandal of Russia 'interfering' with the American electoral process in unseemly ways that Americans do themselves on a daily basis, and the scandal of using the prospect of Russian interference as a pretext for the ruling party of the time to commit a series of security state abuses against an opposition candidate and then setting in motion processes to prolong a campaign-year election conspiracy to tar the victor as a traitor.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>The first is, if not a non-issue, best understood as wildly inflated beyond proportion by parties interested in propogating the second. There is no evidence that anyone has found that Russia tampered with vote tallies of election day. While there is evidence Russia explored/in a few instances established a cyber capability to tamper with voter rolls in some state digital systems, there's no public evidence that they actually did so. Russia may have hacked a DNC server and released embarassing emails- but the American government is taking the DNC's word on that, and the DNC is a primary party in the second scandal, while all competent foreign countries have an interest in accessing such servers for diplomatic intelligence if nothing else- it was in no way unusual even if it was Russian. Russian 'interference' generally amounts to propaganda efforts, via social media or otherwise, whose novelty was their covert-origin and being indistinguishable from the ocean of fake news and domestic propaganda that comes made in the USA every election cycle. Attempts to astro-turf the American public at a time when the Americans spend magnitudes more money, manpower, and effort to do the same thing.</p>
      <p>If you base concern on it's impact, there's no real reason to think the Russian-driven effort was particularly successful, and thus reason for your concern. The political relevance, however, was always less about 'what they did' (because it wasn't much) but rather 'why they did it', with the narrative behind that conclusion being used to villify the Trump administration and used to characterize his relative ambivalence/disinterest with Russia as indication of corruption or treasonous collusion.</p>
      <p>A cynical observer of Russia would note that Russian dis-information spread is a very, very, very old practice, being a systematic process during the Cold War and not exactly going away since- Russia's published military doctrine explicitly identifies information warfare as something that does and should occur as a routine measure of advancing national interest by confusing, demoralizing, and most importantly dividing adversaries before a war can begin, in order to make any war more favorable for Russia. This is... far from unusual, and is pretty common in states with formalized foreign propaganda doctrines. In this viewpoint, based on Russian history, 'helping one side' with information warfare isn't actually about helping one side or the other 'win' the internal diplomatic fight- it's about trying to maximize internal conflict and division. </p>
      <p>In this context, 2016 was a massive success for the Russians not because Trump won, but rather because the immediate American Democratic reaction was a sustained partisan conspiracy campaign across most media and many cultural institutions villifying the American president and a significant part of the country, resulting not just in a massive impact of support for the American government not just domestically, but in Europe as well, increasing the impact beyond what a more neutral media coverage of the same events would have been. American global influence power was turned against the American government, to Russian interest. Had Trump lost, Russian disinformation would almost certainly have continued, just changed form- there were some media reports late election eve/the first day after that some Russia-associated propaganda accounts started pushing 'Trump lost' narratives... after Trump had already won! In other words, pre-written narratives that were planned, but had to be retracted after the surprise upset. (Sadly, most of the initial material was understandably withdrawn/deleted, and the post-election media swarm on the results has long since buried those few watching-anything-but-the-election sources.)</p>
      <p>In the more contemporary context, Russia-watchers would also note that even token interference/trouble making in the 2016 campaign could be considered a tit-for-tat by Putin for Hillary Clinton's own actions as Obama's Secretary of State, when Americans and Europeans led their own influence efforts in Putin's then-most-recent Presidential Election. This visualized in the West mostly in fawning/favorable public coverage for select (pro-Western) opposition candidates, but outside of public view also in support for NGO activities trying to help organize/support said candidates on and off-line, and in negative framings of Russian government officials/corruption scandal coverage/etc. Due to long-standing government-civil ties between Western governments and pro-Western NGOs, Russia's position/common government belief is that more or less all Western NGOs are government-directed/sponsored organizations extending government-directed influence efforts into other countries, including Russia. What Americans/Europeans often consider non-offensive benign soft power, Russia considers (or claims to consider) external interferance in their electoral process, of which Hillary was the Obama Administration organizer. That Russian elections are hardly free or fair is irrelevant, or rather, that's the point- even if you take the most benign view of NGOs as pushing for freer/fairer elections, that is a form of 'foreign interference' that challenges a ruling party that relies on manipulating election cycles.</p>
      <p>In this context, 2016 was mostly a Russia tit-for-tat for Obama Administration support for general 'support democracy' efforts in Russia, a tweak of the nose and not much more. It's measured nature (accessing voter rolls, but not apparently tampering with them or votes) is a demonstration of capability, which itself is a form of deterence in the sense of 'now that you know what I can do, I bet you don't want to interfere in my future elections lest I actually do it in future retaliations.' While an American reaction/retaliation was undoubtably expected, it was probably expected to be manageable/tolerable for Russia in part because this could easily be viewed as, well, not exceptional or severe- a tit-for-tat for actions the Americans already did, and routinely do in other countries where American-led global media routinely supports or pressures various parties in vaguely pro-Western-interest ways. The American Democrat reactions were probably beyond their expectations, in part because they (Russia) wouldn't necessarily reasonably expect the Americans to latch on to it for domestic political vendettas... because no one has ever found evidence that the Russians actually expected Trump to win.</p>
      <p>Which is a key flaw with the third but most widely circulated 'why', the 'Russia wanted Trump to win' narrative. Unlike the previous two rationals- general division and/or a particular tit-for-tat- this is the only theory in which Russia can/could have 'failed' in their strategic efforts. If the goal is to divide Americans or tweak Hillary's nose, then Trump winning or losing is irrelevant. Only by tying Russia's strategic objective to something that could fail, could anti-Russia sentiment, well, succeed by opposing whatever the Russians nominally want. That Russia didn't spend money or resources to maximize their chances of success like they were really trying to- that they didn't aggressively target voter rolls to hinder anti-trump demographics, or undermine election results in Democratic states to delegitimize the future-opposition party, or limited their proxies to established organic anti-Western ideologues like wikileaks- well, that's rarely brought up by anyone advancing this theory.</p>
      <p>The assessment that 'Russia is trying to help Trump win' is publicly legitimized mostly by a late-Obama administration Intelligence Community assessment to that effect, which also ignorred the other options (not least because the few governments will ever acknowledge/frame someone else's tit-for-tat as being in response to an one's own action). But it remained just that- an assessment of Russian motive- rather than sourcing to some specific intelligence of a Russian motive. Educated guesswork versus 'this is what we have telling us this.' And, less convincingly, joint-assessments of that level and circulation (Congressional and public) go through the political-appointee level of agency leadership.</p>
      <p>As the second Russia scandal- the FISA-court abuses, systemic unmasking of electronic survilance of the opposition campaign, use of political party opposition 'research' as third-nation intelligence while masking the origin, investigators over-ruling lower agent recommendations to close cases in order to expand them and use them as basis to launch other initiatives- featured repeated abuses by political-level officials...</p>
      <p>You probably should be worried less about Russia, and more by what was done in the name of opposing Russia.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>