<post>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2020-10-08T00:38:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g827dpy/</link>
  <title>The Americanization of politics in Hungary</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>(Small note: "Meseország mindenkié" literally means "Fairytale-country belongs to everyone" and I suspect it's an allusion to the slogan "Magyarország a magyaroké", meaning "Hungary belongs to the Hungarians" (or "Hungary for the Hungarians" to be more slogan-y), which was a 2009 slogan by Jobbik (but Fidesz also used it), and is I think in turn derived from the Monroe Doctrine "America for the Americans".) ("Hungary belongs to the Hungarians" was mostly an anti-Roma message, but today it's also used in an anti-immigrant way.)</p>
      <hr />
      <p>I also want to make a bigger point about this. I really dislike the Americanization of politics in Hungary.</p>
      <p>We used to have our own topics and controversies, but since the emergence of social media people are aping whatever is popular abroad. Abortion, religion, gender, race, MeToo, immigration, conspiracies... These just didn't used to be the topics. Controversies used to be over interpretations of Hungarian history, over countryside vs Budapest, politicians stealing public money, shall we have paid hospitals or not, should Hungarians in neighboring countries be allowed to vote, etc. But all those American topics are on the rise. I'm wondering how long until we'll have a "gun control debate" in Hungary, despite virtually nobody owning guns.</p>
      <p>While not really enthusiastically supportive, Hungarian society used to be pretty tolerant as regards homosexuality. We used to have fairly liberal laws around it, with registered partnerships, and legal transitioning. All this was fairly out of public debate, it was stuff that the respective minorities knew about, but most people didn't really care.</p>
      <p>Enter social media. Now everyone is much more up-to-date and the opinions and dividing lines match up more and more with the American ones, even when it historically doesn't make sense. Sure there are other contributors, like the Pride "carnival", which has been controversial from the get-go.</p>
      <p>But I'd say this whole issue from both sides is quite artificial and self-serving in my eyes. Especially young, educated (English speaking) people nowadays just take their opinions from international media and LARP it in Hungary.</p>
      <p>Remembering back, even just 5 years ago, when I read something on Slate Star Codex about the American culture wars, it took very long until I read about the same topics in Hungarian news. Nowadays these worlds have merged basically, I read about this stuff now everywhere. (Tangentially, this also applies to the AI stuff: while LessWrong was quite fringe at the time, many of those ideas have gone mainstream and indeed appear in Hungarian print media as well.)</p>
      <p>Old, loyal, pro-government prime-time TV show hosts are doing "culture war roundups", cherry picking the craziest, most outrageous news about transgender babies, unisex toilets, safe spaces, and so on. Newspapers write about American campus freedom of speech problems, cancel culture as if this was happening in Hungary. Everyone loves a good juicy outrage story, and journalists just can't resist (and it's so much easier to translate these small tidbits than to dig around to find important local stories). While in 2017 you had to go out of your way as a Hungarian to ever read about Jordan Peterson or Bret Weinstein's crusades against "political correctness", today even the grandmas who watch these political TV shows know about trans people and critical race theory.</p>
      <p>The reverse is also true. Before the last few years, there was not much international press interest in Hungarian affairs. It's only reported on nowadays because it fits (or is made to fit) this very simple narrative. And it seems Fidesz is also leaning into this narrative now (Orbán has always had illusions of grandeur, so he's bathing in all this attention).</p>
      <p>Overall, the far-right Mi Hazánk (recent spinoff from the Jobbik party) have no good way to differentiate themselves, since the ruling Fidesz is already trying to take on the role that the "new right"/"alt right" takes on elsewhere. So Mi Hazánk picked LGBT, as it seems Fidesz has been focusing too much on immigration, leaving a gap for Mi Hazánk to fill, regarding LGBT. (Immigration was never a topic in Hungary before the 2015 crisis, but since then it's all over the government media, even when zero migrants are coming.)</p>
      <p>Hungarians are quite irreligious, mostly because of the anti-religious communist regime. But even those that are religious aren't USA-style actually-taking-it-seriously people, but people who pray, read the Bible to uplift their soul, like the community aspect etc., but there aren't any substantive religious groups who'd care about gays, abortion, Satanist music or any other craze as in America.</p>
      <p>"Christian" was used more as a codeword for non-Jew. (Nowadays Orbán also uses it as code for white.) But gradually, slowly, religion is also becoming a thing to refer to regarding policy. </p>
      <p>Black people used to have a pretty good image in Hungary, as most of them have been fairly rich exchange students or expats here since the 90s. Even the racists and skinheads were mostly focusing on the Roma and the Jews. Only the most fundamentalist racists cared about black people, as the whole thing is fairly abstract and theoretical in Hungary. As for Islam and Arabs, Hungarian far-right types saw little else in them than vague allies (in hating the Jews). Perhaps they will switch sides to Israel now? (Or just keep on hating both.)</p>
      <p>Nowadays most of these differences are melting away, "we're all living in America" as Rammstein sang.</p>
      <p>I do wonder when the "pro-free-market capitalism" idea will also switch sides in Hungary, since this has been associated with the liberal left here, as free markets and private enterprise was seen as the modern new Western thing after the change of the system. The right has been more about the nation, the people, redistribution, free education and healthcare at least in words. Counter-intuitively, privatization in healthcare has been pushed for by the leftist Socialist governments. But if the Hungarian right keeps aligning towards the US, perhaps they will become more libertarian too? It used to be the right, who were pushing to stop market greed and exploitation of nature (hand waving towards "the Jews"), preferring the esthetic of small-scale rural traditional folk life, etc.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>So overall, both the book and the reaction to it is simply a carbon copy, a CTRL-C, CTRL-V import.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>