<post>
  <author>Folamh3</author>
  <date>2020-10-08T08:36:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g83b3u3/</link>
  <title>The Americanization of Irish Politics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I live in Ireland, and the same trends are very visible here. Young people get the majority of their news from Instagram and TikTok, primarily celebrities who tend to be American or resident in America, and come to believe that they live in America, or that the issues that affect America are the same issues that affect Ireland, or that Irish history closely tracks with contemporaneous American history. A few examples off the top of my head:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Back in June I read <a href="https://www.thejournal.ie/readme/diane-ihirwe-black-lives-matter-george-floyd-5114377-Jun2020/">an article</a> in a major Irish publication from a black woman describing her experiences of racism in Ireland. I don't dispute her lived experience, but one passage jumped out at me: "Are you walking into an office with all white people? That’s not right. You know it’s not right. And, now, there’s no excuse. So speak up." I think this opinion is predicated on the assumption that racial demographics in Ireland are broadly commensurate with the racial demographics of the US. This assumption, of course, is false: black people represent <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demographics_of_the_Republic_of_Ireland#Ethnic_groups">barely more than 1%</a> of the Irish population. What's more, the black population of Ireland skews younger, so of that 1.3-1.4%, many have not yet entered the labour force. It's <del>barely an</del> not even an exaggeration to say that, if tomorrow every Irish office decided to make it its mission to hire at least one black person in the next 3 months, there wouldn't be enough black people to go around.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>EDIT: Just for fun, I crunched the numbers on this point. Assuming black people resident in Ireland are 1.3-1.4% of the population, there are at least 62,000 and at most 67,000 such people. According to the Central Statistics Office, in 2016 there were slightly more than  <a href="https://www.cso.ie/en/releasesandpublications/er/bd/businessdemography2016/">250,000 active businesses</a> operating in Ireland. Even assuming the upper limit of 67,000 black people in Ireland, and assuming that all of these are in the labour force, and ignoring urban concentrations of demographics, there simply aren't enough black people in Ireland for every active business to hire at least one such person. "Demand" exceeds supply by 74%.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>Sort of a sub-point to the aforementioned, but there tends to be this general assumption that black people in Ireland have the same history of institutionalized oppression that black American descendants of slavery have. Ireland has no analogue to the cotton fields or to Jim Crow. My mother tells me that when she was growing up, on the extremely rare occasions that she saw a black person on the street, it was reasonable to assume that they were a doctor, as one barely ever encountered black people in any other profession. It is indisputable that black people in Ireland experience racist abuse on occasion, but the institutionalized racism towards black people found in the US simply doesn't exist and <em>never existed</em> in Ireland.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>A commenter in <a href="/r/ireland">r/ireland</a> pointed something out the other day: it's very common for young Irish people to address people older than them with the dismissive slogan "ok boomer", but the "slur" doesn't really carry the same weight in Ireland as it does in the US. Members of the American baby boomer generation really were (on average) fantastically wealthy and privileged compared to the previous generation, so the phrase "ok boomer" is effective at taking the wind out of their perceived beleaguered entitlement and inflated sense of self. By contrast, Irish people born in the same period (1945-64) were, almost without exception, dirt poor, given that Ireland was for all intents and purposes a Third World country until the 1970s.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>This morning I heard <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F1OE_D2Pvd8">a song</a> by a young Irish rapper called Ahmed, With Love (I quite enjoyed the song). One of the first lyrics in the song is "Golly he should keep it real quiet, they might kill him/the guards [Garda Síochána, the Irish police service] see an unknown teen, they might drill him". Ahmed seems to be suggesting that young black men in Ireland live in constant fear of being killed by police officers, much like their analogues in the US. While this fear isn't <em>completely</em> unfounded in the US, it <em>is</em> completely unfounded in Ireland. The vast majority of Irish police officers <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garda_S%C3%ADoch%C3%A1na">do not carry guns</a> ("more than three-quarters of the force do not routinely carry firearms"), the few who do rarely discharge them, and to the best of my knowledge there has literally never been a case of an unarmed black man being shot by an Irish police officer.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Even as someone who is no fan of Trump, the "Not My President" protests of 2017 made me roll my eyes, a wilful refusal to engage with reality and understand how a political system works. That didn't stop a group of Irish people organizing a "<a href="https://www.independent.ie/videos/irish-news/video-scenes-at-the-not-my-taoiseach-protest-outside-government-buildings-37717142.html">Not My Taoiseach</a>" protest last year, even though the Taoiseach isn't a direct analogue of the POTUS and doesn't take office the same way.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>I can maybe understand the idea of having a massive Black Lives Matter protest during a pandemic, if you're protesting issues that happened in your own country. I cannot see the merit in holding a massive Black Lives Matter protest during a pandemic, in order to protest issues that happened in <em>another</em> country. And yet, Ireland saw <em>multiple</em> BLM protests this summer, with attendance in the tens of thousands. I suspect that if I asked the typical attendee who George Floyd and Michael Brown were, they would be able to give me a detailed biography; if I asked them who Pádraig Pearse, Joseph Plunkett or Constance Markiewicz were, I would probably get a blank stare.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>