<post>
  <author>HlynkaCG</author>
  <date>2020-10-06T20:31:33Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g7xnjay/</link>
  <title>The utilitarians can have their wire-heading and the nihilists their smug sense of superiority. I choose life</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I want to know why. What is the secret sauce that causes religious people to defy the trend of below replacement fertility?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I have a theory, but I don't think a lot of people here are going to like it. I think it's safe to say that in most industrialized countries the vast majority of "the irreligious" subscribe to some flavor of secular humanism. The major tenet of which being the centrality of the individual human mind/experience, from which it draws it's name. Furthermore in more western countries you get the additional mantra of "I am my own" and the adjacent baggage associated with . To be blunt, this is not a philosophy that is particularly conducive to family formation/child rearing. If you value autonomy and freedom, pregnancy, child-birth, and child-care (especially infants and toddlers) are all going to deny it to you. Heck the simple matter of being "in a relationship" is a loss of freedom in so far as it means always having to place the welfare of another alongside your own.</p>
      <p>Internet Nihilists' sneers about "slave morality" aside, the sentiment towards service that comes baked into the Abrahamic Religions (seriously FireFox? you're going to try and correct "Abrahamic" to "abracadabra") handily addresses this issue. We all serve, and we are all served. Rousseau was wrong. We are not our own and no one is born without chains. Some of the chains are placed upon you by the vagaries of fortune, (who your parents are, where you come from) others are taken up as you go along (allegiances to friends, family, an organization, or a principle) but the end result is the same. From womb to tomb we are bound to others.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://biblehub.com/deuteronomy/30-19.htm">The Lord hath set before us blessings and curses</a>. The utilitarians can have their wire-heading and the nihilists their smug sense of superiority. I choose life.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>