<post>
  <author>LoreSnacks</author>
  <date>2020-10-08T12:28:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g83ootk/</link>
  <title>Trump as Scapegoat For Health Expert Failures</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The biggest problem with having Trump as President right now is that he makes a great scapegoat for the health "experts" who have completely failed us.</p>
      <p>It wasn't Trump who stopped us from having large-scale testing early on, it was the author's colleagues working as professional bureaucrats at government agencies who established layers of red tape and kept insisting they almost had a government-approved test ready.  (The PPE issue is overblown anyway, but Trump didn't set the PPE reserves on fire either, they were used up in Obama's 1st of 8 years in office and never replenished.)</p>
      <p>Trump could have done a better job.  He could have put someone like Balaji Srinivasan in charge of beating back the "experts" at the CDC and FDA.  But there's no way any of that would have been done under a hypothetical Clinton regime either.  By far the best thing he could have done is accelerated vaccine development by loosening testing requirements and moving quickly ahead with challenge trials. But again, it's the "experts" who are in the way there. The article argues from the assumption that the "expert" bureaucrats would have done better, without any analysis of their very real failures or evaluation of what they were actually suggesting at the time.</p>
      <p>The article cherry-picks countries with better stats and ignores the dumpster fire that is nearly every country in Western Europe.</p>
      <p>The only kernel of truth in the article is that "strict quarantine and isolation" could have been effective at early stages.  But they don't elaborate on exactly what that means, which is the police dragging everyone who has come in contact with an infected individual (and in contact with them too) to a centralized quarantine facility, and turning people back who try to cross state borders.  Hard to imagine that being implemented in the U.S. and I haven't seen any politician advocate it.<br />
Given that, they should probably address the evidence on how effective weaker lockdown without centralized quarantine is, but they do not.</p>
      <p>The part ranking countries based on "tests per infected person" is completely ridiculous.  This is just another way of complaining we have lots of infections.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>