<post>
  <author>ChrisPrattAlphaRaptr</author>
  <date>2020-08-15T21:33:58Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i6yuis/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_10_2020/g1npsjq/</link>
  <title>NYT's Nuanced Take on Cancel Culture</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Nuanced take from the NYT on Cancel Culture</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The Daily from the NYT is a 30-60 minute Mon-Fri news podcast. Earlier this week, they did a two (<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/08/10/podcasts/the-daily/cancel-culture.html">1</a><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/08/11/podcasts/the-daily/cancel-culture.html">2</a> part segment on Cancel Culture, links have both the podcast as well as the transcripts. I can save you some time though - none of the content is going to be new to this audience (particularly the first episode, which is just a summary of what people mean by Cancel Culture), but rather, I think their stance is interesting.</p>
      <p>The podcast focuses largely on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HU4_ufWgP9Y">'I feel threatened' Costco man</a> incident. I saw it, cringed, and went on with my life. Meanwhile, twitter mobilized, doxxed the man, and I'm sure you know the rest (summary <a href="https://nowthisnews.com/news/i-feel-threatened-man-fired-from-insurance-job-after-mask-tirade-at-florida-costco">here</a> if you don't). What's interesting to me is the perspective of the NYT as told through the lens of freelance journalist Zeeshaun Aleem:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I was sort of confused about it, I suppose. There is basically a 17-second clip here. And the idea of immediately playing the role of judge, jury, executioner in terms of taking a person’s job seemed to me sort of a hasty conclusion to come to and not something that, given the time span, could have necessarily been sort of well thought out. I also wasn’t sure whether or not the idea of trying to identify someone random on the internet was a good idea. There’s a number of documented cases of people identifying the wrong person based off of who they think they found on a photograph or a video. And then, you know, the wrong person getting doxxed or getting fired or getting threatened by random people on the internet. And so I think targeting jobs is a bad idea.
...the issue of this sort of severity of this sentence. In American society, when you lose your job, you’re not only losing your income, but you’re also losing your health insurance. And if you are the earner in a family, that could also potentially mean that your family also loses their health insurance. And then of course, you have to take into account that we have a very weak social safety net...</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Zeeshaun tweets skeptically at the individual spearheading the doxxing campaign Costco Man, who dismisses him. Zeeshaun is then retweeted by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Posobiec">Jack Posobiec</a>, leading to an influx of alt-right people trying to cancel the doxxer for older, racist tweets.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I don’t think that Twitter rewards asterisks and ums and skepticism, ambivalence, questions. I think Twitter rewards absolute claims, simple sort of black and white, good and evil allegories and binaries, and strong declarations of truth that leave little room for interpretation.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The most 'pro' cancel culture quote from both segments?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>You know, it’s a sort of testament to the power of a medium like Twitter that has really democratized thought and opinion.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>There are maybe 2-3 allusions to this 'democratization of opinions,' but the idea is never elaborated on, and nobody is interviewed to defend that perspective. Their overall stance seems to be summed up by Obama's largely negative <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qaHLd8de6nM">take on Cancel Culture</a> last year, which they also directly cite.</p>
      <p>So why am I bringing this up?</p>
      <p>I've argued, mostly privately I suppose, that this space is very echo-chambery when it comes to discussing the NYT/media. Most pieces that are shared here are to the tune of 'Can you believe this terrible thing the NYT just published!' It's just...outrage porn. I'm not going to pretend that a small internet community has any noticeable effect on the revenue of any news agency, but every time we do this <em>we're feeding the very problem we're decrying.</em> When the NYT produces a measured, nuanced article like this it's largely ignored, while the 1619 project or the latest hot take on George Floyd generate massive attention. </p>
      <p>This used to be something, I think, that we could <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aOCOdKzFcdY">agree on</a>. I think left and right used to be irritated by the media in equal measure, if for <a href="https://boingboing.net/2015/03/31/arrested-for-same-crime-in-ne.html">different reasons</a>. Now, the media is just another politicized wedge issue used to divide and control us, ironically ensuring we'll never be able to meaningfully address the problem. I'm not sure what to do about it besides try and push back on what I see as polarizing effects in the spaces I frequent. I think if you reach out, there's plenty of people on the other side with views like yours.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>