<post>
  <author>gattsuru</author>
  <date>2020-08-17T15:04:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ib82ju/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_17_2020/g1v7paa/</link>
  <title>The Tangled Ties of Nature and Nurture in Homosexuality</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>are these studies just "cherry picked bad science" promoted by homophobic social scientists that have some kind of conservative agenda? </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>To be more charitable are at least badly underpowered: the molestation-homosexuality link is also a <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3535560/">non-sexual maltreatment</a>-homosexuality link.  But I don't think that's the core of the disagreement.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>or is everyone just going along with the "born that way" thing to serve a greater social cause, even though many thinking people are aware that it's not literally true for many/most LGB people?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>A lot of the <em>actual</em> conversation is really a proxy for whether you can change adult sexual preferences in that extent (and even as someone who likes orientation play, it doesn't really work), rather than serious adherence to blank slate versus hbd.  Or pushing back against the molestation link for its own political reasons.</p>
      <p>So be warned about that.</p>
      <p>But I don't think it's something that's made up, entirely, either.  Sexual orientation is... complicated to talk about, but one of the things that helps het folk close the understanding is the concept of the Gold Star.  These are people who, for an example I'm familiar with, will turn down a threesome with a guy they want badly because his girlfriend wants to watch.  It's a category, with both beneficial and negative connotations, mostly heavily among lesbian women but also used among gay men, to describe people who have only had sex with same-sex partners, <em>and it's not the assumed default</em>.</p>
      <p>Like, Dan Savage's <a href="https://www.thecut.com/2017/05/dan-savage-lost-his-virginity-in-a-cosplay-threeway.html">first time was with a woman</a> (cw: nsfw text, sexual abuse of a teenager, and worse not really realizing it).  Gay men are more likely to have had (not forcibly non-consensual) sex for the first time at a younger age than straight men, and while a lot of that's finding that any dude horny enough to trade a handjob is a lower bar, a surprising amount of it's trying women of the same age.</p>
      <p>It's not just that the mechanics didn't work (uh, always; a lot of folk end up 'pushing rope', but the blue pill can fix that surprisingly often), but whether scent or touch or something else, at best it's "lie back and think of England" territory except you have to be active the whole time.</p>
      <p>Which isn't necessarily incompatible with the 'driven into it from childhood experience' story -- while the age gap in Savage's case is unusual, even the healthy stuff isn't often great relationships -- but it's not a comfortable fit, for either the not-quite-bisexuals, or even the broad selection of Gold Stars men without a history or who knew long before they ran into anything sexual.  It's hard to frame something as a result of childhood intervention or Pavlovian conditioning when you're actively trying to react different and nothing happens even if you can get the physical side in place.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>... additionally, when i was a young person living in a large city with a great deal of LGB people in the 80s many adult LGB explained to me that they became LGB due to specific childhood sexual experiences, although at least one told me that he was always gay ever since he could remember.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It's plausible, but you hear similar 'conversion' stories from furries or foot fetishists, and while I can imagine <em>Zootopia</em>'s tigers ticking something in a normie brain, most people walk away from the ouvre of Tarantino without needing to suck toes.  And even with furries, Disney's Robin Hood had a big impact, but you needed a certain predisposition.</p>
      <p>I'm also not sure how easily a het person could distinguish between the "realized I was" story rather than "and then I became" stories.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>but it seems to obviously politically advantageous with respect to the promotion of the concept of inalienable rights and whatnot</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Yeah, there's definitely some political interest from a legal perspective, although given how much of the modern 'animus' theory was custom-tailored for LGBT rights alone, it's not clear what direction the causation happened.  And it's not like the 'we were converted into it but can't change back' thesis would be incompatible, either; there are anti-age and anti-chronic illness laws, and one of the big focus points for 80s LGB activism was reducing discrimination against HIV-positive people (and not in the modern tumblr sense; there were people kicked out of apartments and one notably kicked out of a public school).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>