<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-08-16T00:01:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i6yuis/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_10_2020/g1ohy7w/</link>
  <title>Chan Culture's Cancellation Mobs</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>And then, you know, the wrong person getting doxxed or getting fired or getting threatened by random people on the internet</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It is <em>interesting</em> that the problem with being able to "play judge, jury, executioner" is that you may screw it up and punish the wrong guy. One would expect otherwise from people who believe in relativity of truth and fundamentality of power relations. But then again you're right: they're just people like everyone.</p>
      <p>Cringe/rant incoming. </p>
      <p>It's no secret that much of modern internet culture came from chans. Channers like to attribute this to their anonymity, creativity and contrarianism; but maybe it's a simple matter of being ahead of the curve, being the first to learn the affordances for mischief that new technology provides. </p>
      <p>Twitter mobs did not originate on chans. Any progressive mobber would repudiate the very thought of association. But they perfectly resemble our raids, which in turn inherit the Fidonet tradition of bullying. (For everyone knowledgeable: I understand the theoretical differences of Тrавля, Набег и Рейд, but they're insignificant in context; please bear with me).</p>
      <p>I grew up alongside 2ch.ru (RIP) and its diasporic offshoots, just like many people of my time across the world matured – or failed to mature – on 4chan. By convention we called ourselves /b/tards – "bastard retards", as it were; and conventional morality was derided. "Raids" were among our favourite pastimes (perhaps rivaled by "Anon, create!" drawing challenges where you had to lead a stickman over a threat, usually giant sharpened spikes, towards delicious cake by means of purple dildo on a rope; copypasta writing; struggle against wiping; and innocent, forever lost moments of true understanding). Our battle cry was ~"Anonym Legion Rushover!" (I can't share with you the hilariousness of the memeplex involved). And by Nomad, rushover we did.  </p>
      <p>Now I was a boring guy even then and didn't participate much in all of that vigorous fun. But, uh, <a href="https://mangadex.org/chapter/12394/15">«I understood the aspiration»</a>. </p>
      <p>(Of note, all academic and "serious" literature I saw still seems to miss the simple point and ethos of trolling. People who claim to have spent years monitoring "trolls" seem to refer such <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90413795/this-journalist-spent-3-years-with-alt-right-trolls-this-is-what-he-learned">to people with strong opinions different from their own</a>. Others still analyse it through "power" framework. It's amazing, and probably indicates some fundamental difference in worldview, if not total lack of empathy.)</p>
      <p>Our targets varied. Explicit <em>immoral puritanism</em> of the Legion demanded attacking only those who could "deliver lulz"; "moralfags" were continuously chazed away with copious shock content; and calls for some crusade were shot down with "not your personal army". So at times it all worked as designed, which is to say, a complete shitshow: doxxing teenagers who make home porn, terrorising superstitious women with Satanic photoshops of their children, all sorts of iconoclasm... (the annoying theme of general incel resentment is already evident here, though).<br />
Yet this is not what Legion remembers, nor what it prided itself on. The most  successful raids and doxxes were, in structure and motivation, indistinguishable from Twitter mob attacks: except we picked more deserving targets. A crazy camwhore who dismembered cats. An oligarch's power-hungry trophy wife who herself abused disabled people for laughs. Shitty kids who killed a person by throwing a tire off a roof (which led to the appearance of... our representatives <a href="https://youtu.be/EEDSQjNop2Y?t=178">on TV talk show</a>). And even when we struck at random, normal people usually dropped us off soon enough. Who did not? A haughty guy from Predisent's admin circles, who threatened trolls with his "connections"; and who soon murdered his own parents. For all of 2ch's filth, I honestly can't remember any instance of such vile and unjustifiable persistence in bringing down powerless and/or generically okay folks that we see on Twitter. </p>
      <p>Perhaps the difference was that we were never as big as Twitter cancel mobs get, and so could not be <a href="https://killsixbilliondemons.com/comic/king-of-swords-10-150/">our own justification</a>. I like to think that it was about our lack of hypocrisy, or really <em>reverse hypocrisy</em> – we rejected morality after we deemed the busybodies of the world to be dishonest and defiling their own creed. Or maybe it has more to do with lack of stake in the game: a Twitterati has to prove herself as an upstanding citizen <em>or else</em>, which is a non-concern for an anonymous /b/tard who is not expected to do anything, nor can be compelled to even in principle. And then there's the issue of supply and demand: America is disgustingly decent, as far as "fair game" demographics and topics are concerned, so you need to invent baddies.  </p>
      <p>But really the point is that people just like witch hunts and will participate in them whenever possible. They like to bring justice to the world and witch-hunt is an easy and fun way to feel succeeding at it. It's pointless to chide them for excess, to ask for moderation. You need to give them a productive outlet. Normally that would have been religion.  </p>
      <p>So, rather than approve of NYT (which is a den of unprincipled vipers and I'm committed to seeing even their best moves as a ploy to lower our guards or feed addiction), I'd rather sympathise with Cancel Culture foot soldiers. I don't approve of what they do. But I understand the aspiration.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>