<post>
  <author>LawOfTheGrokodus</author>
  <date>2020-08-13T05:26:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i6yuis/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_10_2020/g1arz56/</link>
  <title>An In-Depth Look at Maryland's Polling Worker Woes</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A good ways downthread, <a href="/u/_malcontent_">u/_malcontent_</a> and <a href="/u/ImSorryButWho">u/ImSorryButWho</a> have the following exchange (malcontent in quotation marks):</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"It shouldn't be too difficult to dramatically increase the number of polling stations for this election. There are tons of schools/businesses that are closed and can be used for polling stations. There are tons of people who are looking for work. It shouldn't take too long to train them. If people are worried about standing in long lines and taking hours to vote (like happened in the last elections a couple months ago) more polling places is the obvious solution.  </p>
        <p>In my district, most, if not all of the volunteers were retirees. I would think that due to coronavirus concerns, there will be much less seniors volunteering to man polling stations this year, so you're anyway going to need to bring in some more people to work the polls."  </p>
        <p>That doesn't seem likely. <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2020/08/04/maryland-needs-13000-election-judges/">Maryland needs 13000 election judges</a>, and is being forced to <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/md-politics/policy-change-lets-maryland-election-officials-use-voting-centers-instead-of-polling-places/2020/08/10/ce1e2c6a-db28-11ea-b205-ff838e15a9a6_story.html">reduce the number of polling places</a>.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>As it happens, I have extensive knowledge of this situation and can speak to what's going on in Maryland. Similar things may be happening in other states. Note that my information is second-hand, and my position is rather biased, so it is possible I'm wrong on certain elements of this.</p>
      <p>In the Maryland election system, there's a few power centers, with the most significant being the State Board of Elections (SBE) and the Governor Larry Hogan. (Hogan, incidentally, is a Republican in a very heavily Democratic state, but is generally quite popular.) There's also all the local election boards (LBEs) and various activist groups. Thanks to the state's strong partisan lean (and really heavy gerrymandering), the result of the national elections should be fairly predictable, but it's still important to run the election right.</p>
      <p>A month or so ago, the SBE presented Governor Hogan with three options for how to run the election:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>A normal, in-person election at all the usual polling places (no one in any position of influence favored this; it was on the list purely for completion).</li>
        <li>A vote-by-mail election with a few vote centers for those unable to vote by mail, in which absentee ballot applications would be sent to all registered voters (the favored option of the Republicans on the SBE).</li>
        <li>The same as option 2, but sending everyone an actual absentee ballot instead of an absentee ballot application (the favored option of the Democrats on the SBE and of most activist groups).</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Governor Hogan decided on both option 1 and option 2: Maryland would essentially run two elections, one in person and one by mail, though the state would also strongly encourage residents to vote by mail, and supplement the pollworkers by encouraging state employees to help out. This proclamation through pretty much everyone else involved in the election system into a tizzy. Even though most voters would probably vote by mail, there's not much room to reduce the number of judges at each polling place to account for expected reduced turnout. With the demands of a vote-by-mail election, far more election workers would be needed. Many LBEs had sent out surveys to people who had previously been election judges or who had signed up to be an election judge before the pandemic hit asking them if they were still able to, and as I understand it, in most places a minority of prospective judges said yes.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>There are tons of people who are looking for work. It shouldn't take too long to train them.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'm one of the people who went through election judge training before current events, but who is now unable to help out in person. (Incidentally, if you're in the US and it's safe for you to do so, please help out! Many areas really need people and you'll be doing way more for democracy than any amount of posting on The Motte!) To be basically a standard pollworker, I had a most-of-a-day training session, with the option to come back in for more practice if I wanted to. While the training wasn't thrilling, it was better run than I had expected, and I don't think it could be substantially pruned down. Critically, the training has to be in person, because one of the most important elements of it is getting to actually physically practice with the election equipment. There might be restrictions on removing that equipment from the Board of Elections buildings too. There's a limited number of trainers, and many of them are older and at particular risk from COVID-19. These aren't intractable problems, but fixing them usually requires money, time, or freedom to change the rules, and LBEs and often the SBE don't have that.</p>
      <p>With an increased demand for election judges, a reduced supply, and a limited ability to increase that supply, something had to give. The SBE and a bunch of activist groups all sent letters to Governor Hogan pleading to at least allow vote centers. This proposal is akin to a souped-up version of precinct consolidation, in which two smaller precincts have their voters cast their ballots at the same location. In this case, each county would have a number of vote centers, and any voter who lives in that county can vote at any vote center in the county. This would require somewhat more effort than a normal precinct (even accounting for the lower expected turnout) because the vote center would have to have very many possible ballots, but it would reduce the number of polling places by ~75% and so reduce the need for pollworkers commensurately. Governor Hogan grudgingly agreed, though he also sent a rather critical <a href="https://governor.maryland.gov/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Letter-to-SBE_8.10.20.pdf">letter</a> to the chair of the SBE.</p>
      <p>Governor Hogan has been very frustrated with the SBE for not having sent out absentee ballot applications yet. However, the SBE maintains that they're working as fast as they can, and gave a very detailed breakdown of how the process is chugging along. I'm not sure how to evaluate this myself — a month is a fairly long time, but sending out applications to everyone is a lot harder than sending them out to a small number of people when requested, the timeline was fairly reasonable, and there are a good number of pitfalls they have to avoid.</p>
      <p>One pitfall I know a lot about is with there being two ways of getting an absentee ballot: having it mailed to you or printing one out. In both cases, the voter fills it out and sends it in through mail or through a ballot drop-off box, but home-printed ones have a problem. Because they're printed just on normal printer paper, the ballot-scanning machines can't read them, so election workers have to manually transcribe them onto official ballots. This is fairly labor intensive during a normal year, but when maybe 20 times as many people are voting by mail as usual, it could seriously hinder the ability of the Board to report the election outcome by the legal deadline. So they'll hopefully be changing the language on the absentee ballot request form to make being mailed a ballot the default, very clearly favored over a print-your-own.</p>
      <p>The vote centers will be at public high schools throughout Maryland. This was the choice for a few reasons. First of all, schools tend to be relatively centrally located relative to population, so hopefully they should be accessible for most of the population. Secondly, the state can't just requisition locations, even for an important cause like the election. Vote centers will have people coming into them from all over their county for almost a week, and most privately owned facilities would want remuneration for that use that the SBE doesn't have the funds for. Public schools are state property, and so can be used by the state more easily for another purpose.</p>
      <p>The whole situation is something of a mess. I don't think the governor really understands the limitations the election administrators are operating under, or how few people are going to prefer to vote in person relative to the amount of resources that takes. He says his hands are tied, but he is able to do quite a bit under Maryland's state of emergency, as when he suspended certain election laws to enable the voting centers. If the General Assembly is needed, they should actually convene and vote on the stuff they have to. This has relatively little to do with national culture war issues — while there's both Democrats and Republicans in this story, it's not fundamentally one of partisanship. But politics exists on a smaller scale, and is ignored at the analyst's peril.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>