<post>
  <author>morcovi</author>
  <date>2020-08-13T02:27:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i6yuis/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_10_2020/g1ab8qh/</link>
  <title>Talking Political Prediction Markets</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>No problem; I'd be glad to. It turns out to be pretty much as simple as you'd think, though. I just look for what's trading, what Nate says the probability is of such events, calculate the ratio of prices, and add in a safety margin--so if something is 30% overpriced, I sell, and if 30% underpriced, I buy. (I don't even worry about the "geometric drag" where 1.3 and 0.7 aren't multiplicative inverses.) This covers fees--and also excludes cases where the market price is some combination of Silver-as-baseline, modified by reasonable additional factors--leaving me as having identified just those opportunities where the only real divergence between his math and the face price is either (1) he's wrong (a chance, but he's served me well so far); or (2) market irrationality. But of course, if Silver is wrong and the market is right, then since I bought at market prices, I don't lose money on average except through fees and lost opportunity costs; it's only if the market is wrong because the truth is in the <strong>opposite</strong> direction to his forecasts that I am going -EV.</p>
      <p>An abridged story: it's 2016 and I've got around $2500 in my account. Silver says the Blue Wall could crack (I forget, let's say it was 20% chance per state) but the markets say it probably won't (again I forget, let's go with 10% chance)--so basically, I'm doubling any money I put in. Nice, right? So in goes $200 and I should see nothing 4 times out of 5, but that last time I make 10x. (9.1x after fees.)</p>
      <p>For the next 3.5 years, it's a story of me making 20%+ annually by insisting that Trump wasn't going to <del>spontaneously combust as a human being</del> resign or die or switch parties or pardon himself or whatever else shenanigans. Hillary neither, nor Comey. Boring, but profitable, and actuarial tables (modified by having better healthcare but higher risks of assassination) confirm that I was hardly in any danger of losing the bets. Nothing to do with 538, as for the midterms they largely agreed (I think?) with the markets, within a certain margin.</p>
      <p>The 2020 primaries were largely an exercise in epistemic humility for me, made easier by the 10% profit fee--it would take a lot for confidence indeed for me to overcome my own ignorance AND a 10% fee. See, I'm not a Democrat, and even if I were, I'd be just one voter in one faction of the party, not some Frankensteinian smorgasbord composed of 20% Socialist and 20% SJW and 20% minority and 20% working class and 20% whatever else comprises the Democrats these days. (Or some more accurate proportions than 20% each.) So I have no idea what's "normal" or "reasonable" or even popular over there, but I <em>can</em> ask a whole bunch of people who <em>are</em> going to vote in the primaries (that's an opinion poll), and so enter Nate Silver once more.</p>
      <p>Did you know Silver's primary model weighted by demographics? By ideological lane? Probably. Did you know it ran a Monte Carlo simulation, because parametrizing all this into a whole forest of closed-form equations, and then solving them, is impractical? If you understood the vocab in that sentence, then yes, you knew that too. But did you also know that his model <em>worked out the chances that any given candidate would drop out at any point, and what would happen if it then redistributed their voters?</em> South Carolina and Super Tuesday showed us the importance of this factor, and combined with the typical I-just-won-a-state polling bounce, uncertainty was high depending on who won what or dropped out when. (For the record, I think earlier on, 538 had Biden at 40-50% or something to win Delaware... but 90% IF he made it that far.) Yet the markets had folks at 80%+ to win certain states in an unconsolidated field.</p>
      <p>So what I'm saying is that I placed bets on Warren in Utah (don't laugh); Bloomberg in Arkansas after his horrible debate performance; and Biden in MA, ME, and the whole enchilada as well. I think I burned $25-100 on each bet, getting Warren 3c, Bloomberg 7c, and Biden at 10-15c. (Nate's chances were all about 80-100% higher.) Well, the Biden ones paid out, so that's another 7-10x, minus fees and other losses.</p>
      <p>This year I'm probably going to go with something between the 538 and Economist models as upper and lower bounds for Trump (the former has a 20% COVID-uncertainty term, which seems like a quick hack more than anything, while <a href="https://twitter.com/NateSilver538/status/1288899006018592768/photo/1">the latter treats current economic conditions as 40% worse than the Great Recession of '08-'09!</a>). A shout-out and a signal-boost, though, to <a href="https://nickyoder.com/">the recently-established site of one Nick Yoder (I don't know him personally),</a> who makes a lot of fascinating modeling points as well.</p>
      <p>Let me know if there's more I can answer, for you or for anyone else. I love talking political prediction markets!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>