<post>
  <author>Namrok</author>
  <date>2020-08-17T17:43:12Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ib82ju/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_17_2020/g1vx7tv/</link>
  <title>Values Drift in Treasured Communities</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I donno man.  Sometimes old timers get weird when the communities they have been a part of for almost a decade experience value drift.</p>
      <p>Happened to me once.  Was on a fairly heterodox super niche game/clan forum for, god, almost 20 years?  Started posting game fan fiction there in middle school, as it was generally the focus of the community.  Gradually it shifted towards just arguing about politics 24/7, and then the politics shifted full on woke, and then one woke moderator with access to too many systems managed to literally steal the hosting, and implemented a reign of terror banning everyone he disagreed with.</p>
      <p>Most even centrist people just tuned out and left.  Some right wingers just hung around, endlessly trolling.  The further left the forum drifted, the more inarticulate and low effort their trolling was.</p>
      <p>But when it comes to woke dogma, it's not hard to poke holes in it, even with inarticulate trolling.  So the same 4 or 5 remaining people posting there would just dogpile, quote a bunch of bizarre platitudes, and consider the trolling refuted.</p>
      <p>So this weird dynamic evolved where the trolls, who still felt some lingering attachment to the community, trolled because it was the only meaningful way they were left to engage with the community.  Every single conversation that was attempted to be started was either ignored if they started it, or pulled towards woke nonsense.  Say you enjoyed a Stardock published game?  Turns into a thread about Brad Wardell being gross and you are gross for playing his gross game.  Repeat with everything.</p>
      <p>God I hate the word gross now.</p>
      <p>Not long ago, the dynamics on the forum hit some sort of peak troll/counter troll.  Only 5 or 6 people even posted anymore, 2 of them were trolls, the other 4 just circle jerked whatever woke nonsense was in vogue.  The same admin who stole the site in the first place just unilaterally shut it down.  Grew sick of hosting a dead forum that only appeared to provide pleasure to trolls/his tribal enemies.  A buddy of mine created a discord channel that a bunch of refugees over the years migrated to, and now he wants to reboot the forum.  I don't see the point.  The problem was the people, and it'll just be the same people, all over again.</p>
      <p>Anyways.  It's possible Darwin has some attachment to this community, that used to align more closely with his values.  That the value drift it's experienced is painful to him, causes him to engage less genuinely, and the only echo of pleasure that once was that is available to him here is plausibly deniable trolling.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>