<post>
  <author>RIP_Finnegan</author>
  <date>2020-08-16T22:02:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i6yuis/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_10_2020/g1rzpjd/</link>
  <title>Excellence in the Academic Literature</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Well, I just meant this to be a book recommendation but it turned into a wall of text.</p>
      <p>The path to follow on this, if you want to get into the academic literature, would be Aristotelian virtue ethics and then probably Straussians. Straussians - and their right-wingier fellow travelers, Burnhamites - place great emphasis on the ancient heritage of the concept of excellence (<em>arete</em>, <em>virtu</em>, etc.), and its historical conflicts with the more 'modern' virtues of equality and freedom. Generally, they tend to argue that all of these have inescapable, tragic flaws, since the human condition is not perfectible. However, it is improvable, and it's possible to move from worse to better forms of each regime, partly by balancing the concerns of each of those three values. </p>
      <p>Excellence is particularly important, though, because it is a universal means. Whatever the partisans of equality or liberty want, greater excellence will help them achieve it, and a disregard of excellence will pull them back. Tyler Cowen's 'state capacity libertarianism' is a perfect example of a liberty-focused guy realizing this. Also, if this rhymes with Omohundro Drives/Nick Land/all the superintelligence stuff, that's not a coincidence. Superintelligence is excellence optimization. To bounce back a couple centuries, though, let's ask Hobbes what he has to say about intelligence/excellence/capacity:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The Passions that most of all cause the differences of Wit, are principally, the more or lesse Desire of Power, of Riches, of Knowledge, and of Honour. All which may be reduced to the first, that is Desire of Power. For Riches, Knowledge and Honour are but severall sorts of Power.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Let's put that in our terminology:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The Passions that most of all cause the differences of Wit, are principally, the more or lesse Desire of Power, of Equality, of Knowledge, and of Liberty. All which may be reduced to the first, that is Desire of Power. For Equality, Knowledge and Liberty are but severall outcomes of Power.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You're right to value excellence, because in many senses it is the supreme value which encompasses all others. However, what a rationalist reading this might say is something like: "Hey, Finn! Didn't you just compare excellence to the coming AI apocalypse? You might be a Yes Chad about replacing humanity with a technogod, but I'm not. Isn't that an argument against excellence, that it is so desirable it forces us to optimize for it and thus ignore other goods? In fact, couldn't you say that our values of equality and liberty are both designed to protect us against others attempting to maximize their excellence through political power?"</p>
      <p>Now, that would be getting to the Straussian heart of the matter. Strauss talks of 'the quarrel of the Ancients and the Moderns', which is fundamentally this: if we acknowledge that these political values are flawed, and no single one can be optimized for, how do we synthesize them? The Greeks talked of a cycle of regimes, with Aristotle's <em>Politics</em> and Xenophon's <em>Cyropaedia</em> detailing them exquisitely in city-states and empires respectively. The Romans believed in individual moral excellence, separate from politics, schools of which fought a running duel between its liberty-syncretic and equality-syncretic forms until Christianity won out. So that's the Ancients' case: the human condition necessitates that political regimes are not perfectible, and improving them - while laudable - will inevitably hit you down the road with the fatal flaw particular to the new regime you impose. It is, literally, a tragic worldview.</p>
      <p>The moderns, on the other hand, came in like an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0N_RO-jL-90">Epic Rap Battles of History team</a> and proclaimed that they've fixed everything. Hobbes is kind of a bridge, but the first truly modern thinkers are Francis Bacon and John Locke (soon joined by a bunch of very clever Frogs who would go on to inspire other, dumber Frenchmen to chop heads). The modern solution is to constrain political power by various means to stop people fighting over it, or at least reduce the collateral damage. This is a wide spectrum of methods, ranging from the US Constitution to Moldbug and his cryptographic weapons locks, but it's generally settled on constitutional liberal democracy as the most successful form. Fascism got whupped, the USSR fizzled out, and what was left was a total victory for a particular model of modernist government. However, a spectre is haunting modernity: the spectre of Xenophon. "Look," the spectre whispers "it's great that you've got such a stable regime. I'm genuinely chuffed for you. However, it is still just a regime. Like every human doing, it decays. It <em>needs</em> to decay, to maintain itself in power. And, once it decays enough, it must be replaced. And if we don't replace it with something better, others will replace it with something worse."</p>
      <p>So there we have it. The Moderns believe that they have stopped the cycle of history. The Ancients, borrowing the phrase which birthed modernity, whisper that <em>eppur si muove</em>. Could an emphasis on excellence break that deadlock and usher in a synthesis? Or would a transition to an excellence-based regime prove the Ancients right? Or, to think darkly for a moment, could it confirm the fears of the Moderns that we have it as good as it gets?</p>
      <p>The tides of history, not the letters of scholars, will decide for us.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>