<post>
  <author>roystgnr</author>
  <date>2020-08-13T15:54:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i8pqi9/trying_to_explore_the_divide_between_people_want/g1c7gbx/</link>
  <title>Modern Kids Are Useless</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I have no desire to live in a world where humans have been overtaken, even if it makes life "better" (subjective).</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think one of my biggest fears about teen suicide rates is that, not only is this despair at being overtaken a natural feeling, but it's now an immediate, concrete, and perhaps incompletely solvable problem, because to some extent <em>it's already happened</em>.  Over the last century and a bit, you've been overtaken, not directly by technology, but simply <em>by adults</em>.</p>
      <p>What were 17-year-olds doing at that age, through most of human prehistory?  Productive work alongside and in support of their community, probably specifically their parents.  At 17 you might not be as good as your elders at hunting (or gathering or knapping or carving or child tending or fire tending or building or tanning or whatever), but you'd probably been watching others for long enough to have learned to be decent at it, and if you weren't as good yet you were at least getting rapidly better, and your elders were all closely related enough to you that you had no reason to suspect you wouldn't be just as good as them soon ... and even in the mean time, everything you did as practice was probably at least good enough to be useful to yourself and your tribe.</p>
      <p>Most of human history didn't manage to change this too much, either.  Technology got more complicated than knapping stone, so you might have to have apprenticed to a specialist in your village rather than doing generalist tasks with your parents, but you'd still be doing useful gruntwork immediately and useful artisan work as you improved.</p>
      <p>But kids in modern times?  You're useless.</p>
      <p>If you're <em>lucky</em> you realize that this doesn't say anything about you in particular, because pretty much all your peers are equally useless, for the same nearly-unavoidable reasons.  If you're unlucky then you read about the one-in-ten-million "child genius invents foo" exceptions in the news, and your brain doesn't know how to divide a qualitative feeling by ten million, and so you feel <em>particularly</em> useless.</p>
      <p>You can't even really fix this by trying to become more useful.  Ironically you can just make it worse, because the more useful you want to be over the course of your life, the more education that now requires, and most of our educations aren't apprenticeships: before you graduate or at least reach "senior research project" or "masters thesis" levels, you spend all your time producing work whose sole value is the exercise your brain gets, not anything publishable much less tangible.  Until then, you're useless.</p>
      <p>From an economic standpoint, this is fine!  You're instantaneously useless because you're investing in yourself in a way that's likely to make you much more useful in the future, and integrating that over a life span it turns out to be nearly impossible for you not to be <em>much</em> more useful to society than even the most talented stone-age tribesman.  Even if you're on the bottom end of the talent distribution, you are likely still going to be more productive than them (thanks technology), more wealthy than them (thanks Baumol effect), and contribute more to society than them (thanks specialization and trade).</p>
      <p>The problem is, I don't think our hindbrains understand all that.  We can learn about "producer surplus" and "consumer surplus", but it doesn't "feel" correct.  We didn't evolve in a world where genius inventors become even more productive when non-genius tradesmen provide them with more free time by trading their services for the inventors' money, we evolved in a world where if someone was much more productive than you that was because they weren't a failure and you were.  We can learn about long-term investment, but even after the invention of agriculture that used to at most mean "preparing for the next harvest or two".  We didn't evolve in a world where 17 year olds are expected to at best just barely able to find productive employment, we evolved in a world where a 17 year old was either practically an adult or was clearly a failure.</p>
      <p>Maybe suicidal tendencies are just brokenness, because the mind is complex and easy to break, whereas in the face of evolution you'd think that killing yourself is just about the <em>least</em> sensible thing possible.  But what I fear is: what if there <em>is</em> an evolutionarily stable tendency to consider suicide <em>when you feel like a total failure</em>?  Occasionally a really bad roll of the genetic dice or a really bad illness would leave someone incapable of surviving without assistance, a continual burden on their family and friends and tribe, and in that case the best thing you could do for them, at least in the cold-hearted evolutionary sense, would be to end the burden.  That probably hasn't been true since the development of civilization (IIRC definitionally according to Margaret Mead: one of the first archaeological signs of civilization is when you find incapacitating bone injuries that were given enough time and support to heal rather than becoming fatal), and it's definitely not true in the rich modern world where food is cheap and loved ones precious, but those aren't the worlds we evolved in.</p>
      <p>There are a lot of superstimuli in the modern world that we're just not evolved to deal with - TV news from across the world that feels like it's happening to us, celebrities who feel like friends and leaders, omnipresent junk foods whose tastes feel like we're getting rare treats ... what if this extended adolescence is a superstimulus for failure?  Biological near-adults, with instincts telling them they should be productive and independent, are instead required to sit still and be instructed to do seemingly-valueless exercises for year after year, as if they were remedial basketweavers being continually punished for unending incompetence.  So their hindbrains learn "I'm useless", and maybe we're lucky that so few of them fail to internalize that this is a temporary condition, not a permanent failing.</p>
      <p>From what I've read of sociology, what makes the most difference here is cultural tradition: it's easier to put up with a temporary lack of obvious meaning to your life if you can see your life as a whole, or even better as part of a larger story that gives it a greater meaning.  Maybe that's another thing getting pulled away from at first-world adolescents today?  Community services are now government services, the higher up the better for the sake of efficiency and reach, but no amount of "it takes a village to raise a child" rhetoric will make DC feel like it's your homely village.  Or, even if you still wholeheartedly believe in a religion or an ideological mass movement, you've at least got to be somewhat uncomfortably aware that the majority of the world disagrees with your pick and yet seems to be muddling along about as well as you are, and that there had better be something pretty special about your pick to distinguish it from all the similar movements that have historically gone overboard and done more harm than good.</p>
      <p>I believe there are ways out of this.  If happiness is composed of pleasure, flow/engagement, and meaning, no level of social or technological obsolescence can take away the first two.  Pleasure gets easier to obtain with technology, and technology removes practical barriers to e.g. artistic engagement, even if it's temptations might enlarge the barrier of willpower.  For those to whom those two components aren't quite enough on their own, it would still take an astounding level of change to completely remove the third.  To some extent, variety becomes more affordable as technology becomes more powerful; in a technological utopia there would always be dignity and meaning for dissenters to obtain as part of "the control group".  Even in a technological dystopia, there would at least be meaning to obtain as part of "the resistance" for as long as that went on.</p>
      <p>In a sense, although the need to find meaning can be feel like an overwhelming problem in the short run, it almost tautologically has to be the <em>last</em> real problem we'll face in the long run, doesn't it?  The Effective Altruism people aren't likely to need to pack up and close up shop any time soon.  So long as we can see that all other problems haven't been solved (hey, that TV news was good for something after all!) then we can find meaning in helping to be part of the solution, even if only indirectly.</p>
      <p>(sorry for the dump truck of overwrought speculation - chunks of these thoughts have been churning in my head for years, and I guess they were just waiting for the slightest excuse to try to fit them all together...)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>