<post>
  <author>UltraRedSpectrum</author>
  <date>2020-08-14T00:13:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/i6yuis/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_10_2020/g1dzouj/</link>
  <title>Jewish Over-Representation and Antisemitism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I don't think it's reasonable to separate Jewish and non-Jewish white people. Jews are one of several extremely high-performing subgroups within the broader white population. They're over-represented and it stands out more because it's easier to count Jews than most other subgroups, but there are plenty of other subgroups that are over-represented in positions of power. Mormons and Presbyterians stand out as two obvious examples, but let's not forget that a disproportionate number of US Presidents have had Irish heritage.</p>
      <p>Also (and now I reveal that I'm the real conspiracy nut in this conversation), I want to comment on something that was brought up downthread.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Elite outlets such as NYT are publishing <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161218170517/https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/02/26/us/race-of-american-power.html">"Faces of power"</a> collages which explicitly claim that all institutional power in the country belongs to "white people", i.e. lacks diversity.  </p>
        <p>-snip-  </p>
        <p>(Of the 19 “Whites” shown, 15 are Jews.)</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Every time one of these things comes up, I worry that these elite outlets might not be dumb as the quoted passage seems to think they are. Somehow all the things they say about "white people" are exactly the same things antisemitists used to say about Jewish people, before antisemitism went out of fashion. And for some reason most of the "white people" they highlight as having "institutional power" turn out to be Jewish.</p>
      <p>You, oaklandbrokeland, are not a real antisemitist. You don't actually hate Jewish people, or even dislike them. (This shouldn't be controversial; if it is, it's because the waters of antisemitism have been clouded. You are nothing like any antisemitist, past or present. It bothers me that our stock image of an antisemitist is someone who cites accurate statistics about Jewish people, while someone who advocates for mass murder flies under the radar so long as they refer to "the rich.")</p>
      <p>But there are plenty of people who hate Jewish people. Hate as in the emotion. Hate as in frothing at the mouth. They may think of Jewish people using some other word, like "white," to protect themselves from the knowledge that they share an opinions with some unpleasant Germans from 1938, but they hate. They post about it on social media, they rant about it in public, they march in the streets, and they wallow in their hatred. And if you check which individual people they direct their hated at, a lot of them turn out to be Jewish.</p>
      <p>Let's borrow some Wokeness for this analysis: A <em>real</em> antisemitist would use dog whistles to hide his true intentions. He would refer to, I don't know, an international power structure designed to benefit one race at the expense of all others. Perhaps a real antisemitist would construct a narrative about how some easily-scapegoated group of people is responsible for all the world's ills. A real antisemitist might even publish the faces of 15 Jewish people in a newspaper and accuse them of conspiring to control a major industry. But most of all, a real antisemitist would protect himself from accusations of antisemitism by using a euphemism to avoid being pattern-matched to a certain genocidal German. A euphemism like, oh, I don't know, "white people."</p>
      <p>Those nasty white people who control Hollywood and the banks. Those nasty white people who built America's wealth on the backs of black slaves (because the South is just lousy with 300-year-old accumulated capital). Those nasty white people who plundered the resources of Africa and Asia (because the Russians had so many overseas colonies). Those nasty white people and their international conspiracy of world domination.</p>
      <p>Look, I don't actually think many, or even any, of the writers for the NYT are crypto-Nazis.  But at the same time, it's impossible to ignore the historical reality that European-derived countries have a tendency to genocide their Jewish populations every once in a while, and I'm getting <em>concerned</em>.</p>
      <p>I'm concerned that the centers of power just brushed off famous celebrities retweeting Louis Farrakhan inaccurately quoting Hitler. I'm concerned by all the "eat the rich" and "kill the bankers" talk I hear in casual conversation. I'm concerned history is threatening to repeat itself.</p>
      <p>Call me crazy, because maybe I am, but if there was a real antisemitic conspiracy afoot, it would look exactly like our elite institutions look right now.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>