<post>
  <author>FCfromSSC</author>
  <date>2020-05-19T23:20:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr6p4sn/</link>
  <title>The #BelieveWomen Memeplex</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Hashtags exist to support policy goals. The policy goals in question here are not obscure; they've been a major battlefield in the culture war for six years running.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/11/Murphy.pdf">TeamHarpy:</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>What this looks like:  </p>
        <p>Don't ask for 'proof'.  </p>
        <p>Don't treat 'both sides of the story' as if they hold equal weight.  </p>
        <p>Do not engage in any type of victim blaming behavior.  </p>
        <p>Listen to the victim. Do it. And don't judge.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The article is worth reading in full to get a sense of the angle they're coming from.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2014/12/06/no-matter-what-jackie-said-we-should-automatically-believe-rape-claims/">The Washington Post:</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Now <a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/culture/news/a-note-to-our-readers-20141205">the narrative</a> appears to be <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/education/u-va-fraternity-to-rebut-claims-of-gang-rape-in-rolling-stone/2014/12/05/5fa5f7d2-7c91-11e4-84d4-7c896b90abdc_story.html?tid=lk_inline_manual_3&amp;itid=lk_inline_manual_3">falling apart</a>: Her rapist wasn’t in the frat that she says he was a member of; the house held no party on the night of the assault; and other details are wobbly. Many people (not least U-Va. administrators) will be tempted to see this as a reminder that officials, reporters and the general public should hear both sides of the story and collect all the evidence before coming to a conclusion in rape cases. This is what we mean in America when we say someone is “innocent until proven guilty.” After all, look what happened to the Duke lacrosse players.  </p>
        <p>In important ways, this is wrong. We should believe, as a matter of default, what an accuser says. Ultimately, the costs of wrongly disbelieving a survivor far outweigh the costs of calling someone a rapist. Even if Jackie fabricated her account, U-Va. should have taken her word for it during the period while they endeavored to prove or disprove the accusation. This is not a legal argument about what standards we should use in the courts; it’s a moral one, about what happens <em>outside</em> the legal system.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This, after one of the most publicized false rape accusations in recent history. Note that the original title of the piece, still visible in the URL, is "no matter what Jackie said, we should automatically believe rape claims".</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.vox.com/2014/10/13/6966847/yes-means-yes-is-a-terrible-bill-and-i-completely-support-it">Ezra Klein, for Vox</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Then there's the true nightmare scenario: completely false accusations of rape by someone who did offer consent, but now wants to take it back. I don't want to say these kinds of false accusations never happen, because <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/double_x/doublex/2014/09/false_rape_accusations_why_must_be_pretend_they_never_happen.html"><strong>they do happen</strong></a>, and they're awful. <em>But they happen very, very rarely</em>. Sexual assault on college campuses, by contrast, happens constantly. This is, in a way, the definition of what it means to be entitled: the rules are designed to protect you from dangers that barely exist at the expense of exposing others to constant threat.  </p>
        <p>Colleges have settled into an equilibrium where too little counts as sexual assault, where the ambiguity of consent gives rapists loopholes in which to hide, and forces women to spend their lives afraid. The Yes Means Yes laws creates an equilibrium where too much counts as sexual assault. Bad as it is, that's a necessary change. A culture where one-in-five women is assaulted isn't going to be dislodged with a gentle nudge. A culture where a frat thinks its funny to <a href="http://www.salon.com/2014/10/08/fraternity_loses_its_charter_for_displaying_pro_rape_no_means_yes_sign_at_a_party/?utm_source=twitter&amp;utm_medium=socialflow"><strong>throw a party</strong></a> with signs that say "No means yes, yes means anal" won't fall without a fight. Ugly problems don't always have pretty solutions.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>...and of course there are many, many more, from a wide variety of prominent progressives. Several common themes emerge:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>There are a very large number of rapes committed in our society each year, and only a small minority of these rapes are reported, much less successfully prosecuted. This is a crisis that demands strong and immediate action.</li>
        <li>False rape accusations are extremely rare. Therefore, if a woman accuses someone of rape, she is almost certainly telling the truth.</li>
        <li>Questioning rape accusations harms the victim psychologically and discourages them from pressing charges against their attacker.</li>
        <li>Concepts of due process do not apply outside the formal justice system. Appeals to such concepts outside of court serves mainly to protect rapists and re-victimize survivors. Administrative and social punishments should be levied against an accused rapist without concern for fairness or due process.</li>
        <li>The trauma of rape often makes women's accounts unreliable; there is no "perfect victim", and we should not use contradictions or false statements made by a victim to call her accusation into question.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>This memeplex, of which #BelieveWomen is only a more recent offshoot, has been an active and extremely prominent part of the culture war since at least 2014, if not earlier. It has been enacted into federal policy. There is an absolute ocean of arguments, official positions and enforced policies to refer to, if one is not familiar with the specifics.</p>
      <p>This memeplex is what people on both sides are referring to when they talk about the<br />
 #BelieveWomen hashtag. This is not a fallacious invocation of motte and baily, or gas-lighting on the part of red tribers. This has been one of the highest-profile Progressive policies of the last decade.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>