<post>
  <author>hoverburger</author>
  <date>2020-05-19T17:29:37Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr5j2tb/</link>
  <title>How US Civil War II Could Happen</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Pithy, not practical: Unless and until you've hit probabilistic subatomic particles and invoked the dread 'quantum', the perception of some uncertainty as aleatory rather than epistemic is just a reflection of the shallow knowledge pool being drawn from.  </p>
      <p>Basically all of the events in that list could, in theory, have been predicted.  They probably were seen as possibilities - just ones remote enough to not bother worrying about.</p>
      <p>In that spirit, I'll take something that can be - and has been - predicted at very low probability and throw it out as the next big thing.  A United States Civil War 2, albeit one that plays out much weirder.  To convince those here (and myself) that it's a real possibility...  </p>
      <p>The divide is growing (to my eye non-linearly) and we're losing the ability to agree on <em>anything</em> above the level of "some food tastes good" by the day.  I have friends who are light-blue that refuse to converse with family members that are light-red.  Not "don't get along" or "dread the Thanksgiving argument" but <em>refuse to converse</em>.  The extremes expand away from the center (and possibly asymptotically towards one another along a closed curve...) at seemingly supersonic speeds, the proportion of the population in the middle shrinks, the sphere of what you are permitted to hate encroaches on ever lighter shades of the enemy, the sphere of what you are <em>required</em> to hate grows at a non-zero rate (which is incredibly alarming!!!) and I don't see a safe way out.  People aren't reasonable enough on a good day, and the 2020 election will not be a good day.  2024 will be worse.  2028?  I'd give it [insert low but still scary percentage] odds that either the summer of 2028 or the period between the election and inauguration give us the spark that lights this bad boy up and we see tens or hundreds of thousands dead.  No, it won't look quite like the original Civil War because there won't be a geographic line that divides the halves (being largely rural vs urban), and there will be <em>less</em>, but far from zero, state action.  Less formal, more guerilla.  Despite the apparent lack of arms in the hands of the blue tribe, it won't be a slaughter.  There will be people who sit out, there will be blues that arm themselves beforehand, there will be "red" defectors who can't condone killing outside of self defense and will provide cover for unarmed blues, there may even be some actual segments of the military under blue control (as odd as that sounds).  The bulk of the federal government, including most of the military, will be paralyzed and unable to support either side.  </p>
      <p>I would lean towards blue sending in a reluctant state force to put down a bunch of reds for breaking laws they strenuously object to and openly flout (though to their credit, peacefully) as the first large act of true violence.  Nobody <em>actually</em> learned anything from Ruby Ridge or Waco, they just upped the threshold required to do that again.  Alternatively, I could see a series of coordinated and armed red storms shutting down clinics and/or university departments until one of them fires back (while <em>not</em> actually sufficiently armed to defend themselves) and causing a whole lot of highly sympathetic blue deaths.  </p>
      <p>Yeah, that sounds about right for "major event that could have been predicted and maybe was albeit at very-low-odds, which the aftermath will refer to as a black swan which completely upends the state of the world".  If it's a horse race between all of them, and Status Quo isn't allowed to compete, that's where I'd put my money.  AI won't go foom yet, a second global pandemic would be lightning striking twice, nuclear war is still off the table for a while yet, aliens... nah.  UBI will never meaningfully happen prior to post-scarcity (it could be tried, but won't work right for second order reasons).  </p>
      <p>To be clear, I'm actually partial to Status Quo and the next decade not being substantially different from the point of view of first world nations, but this thread is for the big shifts.  I think the runner up relates to China and manufacturing, but the <em>big</em> swing will take longer than that as China tries its hardest to incentivize global supply chains to keep them in the loop.  So, Civil War it is.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>