<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-05-19T00:46:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr33hcg/</link>
  <title>Provocation from the Weimar elites</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Look, none of this justifies the alt-right. Nowhere was Arendt saying that the Nazis had been in the right, not at all. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Condemning Nazis is a given. But the other question remains: were the many ordinary Germans, insulted by Weimar decadence and hypocrisy, right about lending Nazis (really a whole bunch of right-wing and sometimes left-wing movements, which only later were pruned into Hitler-approved shape) their silent or vocal approval for dismantling Weimar status quo in early 30s? Very few could foresee the sheer scope and violence of things to come, but everyone could make a judgement about elites active at the moment, and notice their smug enjoyment of effective cultural monopoly, and complete unwillingness to cede ground. It's not just that open malice is more attractive to onlookers than insincere, duplicitous one: it's that you feel liberated when refusing to play by the rules your enemy has forced on you, shaking off the rhetorical framing and win-lose-foul conditions. This is most easily understood by people who were bullied as children. Bullies are, contrary to the way normies imagine it, extraordinarily good at <em>not</em> being openly violent; the most talented ones avoid even straighforward verbal abuse, goading others and provoking the victim with clever, biting mockery and concern-trolling advice instead. To an intelligent onlooker, the nature of the act is obvious, but it can get exasperating thinking of how to intervene legitimately, so most don't think. When the despairing victim stops pleading and negotiating and lifts his fist, it's used against him, complained about to the authorities; but it's an act of refusing to justify your appeals to a hopelessly hostile interlocutor, and thus a release from mental prison. It's no wonder school losers are associated in public consciousness with school shooters, and incels, and right-wing extremists, and white supremacists, and Nazis. </p>
      <p>The problem is, it's not a relatively minor issue of class animus (or class bullying). In modern America, liberals easily brush off every notion of their actions being in any way harmful, and even here we mainly discuss tolerable and sometimes rather abstract problems: censorship of inherently inflammatory beliefs, effective one-party control of mechanisms of social networking, ineffective solutions to social injustices, economic damage, exacerbation of tribalism. But elites like these create a rather suffocating atmosphere. However much we ridicule Alex Jones, he expresses a sentiment far more common than can be admitted in a polite society: that the elites are <a href="https://thealexjonesprisonplanet.bandcamp.com/track/image-of-the-beast-erased-forever">"Satanic", "parasitic" and actively anti-life in general</a>, to the extent irreconcilable with long-term survival of the group (<em>"...And destroy the great birth right that you are given As builders of this world And builders of countless more to come"</em>). Maybe his target audience really is the 21st century's equivalent of cartoonish superstitious peasants with pitchforks. But from elite's viewpoint, aren't they even less than that, some sort of unattractive local fauna, pests you've formally got to tolerate while developing your industry? As Tucker Carlson <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/PoliticalCompassMemes/comments/fwnwft/peak_auth_unity_achieved/fmtiglr/">allegedly</a> said: <em>"if I could tell working Americans one thing, it's that your elites hate you. I used to hobnob with these people. They hate you, they hate your work, they hate your families, they hate your religion, they hate your way of life."</em> Tucker is playing to his audience, too. And they want to hear what they already feel. </p>
      <p>Man is a strange creature, a mix of robust and fragile parts. He can live in a pod and eat bugs, grow up inhaling lead and still work for 60 years straight. But stress him out with evidence of inferiority and his cardiovascular system falters, his hormone levels out of whack; put him in a buzzing city and his reproductive ability is drastically reduced; surround him with revolting art and neurosis-inducing propaganda and ugly modernist architecture and he feels that the world is a bleak dystopia despite unprecedented, if a little distasteful, material prosperity in every bite of HFCS-filled junk food. Make him feel unwelcome, at the brink of exile from community, gaslight him into doubting his sanity -- and he'll either break down, eventually dying of despair, or rebel against this increasingly hostile, censorious, alien hellscape and its apparent masters (or, at least, those who seem to revel in his suffering). You can shut down every avenue of legitimate public expression for him, taboo the very words he could use to express his yearnings; but he'll connect the dots on his own, and chances are, he'll do so in the most destructive and misguided way possible.  </p>
      <p>Peter Turchin has this neat idea about elite overproduction as the mechanism of civilizational collapse. Despite the fact that "elite" status is kind of relative by definition, it is possible to make a plurality, if not the majority, of people imbued with the sense of their "eliteness" and all associated values. I wonder if this has something to do with the degree creep in the US and ideological capture of scientific institutions; with the way the noun "elites" is so often accompanied by adjective "educated"; with the enforced <a href="https://aeon.co/ideas/say-goodbye-to-the-information-age-its-all-about-reputation-now">cult of credibility</a> and the way mediocre liberals are invested in this image of science-loving erudites who talk in a patronising fashion to the uncouth masses. Then, with a bit of clever coalition-building and immigration policy, it's possible to not only disorganize and shout down the plebs, but also outnumber them; or so the plan goes. It might work; it might fail. If there's no such plan at all, that's a tragedy in and of itself, because it will still be resisted. </p>
      <p>To answer the question in first paragraph: I suppose ordinary Germans were wrong to support Nazis and their associates even in the early 30s. But Weimar elites were very, very wrong to not share with the common man, both financially and culturally. They could have done everyone a service by toning their hostility down a notch or two. Alas.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>