<post>
  <author>Iron-And-Rust</author>
  <date>2020-05-19T22:02:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr6gdle/</link>
  <title>The Unintuitive Draw of Unfaithful Partners</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Well, there's something inherently more attractive about a man who other women desire. That's something like the woman's equivalent of men liking big boobs, to put it crudely. If other women like a man, that's a sexual trigger in women. Other women liking your man would turn you on.</p>
      <p>Of course, you don't actually want your man sleeping with those other women. You want him all to yourself, even as other women lust after him. But we see these competing concerns playing themselves out chaotically in reality. It's not so simple as "unfaithful man" being an instant dealbreaker. It's more like it competes with the appeal of having a man who <em>could</em> be unfaithful if he wanted to. And he almost kind of has to skirt really close to the edge of being unfaithful once in a while to prove that he can be. So you may grow to tolerate a man who only occasionally sleeps around, but you may set limits on it, like, he may sleep with women, but he isn't allowed to do things that indicate he cares about them. He may <em>fuck</em> them, but he <em>loves</em> you; he's still faithful, within this rationalization.</p>
      <p>There's also the problem where faithfulness isn't simply a statistic on someone's character sheet. What leads to that behaviour also leads to other behaviours, so in selecting against it you may simultaneously select against other positive behaviours to which it is intrinsically linked. Perhaps ideally, an "intrinsically" unfaithful man would employ his willpower to resist his unfaithful urges, thus giving you all the upsides to which it is linked without any of the downsides. But even there, he still has to expend willpower to resist that urge, which means he isn't expending it on something else negative.</p>
      <p>Ultimately, it's very hard to balance this stuff. But people do seem to have some intuitive understanding of these dynamics. Which is why you see things like women not allowing their men to have one-on-one private conversations with other women. They know what's going on: That they selected for a man who they know could be unfaithful, who in some situations probably would be unfaithful, but he resists the urge to do so through willpower, through planning his life around those situations not occurring, etc., like an alcoholic avoiding alcohol. She also helps out, by keeping her watchful eye on him, for those moments when he otherwise would fail. Of course, she also keeps a really watchful eye on other women, to make sure they don't worm their way around her man's defences, as she knows women are good at doing because she's good at doing it. But then when he fails, as you maybe expected him to, you may not necessarily see that as such a big deal, at least as long as he quickly breaks it off to show he cares more about you than her. You may even feel you failed with him, since you knew he was this way and you failed to help him resist it and to ward the women away. At least as long as e.g., he recognizes it as a failure and seeks to avoid the same thing happening again; having learned that he can't trust himself in the situation that lead to it.</p>
      <p>We might even frame this behaviour in men as an uncontrollable urge, which is how a lot of traditional societies frame it. I'm reminded of the back-and-forth between Scott and Bryan Caplan, specifically the recent <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2020/01/15/contra-contra-contra-caplan-on-psych/">CONTRA CONTRA CONTRA CAPLAN ON PSYCH</a>, where he uses the analogy of a person with tourettes who <em>can</em> resist slapping himself in the face if you put a gun to his head... but eventually, hold it there for long enough, and they choose the bullet over having to resist the urge. That's not to excuse men who cheat as somehow acting on something beyond their own control (except in the pedantic, "deterministically, everything is our of our control" sense), and personally I think cheating on your partner is deeply immoral and one of the worst betrayals you could do to someone (but that's my cognitive profile, which isn't the same as everyone else's), but I think there is a non-trivial amount of truth to this. Like a woman's body can't resist being overpowered by a man physically, a man's mind often can't resist being overpowered by a woman sexually. And I think that people act as if this is true is strong evidence of it being true. But that your body can't resist being thrown out the window during a collision doesn't mean you don't take measures to prevent that from happening. You try your best to avoid situations that might result in your body being propelled through your windshield, and you have countermeasures ready for if the worst does still happen. So you drive carefully and you wear a seat belt.</p>
      <p>Anyway. I think it's more complicated than "she just couldn't do anything about it". This happens all the time this day as well, and women are perfectly able to do lots of things about it, but they still tolerate it and sometimes seem to even enjoy it.</p>
      <p>But naturally, as an aside, if someone sees men and women as exactly (or even largely) the same, and so see women's sexual choices from the perspective that they <em>want</em> to act like men but they just aren't able to because they're so weak and powerless and oppressed, then this doesn't make much sense. Men rarely care what other men think about their women, except to keep those men away from her. A man sees his sexual triggers and he's ready to go. What you think about my woman's tits doesn't really matter to me. Heck, if you think they're shit then that might be a good thing; less competition. Of course, I might not tolerate you saying that out loud in public. But what another woman thinks about your man does matter to you. Which makes sense, considering the different mating strategies. Men want fertile women, and the things women do remain largely the same type of low-risk stuff everywhere you go. But men are more varied, and what exactly you should look for in one isn't obvious. Women want men who are well-adapted to their environment, and since humans seem to be something like niche-explorers - we seek out novel environments and adapt to them through learning - how exactly that looks changes a lot depending on the local environment. So she has a much harder decision to make than a man has, and one of the ways she deals with this is by outsourcing a lot of the work of figuring out which men are Good Men to the greater social network. So you would expect women to be turned on by men who turn other women on. And if the price of that is that he sleeps around when you're not watching, then, well, maybe the cost of watching your Good Man after you've bagged him is lower than the cost of finding one among all the substandard stuff on offer. Also keep in mind that, the perfect is the enemy of the good. You won't find a perfect man, but you may find a good one, and that's better than a "good enough" one.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>