<post>
  <author>kromkonto69</author>
  <date>2020-05-19T06:07:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr3wq3b/</link>
  <title>Gun Control: A numbers-driven analysis</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm arguing with a friend about gun control, and did the following little write up for them. I wasn't going for total scientific rigor, but I would very much appreciate any critique people have to offer, or areas where my reasoning is weak or motivated. The context of this conversation is that my friend claimed that owning firearms for self-defense doesn't make sense, since firearms pose more of a risk to your family and friends than any benefit they end up providing.</p>
      <p>(Sources at end)</p>
      <p>So, I've been going through the CDC data, and I don't think firearm ownership poses all that big of a risk to a person or their loved one's and friends. (This is only going to be looking at the question 'are you putting your friends and family at risk for very little benefit if you own a firearm and keep it in your house?')</p>
      <p>First, accidental deaths and injuries.</p>
      <p>In 2018, there were 458 unintentional firearm deaths - most of which happened in people's houses. Pretty comparable to unintentional pedal cyclist deaths - 342. Way behind the #1 and #2 unintentional cause of death: accidental poisoning at 62,399 (which is mostly due to drug overdoses) and motor vehicle traffic 37,991.</p>
      <p>That number is also comparable to the number of children 1-4 who died in unintentional drownings 443, most of which happened in backyard pools. (Only 30 1-4 year olds died in unintentional firearm incidents.)</p>
      <p>Now aside from deaths, there is the matter of injuries requiring hospitalization. For every unintentional firearm fatality, there are more than 10 injuries requiring treatment in an emergency room - resulting in ~5000 injuries. However, something like 60% are treated and released - only ~15% required hospitalization. For comparison, the ratio of unintentional deaths to unintentional injuries requiring treatment in hospitals is much higher for pedal cyclists. That is, because a comparable number are unintentionally killed due to pedal cycling and firearms - way more people require treatment in emergency rooms due to pedal cycling related accidents than require treatment due to firearm related accidents.</p>
      <p>So, on this dimension firearms are comparable to pedal cycling in their risk profile. Now, the question would be if firearms provide as much utility as pedal cycling. If not, then perhaps the risk isn't worth it.</p>
      <p>Second, the elephant in the room - suicides.</p>
      <p>The biggest risk factor for private firearm ownership in the house is suicide - there were 23,854 suicides in 2018. 5 to 14 year olds in the United States are about 8 times more likely to die via firearm suicide than kids in other OECD countries.</p>
      <p>Third, homicides.</p>
      <p>While most homicides are commited by someone who knew the victim, it does not appear that keeping your gun in the home is actually that big of a homicide risk - to quote Hemenway (2011), "Whereas most firearm suicides shoot themselves at home with the family gun, most homicide victims — except for children and older adults — are not shot at home. And those shot outside the home are almost always shot with someone else’s gun. So although the existing ecological studies provide evidence about whether more guns in the community are associated with more homicides in the community, the results have limited relevance concerning whether a gun in your own home increases or reduces your own risk of homicide."</p>
      <p>Finally, the possible benefits.</p>
      <p>In 1994, Ikeda et al. used data from a phone survey to conclude that each year there are around 497,646 incidents where a home invasion occurs, a firearm is retrieved and the home invader is scared away with a firearm.</p>
      <p>Priorities for Research to Reduce the Threat of Firearm-Related Violence (2013) has both a low esitimate of 108,000 annual defensive uses based on the National Crime Victimization Survey (compared to 300,000 violent crimes involving firearms in 2008) or (and I lend less credence to these) other estimates ranging from 500,000 to more than 3 million.</p>
      <p>In 1990, Kleck et al. looked at methods of resisting rape, and whether they resulted in further injury besides rape to the woman resisting rape for a sample of 571,811 rapes and attempted rapes. Women who resisted rape using guns were succesful in stopping the rape 99.91% of the time, and they were further injured by their attacker 0% of the time. Compare to those who defended themselves with knives, who were succesful in stopping rape 100% of the time, and were further injured by their attacker 69.4% of the time.</p>
      <p>The problem with all of these is that they are very speculative. Everywhere (even the pro-gun researchers) acknowledge that determining the exact number of defensive gun uses is very difficult. Most defensive gun uses probably never get reported to authorities, especially those where the "gun use" just consists in raising a gun to prevent someone from commiting a crime, while never firing it.</p>
      <p>I think with as much uncertainty as there is, the two most important factors are - how much do you weight the increased risk of suicide? All the other costs are swallowed up by that number. Then you have to look at benefits, and see if even the low esitimates of 108,000 annual defensive uses is worth it to you.</p>
      <p>Sources:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            <a href="https://webappa.cdc.gov/cgi-bin/broker.exe?_service=v8prod&amp;_server=aspv-wisq-1.cdc.gov&amp;_port=5099&amp;_sessionid=UellQVANQ52&amp;_program=wisqars.dd_leadcaus10.sas&amp;log=1&amp;rept=&amp;State=00&amp;year1=2018&amp;year2=2018&amp;Race=0&amp;Ethnicty=0&amp;Sex=0&amp;ranking=20&amp;PRTFMT=FRIENDLY&amp;lcdfmt=lcd1age&amp;category=UNI&amp;c_age1=0&amp;c_age2=0&amp;_debug=0">https://webappa.cdc.gov/cgi-bin/broker.exe?_service=v8prod&amp;_server=aspv-wisq-1.cdc.gov&amp;_port=5099&amp;_sessionid=UellQVANQ52&amp;_program=wisqars.dd_leadcaus10.sas&amp;log=1&amp;rept=&amp;State=00&amp;year1=2018&amp;year2=2018&amp;Race=0&amp;Ethnicty=0&amp;Sex=0&amp;ranking=20&amp;PRTFMT=FRIENDLY&amp;lcdfmt=lcd1age&amp;category=UNI&amp;c_age1=0&amp;c_age2=0&amp;_debug=0</a>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/PDF/ss/ss5307.pdf">https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/PDF/ss/ss5307.pdf</a>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/fastats/suicide.htm">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/fastats/suicide.htm</a>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <a href="https://www.hoplofobia.info/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/1997-Estimating-Intruder-Related-Firearm-Retrievals-in-U.S.-Households.pdf">https://www.hoplofobia.info/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/1997-Estimating-Intruder-Related-Firearm-Retrievals-in-U.S.-Households.pdf</a>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/249985228_Rape_and_Resistance">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/249985228_Rape_and_Resistance</a>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <a href="https://www.nap.edu/read/18319/chapter/3">https://www.nap.edu/read/18319/chapter/3</a>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <a href="https://www.comedsoc.org/images/Risk%20Guns%20at%20Home%20Hemenway%20Am%20J%20Lifestyle%20Med%206-12_copy1.pdf">https://www.comedsoc.org/images/Risk%20Guns%20at%20Home%20Hemenway%20Am%20J%20Lifestyle%20Med%206-12_copy1.pdf</a>
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>