<post>
  <author>Mexatt</author>
  <date>2020-05-20T05:33:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr7on0p/</link>
  <title>Tax Curves, Factories, Unions, and the Misrepresented Past</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I can't ask him how economically secure or insecure he felt while supporting a wife and five children working for the telephone company.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I can answer for him: Pretty damned secure.</p>
      <p>Bell employees and the employees of the Baby Bells that have stayed mostly unionized labor have and continue to do well. It's not like it once was, but it's still a solid job with good job security. It was even <em>moreso</em> back then, of course, because Telco service was highly price regulated and Bell employees were an absolutely <strong>gigantic</strong> voting block across the whole country. When Bell went hat-in-hand asking to raise tariffs to the local regulator, if the union leadership said jump then politicians leaned on the regulator to make it happen for Bell if they wanted to continue to win elections. Then Bell would split the proceeds with the unions in the next round of CBAs.</p>
      <p>There are less of those good jobs around with Baby Bells than there used to be, but mostly because Bell literally invented the computer age and digital automation to deal with its absurd labor costs. A CO with an ESS digital switch has a tiny portion of the labor force of a CO with a step switch (and modern COs with VoIP equipment are un-manned, mostly).</p>
      <p>But that's just one company (and its court-ordered divestments). Even then I'd be willing to bet modern field techs working for Bell Atlantic or Bell South/whatever their modern company names are get paid better in inflation adjusted terms than the telephone repair men of yesteryear. The guy who installed my internet a few years ago told me he made $140,000 between overtime and profit sharing the year before.</p>
      <p>This is pretty generally true. Incomes in the 50's and 60's more resemble modern Russia or Italy (Russia at the beginning, Italy at the end) than modern American incomes. Not desperately poor, by any means, but a bit austere by our standards. If you have any older relatives left beyond your grandpa ask then how many times they went out to eat in a year.</p>
      <p>The narrative that people in the 50's were <em>better off</em> than people today is essentially completely false. Incomes are way up, most things are way cheaper, some things that didn't exist back then are affordable and easy to get, and those few things that are more expensive/harder to get have some ameliorating circumstances (healthcare, for example -- the standard of healthcare available to someone in the 1950's is actually still pretty cheap: just don't whine about dieing in your 60's; or college, where college is more expensive today but most people in the 50's just didn't actually <em>go</em> to college to pay those cheap 1950's prices).</p>
      <p>Things aren't perfect today by any means, but people who get nostalgic for the post-war boom like <em>it would actually be an improvement to go back</em> are fooling themselves.</p>
      <p>As to the actual point you're making:</p>
      <p>Super high tax rates aren't really about raising revenue. Art Laffer himself is a bit of a kook and the Laffer Curve has been abused by anti-tax people for decades, but the fundemental insight that there are diminishing returns to rate increases is true. Super high tax rates aren't about raising revenue, they're about suppressing incomes. Very high incomes in those days didn't exist because it didn't make sense to pay your superstar employees a whole bunch of cash when 90% of it would be taxed away. Instead, high earners got their compensation in other ways: Some using methods that took advantage of outright tax loopholes specifically put into the code to allow just that, some in ways that just weren't taxed because of an oversight.</p>
      <p>That's what company provided health insurance is for normal workers, for example: In WWII <em>everybody</em> paid high taxes and wage rates were set by law. But benefits like health insurance wasn't taxed or fixed by law, so companies started offering insurance plans as an additional form of compensation.</p>
      <p>What we would today call the upper-middle class functionally didn't exist in the 50's and 60's, it was taxed out of existence. The people holding jobs that today have upper-middle class incomes got 'merely' middle class wages. After the rate cuts of the 1980's this class recovered over the course of the 1980's and 1990's.</p>
      <p>So yeah. Rate decreases in the 1960's (JFK) and 1980's (Reagan) didn't effect revenue levels very much because high rates weren't designed to raise revenue in the first place. They were income suppressors and, in other cases, capital controls used to direct investment. Before Reagan, the tax code was even <em>more</em> insanely complex than it is today, riven through with credits and loopholes put in to incentivize people to spend or earn in a particular way. The whole Reagan tax cut push was a compromise: Simplification of the tax code (ie. closing loopholes) in return for rate cuts (so, effective tax rates stay ~roughly the same, but statutory rates go down).</p>
      <p>Raising drastically more revenue is actually pretty difficult and involves heavier taxes on the middle and lower class.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>