<post>
  <author>mokoroo</author>
  <date>2020-05-19T08:55:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr47hh8/</link>
  <title>"LoveForLandlords" and the Joy of Fake Outrageousness</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So <a href="/r/LoveForBillionaires">/r/LoveForBillionaires</a> has been banned.</p>
      <p>I'm going to give some context around this, along with some thoughts on transgressive humour more generally.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="/r/LoveForBillionaires">/r/LoveForBillionaires</a> is an offshoot of <a href="/r/LoveForLandlords">/r/LoveForLandlords</a>, which in turn is an offshoot of <a href="/r/Drama">/r/Drama</a>.</p>
      <p>Essentially, <a href="/r/Drama">/r/Drama</a> (for the three posters here who don't also post there) is self-explanatory. In times gone past, members of the subreddit would 'ping' (by writing something like <a href="/u/mokoroo">/u/mokoroo</a> to have it pop up in the user's alerts) someone in another subreddit if they thought that person would come and argue with them, and that it'd be funny to antagonize them.</p>
      <p>It's not a very nice place, admittedly, but I like it. It's one of the last outposts of the old free internet versus the new sanitized, corporate internet. </p>
      <p>However, pinging was banned - primarily because it enables obvious harassment - you can ping a user all day long if a subreddit dislikes them, and that wasn't unheard of. Likewise, brigading (or posting in linked threads) is heavily frowned on by reddit, and <a href="/r/drama">r/drama</a> is under far more scrutiny than most.</p>
      <p>So the problem for <a href="/r/drama">r/drama</a> arose. How do you get your fix of angry incoherent people if you can't ping them or go to them?</p>
      <p>The answer was simple enough, create a giant honeypot and lure them in.</p>
      <p>Before I discuss that any further, I want to draw some parallels. </p>
      <p>In 2010, a brief video called <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v401YR0YmXg">Alf Stewart Rape Dungeon</a> came out, and was an immediate and massive hit among university students in Australia. Alf Stewart is a character on the Australian soap opera Home and Away, and is the longest-running and probably most-beloved character on that soap. He's an older Australian who speaks with a more traditional ocker accent and while he can be a bit rough around the edges, he has a heart of gold. It's also one of the most popular pieces of Australian media period, having been syndicated in over 80 countries.</p>
      <p>Why was this piece funny?</p>
      <p>For two reasons. The first, it was transgressive. Alf Stewart is a beloved character who is also a decent person. Rewriting his dialogue to make him a monstrous serial killer and rapist is so far out there it makes you laugh. It's funny because it's beyond implausible, it's the same reason we laugh at parodies of children's characters drinking or smoking, it's taking something good and tarnishing the hell out of it.</p>
      <p>The second is that it's <em>exclusionary</em>. This was the sort of humour your parents wouldn't get. In the media this clip was bandied about as promoting rape, as assaulting the character of Ray Meagher (the actor), and I recall one particular <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_RCY18iIU3k">media segment</a> that aptly sums up the views of the over-30s at the time. It's the sort of humour that either puts you on the side of 'gets it' or 'doesn't get it', and that made it a lot funnier to us.</p>
      <p>Growling out 'so, you found my rape dungeon' and having someone shout back 'ya cunt' in lieu of a regular greeting was a pastime among both the men and women of the residential college I attended for about a month after the clip came out. I suspect some of them found it horrifying but couldn't stand the idea of being seen like they weren't in on the joke.</p>
      <p>Before I circle around back to <a href="/r/LoveForLandlords">/r/LoveForLandlords</a> there's a really great post on <a href="/r/Drama">/r/Drama</a> - original <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Drama/comments/gkbbtd/loveforlandlords_was_a_great_addition_to_the_drma/fqqraz5/">here</a>.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The reason they don't like it is that humor is almost universally incompatible with authoritarianism. See, for instance, the Chinese wordplay ban, or a really interesting, albeit Norwegian apologist monograph called (oh shit) Folklore Fights the Nazis, or for the illiterates who get this sub read to them by their lunchtime handlers, a documentary called Hammer and Tickle. This is the same reason that the true believers on neither the American left nor right can meme.</p>
        <p>This is why they hate us. Our mean-spirited snickering erodes the very foundation of their worldview. You can't control something that doesn't take you seriously.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is why <a href="/r/LoveForLandlords">/r/LoveForLandlords</a> exists. There's certainly some typically alt-right posters there (any time you create a subreddit that is designed as a honeypot to mock the hyperliteralist humorless leftist posters you're going to draw quite a few of their natural enemies), but the ultimate goal is to draw in people who hate landlords by pretending to be absurd parodies of landlords - landlords who rape their tenants, steal their insulin, visit them in the hospital to deliver eviction notices, and evict single mothers into blizzards for being fifteen minutes late with the rent.</p>
      <p>The mean-spirited snickering here isn't at the expense of landlords (who are not genuinely being accused of doing all these horrifying things as a matter of course), but at the expense of the people <em>who believe it's real</em>. It's the same joke as trying to convince someone New Zealand doesn't exist, or that cows are really just big shaven sheep. The joke is perpetuated on these people because when they're convinced by it they become self-righteously angry, and making fun of someone for being self-righteously angry at an incredibly obvious lie is a lot of fun. You can then pretend to be further serious, and skewer other sacred cows even less subtly. </p>
      <p>That's the core of the joke. The less subtle it is, the funnier it is. If someone falls for a long-winded fifty paragraph story about a landlord who hints at doing these things, that's maybe potentially funny. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/LoveForLandlords/comments/gd7gkz/sexually_aroused_when_evicting_tenants_serious/">This</a> is a masterclass in internet trolling - it's obviously not true, uses bizarre tells to show it's not true such as 'my wife thinks its normal', but despite being incredibly obvious, a lot of people fell for it. </p>
      <p>The more obvious it is that the joke is fake, the funnier it is when someone gets self-righteously angry about it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>