<post>
  <author>RIP_Finnegan</author>
  <date>2020-05-19T23:49:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr6s4zl/</link>
  <title>Reflections on Moldbug, Neocameralism, and Liberalism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Great series. I would say that you've identified the weakest part of Moldbug's NRx (how to improve a bad order), though you've skipped his solution to it: market incentives for good governance, including exit. It's a rather implausible solution in practice, but it does show that Moldbug knows the problem is there. Your exit of Mormonism would be a perfect example, a case of an individual exiting for a preferred governance structure rather than attempting to tear down the original order - if the Church had been as chill with Luther's exit, things may have gone far better than they did for the 17th Century.</p>
      <p>I don't know if you've seen Moldbug's <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RRQO3VbJsMw">talk</a> with Justin Murphy or his recent essay on the <a href="https://americanmind.org/features/conservatism-in-the-bronze-age/the-deep-state-vs-the-deep-right/">art-right</a>, but it seems to me he's changed his tune on some of the less defensible and more peripheral aspects of his thought, like neocameralism. One thing I really appreciate about Moldbug is the way he's able to maintain his meta-level weltanschauung while improving his object-level positions. Many people just stick to bad object-level theories because they don't want to admit change, but Moldbug's gone through a fair number of ideas about NRx praxis by now. </p>
      <p>Moldbug's biggest issue, in my opinion (I'm a right-accelerationist Landian type, so obviously not interested in most prog criticisms), is that while he correctly and intelligently decouples social development from technological development (and considers one to be going down as the other goes up), he doesn't account enough for the way in which technology changes what is sociopolitically possible. All the elements are there in his thought, but he fails to center it in the way that Nick Land does. Modern regimes would not be possible without modern technology; anarcho-tyranny would degenerate into either anarchy or tyranny as Rome did. Furthermore, the regimes of the future will not be possible without future technology. Moldbug bases his ideal neocameralist state on cryptographic weapons locks, but apparently the only thing we've invented by then is a futuristic gun safe? Maybe he doesn't like futarchy, but surely there will be more effective ways for his future CEOs to collect and process information, including the revealed preferences of their citizens, than exist currently. Is it not possible that technology could, equally, place actual limits on power of a kind which were never before possible through systems like smart contracts? On the other hand, is it not likely that the technological calculus will, even temporarily, favor a country like China which chooses 'bad order' over Singapore's 'good order'? Moldbug's market for governance relies on the belief that good government in the present and ability to adapt to the future are tied together, but the Coronavirus is challenging that assumption. To get passivism right, an intelligent young NRxer should look at Moldbug's actions rather than his writings, and take building alternatives and route-arounds far more seriously than NRx actually did (one reason NRx fell quiet is that the people actually 'building alternatives' were mostly alt-righters like Chuck Johnson who got into stupid internal drama and flamed out).</p>
      <p>As for 'for what', I think this is where Moldbug betrays the fundamental liberal cultural assumptions of his thought, which few of us notice because they're inherited from Hobbes instead of Locke. His 'for what' is essentially the same as liberalism: to pursue happiness as you want within the limits of order - he just has a very different definition of the limits of order to, say, Mill's harm principle. He makes this explicit, too: the opening of his inquiry is finding a way to optimize for a lack of violence. Society is not aimed towards a positive Good but a lack of evils. In that respect he differs both from traditional thinkers like Aristotle or Heidegger, who see a good society as requiring a vision of the Good or the True, and from accelerationists like Land (or Nietzsche, by extension) who see humanity as aiming towards something greater than the human. Moldbug is, fundamentally, an illiberal liberal. Not even that illiberal, by the standards of the founders of liberalism (this is, by the way, why the libertarian-to-NRx pipeline exists and is so effective). If we put him into that context, as someone attempting to achieve liberal goals by an honesty about the realities of power necessary to  achieve them, the answer to 'why rebel?' becomes obvious: Moldbug's system may (<em>may</em>) achieve these liberal goals better on average on a hundred-year timescale, but within the foreseeable future an individual step of liberalization generally delivers those goals better than a step in the direction of order. Ultimately, neocameralism fails in the same way as Plato's Republic - it would require a truly wise society to maintain the regime, but a truly wise society wouldn't need it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>