<post>
  <author>SlightlyLessHairyApe</author>
  <date>2020-05-19T22:00:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr6g3c6/</link>
  <title>Slogans As Calls For Relative Movement</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I read Faludi's arguments and I'm just confused. I don't see how "Believe Women" is materially different from "Believe All Women". </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think it's quite parseable, just the same as you could parse someone that said "Respect Gun Rights" or "Increase School Funding" or any other political slogan ought to be read as relative to the status quo. Political slogans are often <em>directions</em> instead of <em>destinations</em>. It's nice for policy wonks to say "we devote 22% of State revenue to schools, we think that 23.8% is more appropriate", but that's hardly a slogan. So it gets truncated to just the direction "Fund Our Schools!" with the implicit "more than we do now". </p>
      <p>Now, if you saw someone with a bumper sticker that said "Money For Books Not Bombs", you might have a rational debate with them on exactly how much they think we ought to fund the schools or how many fewer bombs we ought to build. But it would be totally ridiculous to cast them as saying obviously they want <em>infinite</em> books and <em>zero</em> bombs. A few might, but many people would endorse that slogan without taking an extreme position. </p>
      <p>Similarly, "Believe Women" falls along the same line -- it is a call to move in the direction relative to the status quo, not to believe a woman who says she was sexually assaulted by aliens from Neptune. Intentionally misinterpreting it might score political points, but it doesn't convince anyone whose position is "we consistently give less credence to women's reports of sexual misconduct than we ought".</p>
      <p>[ And of course, you might not believe that statement is true. But that's orthogonal to whether you can state the view that you disagree with in terms that a proponent would recognize as their own. ]</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>