<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-05-19T22:15:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr6husv/</link>
  <title>Neoreaction, Synthesized and Regurgitated</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>(3/3)</p>
      <h3>
        <strong>My thoughts:</strong>
      </h3>
      <p>
        <strong>I: My core objection</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Almost every ideology I know of claims to base its views on objective, impartial analysis of truth. Neoreaction is no exception. The leftist narrative is one of class struggle, and they aspire to inspire class consciousness and lead to a Revolution. They look at the world through Hegelian and Marxist lenses and point to Chomsky's <em>Manufacturing Consent</em> and similar works to explain more mainstream takes. The democratic/progressive narrative Moldbug focuses so much on is one of history always moving forward as we discard the moral errors of the past, with a constant thread of lurching back into Reaction. The neoreactionary narrative is one of a world always crying out for order while Cthulhu swims leftward and drags us all into slow but persistent chaos. </p>
      <p>I think a fact-first view of ideologies can be a mistake. Factual truth is important, but brilliant people have been convinced to follow every ideology under the sun. The narrative, the feeling of the whole thing, the itches it scratches... that's what convinces people. Some of Moldbug's examples are accurate. Others are exaggerated. Still others strike me as absurd. But the facts are not the key. Honestly, this may be where Moldbug loses me the most. I think his Antiversity idea would be interesting, but I don't believe for a second it would proceed from pure, unvarnished truth. It would just throw a different narrative coating over the underlying factual claims. </p>
      <p>Like any other ideology, Neoreaction is fundamentally aiming to answer what ought to be, not what is, and like many others, it cloaks that in a claim to be sticking to the <em>is</em>. I don't think its factual claims lead obviously to its overarching narrative, but a narrative doesn't need to be perfectly coherent, only to be good enough to allow for stable belief.</p>
      <p>Its narrative falls apart for me in exalting order itself, never quite answering the "for what" to my satisfaction. Yes, it could lead to atrocities, Moldbug says—but other systems <em>have</em>, and most of the time human nature and the incentive structures in place mean it wouldn't. As a narrative, that can work. In practice, the question I think Moldbug ends up grappling least with is the one he has the most duty to answer. <em>Why</em> do people rebel against the perfect order of his Right? Why does his order descend into chaos? He attributes it largely to weakness. </p>
      <p>But Luther nailed his theses to the church door for a reason. People opposed slavery for a reason. Communism gained a foothold for a reason. I left Mormonism for a reason. Something wasn't true. Some part was unjust. Something didn't fit. Some part of the system broke down and caused misery for someone or some group, and that injured party fought for whichever alternative they could find. Order is great... until it isn't. And no matter how patiently you explain to someone that, if you just look impartially at the evidence, you'll find that x or y is the best way to do things... if they're the one getting the short end of some stick, no amount of perfectly conceived order is enough to satisfy them. For one simple example, divine right more-or-less worked until people stopped believing in it, and once you lose the reason for the order, you lose its support. Neoreaction exalts order, but its response to the pitfalls of that order is lacking. </p>
      <p>Having tasted both, I'll freely admit I prefer most of the fruits of order, but when I no longer fit into that order I saw no choice but to walk away. I can't fault the world for doing likewise, even though I still hold out hope for a better sort of order. As such, I reject Neoreaction's narrative and its vision, but some of its factual claims are still worth taking note of.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>II: Neoreaction's value</strong>
      </p>
      <p>For those of us who disagree with its overall narrative, Neoreaction is useful in the same way that the prosecution is useful in court, by the same logic that causes the Catholic Church to employ Devil’s advocates. Courts split into prosecution and defense for a clear reason: each side is only really motivated to emphasize part of the truth. Moldbug is democracy’s Devil’s advocate. He examines the same fact picture as the rest of us, determined to shape it into a narrative counter to the one most of us choose. By placing himself so clearly and unambiguously in opposition to a) progressives and b) democracy, he examines the traditionally unexamined, and is therefore likely to spot errors most others overlook.</p>
      <p>This is compounded by his actionable advice and his real-world actions. Twelve years on, I don’t think an Antiversity exists, Moldbug's hopes aside. But I do think a Reactionary university would be a genuinely useful thing to have, equal and opposite to a Harvard or a Yale, able to cross-examine it and prepared to collectively arrive at a more complete truth. And, while that doesn’t exist and likely won’t, he’s the sort of person who has already created an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urbit">alternative to the internet</a> from the lowest possible level up. That may or may not catch on, but someone willing to put in that amount of serious work deserves a bit of serious consideration.</p>
      <p>His work, in other words, has some potential to add or inspire genuine ideology-neutral value in the world. It encourages people to build useful things, and that encouragement is backed up by serious work in… building useful things. That's as it should be. The fruits of an ideological movement should provide clear evidence of the value of that movement.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>III: On movement-building</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Neoreaction’s path to power is an ideologically neutral one, and it isn’t senseless. Whether someone supports or opposes it, that pattern is worth paying attention to. Its focus on the far future parallels that of Communism and Christianity, calling for the Reaction instead of the Revolution or the Rapture. I do find that impractically ambitious in the sense that its goal is to change nothing until it changes everything at once, and that’s probably already enough to keep it from success by its standards (something that should be encouraging for those of us who would rather not see the Reaction). I like the idea of passivism, though, and appreciate that it says “create something better” before its “smash the system” step. Both of those make it less likely to turn into something truly nasty. The approach of aiming for a smart, focused, committed group toeing the party line first, then slowly branching out and becoming part of the broader fabric, is the sort of thing that can lead to lasting changes in the ideological ecosystem thirty or so years down the road if it succeeds. Has that approach succeeded? Ask me again in fifty years.</p>
      <p>Examining the approach with an eye towards movement-building, I think it would be more effective if it encouraged people to make real, substantive, immediate changes in their lives, spelling out what those changes were. It sketches some of that out, but there’s no lifestyle inherent to it, only the future vision. “Build cool things” is a good step, but not enough alone to sustain a movement. It mentions organizing, but only as a means to an end. It lacks an inherent sense of community or commitment, even though it tries to hint at them, and perhaps that’s why ten years out it hasn’t gone all that far beyond getting some ideas out into the conversation. Unless, of course, they’re doing something massive just out of sight, and have organized much more than it seems, and/or if Urbit somehow gets Neoreaction to take off even though Moldbug has stepped away from the project.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>In summary, I don't think Neoreaction has quite the organizational vision to become a serious force, nor the moral core to allow me to root for it even if it does, but I do think it has enough to bear some useful fruit and to act as food for thought to other aspiring movement-builders.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>