<post>
  <author>Cheezemansam</author>
  <date>2020-07-21T14:57:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fyrr8eu/</link>
  <title>Algorithmic Bias and Predictive Policing</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I agree that, in general, you're going to have biased training data (with a bias that's difficult to measure) and so inherently policing recommendations will be biased. This is particularly problematic when it comes to arrests for crimes that are inherently 'selective' in their enforcement. Eg; drug-related crimes, public intoxication, loitering, trespassing.</p>
      <p>But the fact is... violent (fatal and nonfatal) crimes do happen at a much higher rate in poor neighborhoods. And black americans are <a href="https://www.bjs.gov/content/pub/pdf/hpnvv0812.pdf">calling the police at high[er] rates</a> knowing full-well what that might imply. More anecdotally, for actual <em>residents</em> of non-affluent areas complaints about police are that there simply wasn't enough police to respond to violent incidents. That is a whole topic in itself but there is this trend in the conversation these days that has shifted from "there's a serious problem with racism in how police go about their job" to "we need less police". Folks in neighborhoods living, the ones who live in and are statistically the recipients of criminal violence commonly <em>do not want</em> police presence to vanish. Even Vox has an article clarifying that <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2019/2/13/18193661/hire-police-officers-crime-criminal-justice-reform-booker-harris">the data shows that people in crime-ridden areas are generally very interested in seeing greater police presence, not less</a>, and studies have shown a larger police presence results in lower arrest rates and lower use of force.</p>
      <p>I think it’s easy to get caught up in tempest and start blaming a large group for the actions of a small minority. And I don't mean "its easy to get caught up" rhetorically, some of the shit involved in the more egregious shit, like straight up fabricating evidence against teenagers, precincts with multiple adjudicated Brady violations (withholding exculpatory evidence etc.), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Walter_Scott">shooting a fleeing men in the back and lying about it in the official report/press release despite being in possession of video proving the opposite, and only releasing the video contradicting their statement at the order of a judge half a year later "Our officer did nothing wrong"-&gt;"Convicted of murder when the public actually gets to see what happened"</a>. So I don't mean it in the sense of dismissing these issues, but my understanding is we’ve done decades of studies and had decades of progress toward reducing violent crime, and increased funding for police has been a main pillar of that effort. Obama’s efforts to provide billions of dollars of police funding, for example, saw decreases in crime rates for cities that received the funding versus increases in cities that missed out. </p>
      <p>If generating a racially fair predictive policing algorithm was merely a question of optimizing for one of these desiderata, it'd be possible in principle. You either ensure that the appropriate racial ratios pop out for the neighborhoods to patrol, or you ensure that racial information and their proxies aren't used in the algorithm. If any algorithm is unacceptable unless it does both, well, you're probably going to be disappointed.</p>
      <p>The evidence available today seems to indicate that officers are using predictive policing to decide where and with whom to employ traditional, enforcement-oriented strategies of stops, citations and arrests.</p>
      <p>For example, according to the <a href="https://www.rand.org/pubs/research_reports/RR531.html">RAND evaluation in Shreveport [Page 37]</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>As described by officers, commanders, and the predictive analytics team, interventions in Districts A and B focused on building relationships with the local community in order  to  get  actionable  information  for  crime  prevention  and  clearing  crimes.  There  was a large emphasis on intelligence gathering through leveraging low-level offenders and offenses. Officers stopped individuals who were committing ordinance violations or  otherwise  acting  suspiciously  and  would  run  their  names  through  database  sys-tems.<sup>4</sup> If an individual had significant prior convictions, he or she would be arrested for the violation (as applicable). If the individual was on probation or parole, officers would check his or her standing with the parole or probation officers. For those not in good standing, a parole or probation officer was asked to come to the scene. Lastly, individuals with warrants were arrested. For those not meeting these criteria, officers stated that they gave these individuals a warning and were as polite as possible in order to note that they were trying to take action against property crimes in the area and to ask whether the individual had any knowledge that would be useful to police. Officers also noted talking to passersby in general about the SPD’s efforts to reduce property crimes and asking if they had any potential tips. In the event that questioning led to potentially important information or an individual was arrested while in possession of potentially stolen goods, details were passed onto detectives.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The RAND researchers found in Chicago: “It is not at all evident that contacting people at greater risk of being involved in violence — especially without further guidance on what to say to them or otherwise how to follow up — is the relevant strategy to reduce violence[.]” As they wrote, “the prevention strategy associated with the predictive strategy was not well developed and only led to increased contact with a group of people already in relatively frequent contact with police.” This is the same study that found the initial pilot “does not appear to have been successful in reducing gun violence.” </p>
      <hr />
      <p>One massive issue in terms of a public policy perspective is that Departments that adopt these tools aren’t providing clear, public policies on how the tools are used. Los Angeles is one example of a place where the absence of clear rules could be particularly concerning, as the LAPD has a common perception (I would argue record) of racial profiling, disproportionate policing of minority communities, and was even under a federal consent decree for more than a decade. Without transparency, it is impossible to have a open and fair debate to begin with. On some level you must place <a href="https://i.imgflip.com/48yqdv.jpg">at least part of the blame</a> on the police departments for not making it clear how such models and techniques are going to be used in the first place.</p>
      <p>Look at what happened in Bellingham, Washington. For two years, the police department considered purchasing a predictive policing system. In 2014, the police department attempted to use a Bureau of Justice Assistance (BJA) grant to acquire Intrado’s Beware software. After serious public pushback, the city council “<a href="https://www.bellinghamherald.com/news/local/article30797004.html">took a vote asking the department to use the grant money to buy something else</a>.” Because of the community pushback, the department dropped their purchase of Beware and decided to look for a new system. In 2015, the police department used a BJA grant to acquire a different predictive policing system, this time from BAIR Analytics. THe police department did not need community approval, instead, the community was given only <strong>seven business days’</strong> notice of a city council meeting in which the department would solicit public comment and, by then, the decision to purchase the equipment was already final.</p>
      <p>Or Fresno, California. When the Fresno police briefed the city council about the Beware system, the council president asked a simple question about those color-coded threat levels: “How does a person get to red?” The officer didn’t know, because the vendor wasn’t saying. As the officer delivering the briefing explained: “<a href="https://medium.com/equal-future/buyer-beware-a-hard-look-at-police-threat-scores-961f73b88b10">We don’t know what their algorithm is exactly… We don’t have any kind of a list that will tell us, this is their criteria, this is what would make a person red, this is what would make a person yellow. It’s their own system.</a>” Later in that meeting, one of the council members asked the officers to run threat assessment on the council member’s own home. It came back yellow, apparently indicating a medium threat in that home (though the council member himself came back green).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>