<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2020-07-22T13:02:05Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fyv9hwf/</link>
  <title>Islamic Terrorism Still Happens, You Just Don't Care</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's still happening, just in the global south where it always was and where your media doesn't talk about much.</p>
      <p>For Americans, the most important thing about Islamic terrorism that most people didn't get was that, at its heart, it's not about America. Surprise, I know, but islamic movements are based in the islamic world, which tend to have their own local concerns based around the impacts of European colonialism, modern (often secular!) autocratic suppression, and the political dynamics of the local regions from the MENA to southwest Asia. In almost all cases, islamic movements (radical or not) are quite reasonably concerned more about local stuff than far away actors who don't actually have as much role in the day-to-day dissatisfactions as egocentric Americans and Europeans like to think they do.</p>
      <p>Al Qaeda was a unique threat not necessarily because of it's tactical technical competence as much as that <em>it specifically cared about attacking America.</em> AQ was a bit of a mutant in radical islamic spheres because it broke the bad guys into the categorizations of near enemy and far enemies, where the near enemies were the secular/insufficiently islamic powers at home and the far enemy was the Americans supporting them (as in the case of Saudi Arabia). But where most islamic groups, again, fight the near enemy first because that's who's fighting them, AQ thinkers believed that the US specifically, and west in general, were the critical threat- that without them, the near enemy states would fall, and that the weak/decadent west were paper tigers who could be forced to withdraw by even relatively limited measures. (This view was validated in the Cold War by Raegan's withdrawal from Lebanon after the bombing of a marine barracks, and in the early 2000s by Spain's withdrawal from the Iraq coalition after terrorism there.) The global radical islamic's view on this was divided- again, AQ was an ideological mutation- but they didn't exactly hate it, and the Taliban in Afghanistan were willing to let AQ shelter there as long as they played by local rules. But for AQ, by making a point of actually <strong><em>trying</em></strong> to attack the US in a big and flashy manner it eventually succeeded with 9-11, at which point the prestige points of doing so gave AQ street cred as the leading (most effective) radical islamist movement. That never meant they actually ran the global radical islam movements- it never, for example, ran the south asia fight, or took over boko haram in Africa- but it gained influenced, and emulators who thought about also doing the far enemy fight for international terrorism, and AQ happily went into Iraq during the American occupation hoping to lead the anti-American resistance (and promptly west so far off the rails trying to start a Sunni-Shia war that AQ HQ disavowed AQ in Iraq).</p>
      <p>The Islamic State (ISIS, or ISIL, or Daesh, or whatever you prefer), by contrast, was 'just' another boring local-area near-enemy movement, which by comparison is a lot safer (for the Americans).</p>
      <p>There's more to it than that, as ISIS tapped into islamic cultural memes in a way most Westerners will never really be able to understand, but fundamentally ISIS was an alliance of three main elements- Iraqi Sunni tribes who felt they were the losers of the Iraqi civil war (another dynamic most people don't really understand- the Americans were caught in the middle of a sectarian conflict more than fighting it), remnants of the Saddam security state that outlived their master, and AQ Iraq-offshot theologians who had mutated away from 'target Americans abroad' back to 'local concerns first' (because the Americans were a local concern). The Tribes provided manpower and territory and grievances with the Iraqi state (where the majority Shia government was unresponsive to Sunni concerns when it wasn't actively taking part in sectarian sqabbles itself), the ex-Saddam Bathists provided the brutality and technical/tactical competence (and lived experience of knowing that Americans/Iraqi states wouldn't stop at taking their jobs next time), and the AQI-scholars provided the ideological/theological justification tying it all together and with the wider islamic world (and in virulent opposition to the Shia Iraqi state, which was opposed to the other two elements). In other words, ISIS-core was built from local national demographics alienated from existing states, veteran totalitarian police state survivors who knew how to run an effective organization, and hardcore theologians whose stated goal in the Iraq War was to make it a religious war against the national majority (who happens to be the global islamic minority hated by a significant minority of Arab Sunni's for a variety of cultural-historical reasons).</p>
      <p>Basically, ISIS was made up of people who knew what they were doing, were very motivated to not give up, and were relatively good at what they did. They fought against a Iraqi government that a significant part of the country didn't trust (for good reason), bordering another country (Syria) that had fallen into a civil war where the government was trapped on the far other end of the country. These two places were linked by a desert that- on a map- looks big and contiguous enough to call itself a state. Which they did, which they used to claim even more prestige and kudos and Big Boy points than AQ did for 9-11, and then leverage that notoriety to try and collect external support from other regions/actors to come and joint the fight for ISIS in ISIS land and swear loyalty to the leader.</p>
      <p>...which, in practice, meant that a lot of local regional radical islamic movements that had friction with AQ (who had a reputation for being a nose micromanager trying to tell people how to run their wars and stop fighting the local crackdowns to go visit 'Murica) just 'swore loyalty' to ISIS instead, got a fancy title as the Totally Real Ruler/Governor of the places they were already operating in that local rubes would respect, and mostly stayed put fighting the local fights they were already fighting, albeit with some relative exchanges with ISIS core, at least until everyone around ISIS bombed the shit out of them and drove them back into the desert. But before that happened, though, the rise of ISIS fractured the radical islamic movement's mojo for international terrorism by stealing AQ's thunder. AQ's unique mutation- the far enemy theory- got de-legitimized/downgraded because ISIS- a near-enemy movement- had gained even better achievements, and in turn legitimized/gave prestige to other near-enemy local movements around the world. AQ-strategists may argue that ISIS only succeeded because AQ set the conditions, but they're not the cool kids anymore and no one has to listen to them.</p>
      <p>From the western perspective, ISIS's primary influence/threat in the short term was using it's prestige/reputation to motivate otherwise unmotivated would-be extremists to either come to ISIS-territory (ISIS's preferred option), or to launch uncoordinated lone-wolf attacks at home (not preferred, but also what national governments fear more because uncoordinated attacks, even if small, are the hardest to stop pre-attack). This sort of mobilizing effect was a factor of ISIS's prestige, however, and ISIS's prestige was it's claim to being a state, ie exercising sovereignty over territory it exclusively controlled. Having lost that territory (and had their noses rubbed in it by Trump- his sort of trash talking was a legitimately good strategy in this context), ISIS stopped being the cool kids everyone wanted to go to, or the sempai that lone wolf weeboos wanted to have notice them, and globally the whole 'ISIS in X-country' network is just a loose social club of lonely men looking for fellow lovers of jihad. Significant for intel agencies, and could potentially facilitate bad things in the future, but not something westies need to worry about.</p>
      <p>(Medium-term, though, the fear of most Western governments have is for the longer term consequences if/when their citizens who went to ISIS return. Country responses have ranged from arresting them to trying to prevent them from ever returning, which is why many 'ISIS family members' remain in camps far away from home. This is an ongoing process, but don't be surprised if/when they come home and do bad things in decades hence.)</p>
      <p>As for AQ and ISIS? They still exist, albeit in rump/distracted forms not focusing on the US or Europe at the moment.</p>
      <p>ISIS still operates, doing terrorist attacks and trying to keep operating space at the margins of the (now ending) Syrian civil war and limits of Iraqi effective control, but short of another division of the Iraqi army running away and abandoning a major city they aren't in a place to regain a meaningful city or population base. AQ, by contrast, is active in Yemen, where it's at the margins of the Saudi-Iranian proxy war. AQ is using the destabilization to try and have its own pocket Afghanistan/safe haven to operate from, but no one involved in the war likes them so they have to keep their heads down.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>As for the rest... well, they never were that well known in the first place. Boko Haram is still a menace in Africa, though the French and Americans have increased low-key operations there over the last decade. Americans stopped caring about Afghanistan activities (almost) decades ago. India-Pakistan is still a mess. In the Philippines, Duerte waffles between hating America and having to admit that Americans are kind of good for some of his far southern troubles. Etc. etc. etc. They never went away, if you know where to look or listen. You just (usually) need to speak another language. (Everyone pretends to not speak French whenever the French ask for more help in their African efforts.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>