<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2020-07-22T15:51:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fyvs8ie/</link>
  <title>A Defense of the Electoral College and Federalism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Over-representation by small conservative states in the Senate and the  Electoral College are arguably two of the major factors keeping the GOP  alive politically in this country.  </p>
      <p>/</p>
      <p>This is the sort of characterization that belies a misunderstanding of contemporary impacts for structural design philosophy. The Electoral College and Senate don't conservatives- these systems 'overrepresent' small (rural) states that (in the midwest) happen to be Conservatives. And it's not an overrepresentation when it's by a deliberate and explicit design- it's just representation, as was agreed upon (and necessary for the agreement of) creating the nation known as the United States at its inception.</p>
      <p>The United States, from the beginning, required a compromise by big states of smaller states if they were to share any form of government. New York was always going to overwhelm Rhode Island. Sea-board locked states didn't have the expansion potential for territorial/population expansion like those not already bounded by states (or Canada). 'Only population should count for federal influence' has been a stance held by New York and other big-state (or big-state allied) polities since the start... and the smaller states not wanting to be totally overwhelmed (as opposed to the current 'whelmed') were never going to agree to marginalization and irrelevance in the face of permanent demographic disparities. You know that. Your political predecessors know that. And the people at the time knew that, which is why they made the compromise they did- a bicameral legislature (as opposed to a population-only House), and a presidential selection system that difused influence geographically. This was in the marriage vows that made the nation, to the point that there wouldn't be a United States had that compromise not been made, and for those not seeking to renenge on that compromise they are very much justified in viewing attempts to as an exercise of 'I have changed the bargain, pray that I do not change it further.'</p>
      <p>Nothing about that is by, for, or in the name of 'conservatives', a label that only has meaning with a contemporary context that wouldn't have meaning projected that far back. New England states, with no expansion prospects, were a core component of Senate and Electoral college. Southern States, with more potential, were arguing the population position, even as they were claiming slaves should count for representation. 'Conservative' and 'liberal' political labels don't even make sense further west for most of American history, being anachronistic labels slapped on regularly shifting political coalitions. Claiming the electoral college favors conservatives is political revisionism- rather, the electoral college favors states that Democrats stopped being competitive in for reasons of policy preferences and cultural divergence.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>Now, you could try a seperate argument that the U.S. should have- and shouldn't now- have a system of government that distributes power to states rather than population centers. You'd probably have a poor time of that, though, because the next step becomes 'why the fuck federalism, then?' and 'how do you intend to balance the concerns of a continent from a powerbase the size of a few cities?' </p>
      <p>Because that's what the modern democratic party- the American faction that wants to change the way elections are run to expand its own power- is. The Democrats aren't a nation-wide party in the sense of being literally distributed across the countryside, they are a coalition of city-based political machines that have generally captured the cities they operate in (except for the cities they don't, which are captured by other, fewer, machines). Removing the the weighting function of the Senate and electoral college increases the power of these cities- the mega-cities in particular- government power base and spoil systems no longer have to expend the resources and compromises to forge (and maintain!) coalitions with smaller cities and non-cities.</p>
      <p>Urban vs rural- NOT liberal versus conservative, class, or even racial divides- is the structural lens that has consistently divided the United States for the past three centuries. Ideology touches, but is tangential to the tension that occurs regardless due to geography and dispersion. Different geographic regions of the US have different interests, politically, economically, and otherwise. Most are taught that the Civil War was a result of tensions between evil slaver south and moral abolitionist north, but few get taught how North Eastern economic interests sought trade and economic policies harmful to other interests (tariffs on manufactured goods especially), or how the post-civil war reconstruction and gilded era saw southern and western states functionally treated as resource extraction colonies for (coincidentally Northeastern) industrialists hosted primarily in northeastern cities. Fortunately for the US, unlike other countries, only one major rebellion had to be put down by the urbanite power centers, in part because structural federalism incentivized (required) coalitions that demanded spreading federal largess and regulatory benefits for more than just the northeastern seaboard where the densest population centers lay.</p>
      <p>That is... not the historical experience of most larger countries, which have far less federalism distributing political power away from the ruling cities and far more capture by capital city-regions which are notoriously neglectful of the less powerful (and populated, and developed) less urbanized interiors. There are reasons that rural uprisings have been a staple across history, with notable examples being 'the entire communist block that almost razed Europe and threatened to unleash nuclear fire over systematic grievances over land and labor grievances long ignored by urban elites.' And there's a reason why continent-spanning empires, ruled by the same centralized elites, had to regularly and bloodily put down rebellions on a regular basis until the world order was shattered and the old empires were broken apart into decentralized sub-units small enough that the people outside of the political power center cities didn't feel too too marginalized and ignored. De facto federalization of empires into states- and then putting those states in a system in which even the smallest had some powers and privilages disproprotationate to their population- is what gave you the most peaceful almost-century in human history, and even the blemishes on <em>that</em> are mostly due to the after-effects of dissolving the empires that had regular rural rebellions in the first place.</p>
      <p>Or, alternatively, you could go with the China model, which has dedicated substantial blood and treasure into using modern technology to cheaply and efficiently suppress hundreds of millions of protests and billions of grievances because, hey, rulers gonna rule. And, coincidentally, China would <em>love</em> an inter-state system in which population alone gave more weight and formal legal power.</p>
      <p>(Whether China is more of a conservative or liberal state is left to reader interpretation, but either way doesn't exactly look kindly on pupulation-centric power distributions. </p>
      <p>Federalism- the cornerstone of why the senate and electoral college exist- is the <em>solution</em> to civilization-shattering problems urban power centers habitually marginalizing and then being revolted against by non-urban regions. The only historical proven alternative to federalism is eternal suppression- an effort the Americans have never tried, and which everyone else has eventually failed at. Even the Chinese state had cycles of collapse.</p>
      <p>But, hey, those Conservatives sure are bad, aren't they? It's <em>unfair</em> that they can win elections by rules that everyone agreed to and have abided by for 300 years, rules that have facilitated one of the most peaceful, progress, and liberal societies and cultures in human history. Just think of how much <em>better</em> everything would be if the modern-day Democrats could have complete, virtually uninhibited power from their city-based political machines that totally haven't done anything to warrant doubt or skepticism in the last year/decade/half century.</p>
      <p>What's federalism good for if it gets in the way of progress?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>