<post>
  <author>j9461701</author>
  <date>2020-07-22T00:51:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fytppcb/</link>
  <title>Diving Into The Wire</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>SPOILERS FOR THE WIRE:</p>
      <p>Early in season 1 of The Wire, Detective McNutly asks out loud "Why can't you just sell drugs and go home? Why all the bodies? Why all the killing behind it?". This question will be echoed by two other characters, D'angelo (nephew of the drug kingpin Avon Barksdale) and Stringer Bell (right-hand man to Avon). In a testament to The Wire's exceptional writing, each character is intrigued by the question for difference reasons. For McNulty, who thinks gangsters are too dumb to abstain from violence, the question is a fun way to make himself feel smugly superior. For D'angelo, the question pulls at his heart strings and makes him wonder if there is a way for drugs to be sold without hurting as many people. For Stringer Bell, violence is an unnecessary expense on the spreadsheets - a profit sink he would really quite prefer to do without if at all possible. </p>
      <p>Let's now change focus a bit, and ask a different question: What is Stringer Bell's fatal flaw? What causes his 'co-op' plan to fail? Well Avon Barksdale tells us, in this scene:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fm9tsIrjhqU">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fm9tsIrjhqU</a>
      </p>
      <p>He's not hard enough for the streets, and not smart enough for legitimate business. He's a man caught between two worlds, and so has no world. But how does that idea manifest, exactly? Especially considering Stringer's huge success as the de facto head of the Barksdale organization between season 1 and 3 - for someone 'not hard enough' for the streets he sure did run a street gang quite profitably. Especially as contrasted against Avon in this period, who would've seen their organisation ground into dust via endless wars with Proposition Joe's people when their heroin supply started to run dry. Stringer's "softness", which is more to say logic, saw the futility of war with Proposition War and instead saw him....acting like a businessman. Going to a competitor, pointing out they would benefit from a merger as they both have things the other desperately needs, and reaping huge dividends from the deal. The Barksdale organization rakes in massive profits for nearly 2 years without bodies and without the police attention those bodies generate. All because Stringer was able to box in Avon's pointless gangster aggression and give himself the freedom to resolve things calmly, coolly, intelligently. </p>
      <p>But then along comes Marlo Stanfield, who completely disrupts the co-op by superficially playing by its rules but behind the scenes exterminating all rivals. Stringer's approach falters against Marlo, and concessions and appeasements serve only to embolden him and entice him to try and seize more money and power. Marlo goes from a relative nobody to the new heir presumptive of the West Side with only a handful of soldiers under his command. How? Why? What went wrong? </p>
      <p>First let's delve into the game theory side of two rival gangs:</p>
      <p>Each side has two choices: Cooperate, or go to war. Cooperate+Cooperate produces good vibes for everyone as drugs get sold, no bodies get generated, and profits get split 50/50. War+war generates lots of dead people, which generates lots of police, which means both side's organizations aren't long for the world outside a prison cell. War+Cooperate allows the war-taking side to secure 100% of the profit, though they're still generating more bodies and more police attention than Cooperate+Cooperate. </p>
      <p>What Stringer Bell doesn't understand is Marlo's preferences are utterly opposite to his own: Marlo adores violence and is indifferent to money, while Stringer loves money and has no interest in pointless violence. Marlo craves the crown:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=90cwlneRjPQ">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=90cwlneRjPQ</a>
      </p>
      <p>While Stringer has never seen a point to it. </p>
      <p>This is why Stringer's "no bodies, just business" approach works with Proposition Joe and fails with Marlo. Joe, like Stringer, just wants money and views violence as an annoying cost of doing business he must pay from time to time. Both Stringer and Joe are cooperation-bots. Marlo, by contrast, is a defect bot, and eats both their lunches. Marlo wants the glory, and the rush of violence and combat, far, far more than he wants to retire to a mansion somewhere at 35:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q2kWBB7k11Q">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q2kWBB7k11Q</a>
      </p>
      <p>But more importantly to the first point, Marlo answers the question asked all the way back in season 1 by McNutly as to why the drug game can't be done 'without bodies and violence'. Ultimately, because all it takes is one defect bot, and any cooperation bots in the game get obliterated. In normal business, the defect bot could be expelled via the legal system - which tends to frown on things like "murdering your business rivals in cold blood". But in the drug game, there is no such recourse and so contracts must be enforced via the threat of personal violence if the other party renegs. Hence even a handful of defect bots can taint the entire ecosystem in a sort of cascade of distrust. The bodies have to be a part of the drug game, because it is illegal, and therefore supremely vulnerable to defectors. </p>
      <p>This also explains Stringer's fatal flaw: He blindly assumed everyone thought like he does, which leads to him believing legitimate business people are cowed by threats of violence and that gangsters can universally be enticed by promises of higher profits. Or to use more rational-speak, he's a victim of typical mind fallacy. Stringer would never choose war, because he <em>does</em> want to retire to a mansion at 35 with millions in his bank account and no one knowing his name. And he blindly assumes everyone else thinks that way too, and so doesn't realize the situation as it stands between the Barksdale and Stanfield organizations. It's not really quite a question of being 'not hard enough' for the streets, he just didn't recognize that Defect-bot Marlo was such a grave threat until it was too late. This is also what happens when he tries to bribe a senator, who cons him out of his money by 'rainmaking' him:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WFYv6sixE0g">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WFYv6sixE0g</a>
      </p>
      <p>He assumes the Senator shares his mindset, and so would never blatantly con someone like that. Because in Stringer's world, conning someone that obviously <em>always</em> results in a beef that ends with one of you dead. It's just insane to do it to someone you're going to be working with long-term, so Stringer doesn't even entertain the possibility. </p>
      <p>Anyway, this is just a little point of The Wire's theming I wanted to talk about, because it's fun to tease apart what the show is trying to say about the overarching concepts it's gesturing towards. Well, aside from the obvious...</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.cnn.com/videos/tv/2020/06/15/amanpour-david-simon-police-reform.cnn">https://www.cnn.com/videos/tv/2020/06/15/amanpour-david-simon-police-reform.cnn</a>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>