<post>
  <author>Lykurg480</author>
  <date>2020-07-24T19:32:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fz4fmqg/</link>
  <title>The Limitations of Tolerance</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>And bolded here is a potential explanation. While there's been a recent uptick of... at least politics-adjacent violence and murder, political violence is still close to an all-time low. Instead of shooting each other in the street, we fight over who gets to use what platform.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>And from in "tolerance is not a moral precept":</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Tolerance is not a moral absolute; it is a peace treaty.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This seems overly positive to me. If people really arent concerned with the well-being of others, they will fight. See for example the variety of civil wars in africa after the nations there were left with "bad borders". Because what would make good borders? Ones which respect tribal divisions. A tribe is a group with strong positive relationships, a people that already care about each other. Without this, there will be conflict. And you can see this in the moral percept article:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Tolerance is a social norm because it allows different people to live side-by-side without being at each other’s throats. It means that we accept that people may be different from us, in their customs, in their behavior, in their dress, in their sex lives, and that if this doesn’t directly affect our lives, it is none of our business</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Yes, definitely, the other 99.9% of society entered into a peace with trans people out of purely tactical considerations. They totally couldnt just have crushed them at basically no cost like they had before. And slavery ended because... actually I cant make anything up here. Whites started to get at each others throats over this, and the military power of the slaves was basically non-existant. Presumably the author approves of these though, so I doubt he really understood what hes saying.</p>
      <p>Clearly, you do need something more if this pluralism thing is supposed to work. Tolerance is an attempt by liberalism to provide that something. But any attempt to concretely flesh out what it is that you have to tolerate is simply another proposed code of law. And so it fails to actually be pluralistic: You can advocate whatever you want... so long as you accept that any disagreement is resolved by adopting the code of law implied in "tolerance" as a "compromise". This is not quite as useless as it sounds. Advocated ideologies dont match up with peoples preferences all that well (consider just the number who would tell you that all humans are equally valuable, and the ones who spend as much on children in africa (even just all of them combined) as their own child.), and this allows them to make compromises that the wouldnt if they really believed their ideologies, without having to admit that their ideologies are insane. But it cant adress proper conflict. After all, why isnt everyone friends? Friends are nicer to each other than people are otherwise, and dont we want to be nice? But some people just dont go well with each other. The same applies to much lower levels of niceness like not killing each other, with consequently lower requirements of going well together.</p>
      <p>Part of the current problem is that people are starting to realise something like the above is true, and consequently the pretending doesnt work as well anymore. And this pushes them to avoid the compromise.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>