<post>
  <author>marinuso</author>
  <date>2020-07-21T14:08:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fyrlulx/</link>
  <title>Taqi ad-Din and His Automatic Spit Turner, or: Why Culture Matters</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>To illustrate how much culture matters, I always like the story of Taqi ad-Din and his automatic spit turner. </p>
      <p>There have been a number of false starts with steam power over the course of civilization, and the usual example is the Aeolipile. But the Romans, I think, can be forgiven for not seeing the potential: the Aeolipile was a toy, and would never have been able to power anything practical. </p>
      <p>Not so with Taqi ad-Din. In the 1550s, he invented what to modern eyes is obviously a crude but workable steam turbine, capable of doing real work, as in turning the spit. He did not see the potential - he went on to draw up designs for animal-powered pumps. But the crucial thing is, neither did anybody else in his society. The Ottoman Empire didn't really do machinery. The work was done by slaves, by hand, and the thinking classes were above such mundane matters. What use would they have for a steam turbine? They didn't have anything to hook it up to. They likely didn't even think about labour-saving devices. And so, the reaction to it, from the upper class, was "neat, it turns by itself!", but nothing more. It wasn't even widely adopted to turn roasts. The ban on printing and general lack of literacy probably didn't help with that either - the idea didn't spread. Taqi ad-Din's day job was making fancy clocks for the Ottoman court - a European affectation that the general populace didn't share in either.</p>
      <p>Compare this to Europe, where primitive machinery was already widespread at this time, generally powered by wind or water. Sometimes even by people. They had day labourers running in giant hamster wheels to power cranes. Parts of Europe straight up industrialized. (The Netherlands is still associated with windmills to this day because of it, and places that used water mills more even had <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flatrod_system">power lines</a>.) When Thomas Newcomen invented a steam engine, everyone saw the potential. As for what caused the difference, I've seen it blamed on everything from HBD, to Christianity, or Protestantism in particular (which did encourage literacy), to the Black Death causing a labour shortage, even on Northern Europe being a relative latecomer to civilization and having less rigid stratification as a result. Maybe it's all of them to some extent. But in any case, genius was mostly wasted on the Muslims. They did have smart people, but they didn't have much use for them.</p>
      <p>In fact, the steam-powered spit turner was later independently reinvented by an American named John Bailey, who funnily enough was also a clockmaker. That time it did catch on, and they remained in use until electric ones took over.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>