<post>
  <author>thewolfetoneofwallst</author>
  <date>2020-07-21T14:12:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fyrm82p/</link>
  <title>Federal Law Enforcement Overreach on the West Coast</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>My comment is about federal law enforcement overreach on the west coast: not this last week’s riots in Portland, but rather <a href="https://www.capitolhillseattle.com/2015/08/man-faces-federal-hate-crime-charge-in-capitol-hill-knife-attack/">this case</a>. A homeless man menaces three gay men with a knife in Seattle, chasing them for a distance before getting arrested. He is federally indicted because the knife he used was manufactured outside of Washington, therefore traveling in interstate commerce.[1]</p>
      <p>As a note of background: I have worked in criminal defense. And so, when I would bring up this Seattle case to socially liberal people as a way of explaining my wariness of outsourcing local crime to federal prosecutors, their reaction was indifference -- the defendant was a violent homophobe, so what does it matter if he gets prosecuted by the feds? It’s not an atypical opinion for people who are leftist or socially liberal.
Likewise, a couple years ago, DHS/ICE began indicting prostitutes using the possession of <a href="https://www.chicagotribune.com/news/ct-met-federal-charges-condom-crime-20180517-story.html">condoms</a> as the interstate commerce jurisdictional hook. Their rationale was they were cutting down on sex trafficking, though their definitions of “pimping” and “trafficking” could often stretch far more broadly than the typical person’s conception.[2] Again, when I expressed to other liberal-minded people my concerns with federalizing a local crime using such a spurious hook, again I got indifference -- or hostility, that I should defend people who were sex traffickers and predators. Never mind that the targets of these investigations could frequently include the moms and boyfriends of prostitutes, or the prostitutes themselves, accused of pimping and facing lengthy sentences. </p>
      <p>Again, not an atypical position for the left. Throughout the protests, I’ve had a number of conversations with abolition-minded friends in which they expressed that they wanted to federalize all police, heighten standards of training and education, and disband local law enforcement. I don’t agree, but at least it’s a concrete plan that one can engage with and discuss. I think it’s misguided, and I think that if they understood more they would not be so eager to promote federal law enforcement. </p>
      <p>Federal sentences are harsher, and unfriendlier to a defendant’s chances of escape: essentially every federal district court has a 90%+ conviction rate. Although times have changed, liberals like Joe Biden were prominent architects of this system; thanks to the Comprehensive Crime Control Act of 1984 for and the Anti-Drug Abuse Act of 1986 that he co-wrote, these established a Sentencing Commission that set controlling guidelines for criminal sentences and the dreaded “mandatory minimum sentence” structure.[3] And apart from such discomforting severity and rigidity in the federal system, at my gut level I inherently trust local law enforcement a little more than national law enforcement. Local law enforcement knows you, they are in your community, they can discern better who are the truly dangerous and offer leniency to the deserving of mercy. I don’t want Alabamans or Virgin Islanders to necessarily vote on or enforce the laws which govern my life, and if Colorado wants to legalize weed it seems like an unfair loophole that the feds can cruise in with their mandatory minimum sentences.</p>
      <p>But federal law enforcement is the one that liberals trust. Peter Strzok and James Comey were <a href="https://www.amazon.com/James-Comey-Hero-Former-Political/dp/B07N5Z86PV">heroes</a> to a large subset of the left-of-center throughout 2017 and 2018, and many people fantasized about the FBI arresting Donald Trump. When the ATF went after militias and McVeigh, liberals did not complain, but perceived them by and large as a necessary force to disarm right-wingers and prevent white supremacist violence. Liberals as gun control supporters decry the Supreme Court decision in <a href="https://www.oyez.org/cases/1994/93-1260">U.S. v Lopez</a>, in which a conservative majority shot down a law against possessing a handgun in a school zone as an overbroad use of interstate commerce -- the odd-for-2020 position of the liberal wing in favor of harsh federal sentences while the conservative wing is lenient on street criminals. Federal prosecutors nail the white collar criminals, bank robbers, sex tourists and corrupt politicians that liberals did not complain about, but rather could feel good about incarcerating -- the Dzohar Tsarnaevs and Bernie Madoffs -- unlike the parade of petty thieves, addicts, and the down-and-out poor that get picked up by local police, which engender sympathy and pity. </p>
      <p>I don’t trust ICE, I think they have turned their focus onto “sex trafficking” to make their powers and typical duties more palatable to the average American, and I have concerns about their potential to function as a insulated paramilitary force that is loyal to a president who feels he cannot control or trust the FBI. But federal law exists, and it is well settled that when localities can’t handle the crime, the feds are available to intercede. The use of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1989/07/11/nyregion/giuliani-s-powerful-image-under-campaign-scrutiny.html">“federal day”</a> selective prosecutions and the targeting of the Five Families in NYC were hailed as victories in cleaning up the city, and the federal government enforced law and order in <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/insurrection-act-was-last-used-1992-los-angeles-riots-invoking-n1224356">1992</a> Los Angeles in a far more bloody and wanton way than what is occurring in Portland now.</p>
      <p>And few complained. In fact, a broad swath of liberals supported the feds stepping in to keep order -- supporting it even up to a few weeks ago, when numerous people endorsed abolishing the police and reinstituting a more professional national-level accredited law enforcement body. I saw this rhetoric everywhere, in social media posts about how local cops are poorly trained and stupid, about how states and counties cannot be trusted to fairly enforce law. Now, not only are these same liberal-minded people rejecting their prior beliefs, they are doing so in defense of mobs of people attempting to burn down federal courthouses -- an action that is clearly, obviously, without a doubt within the jurisdiction of federal criminal law, far more so than knives and condoms. They are pointing to the crowds of protestors and <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2020/07/20/portland-protests-wall-moms-formed-protect-demonstrators/5470348002/">“Portland moms”</a> as a way of claiming widespread support and legitimacy; you might have found such a crowd outside Fort Sumpter in 1861 cheering destruction of federal property, too. Destruction of federal property and assaulting federal law enforcement is now presented as the obvious moral choice, as if the debate has already happened and it is decided. </p>
      <p>This is a massive, massive veering of the public opinion on federal prosecution. I can’t understate how strange it feels and I do not feel good about it, even though I share many of the left’s usual concerns about overreach, because I feel this radical opinion shift is a mile wide and an inch deep -- borne out of nothing but social media activism. I suppose this is to say that this breeds cynicism -- that these issues exist for years and decades, and nobody cares whatsoever UNTIL there is an instagram story they find moderately convincing, and now they are under a sort of social media mass psychosis. Any of their preconceptions about justice, the rights of states, the legitimacy of government, the rights of criminal defendants -- all that is thrown out of the window to be replaced by totally new opinions, to the point that they can’t even countenance that their old opinions were even ever held by them, or even commonly held by others on the left. I apologize if this seems too consensus building. I am starting to believe that the average person doesn’t hate injustice. They just hate any justice that is not in their favor.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>[1] If the crime involves “an instrumentality used in interstate commerce” the federal government has jurisdiction to prosecute. Interstate commerce was the mechanism by which the feds cracked down on hotels in the South that would not permit black guests; it is also the mechanism by which the feds have prosecuted their war on drugs, and hauled in Aaron Swartz for what was a minor burglary.</p>
      <p>[2] I asked an ICE agent one time whether she worried that this practice might incentivize the women not carrying condoms so as to avoid federal jurisdiction; she replied that they were bound to use something made in interstate commerce, like a cell phone or computer. So I asked whether street corner prostitution in cash transactions might be the adaption that evolves, and whether this creation of harm might not be worth the couple petty cases that ICE might get. I was met with a look as if she could not even begin to understand the tradeoffs, and that these prosecutions were so self-evidently good that no right-thinking person could oppose them.</p>
      <p>[3] Ginsburg and Breyer dissented from a <a href="https://www.oyez.org/cases/1995/94-1664#:%7E:text=They%20were%20convicted%20under%2018,Guideline%2C%201992%20USSG%20Section%202H1.&amp;text=The%20sentencing%20range%20after%20the,each%20petitioner%20to%2030%20months.">prominent challenge</a> to the constitutionality of the Sentencing Guidelines -- maybe because the challenger was an officer convicted for the Rodney King case, and this was the era when liberals endorsed “superpredator” rhetoric and tough on crime tactics.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>