<post>
  <author>TulasShorn</author>
  <date>2020-07-24T05:47:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fz2avp9/</link>
  <title>The Tension Between Wokeness and Christianity</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Instead of just making fun of you for your laughable understanding of Christianity, I'll answer your question:</p>
      <p>The 2 (Evangelical) churches I am somewhat involved in have both responded to this moment with pretty explicit support of BLM, and explicit discussions of racism. This actually worries me, as I think these churches do not know the full ramifications of accepting the anti-racist worldview, and the extent to which it, while masquerading as something benign, explicitly contradicts the Christian worldview*.</p>
      <p>I think Christianity is uniquely weak to wokeness, in that wokeness comes cloaked in the language of Christianity. Despite your absurd and ridiculous sense that Christianity is inherently racist, every Evangelical I have ever known in my entire life would consider themselves fiercely committed to being against racism. I really want to impress this point on you; being against racism is <em>deeply</em> woven into modern Evangelicalism. Consider the term "Evangelical"; would they really be so dedicated to going to other countries to preach the Word if they thought of the other ethnic groups as worthless?</p>
      <p>The caveats: of course, they have a colorblind view of racism, and do not, in general, accept the structural view of racism. Despite their aspirations, I am sure they have failed many times and been racist (but which ideological movement hasn't struggled with living up to its values?).</p>
      <p>So, of course Christians, who generally consider themselves against racism, would naively hop onto a movement which markets itself as anti-racist. </p>
      <p>*- How is wokeness incompatible with Christianity?</p>
      <p>1) Christians believe in grace and forgiveness, the woke do not</p>
      <p>2) Christians believe that ALL have sinned and fallen short of the glory of God, the woke believe only certain races are tainted with original sin (privilege).</p>
      <p>3) the Christian view of identity is of people of different backgrounds coming together as Christians, and then the Christian identity takes the foreground, and is the main delineating factor is between them and the World. The Christian identity is meant to be the <em>primary</em> identity for Christians. The woke doubt that anything can overcome race and/or political ideology. </p>
      <p>4) The woke view of religions is that all are valid. This is not the Christian view.</p>
      <p>5) I am coming from a Protestant perspective, but I think to a certain extent this applies to all denominations. Evangelicals believe that salvation comes from a personal relationship with Christ, and an individualistic accounting for sins. The woke do not believe in individualism, and believe that you should be tainted with your father's sins. </p>
      <p>I have known multiple people who attempted to to be both woke and Christian; at the end of the day, they failed. When forced to choose between the two, they left Christianity. Because, there <em>is</em> an actual incompatibility between the two; at some point you have to accept the hetero cis-male white Christian as your brother... or not. And that choice determines whether you remain a Christian or not. </p>
      <p>So, to answer your question, no, the churches aren't being cynical or hypocritical; they are being naive. They do not know what they are allying with.</p>
      <p>To answer your last question; there will be no coalitions between Christians and the left, due to the very basic reason that the left does not support religious rights. When the left finally accepts that maybe it is acceptable for a religious school with private enrollment to care about [some enormous religious bigotry], then, finally, at that point, will Christians start to wonder if they can vote leftwing.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>