<post>
  <author>Vincent_Waters</author>
  <date>2020-07-23T04:52:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fyy8ifl/</link>
  <title>Why String Theory Appealed, and What Could Come Next</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>From a fairly technical perspective, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B01AMPQTRU/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1">Fashion, Faith, and Fantasy</a> by Roger Penrose is the best source I know of in terms of explaining why string theory was appealing initially and how it became not-so-appealing. The technical arguments were over my head but I greatly appreciated seeing the <em>real arguments</em> and not some heavily watered down and abstracted layman interpretation. Of course, I'm sure he doesn't capture the full technical detail and Penrose thinks he's doing hte layman's version, but still.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0764BZW8S/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1">Lost in Math</a> by Sabine Hossenfelder hits on it a bit, but i would probably more recommend it for its discussion of supersymmetry. This is a much lighter read.</p>
      <p>If you want some aggressive assertions that what the physics community did with string theory was criminal, with little in the way of the technical side, you can listen to Eric Weinstein rant to his friend on <a href="https://art19.com/shows/the-portal/episodes/201679f5-f770-407d-9153-d41616dfb004">this episode</a> of The Portal. He also rants about the failure of low-energy supersymmetry.</p>
      <p>But yeah, a good clean writeup written from a sociological perspective that brings all of the different sources and arguments together, preferable written by someone with first-hand experience, would be amazing, but I'm not aware of one.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Bonus content:</strong>
      </p>
      <p>If you were to ask me what the next "string theory" is, I think it's likely to be lambda CDM cosmology. <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Deconstructing-Cosmology-Robert-H-Sanders/dp/1107155266">Deconstruting Cosmology</a> is a fairly short read that goes through the history of the current paradigm [1], the evidence for it, and its successful predictions. My reaction is: Oh my god, cosmology is a complete joke. I'd bet my life that lambda CDM is totally wrong in some majors ways.</p>
      <p>For contrarians, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Philosophical-Approach-MOND-Assessing-Milgromian-ebook/dp/B084SDVMZC">A Philosophical Approach to MOND</a> has been getting some serious praise, though I haven't read it yet. (If you are unaware, MOND is an alternative to dark matter, that <a href="https://tritonstation.com">some people</a> think fits the evidence better.) </p>
      <p>I find this important and concerning because searching for dark matter is one of the major sources of funding for physics departments, and if there's no dark matter... I know many physicists who are working on dark matter personally, and to me it looks like regular old group think and regurgitated arguments. I honestly don't think most of them have really ever even questioned the conventional wisdom. Universities lull you into a false sense of security by teaching you confirmed theories, and then teach you the random modern bullshit without any real change in method. It seems like even physicists seem to struggle with the notion that all theories are not equal just because they've achieved some level of popularity.</p>
      <p>[1] On a partially unrelated note, you've probably read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Structure-Scientific-Revolutions-Thomas-Kuhn/dp/0226458083">Kuhn</a>, but if you haven't, it's pretty critical for understanding the mindset of scientists from these generations, who all read Kuhn and were influence by him. I've spoken with many older professors, and you can always see Kuhn is lurking below the surface. Then you ask them if they've read Kuhn, and the answer is always yes. Reading Kuhn was a real "red pill" for me, in that it was a sudden rush of insight as to why older researchers chose to present their work in certain ways.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>