<post>
  <author>CanIHaveASong</author>
  <date>2020-09-25T16:35:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6js9bo/</link>
  <title>Against the Tradwife Meme</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A few weeks ago, a poster sang the praises of the tradwife.  It made me deeply uncomfortable.  I think the tradwife trend is not praiseworthy, but worrying.  My thoughts are well summed up in <a href="https://unherd.com/2020/01/why-tradwife-just-isnt-trad-enough/">this article</a>.  Tradwives simply aren't traditional, but were an artifact of a very brief moment in history.  Tradwives get one thing right:  We need to find ways to free mothers from wage slavery for the good of themselves and their families.  However, tradwives then swing to another extreme, denying women's very real need to produce economic value, and to have interests outside the home.  </p>
      <p>If you're not familiar with tradwives, they are a subset of housewives:  They stay home and raise their children, contenting themselves with cooking and cleaning.  They submit to their husbands and receive an allowance from them.  To tell you the truth, I'm not sure what the difference between a standard housewife and a tradwife is, aside from the submissiveness obsession and the 50s aesthetic.  </p>
      <p>Many women who adopt the tradwife lifestyle say they're exercising their choice under feminism.  With a dizzying array of lifestyle choices in front of them, they are choosing the one that will give them the most fulfilling lives.  Their critics say they're throwing away the advances of feminism.</p>
      <p>Both vews have some truth in them, but they fail to see the big picture.  Women have dual needs of economic participation and childraising, and denying either leads to unhappiness.  We can see these dual needs expressed in women's preferences.  In a <a href="https://www.pewsocialtrends.org/2007/07/12/fewer-mothers-prefer-full-time-work/">Pew research poll from 2007</a>, 60% of mothers said their ideal arrangement is working part time, with 21% saying they prefer full time work.  What about those 20% who prefer to stay at home?  They dream of work, too.  <a href="https://thefinancialdiet.com/the-spirit-of-the-girlboss-is-alive-in-mlm-schemes/">SAHMs are very susceptible to pyramid schemes</a>.  We all have a friend or three who has fallen for the ruse, who works for free or even pays money for the chance to do something- anything- economic while keeping their children primary in their lives.  They're not the only ones inventing work.  Among those who do not work at all, hobby farms and homeschooling are prevalent.  Women who have no economic contributions arrange their lives to simulate economic productivity.  Every single stay at home mom I know either dabbles with a side hustle or homeschools.  Often, they do both.  Women have a deep need to be productive.  </p>
      <p>This should come as no surprise!  Over the course of history, women have been workers.  Our nomadic ancestors gathered and prepared food.  They beat out animal skins and fashioned clothing.  Our farming ancestors led the oxen while their husband drove the plow into the ground.  They canned food for the winter, sewed, and created goods for sale.  Other women worked the front end of their husband's shops, did the finances, or learned the trade themselves and worked as partners in the family business.  Women's work has historically been the kind of work that can be done while caring for a suckling child:  Close to home, and easy to stop and pick back up.  </p>
      <p>All this shattered in the industrial revolution, when working away from home became the norm.  Work changed before gender roles did, and for a brief time, we had women who did no economic activity at all, but only upkept the house.  Under this system, women felt suffocated.  Betty Freidan describes it best:  “Each suburban wife struggles with it alone. As she made the beds, shopped for groceries, matched slipcover material, ate peanut butter sandwiches with her children, chauffeured Cub Scouts and Brownies, lay beside her husband at night- she was afraid to ask even of herself the silent question-- 'Is this all?”   As soon as gender roles opened up, women flocked to back work.  But this time, it was a different kind of work- all-consuming work that doesn't allow you to care for your children.  </p>
      <p>Is it any surprise that women are rebelling against this?  Is it any surprise they're romantisizing the near past when their foremothers could witness their children's first steps and didn't have to work a second shift at home after a busy day at the office?  Yet there is more going on here than meets the eye:  Even the strongest proponents of the tradwife trend are themselves part time workers. Alena Kate Pettitt, the face of tradwives if there ever was one, <a href="https://www.thedarlingacademy.com/etiquette-books/">sells books on etiquitte</a>.  She has monetized being a stay at home mom.  She is an economic participant in her household!  If hers is the example to be followed, then I say good for her and good for tradwives!  Let us have more mom-run home businesses!  But that isn't the image tradwives project.  The fantasy is not of the woman who puts her husband and children first and operates a business on the side, it is the image of the woman who has no interests beyond her home.  </p>
      <p>More and more moms are <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/sarahlandrum/2018/02/09/more-millennial-women-are-becoming-stay-at-home-moms-heres-why/#3e69deed6a2b">rejecting the all-consuming nature of full time work</a>.  Good for them.  But can we stop moving from one extreme to another?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>