<post>
  <author>d4shing</author>
  <date>2020-09-25T01:56:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6hr70h/</link>
  <title>Summarizing 'Debt', by David Graeber</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The book is really worth reading -- it's one of my all-time favorites, and I've read my favorite parts more than a few times. This is all from memory, so forgive me if I make a hash of parts of it.</p>
      <p>The first third of the book tries to figure out what debt means. What's the difference between a debt and a moral obligation? Debt is countable. He writes about a Confucian scholar who estimated the amount of breast milk that each mother provides to her child, a price for the breast milk and an appropriate rate of interest. The scholar concludes by justifying filial piety as a matter of debt service on a staggeringly large financial obligation to one's mother. He writes about an African tribe where brides are sold, but can never be fully paid for. Instead each husband owes his inlaws a stream of payments over time, payable in copper rods. He tells a lot of colorful stories that show the notion of the kinds of acts that give rise to moral obligations that are measurable and divisible are culturally determined / socially constructed.</p>
      <p>The next third of the book traces the history of modern finance. The thesis here seems to be that monetary systems go between specie/precious metal backing and credit backing. He talks about currency debasement in Rome, paper money in Imperial China, the negotiable promises of Islamic merchants, the temple system in India and recurrent waves of dethesaurization and anti-clerical riots, and the ordinary social prevalence of debt throughout much of the world. The incredible thing, to Graeber, about Locke's famous quote (that I am about to butcher) about how 'it is not from the benevolence of the baker that we expect our bread' is that it was literally untrue on a sociological level at the time - there was a massive shortage of specie, so everything was sold on credit: the baker would keep a tally of all the families in the village who owed him for bread, and every six months or a year or so net it out against what he owed the other families, usually without exchanging much coin. If the baker didn't like you, because you were untrustworthy or from out of town, you wouldn't get bread. He continues to trace the evolution of the monetary system through the Opium wars, the world wars, culminating in Nixon's abandonment of the gold standard and the 2008 financial crisis, all liberally sprinkled with anecdotes.</p>
      <p>The last third is sort of political. He goes back to the ancient near east and the year of the Jubilee. Nations there would insist on creditor friendly laws, making sure each debt was repaid. But a bad harvest or a flood at the wrong time or even just borrowing money to pay for a wedding could put families into debt, and result in them being sold into slavery. If you start to sell too many of your people into slavery, there's nobody to work the farms, and people just flee the farms and the cities and live in the wild or join neighboring tribes. Pretty soon, the creditor class and their wealth is easily taken and destroyed by neighboring tribes, with nobody able or willing to defend them.  So the year of the Jubilee was created, and every 7th year, everyone was forgiven of their debts and could return home, and the debt slaves were all freed. This dynamic is repeated in Rome (once the wealth distribution became too lopsided, there were not enough, er, middle class Romans to provide soldiers to protect it all) and in general is part of a historical theme of governments needing to balance the interests of debtors and creditors. He recounts more examples, and contextualizes earlier examples/stories in that context. How does it seem that balance is struck today? Are debtors too powerful, or are creditors? As someone with hundreds of thousands of non-dischargeable student loans, I'm inclined to say the latter.</p>
      <p>He concludes with a brief plea for compassion on behalf of the idle and the poor. Someone who takes a year off to spend time with their dying mother is creating no economic value. They may have a hard time paying their debts -- they're certainly not inventing a new website or extracting hydrocarbons. But maybe that's OK, and maybe we should be a little less hung up on each person's Net Present Value.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I suppose I was hung up on the technical one of how you gonna get new loans if you don't pay the old ones?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Ask the Argentines. Or anyone who's provided (or received) a DIP facility in a chapter 11 proceeding. Or scholars of Islamic finance, where the idea is that if you finance a venture and that venture goes badly, the creditor is <em>supposed</em> to suffer losses alongside the venturer.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>