<post>
  <author>Gbdub87</author>
  <date>2020-09-22T16:35:03Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6882k9/</link>
  <title>Outgroup Homogeneity and "Defund the Police"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Does outgroup homogeneity bias play a role?</p>
      <p>With some notable exceptions, a lot of the victims of police brutality are of a type - what the police might call frequent fliers. This doesn’t justify them getting killed/shot/brutalized, but we’re generally talking about people who are genuinely involved in criminal activity, and not for the first time. </p>
      <p>When the victim is white, the mostly white audience and media pick up on the cues that the victim was of that sort that’s likely to come to a bad end one way or another. He’s not really “one of us”. But there’s a tendency to treat poor Black people as a homogenous (and sympathetic, even to the point of benevolent condescension) mass. </p>
      <p>A very large fraction of white people (and certainly the majority in the media and “very online” set) want very badly to avoid being seen as racist, and this can manifest as a willful blindness to facts that might complicate the narrative of sympathetic victims of racist police, lest such evidence “perpetuate harmful stereotypes”. (How much air time did CNN devote to Jacob Blake’s dad condemning the cops for “chaining his son to a bed”? Meanwhile I don’t think they ever mentioned, let alone attempted to interview, the woman he allegedly raped, the warrant for which was why he was handcuffed).</p>
      <p>Bluntly, no such sympathy and willful blindness is extended to “white trash”, which are pretty much the only socio-ethnic group you can safely bash in public in America these days. </p>
      <p>And it does seem to be an outgroup thing - I think the polls showing that “defund the police” is actually unpopular among Black Americans strongly hint that there is a recognition that the police may be flawed, may act with excessive force, but are largely acting against criminals who are a real threat to the Black community. More crudely there’s the classic Chris Rock bit about “Black people vs. n****z”...</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>