<post>
  <author>is_not_strained</author>
  <date>2020-09-26T01:06:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6ld1kp/</link>
  <title>Contra Judith Jarvis Thomson on Abortion</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Suppose we live in a world much like this one, but that cares much more about classical music.  It is the one great joy of most of the population, and many people openly state that it is their main reason for living.  </p>
      <p>In this world, creativity has been pretty  much washed out, perhaps due to how long people have been composing.  But, we found a solution to this.  There is a strange fungus, which is very hallucinogenic, but which gives very clear hallucinations of musical performances, which end up seared into the brain of the person who takes it, allowing them to remember it perfectly for months.  Of course, these mushrooms have a downside - they destroy your liver, and as a result you need a continuous transfusion for 9 months, until your new liver is grown.  </p>
      <p>It is common in this world for pairs of people to go search for these mushrooms, and once they find one, rush to the hospital to hook themselves together.  The next 9 months are often the highpoint of both peoples' lives as the symphony is slowly trascribed from the hallucinations.  The creation of pieces of music like these are perhaps the most valued things in the society, and are valued above essentially all else. Musicians tend to produce the best pieces, due to prior training, perhaps.</p>
      <p>One morning you wake up and find yourself hooked to a famous violinist.  It seems he took the mushrooms, and for some reason, he ended up hooked to you.  Everyone is so excited for you.  There is talk of renting a particular concert hall for the first performance, and casting the various roles if already being talked about, despite not even knowing if there will be singing roles.  </p>
      <p>Do you have a right to disconnect the violinist?  The question is strange.  Why would you want to do a stupid think like that?  He is a famous violinist. The symphony will probably be amazingly special.  This is your chance to make a difference that will outlast you, and contribute to society is a meaningful way.  </p>
      <p>Do I disconnect the violinist in this case?  I am pro-abortion, but I can't really find it in me to argue for disconnection.  Yes, it is awkward that I was hooked up without consent, but someone's life was in danger, and presumably I was the person at hand.  I understand that while I might not be particularly fond of classical music, everyone else is nuts about it, and everyone says I will grow enormously attached to the piece over the next 9 months.  I'd stay hooked to the violinist.  It is only 9 months, and I hope he doesn't snore.</p>
      <p>I find Singerian arguments for abortion, based on the fetus not being a rational human much more compelling.  I find arguments based on bodily autonomy very weak indeed.  I see that people everywhere have a responsibility to society, whether it means going to war, or cleaning the house.  Society helped us, and as a result, we have an obligation to help back.  A claim of bodily autonomy is a claim that there are things that society cannot ask us to do.  I don't see what the body is the clear line here.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>