<post>
  <author>is_not_strained</author>
  <date>2020-09-25T21:33:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6kq8xq/</link>
  <title>Economic Benefits of Immigration: A Skeptical Look</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Immigration is one of the most efficient ways to increase global and local GDP. There are strong differences in the institutions between regions in the degree to which they foster economic productivity.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>One major question is why it is not easier to change the institutions in the source countries.  It if far easier to send a few textbooks with rules for institutions than it is to move people, yet source countries very rarely change how they are governed, and continue to bleed migrants.  Why is it do hard for countries to improve their governance?</p>
      <p>Consider Central America:  Baja Mexico is just like Southern California, but with twice as much coast.  Baja Mexico is poor, and Southern California is rich.  Mexico is ostensibly a democracy, so its governance is decided by a vote of its citizens.  Southern California, and soon all of California, has a majority of people from Mexico, and as it is a democracy, why will descendants of Mexicans vote for different policies depending on where they live?  </p>
      <p>I suppose the reason is path dependent, and California is rich because of some luck in the past.  This sounds good, but does not really match up with the facts on the ground.  Silicon Valley is not rich because of actions in the 19th century, and Hollywood isn't really either.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>low productivity areas to high productivity ones</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Why are some areas high productivity and some low?  Consider Indian programmers, many or whom immigrate to the US.  Their job can easily be done in India, as programming is perhaps the easiest job to move remotely.  Why are they less productive in India than they are in the US?  How do Indian institutions make them less productive in their work?  It is hard to imagine governmental institutions making a programmer worse at programming without going to French levels of government intrusion in to working conditions.  If Indian programmers are as productive in India as they are in the US, then there should not be an incentive to move to the US, as companies should pay them as much in India as they do here.  This isn't the case, which points to something else going on.  </p>
      <p>The same question can be asked of Mexican agricultural workers, who could work in farms South of the border, but prefer to work North?  Why are farms more profitable north of the border?  Why is a laborer's work worth less South of the border?  It can't be productivity, as there is free trade.  I think this points to a major societal difference being the distinguishing factor.  Both Indian programmers and Mexican farm laborers are treated better in the US, because of a cultural norm that society should reward people more evenly.  This norm may be lacking in both source counties, and it seems more likely that it is societal attitudes like this that make America a nicer place than government institutions.  However, it seems very plausible that these attitudes will come to the US with immigrants, and the US will lose the benefits it had as a result of immigration.</p>
      <p>Looking at these two examples, farm workers and programmers, can you really believe that it is government institutions driving the difference in productivity, especially given the existence of multi-national companies.  If it is not productivity, why are immigrants paid much more in the US?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>