<post>
  <author>Mexatt</author>
  <date>2020-09-24T22:21:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6h51eg/</link>
  <title>A Critique of David Graeber Through the Lens of Anthropology</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The short of it is that, where he is a trained professional -- anthropology -- he is pretty good, albeit with a habit of letting lack of evidence serve as evidence of lack. He often spins conclusions from his field of expertise far outside of it, though, where he should not be treated drastically better than a layman. <em>Debt</em> is what I am most familiar with but <em>Bullshit Jobs</em> is not a work I've ever seen anyone who ought-to-know praise for anything.</p>
      <p>The long of it? Well, watch this space, hopefully I'll be able to get something out this evening.</p>
      <p>EDIT: OK, so my familiarity with Graeber comes specifically from the 'origins of money' perspective. All the dumb shit (like the Macbooks) doesn't interest me. What he gets wrong is his completionist presumption.</p>
      <p>So, one of the primary pieces of evidence he brings on the origin of money is that <em>all</em> of the earliest records we have on exchange involve temple debt at Uruk/Sumerian city-states, where a central organization collects production and distributes it according to a system of accounting debt. He gets this correct: That is what the archeology has been able to find. That is what we find as deeply important to the development of writing in Mesopotamia (it was about accounting). We don't find any real records of barter, mercantile exchange, or asset money. </p>
      <p>The problem ends up being that us not finding something <em>doesn't mean it doesn't exist</em>. Archeologists, as a profession, are <em>thirsty</em> for evidence of any kind because, for the most part, very little of any particular period at any particular site is actually going to have survived down to our day. Cuneiform is something of an archeologist's wet dream, because clay tablets with writing on them are <em>baked into a much more durable form</em> when they are burned, as many historical sites would have been. Because Mesopotamia <em>seems</em> to have been the oldest literate civilization (there's a decent chance Egypt learned to write from contact with the Fertile Crescent and signs of earlier literacy in China are extremely tentative), a lot of what we know on details of the earliest large scale civilizations comes from Mesopotamian tablets.</p>
      <p>And the things David writes about Mesopotamian tablets accord with the evidence: Internal trade in Mesopotamian city states from the Uruk period, through the Sumerian period, and into the Akkadian Empire/Ur period, involves varying degrees of focus on temple institutions as organizing the city's economy through a system of credit accounting we can see in the tablets. The Uruk period, especially, seems downright communist from what the evidence tells us.</p>
      <p>There are two problems with this, both related to the <em>incompleteness</em> of this evidence:</p>
      <p>\1. Graeber himself never contested that <em>long-distance trade</em> looks a lot more like the Mengerian story of increasingly sophisticated systems of barter. And these long-distance trading networks were <em>really, super important</em>, from the very earliest times. The 3rd Millennium, the dawn and early efflorescence of the Bronze age, absolutely required tin in large quantities for turning copper into bronze. The problem: Not a lot of tin in the Near East. Turns out that very large tin trade existing between the Fertile Crescent and <em>Afghanistan</em> since prehistoric times. We can tell because Mesopotamia also got its Lapis Lazuli (a very popular gemstone at the time) from the same sources. Trade with Egypt was also important, being the primary source of gold for essentially the whole Bronze age. There was no room for the kind of high trust, highly institutionalized credit systems that existed for <em>intra-state</em> trade in this long distance trade: The Levant was civilized but not a direct part of the state-system in Sumerian times, so the Egyptian trade had to pass through dangerous areas and often through middle-men, and the whole trade with Afghanistan passed through what was essentially wild-lands in Iran and Central Asia in the 3rd millennium BC. This depended on the kind of barter -&gt; separation of wants -&gt; search for medium of exchange -&gt; money story that looks like more like Menger.</p>
      <p>The problem with a lot of the above is it's hard to see long distance trade routes in the archeological record. We have to deduce their existence through finding goods that come from one place in an entirely different place.</p>
      <p>\2. <em>Just because we don't see non-credit based internal trade doesn't mean it didn't exist</em>. The credit-accounting systems of the temples in Uruk and Sumerian Mesopotamia were, ultimately, <em>highly</em> authoritarian and centralizing. The beginnings of Kingship in Mesopotamia comes from this period: The Sumerian word for 'king' is 'lugal' and, in earliest records, means something more like 'headman' or 'bigman'. While our records are wholly insufficient to draw a detailed picture, we can trace the rise of these big men from periodic war leaders, to permanent war leaders, to all powerful kings in what we do have. It's not hard to theorize that early Mesopotamians didn't have a clear concept of private property in land and the idea of collective ownership over land evolved into the temple system. After all, we see something similar in China, with the king's ownership over land leading to absolute authority over labor evolving out of a much more egalitarian system (mostly from assumptions based on burial practices).</p>
      <p>This is important to remember because, in the aftermath of the Akkadian Empire at the end of the 3rd century and the fall of the 3rd Dynasty of Ur, we start finding records <strong>immediately</strong> about elaborate practices, custom, and law surrounding land transfers. Why would a people with <em>no</em> familiarity with property and market exchange suddenly invent what seems to be a shockingly modern system of land ownership out of no where? The only thing that really makes sense is that there were un-written customary systems of law surrounding various kinds of property ownership in previous eras of Mesopotamian civilization, we just don't have any evidence of them because you can't see them in the material record and literacy was restricted to the temple economy based infrastructure that originally invented modern writing (earlier, proto-literate systems exist and have much more to do with private individuals -- the cylinder seal was invented centuries prior to the rise of the temple economy in the Uruk period and there are plenty of surviving cylinders with symbols that look a lot like proto-writing).</p>
      <p>That ends up being Graeber's main failing, then: He thinks <em>all the stuff he knows</em> is <em>all there is to know</em>. To be entirely fair to him, he has powerful command of the existing state of the art in many areas. However, he doesn't appreciate that the state of the art isn't <em>perfect</em>, in the grammatical sense. When he extolls debt jubilees, he completely ignores that we have <em>no</em> serious evidence on their economic effects in various areas. He has no theory on the differential effects between relatively un-monetized agricultural economies and modern, highly monetized post-industrial economies. He replaces the surity that comes from <em>really</em> knowing you've got a complete, evidence-based picture of the past with the surity he gets from having found enough evidence to satisfy his own motivations. He <em>wants</em> his debt-based picture of money to be true. He <em>wants</em> debt jubilees to seem like a natural thing to do. And he's got just enough evidence to prove it to himself.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>