<post>
  <author>OrangeMargarita</author>
  <date>2020-09-26T03:50:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6m4pkd/</link>
  <title>A Look at Amy Coney Barrett in Her Own Words</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So rumor has it tonight that Trump is going to nominate Amy Coney Barrett.  </p>
      <p>If the rumor mill is wrong, this post may end up being less relevant, but assuming it's true, I'm sharing <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7yjTEdZ81lI">this video</a> of a lecture and Q &amp; A that Barrett gave just a few days before the 2016 election.</p>
      <p>I watched this way back when there was speculation on Barrett for Kavanaugh's seat, and now obviously I was glad I did and have it to refer back to because I think you get a good sense of her judicial philosophy, etc.  It's worth noting at this time that everyone thought Clinton was going to win, and Barrett was not yet a federal judge, so she's opining on potential nominations in the future Clinton or Trump administration probably not imagining she would actually be one of them.  (One funny moment, where she explains the types of judges she expects Clinton will appoint, and then says as for Trump "who knows?" and kind of makes the face we probably all would have made answering that question in 2016.)</p>
      <p>Because it's a long video, some time stamps:</p>
      <p>4:00 mark - Introductions over and ACB begins talking about originalism, textualism, living constitutionalsism, etc.   She speaks in a really accessible way about this stuff for lay people.  She also talks specifically about Justice Scalia quite a bit (who she clerked for), as he had passed earlier that year, so some retrospective on his affect on the Court, etc.  </p>
      <p>20:00 or so in, this shifts to an interview of ACB by the host, and right around the 25:00 mark she gives a pretty quick rundown of how she sees the role of a justice, and again, I think this is a really clear and accessible way to explain it to an audience who are not all lawyers.  Basically, she says she tells her law students to think of Odysseus being tied to the ship's mast in order to resist the call of the sirens, that's the Constitution.   She said it's basically sober us setting rules for drunk us, that there's going to be times when we get swept away by passion or emotion and want to mandate or ban something and the Constitution is that rope holding us back.  She gave an example as Scalia's decision in a flag burning case in Texas.  He didn't like flag burning, it's a very emotional issue for some, but that he saw the Constitution as saying to him you may not like it, but you can't ban it as a judge, because we've already made a deeper commitment under our Constitution to the value of protest and freedom of expression.</p>
      <p>Conversely, she also says that there are a lot of things the Constitution is silent on and doesn't really forbid, and thus there might be things states or Congress want to do that you don't like or think are super smart, but you should allow under the Constitution as a judge, because the Constitution has given the people the freedom to innovate in that way.</p>
      <p>37:00 mark she talks about abortion, in response to a question.  She says that under a more conservative court she does not think Roe v. Wade would be overturned.  She said that the debate in the future would be about the test under Casey vs. Planned Parenthood and how far states can or cannot go in restricting abortions, most likely related to restrictions on late term abortion.</p>
      <p>Other stuff about substantive due process, public policy making, and the question of "who decides" the legislature, the courts, etc.</p>
      <p>Overall, I think she comes across as a very smart, reasonable, well spoken and accomplished woman who people may agree or disagree with politically.   But while the right and left spend the next however many days canonizing and/or demonizing her, I thought for those interested, this is a pretty good preview of the person we're likely to see actually show up at confirmation hearings.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>