<post>
  <author>randomerican</author>
  <date>2020-09-23T02:45:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6a534z/</link>
  <title>Thoughts on seeing Cuties</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Thoughts on seeing <em>Cuties</em> (full of spoilers BTW)</p>
      <p>This started as a reaction to a comment under last week's <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/iseo9j/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_14/g5ff9yn/">bare link to a paywalled piece by the director</a>. But it's a new week, so thought I might as well put it here.</p>
      <p>Someone commented:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>according to the two reviews I've read by people who actually watched it, the second half of the film displayed the children lasciviously on purpose as if in a music video, showing their journey into sexualized dance as a hero's journey, not an ill-regarded attempt to get attention from their peers and adjacent groups.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I also actually watched it...</p>
      <p>It didn't. It only showed as much as necessary for us to see the progression from a sports-movie "hero's journey"--others have pointed out the director uses these tropes to good effect--into something gross and unhealthy.</p>
      <p>You see their initial, more normal routine; then you see Amy (Ah-MEE, BTW, short for a Muslim name) watching adult dancers doing "sexy" moves. (On a stolen phone, already not a good thing, but sports-movie tropes make this first step forgivable. Then later you see her abandon her and her little brother's morning ritual because she's absorbed in checking for likes on this phone. And now you see that there are problems here.) You see her teaching these moves to the others--you see that these moves don't come naturally to the kids, they need to learn them. Because they're kids. You see that learning them together, messing up and laughing and trying again, helps them bond and that, of course, is part of the attraction. You then see that they've learned the moves. Those are all the dance scenes except for the final performance scene, which is the only one where they're also dressed in a sexualized way. (In some of the earlier scenes, they're wearing "normal French" clothes which are also still risque from a Senegalese POV; the film does show Amy noticing that, which I guess could be mistaken for "the camera perving." But her noticing that is part of the point--to her it's <em>all</em> risque, which is partly why she can't tell the difference and gets sucked in.)</p>
      <p>The background to all this is that her mother is miserable because her father is taking an additional, junior wife; her family is focused on preparing for her father's return from Senegal with this girl, and their wedding. Amy spends some time in denial; for example, when her friend convinces her to sneak into the new room being prepared in their home--a room "fit for a princess," as her friend says, with an "amazing" bed that :wince: the girls enjoy bouncing on. (A great way to drive the painful point home to the viewer. "Senegalese men aren't better," would be one way of putting it.) The friend asks whose room this is and Amy says, "I don't know." She knows. She just doesn't <em>want</em> to know.</p>
      <p>You can see that Amy has pinned all her hopes for some kind of future better than her mom's...on this sexualized dancing, and it's not healthy. When she's kicked out of the dance troupe, she tries to get them to take her back by showing up to practice and "just dancing" (it worked before); this time she's manic about it, then panics and throws a fit when they still won't take her back. When her friend from the troupe says she'll still be her friend, she hugs the girl so hard that the girl complains, "You're hurting me!" and eventually has to push her away. You expect something bad to happen to make Amy realize sexualized dancing is not the solution she so deperately needs it to be, and you just hope it won't be too harmful to her.</p>
      <p>And then she actually <em>pushes her replacement into the river</em> so they'll <em>have</em> to let her back into the troupe. Her one less-horrible act there is that she waits till she sees her ex-friend will make it to a buoy and not drown before she walks off. But I mean come on. Obviously pushing your rival into the river so she won't show up to the competition and you can step in to replace her is <em>not</em> a heroic act. She is on a wrong path and that is <em>very</em> clear by this point.</p>
      <p>Others have said the way she suddenly breaks and runs away in the middle of the final performance is unrealistic. I agree that it is a little. OTOH it's clearly a callback to when she breaks and runs away in the middle of carrying food to her father's wedding to the new junior wife. IOW: She's run from traditional Senegalese/Muslim culture, now she runs from sexualized social media culture as well.</p>
      <p>It's also somewhat clearly done for the sake of kindness to the character and the viewer--realistically, the bad thing that would've happened to her to make her realize this isn't the solution she's looking for, would've been some guy would've physically hurt her. Here, instead it's the contrast between the disapproval of the female audience and the lascivious enjoyment of some of the male audience. (During the performance we see a couple of pans over the audience and the last one especially--right before she runs--shows frowning women and a leering man.)</p>
      <p>I love the ending where Amy has laid out her sexualized competition outfit, and also her traditional outfit for her father's wedding, and she kind of pauses and looks at them both...and then puts on a "normal French" outfit (jeans and a sweater). And goes outside and finds some girls jumping rope and joins them. She's found a middle path.</p>
      <p>(In reality that's also unrealistic. But it's what we wish for.)</p>
      <p>(Edit: Typo, and I know most people here don't want to see it but just in case, added spoiler warning.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>