<post>
  <author>wlxd</author>
  <date>2020-09-26T01:13:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6ldqmy/</link>
  <title>Contra Judith Jarvis Thomson on Abortion (2)</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Towards the end of the video Shonalika asks why Judith Jarvis Thomson's violinist argument hasn't become the standard line on pro-choice activists everywhere. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Because it's not a very good argument for a general case, if you think about it. It's a strong argument in case of abortion of pregnancy as a result of rape, but regular pregnancy as a result of voluntary intercourse is <em>wholly unlike</em> waking up with a violinist attached to you for no reason at all. After all, when you have a sexual intercourse, becoming pregnant is widely understood as a normal consequence of the act, while waking up with a sick violinist attached to you is by no means a normal result of going to sleep.</p>
      <p>The original paper recognizes that, of course, and offers a riposte, to which one can offer another counterargument etc. Overall, I don't think that this argument is particularly convincing beyond the scenario of pregnancy as a result of rape.</p>
      <p>However, since we're talking about the paper anyway, I'd like to comment on some things said there, which rarely reach YouTube spotlight:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>First, while I do argue that abortion is not impermissible, I do not argue that it is always permissible. There may well be cases in which carrying the child to term requires only Minimally Decent Samaritanism of the mother, and this is a standard we must not fall below. (...) And it also allows for and supports our sense that in other cases resort to abortion is even positively indecent. It would be indecent in the woman to request an abortion, and indecent in a doctor to perform it, if she is in her seventh month, and wants the abortion just to avoid the nuisance of postponing a trip abroad. </p>
        <p>(...)</p>
        <p>Second, while I am arguing for the permissibility of abortion in some cases, I am not arguing for the right to secure the death of the unborn child. It is easy to confuse these two things in that up to a certain point in the life of the fetus it is not able to survive outside the mother's body; hence removing it from her body guarantees its death. But they are importantly different. I have argued that you are not morally required to spend nine months in bed, sustaining the life of that violinist, but to say this is by no means to say that if, when you unplug yourself, there is a miracle and he survives, you then have a right to turn round and slit his throat. You may detach yourself even if this costs him his life; you have no right to be guaranteed his death, by some other means, if unplugging yourself does not kill him. There are some people who will feel dissatisfied by this feature of my argument. <strong>A woman may be utterly devastated by the thought of a child, a bit of herself, put out for adoption and never seen or heard of again. She may therefore want not merely that the child be detached from her, but more, that it die.</strong> Some opponents of abortion are inclined to regard this as beneath contempt--thereby showing insensitivity to what is surely a powerful source of despair. All the same, I agree that the desire for the child's death is not one which anybody may gratify, should it turn out to be possible to detach the child alive.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>and</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Again, suppose pregnancy lasted only an hour, and constituted no threat to life or health. (...) So my own view is that even though you ought to let the violinist use your kidneys for the one hour he needs, we should not conclude that he has a right to do so--we should say that if you refuse, you are, like the boy who owns all the chocolates and will give none away, self-centered and callous, indecent in fact, but not unjust. And similarly, that even supposing a case in which a woman pregnant due to rape ought to allow the unborn person to use her body for the hour he needs, we should not conclude that he has a right to do so; <strong>we should say that she is self-centered, callous, indecent, but not unjust, if she refuses</strong>. The complaints are no less grave; they are just different. However, there is no need to insist on this point. If anyone does wish to deduce "he has a right" from "you ought," then all the same he must surely grant that there are cases in which it is not morally required of you that you allow that violinist to use your kidneys, and in which he does not have a right to use them, and in which you do not do him an injustice if you refuse. And so also for mother and unborn child. Except in such cases as the unborn person has a right to demand it--and we were leaving open the possibility that there may be such cases--<strong>nobody is morally required to make large sacrifices, of health, of all other interests and concerns, of all other duties and commitments, for nine years, or even for nine months, in order to keep another person alive</strong>.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'll try to summarize. The pregnancy itself is somewhat a red herring here: the core issue is that people (understandably) do not want to upend their lives by having actual babies, which tend to do just that. If pregnancy only lasted an hour,  and constituted no threat to life or health, I believe that pro-choice people would still argue for right to abort. Why, if there would be an obvious compromise to be made? After all, you could just give up the baby for adoption after the hour-long pregnancy, and get on with your life as if nothing happened. However, I can scarcely believe that pro-choice people would accept that bargain -- as Judith Jarvis Thomson observes above, women which would otherwise be happy to abort, <em>would intuitively consider giving up a child to be morally wrong</em>. Therefore, what pro-choice people do is to simply depersonify the fetus, to fend off the conscience. </p>
      <p>This is why the violinist argument isn't more popular: the pro-choice people do not believe it is valid, because in their framework the fetuses aren't people (violinists) anyway, so the whole argument hinges on the false assumption. The argument is meant only to exploit the perceived contradiction of the other side's belief system. However, it's not very good at that job either: it is strongest in case where pro-life people do not need much convincing anyway (pregnancy resulting from rape).</p>
      <p>I'd like to state here that I am generally pro-choice, exactly because I do not believe that early-term fetuses are persons. At the same time, I think that widespread use of contraceptives and abortion are destroying our societies, but it seems that I'm still too much of a (classical) liberal to believe that the well-being of the collective trumps the well-being of individual to argue in favor of banning them.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>