<post>
  <author>cincilator</author>
  <date>2020-09-21T21:36:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g65h50t/</link>
  <title>D-Day, Mistakes, and Social Media</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Someone once asked a question "why did D-day landing craft have one door in front instead of two doors at sides so German machine gunners would have two targets instead of one?"</p>
      <p>Well, I am not an expert in boat construction but that question reveals that general public is still unaware that there wasn't supposed to be any German machine gun fire on D-day. It was only due to various mistakes that soldiers had to run into any machine gun fire at all.</p>
      <p>See, D-day landings were preceded by the massive bombardment of beaches. But weather was poor and the navy was concerned that bombers might accidentally drop bombs on allied ships. Bombers were therefore ordered to release the bombs as late as possible, completely missing the beaches and succeeded only in killing some French sheep.</p>
      <p>That wasn't the only mistake made on that day. Amphibious tanks were also deployed to destroy German bunkers but they all sank again due to bad weather. So in the end it was up to infantry to rush German machine gun nests like Rambo. And many of those soldiers were seasick -- they gave them full meals evening before as a morale booster, which made them nauseous due to bad weather.</p>
      <p>I am not trying to say that Allied high command was inept. Overall, I think they were surprisingly competent. But even when you have the best plan in the world and competent people to execute it, tons of stuff can still go wrong. And they did win in the end which is what counts. But I am saying that even operations that were mostly competently planned and executed still contained big mistakes.</p>
      <p>There was also a string of blunders American Navy committed just before Pearl Harbor attack. They were caught with their pants down despite it being obvious for weeks that relationships with Japan were worsening and that in any Japanese assault Pearl Harbor would be a prime target. At the very least, the brass was guilty of gross incompetence.</p>
      <p>But imagine that social media existed back then. It would be easy to make everyone in Allied high command look like total and utter morons. Pearl Harbor in particular was remembered as a tragedy in part because the media back then was almost exclusively top-down. And people on top were interested in that event being remembered as a tragedy. But there were many elements of farce and twitter would have accentuated those elements.</p>
      <p>Then there would have been questions, like "why are we helping Europe when it was the Japanese who attacked us." Those questions were easily muzzled in actual history but with the help of social media, it would have been impossible to ignore.</p>
      <p>Also it is worth remembering that there were many stories of German atrocities circulating in the First World War. Many of those atrocities were subsequently proven to be exaggerated. Undoubtedly there would have been many people doubting the Holocaust simply based on heuristics from WWI. Sort of "Ah they want to make us hate 'The Hun' again, but we won't fall for it this time." Of course the Holocaust was very real as was subsequently proven, but skepticism at the time was somewhat understandable.</p>
      <p>Or imagine conspiracy theories. Imagine if "Roosevelt had advance-knowledge of the attacks" theory emerged a week after the attacks instead of years later. The chances for any unity would have been nill.</p>
      <p>My point here is that I believe that social media is making all countries ungovernable because it is no longer possible for leaders to establish a narrative. One can argue that the present leaders are also very inept -- which is probably true -- but even if you resurrected Washington, Lincoln and Eisenhower the social media would have found reasons to hate them all. Because ultimately criticism is easier than doing anything and social media makes criticism easy.</p>
      <p>On the one hand I really, really hade any kind of censorship, including private censorship. On the other, I really don't see America winning the World War II if it had current social media in place. It is difficult for me to reconcile the two.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>