<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2020-09-18T19:20:47Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iseo9j/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_14/g5qe279/</link>
  <title>Reflections on the Dragon Tyrant</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I firmly agree with this, and in case anyone hasn’t already seen it, I think Nick Bostrom’s <a href="https://philosophynow.org/issues/89/The_Fable_of_the_Dragon-Tyrant">Fable of the Dragon Tyrant</a> is a wonderful classic little argument against more benevolent or quietist views of death and ageing. </p>
      <p>/</p>
      <p>Really? When I read it, I felt the opposite- it drove me more towards an appreciation for live via death, because all that was good in the fable- the peace, the progress, the cooperation and gentleness in life in the face of terrible certainty that makes the people sympathetic- is the product of the people who accepted that view, and the moral of the fable rests on assuming the conclusion, which isn't sold in the story itself.</p>
      <p>It kind of came across as a whiplash of what the moral was, because protecting/expanding the output of these death-fearing people with their gentler, more peaceful, and progressive is the motive for slaying the dragon. 'Look at all these good people and the good things [quietist views of death and aging] do- we shouldn't have to sacrifice [good things built and sustained by quitest views of death]!' </p>
      <p>Nothing that the dragon-fearing people do is morally wrong because they are dragon-fearing, it's wrong because it's wasteful. Why should all these good dragon-fearing quietest views of death people be unnecessarily sacrificed? But it's only wasteful because it is unnecessary, and it's only unnecessary because the fable ends with the attempt to slay the dragon succeeding.</p>
      <p>Why? Because if the attempt to slay the dragon failed and it then wiped out everyone and not just the tribute, the moral would be reversed, and by ending before the post-dragon reorganizing begins, the the fable doesn't have to worry about if a post-dragon-fearing society is any <em>better</em> morally, practically, or even in sheer body count. It just assumes it.</p>
      <p>Which is a problem, because the fable is consequentialist to the core, but having to assume the consequence to justify the morality is such a 'victor right the history' approach is undermines any pretense at intrinsic moral value.</p>
      <p>Like, take a step back and just change whether the Dragon Killing device worked. If it failed, the entire story stops being a paeon of 'this society was tragically wasteful of its lives and tax revenue.' (Seriously, the focus on government expenditures and bureaucracy made me think it was parodying American conservative arguments to build an opposite conclusion.) Instead, it becomes a fable of how people, when faced with terrible truths and unsurmountable obstacles (as all people face), came together, made hard and tragic compromises, but also made the best of it and achieved something good until  people who weren't there for the hard parts didn't like it and ruined things for everyone.' </p>
      <p>If the consequence flips- if it turns out that unpleasant compromises are necessary to minimize human suffering and maximize human happiness, even when some people will always lose- then so does the moral of the fable. Which is alright in one aspect, since fables are meant to teach specific lessons, but bad <strong><em>as a fable</em></strong> because fables should teach broad/generalizable lessons, the sort of moral lesson that can be almost universally applied.</p>
      <p>Take the Good Samaritan Fable from Christian tradition. Generic everyman self-projection protagonist goes traveling as everyone does in life, has misfortune as everyone does in life, and needs help, as everyone does in life. Three individual of supposed virtue/social standing/positive reputation pass by and don't help. An individual of poor reputation/prejudice/stereotype, surprise!, does, and gives help. Moral of the fable: people of good reputation aren't always good, people of bad reputation aren't always bad.</p>
      <p>Thing is, though, the moral of the fable doesn't reverse in this case even if you reverse the 'twist.' If the Good Samaritan isn't Good and doesn't help, it doesn't change that the other supposedly virtuous people weren't, and it doesn't mean that all people of bad reputation are (because they did the same thing as 'good' reputation people). Similarly, if you changed one of the three bypassers to good- say that the third good man and the suspicious Samaritan both come across the traveler at the same time and help- the fundamental moral doesn't change at all. People of good reputation aren't always good (even if one is), people of bad reputation aren't always bad.</p>
      <p>A good fable's moral is resiliant to changes in the story, not just because most fables were oral traditions which varied inevitably anyway, but because good fables teach broadly applicable morals that should still be valid even circumstances change. The Dragon Tyrant fable doesn't, though. And aside from being horribly structured as a fable- keep it simple, people!- it kind of fails to give a moral judgement on the people.</p>
      <p>The dragon-tyrant <strong><em>system</em></strong> is condemned as a wasteful, unnecessary self-propegating system causing unnecessary human suffering, but the dragon-fearing <strong><em>people</em></strong> are the protagonists, even if that name nominally changes by the end. Moreover, their cultural norms and virtues- the sort that values grannies teaching grandsons to bake and values stability and peaceful disagreements and the prospect for technological progress- are the ones who's loss (to the dragon) are treated as bad. Dragon-fearing people society isn't bad- Dragon-fearing society sacrificing to the dragon is bad, but this One Technological Trick will change that. The moral victory of the tale is that Dragon-fearing people no longer have to be Dragon-fearing, and the system that imposed costs on them can be removed.</p>
      <p>It's still Dragon-fearing culture expected to continue. Not literally, of course- they accepted risk and killed the Dragon- but everything else that was them. The peace, prosperity, the kind of people who can tolerate dissent, encourage technological development, and teach grandchildren to bake cookies is expected to remain, even expand, the number of people who tolerate dissent, encourage technological development, and teach grandkids to bake cookes. It's implicitly not going to enter into a loss of compassion as dragon-fear contentment gives way to historical ambition, civil wars as the bureaucracies and kings lost their legitimization and other people want that power or tax revenue, or the total genocide of all humanity as dragon-killing weapons get developed into nukes by people whose social revolution was killing the great big threat turning against eachother. </p>
      <p>But this consequentialist fable- despite spending reams of time and text on describing causal reasons for why everything else was the way it was, never establishes why this is the way thing will be without the Dragon. It just assumes it.</p>
      <p>Which, okay, the text is long enough on its own, but it's kind of like taking the Christianity out of Christians and expecting them to be even better Christians now that they don't have to worry about damnation, salvation, or those arbitrary commandments. Taking the Christ out of American Liberals didn't make more tolerant, less dogmatic, or more forgiving as a people, it made American Progressives.</p>
      <p>The Fable of the Dragon Tyrant is a story of this bad circumstance that perpetuates an injustice against good people who are good in the context of this looming injustice, removes the context that led to them becoming good, and then acts like the only thing that's going to change is that unnecessary government bureaucracy and taxes can be decreased now that the problem's gone.</p>
      <p>Please, reducing the bureaucracy is the least plausible thing in that story!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>