<post>
  <author>gattsuru</author>
  <date>2020-09-20T22:53:57Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iseo9j/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_14/g61iocm/</link>
  <title>Jimmy Carter, Reactor Cleanup, and Nuclear Non-Proliferation</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Carter lead the cleanup of the Canadian NRX reactor after communication and control issues caused a core dump in '52, and was pretty open about it as a formative experience.  He was most overtly anti-nuclear in the reasonable context of nuclear weapons, but his anti-proliferation policies had a severe and often technically questionable impact on civilian nuclear power.</p>
      <p>The big and well-documented one is the <a href="https://www.nrc.gov/docs/ML1209/ML120960615.pdf">prohibition on nuclear waste reprocessing</a>: where Ford had questioned it earlier, Carter started a complete ban in April of '77 and vetoed legislative authorization.</p>
      <p>At least in public, Carter said that this was to prevent plutonium proliferation.  The problem is that civilian reactor fuel generates both Pu-239 and Pu-240, with the exact ratio dependent on how long its fuel replacement cycle runs but usually around or under 70% Pu-239, and the technology to separate the two isotopes is much, much harder than just building a normal plutonium production reactor.  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plutonium-240">Pu-240 makes wonderful nuclear generator fuel -- it's a basis for one of the more popular types of MOX -- but an awful bomb</a>: it makes too many loose neutrons on its own and capture too many neutrons without fission to avoid igniting itself in a far more boring manner.  As a result, reactor fuel is one of the least useful ways to produce bombs-grade plutonium possible.</p>
      <p>((It's possible Carter was trying to prevent Neptunium-237 isolation, and the stated goal of blocking plutonium was to hold that a secret.  Np-237 can be turned into a bomb, though if it's ever been done it remains classified; worse, it has civil uses as an intermediate isotope for producing Pu-238, an excellent radiothermal generator fuel.  On the other hand, it's easily produced by irradiation of Uranium-238 <em>outside</em> a civil power reactor and far simple refining techniques, so it'd still be wrong, just not so clearly stupid.))</p>
      <p>The ban wasn't bad in the sense of lost time or increased storage requirements for waste while it was active, but it also came about just months after the Barnwell Nuclear Fuel Plant had completed its first automated test load and was waiting for a permit, after a major investment.  This was to be the first civilian plant to reprocess nuclear power plant waste, and it had already signed up customers like the Clinch River Breeder Reactor (which was also blocked).  Not only did this screw them over while the ban was in place, even after it was dropped in '81, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission refused to issue licenses to anyone.  The plant's founders <a href="https://openjurist.org/839/f2d/1572/allied-general-nuclear-services-v-united-states">weren't even able to argue it as a taking</a>.  As a result, Allied noped the hell out of Barnwell; Clinch River's proponents dropped it in '83 when it became clear that their first-in-class plant's only remaining source of fuel would require getting more than half of the then-available military stockpile.  Neither the reprocessing plant, nor their customers, could make sense if they risked having to start and stop every time the federal government changed its mind, as either waste would be piled up and need storage, or Plutonium-dependent reactors would find themselves needing replacement material.</p>
      <p>The more subtle problem is a physics one.  Some portion of uranium power plant nuclear waste is Pu-241: it's an intermediate step of plutonium thermal neutron irradiation, so it's never there long, but there's always some when you change fuel.  Pu-241 is short-lived and, over a few years, starts turning into Americium-241.  Am-241 is very useful once separated and turned into AmO2.  You probably have some in your house in a smoke detector.  But it's an absolute pain for fuel reprocessing, as it gets everywhere and you really don't want an alpha and weak gamma emitter doing that near your fleshy lungs.  Barnwell was an attempt to solve that problem through automation, by making a plant that didn't care about alpha and low-energy gamma rays.  Anyone smaller would be stuck doing things by hand in glove-boxes, and the longer the fuel sat in waste fuel storage ponds waiting, the greater the radiation dose awaiting the next <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harold_McCluskey">McCluskey</a>.</p>
      <p>Leaving vastly greater amounts of nuclear waste spread in cooling ponds across the country wasn't just putting the problem off or making it seem larger than it genuinely was, by including recyclable spent fuel with genuine transmute-or-store-waste.  It genuinely made it harder to solve.</p>
      <p>And, of course, the US not doing a thing was absolutely no motivation for other countries to not do the same thing: it didn't slow any of them.  Carter tried to push Western countries to do the same, but ended up dropping the requirement entirely early on (despite it technically being required under the Nuclear Nonproliferation Act he championed), and Soviet-related countries didn't even pretend to care.  Japan <em>may</em> have agreed to something similarish, but if so it remains classified, the agreement was under Reagan, and Japan was and remains the country least interested in nuclear bombs anyway.</p>
      <p>Carter's era of NRC also made a general regulation against MOX reactors (theoretically until results from studies came in), increased inspections requiring a full shutdown of a reactor, and another fuel reprocessing plant (from Exxon, ugh) got indefinitely suspended as well.  Carter himself called against the US becoming <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1976/05/14/archives/carter-proposes-a-nuclear-limit-at-un-he-advances-plan-to-halt.html">dependent on nuclear power</a>, and the shape of the Kemeny Commission (in particular its emphasis on avoiding the appearance of being tainted by the nuclear industry, and the short timeline) made a mess of that.</p>
      <p>Carter wasn't the only cause for the end of the age of the atom: well-organized lawfare against permitted nuclear plants under construction began in the late 1960s and took off before Carter's election, inflation made nuclear power plants a dangerous investment anyway, and both the Dresden II and Three Mile Island incidents, while not especially severe in impact, definitely made the public more nuclear-cautious.</p>
      <p>It's not even clear that the breeder reactors as implemented were a terribly good idea, were they to be allowed.  Clinch River and nearly all of its progeny were to be a sodium-cooled reactor, which has all manner of stupid problems; its funding structure was Nixonian zaniness; and much of its economic model depended on either vastly reduced supply or increased demand (or both) for uranium that was unlikely to materialize.  But the result didn't just kill Clinch River, or sodium-cooled reactors, or breeder reactors.</p>
      <p>The end result put the writing on the wall.  While the original Carter rule argued on the matter of nuclear non-proliferation justified it, the resulting NRC regulations and federal court jurisprudence made clear that they could cut an in-construction or newly-operating power or reprocessing plant for any reason or no reason, with no recourse.  The more novel or interesting the reactor, or the more capable the reprocessing plant, the greater the risk.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>