<post>
  <author>HelloGunnit</author>
  <date>2020-09-17T21:25:54Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iseo9j/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_14/g5mw3t2/</link>
  <title>Protests: A Police Officer's Perspective</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Purely anecdotally, I can offer my perspective as a police officer.  While my city may be a bit of an outlier (Portland has both been hit disproportionately hard by the protests/riots, and has historically had a fairly low baseline homicide rate), I suspect the general pattern here broadly fits the nation's other large cities.  Our homicide rate has certainly <a href="https://www-oregonlive-com.cdn.ampproject.org/v/s/www.oregonlive.com/crime/2020/08/portlands-deadly-july-domestic-violence-suspected-love-triangle-and-gang-retaliation-among-15-killings.html?amp_js_v=a2&amp;amp_gsa=1&amp;outputType=amp&amp;usqp=mq331AQFKAGwASA%3D#aoh=16003758287798&amp;referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com&amp;amp_tf=From%20%251%24s&amp;ampshare=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.oregonlive.com%2Fcrime%2F2020%2F08%2Fportlands-deadly-july-domestic-violence-suspected-love-triangle-and-gang-retaliation-among-15-killings.html">spiked since April</a>.</p>
      <p>Firstly, prolonged protests themselves are a <em>huge</em> personnel sink.  Any single large protest can be handled without real lasting effect on staffing; you just hire a bunch of extra officers in overtime that day and pull some more bodies off of patrol.  Sure, that one day will have worse response times to calls, but it's just a blip.  When the protests go on for weeks (months, in our case) you simply can't afford to keep hiring overtime at that same rate, so you have to move more and more bodies to protest duty.  Here in Portland, it's not unusual to have more than a third of the cities active patrol officers assigned to protest duties on any given night.  Plus, it's not merely beat cops being displaced.  Here in Portland (and I believe this is not uncommon in other large cities) detectives get pulled to be part of the arrest processing, as the large numbers of people arrested at each protest cannot be processed effectively without a dedicated team doing that (the actual arresting officers, who are in the front line of the crowd-control teams, need to remain there to keep controlling the rest of the crowd).  Furthermore, all the overtime being worked for the protests means those officers are less likely to fill other, pre-existing overtime needs.  </p>
      <p>Outside of direct effect on staffing, the protests and perceived lack of support from the populace and local government has led to an uptick in retirements and officers leaving to work for more suburban or rural departments.  I imagine (although I'm not personally privy to the number) that it is also reducing the number of people applying to become officers.  This, at least here, is irrelevant, in that defunding measures passed by our city council have forced us to halt all new hiring in order to reduce staffing down to the new, reduced numbers called for in the new budget.  We have also been ordered to disband our Gun Violence Reduction unit (disproportionately arrested black men, <a href="https://www.wweek.com/news/2020/06/09/mayor-ted-wheeler-agrees-to-disband-the-portland-police-bureaus-gun-violence-reduction-team/">so therefore was racist</a>) and disband our School Resource Officers (having cops in schools <a href="https://www-opb-org.cdn.ampproject.org/v/s/www.opb.org/news/article/superintendent-says-discontinue-police-presence-portland-schools/?amp_js_v=a2&amp;amp_gsa=1&amp;outputType=amp&amp;usqp=mq331AQFKAGwASA%3D#aoh=16003753534813&amp;referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com&amp;amp_tf=From%20%251%24s&amp;ampshare=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.opb.org%2Fnews%2Farticle%2Fsuperintendent-says-discontinue-police-presence-portland-schools%2F">was also racist</a>, somehow), and to disband all of our Transit Officers (cops on light rail was <a href="https://news.trimet.org/2020/06/trimet-reallocates-1-8-million-in-funding-from-transit-police-and-additional-sources-to-community-based-services-that-preserve-public-safety/">apparently racist</a>, as well).</p>
      <p>Lastly, independent of staffing numbers, is the issue of officer motivation and morale.  Between the above-mentioned defunding, our own city councilors <a href="https://katu-com.cdn.ampproject.org/v/s/katu.com/amp/news/local/commissioner-jo-ann-hardesty-claims-officers-starting-fires-police-chief-chuck-lovell-union-president-daryl-turner-want-evidence?amp_js_v=a2&amp;amp_gsa=1&amp;usqp=mq331AQFKAGwASA%3D#aoh=16003759358440&amp;referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com&amp;amp_tf=From%20%251%24s&amp;ampshare=https%3A%2F%2Fkatu.com%2Fnews%2Flocal%2Fcommissioner-jo-ann-hardesty-claims-officers-starting-fires-police-chief-chuck-lovell-union-president-daryl-turner-want-evidence">accusing us of committing widespread arson</a>, Oregon's House Speaker declaring the police using tear gas to stop rioters who were trying to burn down the union office to be "unlawful," stating <a href="https://www-oregonlive-com.cdn.ampproject.org/v/s/www.oregonlive.com/crime/2020/07/police-union-president-responds-to-oregon-house-speaker-tina-kotek-asking-why-she-didnt-decry-vandalism-to-police-precincts-local-businesses.html?amp_js_v=a2&amp;amp_gsa=1&amp;outputType=amp&amp;usqp=mq331AQFKAGwASA%3D#aoh=16003763222480&amp;referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com&amp;amp_tf=From%20%251%24s&amp;ampshare=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.oregonlive.com%2Fcrime%2F2020%2F07%2Fpolice-union-president-responds-to-oregon-house-speaker-tina-kotek-asking-why-she-didnt-decry-vandalism-to-police-precincts-local-businesses.html">"What needed to be protected last night? An empty office building?"</a>, and a District Attorney who has openly declared that <a href="https://katu-com.cdn.ampproject.org/v/s/katu.com/amp/news/local/multnomah-co-das-policy-on-protest-arrests-focused-on-property-damage-theft-violence?amp_js_v=a2&amp;amp_gsa=1&amp;usqp=mq331AQFKAGwASA%3D#aoh=16003765373603&amp;referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com&amp;amp_tf=From%20%251%24s&amp;ampshare=https%3A%2F%2Fkatu.com%2Fnews%2Flocal%2Fmultnomah-co-das-policy-on-protest-arrests-focused-on-property-damage-theft-violence">he won't prosecute the vast majority of BLM/anti-police protest arrests</a>, most officers have the distinct feeling that they are not wanted here, and are acutely aware that anything they do that involves a bad outcome (whether or not they are in any way at fault) is liable to bring about a swift end to their career.  When you systematically crush morale, and then build an incentive structure where there is little, if any, risk in doing the very minimum necessary each day, and an enormous risk with zero reward for doing anything proactive, you end up with a broken system.</p>
      <p>With staffing and budgets slashed, and officers who are well aware that they have a political bullseye on their backs, you get some serious depolicing, and this doesn't go unnoticed.  Anecdotally, I've seen a large increase in brazen behavior by my local thieves, dealers, vandals, and chronic trespassers.  I suspect that the reason why these numbers are not also spiking is that they are going largely unreported.  When you call 911 to report one of these types of things, and it takes an officer six or more hours to respond (not unusual in Portland these days) are you still going to be home, or even care to report it at that point?  After that experience, are you even going to bother calling at all the next time something happens?  Well, the gangsters are getting more brazen too.  With the shootings and homicides, though, I suspect the reason that the spike is so apparent is that you can't really ignore or shrug off a bullet wound (and hospitals will report GSWs), and dead bodies are hard to ignore (they start to smell, especially in the summer).</p>
      <p>*Edited to fix type-o and link</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>