<post>
  <author>INH5</author>
  <date>2020-09-14T23:23:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iseo9j/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_14/g5at80b/</link>
  <title>Cancel Culture Is not New</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The whole concept of cancel culture is something that seems to be an aberration.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It really, really isn't. You don't even need to go back to McCarthy, going back to early 2003 will suffice.</p>
      <p>Everyone remembers what happened to the band formerly known as the Dixie Chicks when they spoke out against the Iraq War. But it wasn't just wacky Country Music fans. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M7Is43K6lrg&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=72">Michael Moore got booed off stage at <em>the Oscars</em> when he spoke out against Bush and the Iraq War.</a></p>
      <p>Nor was this confined to the entertainment industry. <a href="https://fair.org/press-release/some-critical-media-voices-face-censorship/">This article from 2003</a> list several examples of reporters getting fired for anti-war views, including 2 who worked at MSNBC and 1 who worked at the San Francisco Chronicle. It also mentions cases of anti-war websites having difficulties with their web hosts:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The website YellowTimes.org, which featured original anti-war reporting and commentary, was shut down by its Web hosting company on March 24, after it posted images of U.S. POWs and Iraqi civilian victims of the war. Orlando-based Vortech Hosting told Yellow Times in an e-mail, “Your account has been suspended because [of] inappropriate graphic material.” Later, the company clarified: “As ‘NO’ TV station in the U.S. is allowing any dead U.S. soldiers or POWs to be displayed and we will not either.” As of April 3, the site was still down.</p>
        <p>The Qatar-based Al-Jazeera news network’s attempts to set up an English-language website were foiled by unidentified hackers who launched a denial-of-service attack. Al-Jazeera is expected to try to relaunch its site in mid-April. The station’s reporters also had their press credentials revoked by the New York Stock Exchange, and were unable to obtain alternative credentials at the NASDAQ exchange: “In light of Al-Jazeera‘s recent conduct during the war, in which they have broadcast footage of U.S. POWs in alleged violation of the Geneva Convention, they are not welcome to broadcast from our facility at this time,” a NASDAQ spokesperson told the Los Angeles Times (3/26/03).</p>
        <p>Addendum, 4/7/03: Al-Jazeera‘s English-language website is, at the moment, available at english.aljazeera.net/, despite losing their contract with their U.S. hosting company (New York Times, 4/4/03).</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The Overton Window expanded a lot after it turned out that Saddam didn't have WMDs and the war turned into a quagmire, but things were still on edge for years afterwards. Razib Khan made <a href="https://www.gnxp.com/WordPress/2019/12/01/the-coddling-of-the-neoconservative-mind/">a blog post about this</a> December of last year, making points that I think will be familiar with anyone who discussed politics online during the 2000s:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Perhaps a more clear and distinct illustration of this tendency is what happened in the 2000s when you attempted to <em>understand</em> the roots and causes of violent terrorism. Periodically we would post things on this weblog trying to be dispassionate and analytical. Inevitably, regular readers and even some contributors would <em>lose their shit</em>. The issue is that 9/11 was still raw and visceral. A non-trivial number of people in the greater New York City area had lost people. The invasion of Iraq in 2003 and the broad public support for it was in large part simply due to the need to “do something.” The events around 9/11 broke the American sense of control and comprehension. Focusing on Iraq refocused us. In the early years critiquing the rationale for the invasion, and even attempting to understand the causal basis of terrorism, were seen as what we’d now call triggering.</p>
        <p>People who in other circumstances were entirely rational would just lose their shit if you attempted to understand the issue analytically. Osama bin Laden, like Adolf Hitler, had become a legend, a monster in the dark. An agent of evil that was supernatural. Perhaps more precisely, terrorism had become a supranatural phenomenon. Above analysis.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>What is new is social media and ubiquitous smartphones. In 2003, internet forums were much smaller, usually anonymous, and had very little reach, and almost nobody carried a video camera in their pocket 24/7, let alone one that could upload video straight to the internet from anywhere with cell service. I shudder to think about what might have happened had that tech been common back then.</p>
      <p>As for the comparison to Occupy Wall Street: First, it isn't actually true that no one got fired because of that. <a href="http://archive.is/I02v">This article from 2011 talks about 2 journalists that lost their jobs due to participating in the movement.</a> Second, while unemployment was high back then, people weren't trapped in their homes out of fear of a deadly virus, so now the collective level of anxiety is higher than at any time since, well, the early years of the War on Terror. Third, you mention that your experience has mainly been with "IT people," and it seems likely that IT jobs have an especially large glut of job applicants right now, because they can be done remotely. Ditto for online journalism.</p>
      <p>Fourth, it's hard to understate how uniquely divisive Trump is. That's a large part of why he was elected in the first place, and then he had the misfortune to be handed a totally unprecedented-in-the-modern era crisis.</p>
      <p>Finally, on a more speculative note, I don't think we can discount the possible role of broader political motivations. The Patriotic Correctness of the 2000s helped boost a bipartisan foreign policy strategy, and I don't think it's a coincidence that we started talking a lot less about Islamic terrorism right around the time that ISIS was defeated and the Foreign Policy Blob set its sights on Iran, making Al Qaeda start to look like an enemy of our "real" enemy again. Given the rarity of attacks by Al Qaeda on the West in the last couple of years, I strongly suspect that this feeling is at least partially mutual.</p>
      <p>Today, a lot of people stand to benefit if Trump were to be voted out of office and replaced with a President with more conventional policies on trade and immigration. And the current protest movement has turned out to be particularly good at decreasing Trump's poll numbers.</p>
      <p>So I think that the current situation has been brought about by a confluence of multiple different black swan events. This too shall pass. If anything, it seems likely to pass much faster than the War on Terror era cancel culture did, because it's not like you could develop a vaccine to make Al Qaeda go away.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>