<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-09-18T00:36:26Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iseo9j/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_14/g5nioo4/</link>
  <title>Metrics That Seem Important: Negative $1 Million Per Second</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>METRICS THAT SEEM IMPORTANT:  negative $1,000,000 per second. (-31.5 trillion annualized)</strong>
      </p>
      <p>[usdebtclock.org[(<a href="https://usdebtclock.org/">https://usdebtclock.org/</a>) has been a big part of my news feed since atleast highschool (maybe even middle school). </p>
      <p>The numbers aren’t always the most accurate, sometimes Employment numbers come out or a large bill passes, and it can take a month or so to be reflected on their dashboard (i don’t currently trade, and I certainly wouldn’t trade off the data on usdebtclock (it again being weeks if not months out of date)) but there is really nowhere else all the core financial metrics, Ie. core Political Metrics, are so conveniently presented.</p>
      <p>One click and its easy to get a feel for the current  cost of the us military, or A rough estimate for the Amount of interest the US pays on its debt in a given year (both federal interest, and just total interest paid by anyone in the economy) and best yet you can get a rough feel for how the metrics are moving.... again probably not the best source... but if you want a rough estimate for how a metric is moving, you can do far worse (heaven help you if you only look at the numbers that pop up in news articles). Again not the best (there’s no way to really interrogate those rates through the platform), but having all the metric together on one page you notice things you’d never think to look up on your own.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>It was on one of these routine checks I noticed a metric that made my jaw hit the floor. <strong>Total Us National Assets</strong> the gross value of every asset currently in the US, everything currently owned by a person, private business, corporation or NGO, (before we apply debts, costs, ect.) is declining by roughly $1,000,000 per second.  Or ~31.5 trillion dollars per year.</p>
      <p>And while an annualized rate  of a single dramatic point in time  can mislead... DebtClock’s projections for 2024, which I’ve always known to be fairly optimistic (I’ve never known actual US debt in Year X, to come in under Debtclock’s projections in (X-4 years)), come in at a whopping $56 trillion less than today, with the current $125 trillion dollars in national assets projected to shrink over 40% to $69 trillion in assets!!! (LOL 69)</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>This leads to the obvious question: The fuck!? HOW!?!</p>
      <p>Is this just some fluke of paper? A Valuation goes up, valuation goes down, but the house remains unchanged  kinda thing? </p>
      <p>the coronavirus pandemic and lockdown (I’ll leave it to readers to argue which is truly to blame), has  already reduced projected US GDP this year from $22trillion to $19.5 Trillion (Note: Gross Domestic Product is GROSS not NET, it doesn’t reflect costs, such as say taxes, or bad spending choices, or asset Destruction)...it would seem the obvious hypothesis that the Pandemic/Lockdown is also the thing responsible for this vast hit to US assets... but again how!?</p>
      <p>Unless you live in the pacific northwest, vast amounts of personal assets aren’t being literally destroyed (I’d be shocked if the riots and forrest fires across the US combined added to to more than 100-150 billion in damage), and Unlike 2008 we haven’t seen a crazy revaluation of personal assets. Home prices is still riding high, vehicle prices are unmoved (and they don’t appear to be depreciating any faster), guns (the most important American asset) are going through something of a Boom, and the stock market is hitting all time highs.</p>
      <p>Also, I‘m not sure they count, but Interest rates are nearly as low as they’ve ever been, so your bond portfolio is still valued very highly.</p>
      <p>Well what else is there?  Housing, Vehicles, Guns, Bonds, stocks.... wait! don’t tell me something’s happened to the Options!?... just checked Options are fine (They’re derivatives of the bond and stock (and housing) market, how so could they not be?)</p>
      <p>Whats left? Household assets, Owned Debt, publicly held business Equity....oh.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>It would seem that all the Damage, the 1 Million dollars a second, is all damage being done to <em>Privately Held Business Equity</em>. Ie. The Most Important Asset Class.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Let us imagine a hypothetical city...lets borrow a historical name, maybe something from a cool war like 1812...lets call it Detroit.</p>
      <p>Now lets imagine that for some reason, a large fraction of the business equity leaves this city. They don’t take the houses, they don’t take the people hell they don’t even take the factories... they just no longer use them. What happens is all those physical goods lose their value, the houses drop in value because you can’t make any significant amount of money if you live in them, the factory buildings and hard assets become worthless because you cant make any money with them, and machines and fittings that might have cost 1000s or tens of thousands to make and install, get stripped for their scrap value.</p>
      <p>Remove enough business equity and even mansions that might have cost millions to build become derelict and empty, as ruined as if they burnt down, only their true ruin comes decades before  their final literal destruction by fire, which comes only once they’re so worthless and ruined no one cares to stop wayward youths from torching them on devils night. </p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>As our hypothetical demonstrates: the value of most every asset: houses, cars, and of course the debt your owed ( and you owe others) is driven by the ability of people to produce things to trade for it. Your Rolex is only worth $10,000 somewhere where someone is able and willing to pay $10,000.</p>
      <p>So when private equity collapses due to its inability to produce as much value (trust me, months of unprecedented money printing and debt buying ensures nothing BUT fundamentals could be driving this valuation collapse...) it trickles through.</p>
      <p>“But wait!” I hear you say.</p>
      <p>“You said the Stockmarket is at an all-time high! What gives!? Shouldn’t it be moving with the rest of private equity?”</p>
      <p>Well thats the thing, it largely is.</p>
      <p>Take out the top companies, hell take out the FAANGs (Facebook, Amazon, Apple,  (Microsoft?), Netflix, and Google), and the market is down significantly from February. Hell even in the Tech world Airbnb and Uber aren’t doing that hot... and Tech is probably the industry least effected. </p>
      <p>The most consistent trend this downturn, with some exceptions, is the smaller your business the more screwed you are. Apple and Amazon are barely effected and can buyback their shares with bargain basement money they can borrow from the FED. The Airlines get bailed out, and of course the banks have all quietly received their bailouts... but companies that didn’t feel the need for lobbyists, and aren’t  the subject of 70.year old stories of regulatory capture (seriously watch <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Aviator_(2004_film">The Aviator</a>)) are going bankrupt, even large ones like Hertz and JC Penny.</p>
      <p>And of course small business is Screwed. Their are conspiracy theories about the lockdown and why politicians don’t seem keen to reopen the second the numbers might allow their constituents to return to normal... are they trying to make trump look bad? Do they just love power? Are they trying to break our will so we won’t resist the aliens? And the obvious answer is the corporations with connections and large political budgets will still be there at the end of any lockdown, worse case scenario you give them another bailout... the small businesses that compete with them, and might dethrone them... they die off and leave cheap storefronts for Starbucks and McDonald’s to move into.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>This is why I broadly oppose the Trump bucks and  extended unemployment, and eviction moratoriums, it anaesthetizes people and the economy to the damage being done.</p>
      <p>If a doctor is preforming surgery to remove cancer, and you’ll die if don’t get it done... well you want to be anaesthetized both to avoid the pain, but as a form of precommitment... worst possible scenario is you chicken out mid incision, then are dying of cancer AND have a massive incision in you. But not all surgeries are like this, some you really want to feel the pain and feedback lest the doctor go to far and do more damage than its worth... brain surgery, for example, requires you to be conscious so you can give feedback, and the doctor will know if you start barking like a dog. Routine dental cleaning and drilling requires the patient be conscious lest the dentist severely strain the jaw of the patient (anyone who’s had their wisdom teeth out knows the severe pain and bruising (not from having the teeth pulled) but often just having your sleeping jaw forced open to useful width).</p>
      <p>If you’re doing a fine cost benefits analysis Its important you feel the pain so you can judge it... otherwise you might come to after a deep massage, only to find you’ve bern paralyzed and your legs broken.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>