<post>
  <author>monfreremonfrere</author>
  <date>2020-09-19T07:03:58Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iseo9j/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_14/g5sk0vx/</link>
  <title>Declining Syntactic Sophistication Over the Centuries?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Declining syntactic sophistication over the centuries?</strong>
      </p>
      <p>If I may offer a low-temperature distraction from the culture war: Occasionally in these threads <a href="/u/Doglatine">u/Doglatine</a> and others have lamented a general decline in erudition among the educated over time. Evidence adduced included <a href="http://graphics8.nytimes.com/packages/pdf/education/harvardexam.pdf">this Harvard entrance exam from the 1800s</a> and also transcripts from the Lincoln-Douglas debates (sorry, I couldn't immediately find who linked these).</p>
      <p>I want to focus on one specific aspect of this apparent decline: <strong>the convoluted and impenetrable writing style of past times</strong>, and what verbal whizzes people must have been back then to be able to parse their own sentences. This is a problem familiar to anyone who went to high school.</p>
      <p>The obvious explanation would be that language changes over time, so texts become harder and harder to understand. Perhaps a Harvard student of the 1800s would have an equally tough time with the SAT reading section today. I find this explanation implausible and inadequate.</p>
      <p>Let's look at U.S. presidential inaugural addresses as a source of directly comparable text samples. Here's the start of George Washington's:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Fellow Citizens of the Senate and the House of Representatives,  </p>
        <p>Among the vicissitudes incident to life, no event could have filled me with greater anxieties than that of which the notification was transmitted by your order, and received on the fourteenth day of the present month. On the one hand, I was summoned by my Country, whose voice I can never hear but with veneration and love, from a retreat which I had chosen with the fondest predilection, and, in my flattering hopes, with an immutable decision, as the asylum of my declining years: a retreat which was rendered every day more necessary as well as more dear to me, by the addition of habit to inclination, and of frequent interruptions in my health to the gradual waste committed on it by time. On the other hand, the magnitude and difficulty of the trust to which the voice of my Country called me, being sufficient to awaken in the wisest and most experienced of her citizens, a distrustful scrutiny into his qualifications, could not but overwhelm with dispondence, one, who, inheriting inferior endowments from nature and unpractised in the duties of civil administration, ought to be peculiarly conscious of his own deficiencies. In this conflict of emotions, all I dare aver, is, that it has been my faithful study to collect my duty from a just appreciation of every circumstance, by which it might be affected. All I dare hope, is, that, if in executing this task I have been too much swayed by a grateful remembrance of former instances, or by an affectionate sensibility to this transcendent proof, of the confidence of my fellow-citizens; and have thence too little consulted my incapacity as well as disinclination for the weighty and untried cares before me; my error will be palliated by the motives which misled me, and its consequences be judged by my Country, with some share of the partiality in which they originated.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't know about you, but on my first read of this I found myself doubling back multiple times per sentence. Should I be embarrassed by this? Am I outing myself as a philistine? To me, these sentences look better suited for sentence diagramming exercises than a speech. I am not sure if I would be able to follow this speech if I heard it recited.</p>
      <p>Notice how none of the vocabulary is particularly difficult for readers today. The meanings of the words he uses haven't changed much. Nor is the content conceptually difficult. All the difficulty for me lies in the syntax, and in particular the long subordinate clauses that make you forget what the main subject or verb is.</p>
      <p>For comparison, Obama:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>My fellow citizens: I stand here today humbled by the task before us, grateful for the trust you've bestowed, mindful of the sacrifices borne by our ancestors.   </p>
        <p>I thank President Bush for his service to our nation -- (applause) -- as well as the generosity and cooperation he has shown throughout this transition.  </p>
        <p>Forty-four Americans have now taken the presidential oath.  The words have been spoken during rising tides of prosperity and the still waters of peace.  Yet, every so often, the oath is taken amidst gathering clouds and raging storms.  At these moments, America has carried on not simply because of the skill or vision of those in high office, but because we, the people, have remained faithful to the ideals of our forebears and true to our founding documents.   </p>
        <p>So it has been; so it must be with this generation of Americans.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Or George W. Bush:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>President Clinton, distinguished guests and my fellow citizens, the peaceful transfer of authority is rare in history, yet common in our country. With a simple oath, we affirm old traditions and make new beginnings.  </p>
        <p>As I begin, I thank President Clinton for his service to our nation.  </p>
        <p>And I thank Vice President Gore for a contest conducted with spirit and ended with grace.  </p>
        <p>I am honored and humbled to stand here, where so many of America's leaders have come before me, and so many will follow.  </p>
        <p>We have a place, all of us, in a long story--a story we continue, but whose end we will not see. It is the story of a new world that became a friend and liberator of the old, a story of a slave-holding society that became a servant of freedom, the story of a power that went into the world to protect but not possess, to defend but not to conquer.  </p>
        <p>It is the American story--a story of flawed and fallible people, united across the generations by grand and enduring ideals. ...</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The difference in readability is hilarious.</p>
      <p>Now I'm not saying that everything from the 18th century reads like Washington's speech. I checked out some other speeches, and some of them are not quite so bad. Nor are these two excerpts directly comparable; for one, Washington is speaking to a small group of elites, while Obama and Bush are addressing millions. But I don't think <em>anyone</em> talks in sentences like Washington's anymore today, not even in the snootiest, most rarefied circles. I don't remember any of my professors talking like that.</p>
      <p>Well, OK, we do sometimes find similarly complex sentence structure in academia. Here's Judith Butler:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The move from a structuralist account in which capital is understood to structure social relations in relatively homologous ways to a view of hegemony in which power relations are subject to repetition, convergence, and rearticulation brought the question of temporality into the thinking of structure, and marked a shift from a form of Althusserian theory that takes structural totalities as theoretical objects to one in which the insights into the contingent possibility of structure inaugurate a renewed conception of hegemony as bound up with the contingent sites and strategies of the rearticulation of power.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>But today, this is the type of sentence that wins first prize in a <a href="http://www.denisdutton.com/bad_writing.htm">bad writing contest</a>. <em>And</em> it's from a scholarly journal rather than a speech, so your eyes get to double back as much as they need to. <em>And</em> it's mainly difficult because of the content; I have no idea what she's saying, but I actually find the syntax a little bit easier to parse than Washington's.</p>
      <p>My opinion is that the straightforward, concise style most authors use today is strictly better than what came before. But style aside, there is still the question of the sophistication demanded of readers and listeners in centuries past. Did educated people back then somehow train their brains to be better at parsing convoluted sentences than we are today? And should we mourn this loss of verbal sophistication? Or should we be glad that less of our brainpower is wasted on untangling relative clauses?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>