<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-09-21T13:52:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g63ohw2/</link>
  <title>Nathan Robinson is Mencius Moldbug and Should Not Be Taken Seriously</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Below, <a href="/u/UAnchovy">/u/UAnchovy</a> posts <a href="https://www.currentaffairs.org/2020/09/we-dont-know-our-potential">a piece from Nathan Robinson</a> responding to Freddie deBoer's <em>The Cult of Smart</em>. I have my own response to the book sitting on the shelf, because I was disappointed with a book I thought I'd love but can't quite figure out how to critique it well when I know so many others (see: Robinson) will critique it awfully. Still, seeing that has spurred me into action towards a related thesis, one I can credit to <a href="/u/UAnchovy">/u/UAnchovy</a> directly for one line of his:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Despite being a piece of almost Moldbuggian longwindedness...</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Here is my thesis: Nathan Robinson is Mencius Moldbug, and you should take neither seriously.</p>
      <p>The Gish Gallop, an overwhelming flood of arguments impossible to respond to, is a well-known technique of dishonest rhetoricians. I mention it because what I observe in both Robinson and Moldbug is <em>not</em> that, but it's a neighbor. Rather than overwhelming you with a flood of different arguments, they overwhelm you with a flood of empty words in service of a single argument, making their cases in such drawn-out length that almost nobody has the patience or time to respond in kind. Their goal is less to convey an argument, more to convey a <em>tone</em> in the trappings of one. Even if they say thirty outrageous things in the process of constructing their pieces, people who support their theses can find comfort and agreement in the overall piece.</p>
      <p>Fortunately and unsurprisingly, there is a parallel to all of this within my own sphere: religious apologetics. Allow me to introduce you all to <em>FAIRMormon - Faithful Answers to Criticisms of The Church of Jesus Christ</em>, and in particular, one article: <a href="https://www.fairmormon.org/conference/august-2006/book-of-abraham-201-papyri-revelation-and-modern-egyptology">Book of Abraham 201</a>. The Book of Abraham, for those of you who bizarrely aren't in tune with the ins and outs of a minor Christian restorationist movement, is one of the most immediately damning pieces of evidence against Mormonism. In his heyday, Joseph Smith bought some Egyptian papyri and claimed to have discovered a new work of scripture on them, penned by Abraham. He "translated" them and annotated the attached facsimiles, providing detailed descriptions of what the whole thing meant.</p>
      <p>Much of the papyrus he worked from remains extant. It is not, alas, penned by Abraham. Rather, it contains a copy of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Books_of_Breathing">Books of Breathing</a> and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Book_of_the_Dead">Book of the Dead</a>. The facsimiles Smith annotated have <a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-kOFfnl7r76c/VGrHkNVhoMI/AAAAAAAAVCA/3SBKvNrJsqY/s1600/BoA%2BFacsimile%2B1.png">since</a> been, ah, reinterpreted slightly. All of this is simple and takes a few sentences to explain. You know what's not simple? Explaining how the Book of Abraham is still a divinely inspired work. In come the apologists, with their 6,000 word text including 31 citations, to do just that. I won't dive into the muck of the object-level claims here, because it's exhausting and wasting people's time with that is how they win. The aim is not to get you to think about the issue. The aim is to assure you that <em>someone else—someone smart and trustworthy—has done the thinking for you, and come out with a coherent worldview on the other end.</em></p>
      <p>
        <em>That</em> is precisely what I see when I read Moldbug, and precisely what I see in Robinson's 20,000-word beast. Except <em>this</em> time, I'm happy to engage on the object level. Not with the whole piece. <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/03/10/response-to-current-affairs-on-against-murderism/">He doesn't deserve that</a>. Instead, I'd like to zoom in on the <em>3,000 words</em> Robinson devotes to picking apart a single deBoer anecdote at the start of Section III. If you'd like to follow along at home, <a href="https://pastebin.com/Wj8g0hau">I've slapped the relevant section into Pastebin</a>. </p>
      <p>First: What is the argument deBoer makes that Robinson wants to refute? Again, it's pretty simple: people innately differ in their cognitive aptitude. This is something obvious to me first at the age of six, when I noticed two (white, middle-class) students in my class who were always far behind the rest of the class, when my teacher asked me to help, and when no matter what anyone did things stayed basically that way throughout our years together in elementary school. deBoer's point stayed so dramatically obvious to me throughout my time in school that I was startled to realize some, like Robinson, would dispute it. It's the sort of thing that takes a lot of education, I think, to become wrong about. </p>
      <p>Throughout his book, deBoer uses plenty of illustrative anecdotes and data. One comes early on, about a favorite student of his in an alternative school for children with severe emotional disturbance, who made enormous behavioral and social improvements but continued to struggle academically. "I just can't do it," deBoer recounts the tearful student saying about one bit of math they had been trying to drill for weeks on end, and deBoer, honest as he is, had to admit the student was essentially right, and that it was simply cruel to pretend all he was lacking was a bit of hard work in the right structure. It's a powerful, troubling anecdote, one that illustrates both deBoer's personal experience with the issue, his stake in it, and his compassion towards those he writes about. </p>
      <p>So of course, when Robinson moves in on the attack, he doesn't use that anecdote. Instead, he picks another time when deBoer talks about weed-out courses in engineeering programs, and he laments the cold cruelty it takes—like justifying sweatshops or nukes!—to insist that a class that makes students cry and drop out is a good idea. He talks about how we cannot possibly know someone is incapable of something until we've structured everything in society to enable their success and they still fail. He illustrates his point with an anecdote of a student of his own, black and from a working-class background, who turned in brilliant papers when she did the work but who was often discounted because she was "disorganized, chaotic, and [had a] chronic inability to get the assignments in on time." And so she struggled in most classes, faced with "an institution too screwed up to nurture one of its most promising students."</p>
      <p>Pause. Do you see what he did? If you see what I see in that paragraph, you know exactly why I am screaming through my screen at Robinson right now.</p>
      <p>Like a true shell-game expert, Robinson has deftly substituted conscientiousness (disorganized? chaotic? chronic inability to get assignments in? <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conscientiousness">where have I heard that before?</a>) for intelligence, noticed a system poorly built to handle a student <em>he himself</em> describes as more intelligent than most in his class, and concluded that because of that, we cannot draw inferences about differences in innate cognitive aptitude. He goes on for a while more imagining variants after which we might finally be able to conclude something about someone's true potential. In a breath, he's acknowledged that he sees ability differences in his group, but because he sees brilliant people fail out for factors unrelated to intelligence, concludes we can't understand anything about innate differences in intelligence. </p>
      <p>A word of advice from someone with the same affliction you notice in your brilliant student, Nathan, though without the working-class credentials I expect would inspire you to care much about my fate: <strong>You're not helping.</strong> I have a tremendous personal stake in figuring out how institutions can better address the challenges of low conscientiousness, and a hefty stake in understanding how to address the challenges of other low dice-rolls as well. But that starts from a correct understanding of things as they are, and Robinson spends thousands of words talking around that reality and obscuring it. It's not out of lack of ability to understand it, but out of an apathy towards any explanation that doesn't flatter his preexisting beliefs.</p>
      <p>Later, Robinson sneeringly confronts deBoer's point that we have tried and failed to overcome gaps using extraordinary methods:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Please tell me about the time when education itself was completely equalized, thereby exposing the outcomes in differences that must be immutable aspects of a student’s inner soul. I would love to hear about that failed era in American history when the socialists took over and transformed everything so that it was no longer built to prepare students to be obedient handmaidens of capitalism but rather gave them every tool they needed to succeed. I would like to hear about the engineering program that did everything it could to avoid incorporating “making people cry themselves to sleep and contemplate suicide” as part of the curriculum, but ultimately concluded such a program was incompatible with Human Nature. Do tell me of it.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Here's my contention: <em>Robinson does not want to know the answer to this question.</em> He doesn't care a speck about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Follow_Through_(project)">Project Follow-Through</a>, or <a href="https://www.cato.org/publications/policy-analysis/money-school-performance-lessons-kansas-city-desegregation-experiment">the Kansas City School experiment</a> (which, anyway, libertarians are writing about so it can't be trusted), or unschooling and Montessori schools or detracking or the thousands of other initiatives we have tried and so often failed with in education. "Why don't you just try?" cries Robinson from a distance, as endless waves of people invested in the sphere do just that, before being forgotten by the Nathan Robinsons of the world so they can cry for resurrection once more.</p>
      <p>[1/2]</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>