<post>
  <author>wemptronics</author>
  <date>2020-09-17T18:59:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iseo9j/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_14/g5m92jt/</link>
  <title>Analyzing the Correlation Between Anti-Police Protests and Violence</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <strong>"And, as arrests declined, shootings increased—the straightforward and expected cause-and-effect."</strong>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>A month ago people were wondering when we would get studies that look at the correlation between mass anti-police protests and violence. Paul G. Cassell, a former judge, has authored <a href="https://archive.is/PnSPU">a short article that does just this</a> pulling from <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3690473">his paper and legal study.</a> I'll try to highlight what I think is interesting and try my best to summarize its content. Apologies if this turns out to be long. For some wider context <a href="https://i.imgur.com/cXMdmzA.png">this</a> is what the number of US homicides looks like over the past 30 years.</p>
      <p>From the article:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The homicide spikes began in late May. Before May 28, Chicago had almost the same number of homicides as in 2019. Then, on May 31, 18 people were murdered in Chicago—the city’s most violent day in six decades. Violence continued through the summer. July was Chicago’s most violent month in 28 years. As of Sept. 1, murder is up 52% for the year, according to Chicago Police Department data. My recent research quantifies the size of this summer’s <strong>Minneapolis Effect</strong>, estimating that <strong>reduced proactive policing resulted in about 710 more homicides and 2,800 more shootings in June and July alone</strong>. The victims of these crimes are disproportionately African-American and Hispanic, often living in disadvantaged and low-income neighborhoods.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>From the paper:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In the wake of the anti-police protests  surrounding George  Floyd’s death, less  policing has  occurred  for  various  reasons.  And even after protests began to wane, police have pulled back from some kinds of proactive policing—that is, self-initiated policing methods designed to reduce crime by using preventive strategies, such as street stops or anti-gun patrols. These reductions have resulted from the protests or other attacks on police, as police have (for various reasons) pulled back from aggressive efforts to combat gun crimes. Likewise, law enforcement capabilities have been diminished by  reduced  funding  and  other  setbacks  (such  as  increased  retirements  due  to  demoralization).</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Cassell calls the increase in homicides "remarkable, suddenly-appearing, and widespread in cities across the country... <strong>At this rate, 2020 will easily be the deadliest year for gun-related homicides since at least 1999,</strong> all the while other major crimes are trending stable or slightly downward." The last part is important. Homicides, aggravated assaults, and shootings have increased while things like petty theft and lesser violent crime have not.  He calls this trend the "Minneapolis Effect" which follows the 2014-2016 "Ferguson Effect."</p>
      <p>Homicides were on a slight decline or holding steady through the first quarter of 2020. Even well into lockdowns and unemployment, as some petty crimes saw decreases, homicides seemed unmoved. It wasn't until the last week of May, the same week the Floyd protests started, that the homicide spikes began. A nationwide 37% increase in homicides. The 105 murders in Chicago that have been reported elsewhere account for a <em>139% increase</em> from the previous year. The city's most violent month in 28 years. Homicides have increased <a href="https://i.imgur.com/T9J85Sz.png">across most of America's largest cities</a>. Dallas, which claims a general 2% decrease in homicides over the year, had homicides double (from 12 to 25) in the month of July compared to 2019. The spike in violence was was not a slow boiling frog that saw numbers of homicides increase as more and more people lost their jobs. It was sudden. Abrupt. Like a kettle blew its lid through the roof of the house and we still haven't seen where its landed. </p>
      <p>Here are the four statements of fact someone has to account for when explaining this homicide spike:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>(1) homicide and shooting crimes have suddenly and sharply increased across the country; </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>(2) other crime categories have remained generally stable;</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>(3) the spikes began in the last  week  of  May;  and  </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>(4)  the homicide  and  shooting  increases  are apparently urban,  not  rural, phenomena.  </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>"Minneapolis  Effect—i.e., reduced  proactive  policing  and  other de-policing—explains these four facts better than any other possibility."</p>
      <p>We don't see a similar spike in smaller American cities or rural areas. It's true that homicides are typically a major urban area thing to begin with. However, more rural areas were not immune to lockdown measures, mass unemployment, and COVID related problems. Most of these homicides occurred away from active demonstrations. The homicide spike appears in cities (Jacksonville, Austin, San Antonio, Phoenix, Los Angeles) where seasonal crime trends tend to have a smaller effect. Unemployment doesn't <a href="https://i.imgur.com/DiLw8yk.png">line up</a> with our spike. COVID lock down measures, unemployment, etc has an obvious effect on society -- while COVID's effect on crime is not fully understood --but it does not appear to be the cause of the spike. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <strong>"Every time we have to drain our resources for protests, the people on the West Side and the South Side suffer."</strong> - Chicago Police Superintendent, July 2020</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>We have to establish that policing has actually changed. </p>
      <p>"In a class-action lawsuit filed against the city in late July, a group of neighborhood residents in a high-crime area alleged that it had been deprived of adequate policing, and regularly were told to call 311..." Cassell goes no further in speculating on the political calculations with regards to MPD or the city leadership. What he does do is <a href="https://i.imgur.com/bfS4uon.png">show</a> via metrics that <a href="https://i.imgur.com/fmCJukB.png">policing actions</a> were on a downward slope just as homicides were sharply trending up. 911 calls were usually answered, but dispatch could/would not send patrol vehicles to crime scenes during the unrest. "This qualitative information does not suggest that Minneapolis residents were declining to call the police." The <a href="https://i.imgur.com/TDTZKh0.png">frequency of calls to MPD</a>, including that of the 3rd precinct where Floyd was killed, does not show a drastic decrease.</p>
      <p>The same sort of things can be said of the other cities studied. <a href="https://chicago.suntimes.com/politics/2020/6/30/21308935/chicago-police-activity-slowed-june-murder-rise-fop-union-blames-morale-john-catanzara">Chicago</a> experienced a decline in typical policing as well. <em>"For example, during June 1 through 28, traffic stops dropped by 86%, street stops by 74%,97 and arrests by 55% compared to the same period in 2019. And murders were up in Chicago by a staggering 83% compared to the same period one year earlier."</em> Compounding factors in Chicago include police are retiring at twice the rate of previous years and a city government that has implemented "more generous" release procedures for criminals charged with violent crime.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <strong>"By the end of June, a total of 205 shootings occurred New York City, making it was the bloodiest June in the city in 24 years. July was even worse, with 244 shootings—a 177% increase over the previous year. New York City had become the “City of Bullets.”</strong>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The graph of <a href="https://i.imgur.com/ubLiyHu.png">NYC arrests</a> versus its homicide spike seems almost too convenient. Arrests were low as NYC experienced the height of the pandemic's delerious effects, but steadily climbed upwards. Now look again at <a href="https://i.imgur.com/3iHtz1I.png">NYC's homicides.</a> At first I thought Cassell had glossed over the April spike, because it hadn't suited his narrative. Now I can see it. NYC experienced the highest homicide spikes when arrests were at their lowest. </p>
      <p>Nobody has completely broken down what explains the decrease in proactive policing. One example he points at is the introduction of chokehold bills. Another is stop-and-frisk. Like Minneapolis, 911 calls to the NYPD haven't been significantly affected throughout the pandemic. Including the spike in homicides. Political pressure on police departments, fed by media scrutiny, from their own city governments has left them feeling politically isolated. Maybe a perfect professional should not need the support from city leadership to effectively police a neighborhood, but uncertainty breeds doubt. The abandonment of police departments has led to a broken morale and the destruction of confidence in doing their jobs. A complete rout it seems.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"It is important to understand  that this article is not implistically arguing that protests-produce-homicides. Instead, the argument here is that <a href="https://i.imgur.com/zBRb8Ae.png">the protests served as a trigger for de-policing..."</a></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Again, Cassell emphasizes that, while he believes the Minneapolis Effect to be real, it does not address the dozens of other factors at large. For example, there are reasons municipalities are attacking policies that encourage proactive policing like stop-and-frisk. Secondly, it hasn't been long enough to accrue the relevant data during this time period. This is more like a preliminary step. However, he begs criminal justice researchers to make understanding this effect "the top priority." </p>
      <p>I feel like the media is more complicit in this than they get credit for, but I don't suppose that's for a CJ researcher to find out.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>