<post>
  <author>Denswend</author>
  <date>2021-05-19T16:45:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ne8ggb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_17_2021/gyps622/</link>
  <title>The Yugoslav Wars of 1990s</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>In short, ethnic spoils and tensions.</p>
      <p>In long, well, ethnic spoils and tensions but with history!</p>
      <hr />
      <p>There are couple of countries in Yugoslavia that comprised it - Slovenia, Croatia, Serbia, Montenegro, Macedonia, Albania, Kosovo. Albania and Kosovo are the same with respect to ethnicity and so are Serbia and Montenegro - up until a while ago they were one country aptly named Serbia&amp;Montenegro. Slovenia and Macedonia are the most unique, in a language sense - Serbs and Croats understand each other (heck, I can understand Serbian language better than some obscure Dalmatian dialects) pretty well. Keeping with the thesis of narcissism of small differences, the crux of conflict were Serbs and Croats, with other countries being there. Slovenes and Macedonians just declared independence and rest of countries were basically "oh, okay I guess". And the crux of the Serb-Croat conflict goes back to (ethnic) tensions persisting in socialist Yugoslavia, which goes back to (ethnic) tensions persisting during the World War 2 (but not really), which go back to ethnic tensions during the Kingdom of Yugoslavia, which go back to (IMO) abject failures of Croat nationalists during the pre-WWI era. There's a bit of Islam peppered into the story, in a way that a modern person (whose exposures to Islam are confined to MENA ethnicities in Western countries) might find very weird. So to begin the story:</p>
      <p>(For the first part of the story, when I say nationalist, think leftist)
The crown of Croatian kingdom was held by Hungarian king, formal title was the "Lands of the Crown of Saint Steven (Istvan for Hungarians, Stjepan for Croats)", and Hungarian king was also the emperor of Austria, in a quite a mixture called Habsburg monarchy or Austria-Hungary, or something like that. The point was that Croatian statehood, which existed in personal union with Hungary was never in question, just its sovereignity (therefore its statehood). The status of Croats under Hungarians was...mixed to say the least, on one hand you had Magyarization (Magyar is what Hungarians call themselves) and oppressive ban (Croatian viceroy) Khuen Hedervary  and on the other hand you had Croat national hero Josip Jelacic break a couple of Hungarian nationalist. Personally, Croatia only prospered under Habsburg rule, and desecration of Austrian Empire, the monarchy in general, was one of the worst moments in Croat history - may Woodrow Wilson burn in hell for it. During this era, three factions of Croat nationalism were born. First one was Illyrians, who sought to manufacture ethnic unity of Croats in Austria Hungary, then ethnic unity of all South Slavs under the moniker of Illyria which was an ancient Roman (and pre-Roman) province. Frankly,  this makes as much of sense as all black people in USA trying to unite under one banner, only to attempt to unify with all black people in Canada, ... and call themselves Cherokee. From Illyrianism, or even opposed to it, came Yugoslavism which would unify all South Slavs  (Jug meaning South, and written Yugo for the leetspeek cred). Ironically, founder of Yugoslavist strain of thought was a bishop, who wanted a Yugoslav Monarchy - and the irony is double because Kingdom of Yugoslavia was horrible, and subsequent Yugoslavia was a socialist state. The third strain, was the one of Ante Starcevic, also known as "Father of the Nation". It's basically bog standard liberal-nationalist version - you have a state, preferably democratic ("not a republic, but parliamentary monarchy" wink wink) of all Croats, separation of Church and State, etc. His phrase "Bog i Hrvati" (God and Croats) was a leftist proclamation that meant that there is no intermediary between God and Croats - it was later coopted by Croatian nationalist (now think right wing). Oh and he considered Slovenes and Serbs to be Croats in denial (the denial of ethnic identity will be a major plot point), with Muslim Croats being the most ethnically "pure" Croats.</p>
      <p>(After World War I)</p>
      <p>After the WWI, after the criminal Woodrow Wilson dissolved Habsburg Monarchy, the South Slav countries were shoved into State of Slovenes, Serbs, and Croats. This State was then merged with Kingdom of Serbia to form <em>Kingdom</em> of Slovenes, Serbs, and Croats. Peasant Party of Croatia opposed such a move. The head of Peasant Party of Croatia was assassinated by member of Serbian Radical Party - the assassin enjoyed luxurious house arrest with three servants (until Yugoslavian communists executed him). King of Yugoslavia then used this as a pretext to abolish the constitution and form a dictatorship. This soured the relations of Croats and led to the formation of Ustashe, which were still nationalists opposed to monarchy so still leftwing. More on them later.</p>
      <p>(WW2)</p>
      <p>WW2 in Balkans is one of the most confusing events, because so many things just defies common sense, and really subverts you expectations. 
It's very well understand that Hitler's scientific racism (ethnicism?) was more or less post hoc rationalizations. When Kingdom of Yugoslavia rebuffed him for alliance (in a stroke of either brilliance or arrogant stupidity), he hastily fixed "Serbs are actually wandering Goth tribe" to "Croats" and he offered Ustashas a puppet state called Independent State of Croatia (NDH). But Croatia has Dalmatia, which Italians wanted, and NDH ceded its rich provinces to Fascist Italy. This, plus a lot of Ustasha mismanagment and cruelty, plus a nascent Communist movement, really soured NDH. Frankly, as someone who is both nationalist adjacent and has sympathies for fascism, NDH was a failure of an ethnic state, failure of an ideological state, and any who unironically support NDH today (which due to Yugoslav Wars, are not that uncommon) are simply retarded. And as someone who is more opposed to communism than fascism, I must admit Yugoslavian communism of 1940s did more to advance nationalist self-determination (as well as add certain parts of Italy). Really bizarre.</p>
      <p>In opposition to NDH, both as a fascist creation (that it failed to embody the fascist principle of autarky doesn't make it non-fascist) and horrors of vengeful Croat fascists (now we come to a point where if you hear nationalist, think fascist), Communist movement (partisans) was created with the express goal of "liberation". Now Serbian fascists (Chetniks) who were de facto resistance to Ustashas, became only de jure resistance, only to be supplanted wholly by Communists after the Allies started negotiating with Tito. Failure of Ustashas to deal with Partisans, or Partisan's tenacity, led to Ustashas (Croat fascists) and Chetniks (Serbian fascists) living in a de facto alliance. The situation became extremely bizarre - imagine if the more extreme of Israel's population made an alliance with Hamas in order to root out joint Israel-Hamas Communist movement. How do different auth-rights coexist? Not very well. You can find memos by Chetniks to daddy Nazis complaining that Ustashas are mocking them ("showing their tongues") and may Uncle Adolf please spank them because we're all in this together. On the other side, it would be customary for one side to commit atrocities towards people of the other side, instead of actually armies of the other side, in a form of impotent and cowardly display of nationalism. My own great grandfather was gang pressed into Ustashe, and when Chetniks massacred his village Ustashas refused to go after them. He then switched sides to Partisans, who did.</p>
      <p>The story basically ends here. Yugoslavia remains the only country to liberate itself during the WWII. And if you support the NDH (in other words, you're clinically retarded), NDH remains the last European Axis power never to surrender.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>