<post>
  <author>ChevalMalFet</author>
  <date>2020-03-25T02:03:26Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fo3q5e/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_three/flfajud/</link>
  <title>The Underplayed US Contribution to World War I</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I just want to jump off here to talk a bit about the US's role in WW1. It's barely talked about these days in school, and of course other countries don't particular care to mention the US's contribution, with the result that lots of people have the impression that you do, that the US was barely involved. However, at the time, the Great War was a very much a Big Deal in the US.</p>
      <p>First, before the US entered, the war was more or less The Issue of the day. Who should we support, if anyone? Was it ethical to sell arms to both sides? What about neutral shipping - did we have the right to sail to Germany, or to sail to Britain with no U-boat interference? Mexico was in a state of tumultuous civil war at the time, too - would both of our nations be drawn into the conflict as part of the larger war (like Germany sorta tried to do)? And of course, the 1916 election turned entirely on whether or not we would be drawn into war in Europe. </p>
      <p>Furthermore, economically, we were inextricably tied to the Allies. While it wasn't to the same Arsenal of Democracy degree as WWII, a significant fraction - I've even heard a majority - of the Allies' ammunition came from American factories. Remember that WWI is a war primarily fought with artillery - shells are the <em>most</em> important weapon of war. Without American support, the Allies would have lost a significant edge even if the doughboys never crossed the Atlantic. </p>
      <p>Then, during the phase of direct American involvement, the US contribution was more significant than simply being in at the kill. US troops started showing up in 1917, just as most nations were running out of manpower. Smaller nations like Serbia and Rumania fell in 1915 and 1916, but by 1917 we see the big boys start to tap out - most notably, Russia. By the time America can deploy large formations in 1918, nations like Italy, Austria-Hungary, and the Ottomans are spent. Britain and France are at the end of their rope. But, crucially, <em>not</em> Germany - not yet. </p>
      <p>It seems almost forgotten now, but the Germans came <em>very</em> close to winning World War One in the spring of 1918. Having knocked out most of their enemies on the other fronts (Russia and Italy, mostly), they concentrated their last reserves and went for a knockout blow in the West in a series of offensives that ripped the front wide open. For the first time since 1914, everyone was <em>moving</em> again, and once again the Germans started to draw near to Paris. </p>
      <p>It was American troops and replacements - alongside the still stubborn and brave French and British veterans, of course - that blunted the offensive and gradually wore the Germans down over the summer. Then, in the Hundred Days offensive, while the US's relatively green troops didn't make the impressive gains that the BEF did, they <em>did</em> tie down a significant amount of Germans in a crucial sector of the front, and were gaining significant ground in doing so. </p>
      <p>At home, the war was huge. Remember, this was our first major war in 50 years, and it was our first major overseas commitment <em>ever</em>. It was a far more active and involved role than the country had ever had outside the Western Hemisphere before, and it was all anyone in the country talked about. This is when German families are supposed to have changed their names to avoid prejudice. People who spoke against the war - famously Eugene V. Debs - were thrown in prison. Domestically, it was a lot like the COVID19 situation today - the only thing in the newspapers, every day, every person doing their part for victory. Rationing, government bonds, the works. And yeah, a significant number of US troops died in the process.</p>
      <p>Did the US win the Great War singlehandedly? No, that's not what I'm saying. What I <em>am</em> saying is that its contribution was far more than token, and that it played a key, perhaps even decisive, role in determining the final outcome. </p>
      <p>None of this, of course, answers the initial question of how much economic damage was wrought on the US by the war. Answer - well, not much, to be honest. The US made a killing (no pun intended) selling weapons and ammunition, food, and other essential supplies - mostly to the Allies due to the Royal Navy. In fact, some historians (regrettably my books are in the United States and I am not, so I can't cite this for you) have claimed that without US artillery shells the French army would have run out of ammunition. At home, lots of Americans decried war profiteering and insinuated that the whole conflict was a conspiracy to make a few men rich at the cost of millions of lives, and that America was only getting involved to make the world safe for business, not democracy. </p>
      <p>Now, <em>after</em> the war, in 1920-1921, there was a pretty major recession right as Harding took office. It's mostly forgotten now, because we bounced right back into the Roaring Twenties, but the initial shocks were as bad as the 1929 crash. How much was the usual post-war bust? How much was the aftermath of the great influenza? Hard to say.</p>
      <p>So yeah, that was a lot of words to answer the question "But does anyone have a good explanation of the cultural or economic impact of the flu?" with a big shrug.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>