<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2020-03-25T08:07:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fneib4/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_23_2020/flfz5ar/</link>
  <title>Boys' Struggle in the Modern School</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I hate this comment. It features grains of truth, but uses it to overexplain everything. Sure, men and women are different, but they aren't aliens from each other. There's a lot of overlap between them.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>When I make statements like "men are taller than women," it's generally understood that I'm speaking about the populations' aggregate, and that I'm not saying that Danny Devito is taller than Aisha Tyler.  Short men exist, and so do tall women. Likewise, male teacher's pets exist, and so do rebellious girls, but the fact remains that girls are more likely to get good grades in high school, more likely to go to college, and more likely to earn graduate degrees.   If you feel like the assumption that I'm talking about aggregates of populations is not sufficiently embedded in any statements about groups, then pretend I said "on average" preceding every mention of "men" or "women" or "boys" or "girls."</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Besides, men are also great at following instructions. We don't have a military full of people blazing their own paths and not listening to instructions. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <em>Some</em> men, certainly.  But when it comes to following instructions like "don't rob liquor stores" or "don't murder people," men are more likely to violate the instructions than women.  (Of course, <del>it need not be said that</del> not all men are violent criminals, but the fact remains that <a href="https://www.statista.com/chart/11573/gender-of-inmates-in-us-federal-prisons-and-general-population/">93% of federal inmates are men</a>, and while you could argue that the criminal justice system discriminates against men, few people would dispute the fact that men are more likely to violate society's prohibitions against violence.  Does it seem unfair to make an argument about men's propensity for rule-breaking by focusing on a tiny portion of the population?  Well, "incarcerated people" represent a larger population than "active duty military," so men's propensity for violent crime seems at least as germane to the discussion to the discussion as men's inclination toward military service.)</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>As for schools, sure, maybe boys get the short stick now. I wouldn't know as I haven't been in school for quite some time. However, it can't be as bad as the what I've seen on many manosphere or alt-right places online. To them the schoolmarm/school is a cartoonish villain who delights in emotionally and mentally castrating boys daily. This depiction reminds me of the feminists versions of neckbeards or communists talking about capitalists. A ridiculous cartoon that has little resemblance to reality.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>If you really believe that "it can't be as bad as all that," I encourage you to read this post in the Washingtonian titled <a href="https://www.washingtonian.com/2019/05/05/what-happened-after-my-13-year-old-son-joined-the-alt-right/">"What Happened After My 13-Year-Old Son Joined the Alt-Right"</a>.  The fact that the story ends with the son joining, and later renouncing, the alt-right is less relevant here than what precipitated his descent into the rabbithole, which the author of the piece describes as kafkaesque:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>One morning during first period, a male friend of Sam’s mentioned a meme whose suggestive name was an inside joke between the two of them. Sam laughed. A girl at the table overheard their private conversation, misconstrued it as a sexual reference, and reported it as sexual harassment. Sam’s guidance counselor pulled him out of his next class and accused him of “breaking the law.” Before long, he was in the office of a male administrator who informed him that the exchange was “illegal,” hinted that the police were coming, and delivered him into the custody of the school’s resource officer. At the administrator’s instruction, that man ushered Sam into an empty room, handed him a blank sheet of paper, and instructed him to write a “statement of guilt.”</p>
        <p>No one called me as this unfolded, even though Sam cried for about six hours straight as staff members parked him in vacant offices to keep him away from other students. When he stepped off the bus that afternoon and I asked why his eyes were so swollen, he informed me that he would probably be suspended, but possibly also expelled and arrested.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The story ends not with the administrators being reprimanded or sued, but with the boy being taken out of school and enrolled at a different one; to that extent, this story represents a new kind of "normal."  (Which is to say, this story isn't <em>abnormal</em> enough to trigger some kind of lawsuit or media pressure against the school to get them to change: not all schools are like this, but when they <em>are</em> like this, society accepts it, at the expense of the boys who attend those schools.)  This is something that is widely discussed in the "manosphere or alt-right places online" that you allude to, but discussion of it is hardly absent from mainstream discourse; you'll find editorials along these lines in publications as mainstream as the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/parenting/wp/2015/02/19/why-schools-are-failing-our-boys/">Washington Post</a>.  See also: <a href="https://www.esquire.com/news-politics/a32858/drugging-of-the-american-boy-0414/">The Drugging of the American Boy</a>.  Nearly 20% of American boys are prescribed with ADHD; millions of them are pumped with Ritalin and Adderall, largely due to the demands of the modern teaching environment.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>