<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2020-03-21T20:19:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fjfnxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_16_2020/fl4utc0/</link>
  <title>Why Republicans Embrace Trump: He Punches Back</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think a good comparison to Trump might actually be Mitt Romney.  Despite the two of them being completely different in temperament and routinely butting heads in the last 4 years, the mainstream media campaign against Mitt Romney in 2012 resembled the one against Trump in 2016.  He was a rich businessman who was out of touch with common American voters.   He was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binders_full_of_women">sexist</a> who <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2012/10/binders-full-of-women-a-meme-that-means-something/263740/">said sexist things</a> and was on the losing side of a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-fix/post/a-war-on-women-trap-for-mitt-romney/2012/04/11/gIQAtym2AT_blog.html">war on women</a>.  His campaign was <a href="https://politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com/2012/07/31/romney-aide-loses-cool-curses-at-press-in-poland/">crass and disrespectful to vaunted media institutions</a>.  MSNBC's Lawrence O'Donnell described him as a <a href="https://twitter.com/Bmac0507/status/1225215821414166528">"uniquely immoral"</a> draft dodger.  O'Donnell also claimed that Romney <a href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2172593/Mitt-Romney-deliberately-got-booed-NAACP-appeal-white-racists.html">'deliberately got booed by the NAACP to appeal to white racists'</a>, and Chris Matthews also claimed that Mitt Romney was similarly making racist dog-whistles when talking about Obama's work on changing welfare work requirements, saying,  "You can play your games and giggle about it, but the fact is your side is playing that card. When you start talking about work requirements, we know what game you’re playing, and everybody knows what game you’re playing, it’s a race card." (Chris Matthews was very fond of the "<a href="https://grabien.com/story.php?id=598">any criticism of Obama coming from a republican is probably a racist attack</a>" line.)</p>
      <p>
        <strong>EDIT:</strong> How could I forget this episode: Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid accused Romney of being a tax cheat, which was a blatant falsehood, and didn't even attempt to offer a shred of evidence for his claim: "So the word's out that he hasn't paid any taxes for 10 years. Let him prove that he has paid taxes, because he hasn't."  Reid never made even the slightest attempt to substantiate his claim with even a shred of evidence, justifying his claim, "I don't think the burden should be on me. The burden should be on him. He's the one I've alleged has not paid any taxes. Why didn't he release his tax returns?" Romney actually did release his tax returns and showed that he had, in fact, paid $3 million in taxes in 2010, but the damage had already been done, something that Harry Reid got great satisfaction from when looking back on the results of 2012, suggesting that the truthfulness of his statement was irrelevant because, "<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZPYdNxYgxEA">Romney didn't win, did he</a>?"  (One possible response might be, "if you believe that your lie resulted in Romney losing the election, you should be ashamed, not proud.")  Remember, this unsubstantiated accusation that Romney had paid no taxes in 10 years did not come from some random renegade freshman congressman; this was the <em>senate majority leader</em> speaking <em>on the floor of the senate</em>, and somehow the media narrative that came out of this episode in 2012 wasn't "the democratic senate majority leader is a liar who says blatantly untrue things about his political opponents in order to cynically damage them during an election cycle," but rather that Mitt Romney was a very suspicious and probably evil business man who probably was figuring out some slimy underhanded way to pay less than he should on his taxes.  Romney was, in all things, guilty until proven innocent. <strong>&lt;/edit&gt;</strong></p>
      <p>In short, Mitt Romney was an evil sexist who was beloved by white supremacists and intentionally courted the support of white supremacists and was a tax cheat who wouldn't release his tax returns.  They ran that playbook against someone as milquetoast as Mitt Romney, and it seems almost certain that they would have run the same playbook against any republican running against Hillary Clinton.  Could any republican candidate have parried the media's attacks as well as Trump did?  If someone like Jeb or Rubio had to weather the same salvo, they probably would have done it in the same way Mitt Romney did, oscillating between indignant "Why, I <em>never</em>," or some kind of sniveling capitulation like "Look guys, I'm <em>sorry</em> I said that thing that <em>sounded</em> sexist, but you need to understand, I'm not <em>really</em> sexist.  I was <em>actually</em> trying to say that I think hiring women is important and in fact I go out of my way to collect resumes from qualified women, so many resumes that I can pack binders full of them." Trump's approach was exactly the opposite of the approach that Mitt Romney took in 2012: instead of trying to weather the storm with quiet dignity, or trying to prove his innocence, he counter-punched at every turn.  Here's how he handled it at one of the early debates:</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Moderator:</strong> You've called women you don't like fat pigs, dogs, slobs and disgusting animals. Your Twitter account...</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Trump:</strong> Only Rosie O'Donnell.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Moderator:</strong> No, it wasn't. Your Twitter account... (cut off by 10 seconds of sustained cheering and applause from the audience)</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Moderator:</strong> For the record, it was well beyond Rosie O'Donnell.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Trump:</strong> Yes, I'm sure it was.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Moderator:</strong>  Your Twitter account has several disparaging comments about women's looks. You once told a contestant on "Celebrity Apprentice" it would be a pretty picture to see her on her knees. Does that sound to you like the temperament of a man we should elect as president? And how will you answer the charge from Hillary Clinton, who is likely to be the Democratic nominee, that you are part of the war on women?</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Trump</strong>: I think the big problem in this country has is being politically correct. (Crowd cheers) I've been challenged by so many people and I don't frankly have time for total political correctness. And to be honest with you, this country doesn't have time either. This country is in big trouble. We don't win anymore. We lose to China. We lose to Mexico both in trade and at the border. We lose to everybody. And frankly, what I say and oftentimes it's fun, it's kidding. We have a good time. What I say is what I say.</p>
      <p>Trump was the first candidate to realize, "No amount of contrition will ever satisfy the media, so why bother even trying to apologize?"  The crowd at the GOP debate saw this and cheered loud and cheered hard, because they finally saw a candidate who was willing to counter-punch.</p>
      <p>I maintain that if you want to understand the mindset of an Evangelical Trump voter in 2016, you can find no better read than <a href="https://townhall.com/columnists/evansayet/2017/07/13/he-fights-n2354580">He Fights</a> by Evan Sayet.  (Here I'm not talking about literal Evangelicals, but the members of the "republican franchise" who turned their back on Jeb and Rubio to embrace MAGA.)</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>My Leftist friends (as well as many ardent #NeverTrumpers) constantly ask me if I’m not bothered by Donald Trump’s lack of decorum.  They ask if I don’t think his tweets are “beneath the dignity of the office.”  Here’s my answer:</p>
        <p>We Right-thinking people have tried dignity.  There could not have been a man of more quiet dignity than George W. Bush as he suffered the outrageous lies and politically motivated hatreds that undermined his presidency.  We tried statesmanship.  Could there be another human being on this earth who so desperately prized “collegiality” as John McCain?  We tried propriety – has there been a nicer human being ever than Mitt Romney?  And the results were always the same.</p>
        <p>...</p>
        <p>With Donald Trump, this all has come to an end.  Donald Trump is America’s first wartime president in the Culture War.</p>
        <p>During wartime, things like “dignity” and “collegiality” simply aren’t the most essential qualities one looks for in their warriors.  Ulysses Grant was a drunk whose behavior in peacetime might well have seen him drummed out of the Army for conduct unbecoming.  Had Abraham Lincoln applied the peacetime rules of propriety and booted Grant, the Democrats might well still be holding their slaves today.   Lincoln rightly recognized that, “I cannot spare this man.  He fights.” ...</p>
        <p>Trump is fighting.  And what’s particularly delicious is that, like Patton standing over the battlefield as his tanks obliterated Rommel’s, he’s shouting, “You magnificent bastards, I read your book!”  That is just the icing on the cake, but it’s wonderful to see that not only is Trump fighting, he’s defeating the Left using their own tactics.</p>
        <p>...</p>
        <p>So, to my friends on the Left – and the #NeverTrumpers as well -- do I wish we lived in a time when our president could be “collegial” and “dignified” and “proper”?  Of course I do.   These aren’t those times.  This is war.  And it’s a war that the Left has been fighting  without opposition for the past 50 years.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Whether you agree with the premise that Sayet lays out or agree with his arguments (which are laid out in greater detail in the <a href="https://townhall.com/columnists/evansayet/2017/07/13/he-fights-n2354580">full piece</a>), the fact is that in 2016, many republicans saw Trump as the first republican who was really willing to <em>punch back</em>, to "fight dirty" in the same way that they had perceived the left as doing for so long.   Trump activated something in the GOP base that had existed for years that no other major candidate was willing to touch.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>