<post>
  <author>Iconochasm</author>
  <date>2020-03-22T12:19:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fjfnxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_16_2020/fl6q223/</link>
  <title>When Obama and a Debate Moderator Incorrected Romney</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Been a few years, might have some of the details wrong.  </p>
      <p>Romney claimed that Obama waited two weeks to call Benghazi a terrorist attack.  Obama countered that he had called it one the next day "go check the transcript", and debate moderator Candy Crowly interjected to tell Romney that she very coincidentally just so happened to have a transcript of that random speech that was on no one's radar in front of her right then, and Obama was right.  Romney was hardcore flatfooted; you could argue that was the pivotal moment when Obama "came back" from his disastrous first debate performance.  Crowly later admitted that she was wrong, and should not have done that,</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/the-press-office/2012/09/12/remarks-president-deaths-us-embassy-staff-libya">Here</a> is the transcript of the speech.  The words "terrorism" and "terrorist" do not appear.  The phrase "acts of terror" is used, after a digression on the 9/11 WTC attack, and some generalized platitudes.  <a href="https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/blog/2012/09/12/president-obama-discusses-attack-benghazi-libya">Here</a> is the White House's own blog post about it, which downplays it even further.  In response to a reporter's question later that day, Obama explicitly said that it was too early to tell if it was terrorism (it wasn't, private discussions, like Hillary to Chelsea Clinton, fully acknowledged that it was a planned attack by an Al Queda splinter group).  But the video of <em>that</em> Q&amp;A mysteriously wasn't released until weeks later, in spite of being nakedly topical and newsworthy.</p>
      <p>And all of this is against the background that the Obama administration spent the two weeks after the attack insisting that it was a spontaneous demonstration against an Islamophobic youtube video that got out of hand.  Susan Rice told that fib on all the Sunday shows, Obama went to the UN to talk about how "the future must not belong to those who slander the Prophet of Islam".  Meanwhile every non-US media source was reporting it as an obvious terrorist attack.</p>
      <p>And then after continuing the lie became completely untenable, the administration flipped like a switch, and insisted that they had never lied about or covered up the situation at all... and the American media mostly just ran with it.  Even to the point of lying to cover for Obama during the second presidential debate.  </p>
      <p>On the general topic of understanding how Trump happened, I think this whole debacle was a key point.  From the perspective of the right, it neutered any criticisms about Trump lying; not only do their opponents not care about lying, they actively lie to support it!  If Trump is post-truth, he learned it from watching you!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>