<post>
  <author>Iron-And-Rust</author>
  <date>2020-03-21T22:22:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fmftdv/against_dog_ownership/fl5660s/</link>
  <title>Anti-Anti-Suffering</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's a particular flavour of madness especially prominent right now, that takes the idiotic naive positions that suffering is categorically bad, as if they don't realize that even the logical conclusion of that argument is that the absence of pleasure becomes indistinguishable from pain and so everything that can feel even just pleasure must be eradicated to escape degrees of pleasure.</p>
      <p>In parallel to that, we experience suffering to keep us alive; its existence, and acceptance of its existence, is necessary to live, and to accept life. Something that does not suffer does not live, at least not for very long. That something suffers is, categorically, not an argument for ending its life. Logically, the argument stops there. Since we cannot quantify pain or pleasure, we have no objective measures for when something should live and when it shouldn't, so we must remain agnostic.</p>
      <p>Practically, we are able to make educated guesses. If I looked the way that thing looks right now I'd probably want to die, so it probably wants to die. I still remember seeing videos of some chinese markets and how they treated their animals. Smaller animals skinned alive and discarded into a pile, their still-living heads raised in confusion to look around them. Bear cubs locked in cages that they outgrow, their malformed bodies squeezed in perpetual agony as their bile is harvested through an open wound. Even as one of those animals, not a human, I'd probably want to die in those situations, sooner rather than later. But even in such low-ambiguity situations, we still have to grapple with the question of improvement. Many of us have been in situations where we've wanted to die in the moment, but then the moment passed. Presumably, we do not regret having survived, and we do not now kill ourselves out of loyalty to our past self's desires. The same must surely apply to many other creatures that would want to die 'right now' (if it could conceptualize such a thought), but wouldn't if its situation changed.</p>
      <p>Even this is probably anthropomorphizing too much. Presumably, if an animal wants to die, insomuch as it can "want" anything beyond the urge present in its mind at any given time, it will just die. It will go lie over there, and refuse to move and eat, and then die (assuming it isn't being force-kept alive, as e.g., the aforementioned bear). If it isn't doing that, it probably "wants" to live, no matter how much <em>we</em> might not want to live in their position (though, who is the irrational one in that case? why is a desire to die induced by the narrator superior to a desire to live in its absence? does the narrator really have <em>your</em> interests at heart? mine doesn't for me). I would not want to live if I were paralyzed, or blinded, or in many other situations. That probably is not good enough reason to run around killing other people afflicted by those conditions.</p>
      <p>As for vegetarians, vegans, and so on, I genuinely don't think they care. I think they see something (in the "best guesses" mode of thinking), feel empathy for it, feel bad because of that empathy, and then seek to destroy the source of the bad feeling. If that involves destroying the animal, then that remedies that person's suffering just as much as anything else would. Wed that to the omnipresent feeling of shame experienced by people who suffer too little (so even the tiniest perceived suffering of an empathetic victim in their presence feels to them like the pea under a hundred mattresses to the allegorical princess), and who experience self-destructive urges born from the shame of self-suffering's absence, and you have a pretty good recipe for a successful meme. This also explains why they do evil things like eradicate the very things they pretend to care about. It's because they don't care about those creatures. They care about the suffering they experience by proxy. That suffering's source must be eliminated, in their personal pursuit of a life absent suffering; failing to realize that this is a goal achieved only upon entry into the grave.</p>
      <p>Instead, we should embrace suffering. The pain of being alive. But in moderation, as with all things.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>