<post>
  <author>onyomi</author>
  <date>2020-03-24T00:55:54Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fneib4/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_23_2020/flbs4eh/</link>
  <title>Cutting Through the West's Fake Enlightenment</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>For now, at least, people are still wearing luxury beliefs like "viruses don't respect borders" and "I don't wear a mask so there will be enough for our medical professionals on the front lines" like badges, up to and including berating people who e.g. wear a mask. Of course we have to lie to people about the efficacy of masks because there is no option between "hoard all the masks" and "make a point of never wearing one at all."</p>
      <p>In my view, this is one of the West's biggest problems, which East Asia, in my experience, largely lacks: too high a percentage of social interaction is driven by the need to signal virtue rather than do what makes sense or just be honest with yourself and others.</p>
      <p>East Asians, Chinese especially are, perhaps with some justification, sometimes criticized for lacking "public virtue"--their top concern is making sure they and theirs are <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30229968/">taken care of</a>, not loudly signalling that their top concern is that everyone in the world be taken care of. But I get so weary of this need to project selflesness and empathy, which, in most cases, I don't believe is real.</p>
      <p>When interacting with Japanese you may have to cut through a thick layer of politeness and formality, but interacting with white people involves cutting through an even thicker layer of <a href="https://twitter.com/robinhanson/status/1236704073728045056?s=20">fake enlightenment</a>. Meanwhile most Chinese will just be like "hell yeah I'm grabbing the toilet paper before everyone else does; by the way, my friend just ordered a whole crate of face masks, you in?..." (yes I am stereotyping everyone here; at least know that I've spent a lot of time living in America and various East Asian countries so my stereotypes aren't based on nothing).</p>
      <p>Perhaps one salutary effect of all this will be revealing the places in e.g. WHO statements where global Western elite culture has allowed fake virtue to corrode efficacy and truth to too great an extent.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>