<post>
  <author>ThirteenValleys</author>
  <date>2020-03-25T00:37:16Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fneib4/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_23_2020/flf2kjj/</link>
  <title>In Favor of a Social Safety Net</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Well the general argument in favor of the social safety net is that it could happen to anyone, so everyone ought to help maintain it. </p>
      <p>Maybe you lose your job and can't find another, maybe your spouse or kid dies, you cope with a little extra booze, then a little more, then suddenly one day you're an alcoholic. Get in a car crash, underestimate your brain's dopamine receptors, congratulations you're hooked on painkillers. Or maybe you turn 23, fresh out of college, surprise, you've got the schizophrenia gene. Now, this forum is full of uncommonly self-possessed and stoic people, so your answer might well be that you <em>don't</em> think Joe Taxpayer is obligated to help you in that situation. What I would wager is that enough people do that it's more efficient, fiscally and ethically, for society to say "Just pay in advance so you don't try and cash out after a lifetime of refusing to cash in". </p>
      <p>But those are tragedies. What about frivolities?</p>
      <p>When I said that your attitude would be mocked by many, I don't mean that you didn't understand that self-deprivation isn't fun, more like "OK but I'm <em>not</em> blowing $400 a week on bars, brunches, and fancy haircuts and I <em>am</em> eating ramen and rice and going to laundromats and clipping coupons and I'm <em>still</em> broke as fuck. You are ignorant of how people are actually living." </p>
      <p>Now, assuming these people aren't lying (some of them definitely are; there's considerable social capital on the left in exaggerating your poverty level, and some people really are un-self-aware enough to defend $9 Margarita Night as 'a necessary expense'), the dedicated critic can always find something to pick at: "You bought rice for $1.79 a bag instead of doing your research and noticing that it was $1.69 a few stores down? Clearly you're not that desperate." </p>
      <p>And dickish as that is, it's factually correct on the merits; any failure to be maximally cheap is a point against your claims of desperation. But hell, you can take that as far as you want, right? Just point to some inspirational story of a musician who lived out of his trunk for six weeks, or a homeless guy who still held down a 40-hour job by eating at soup kitchens and showering at the YMCA.</p>
      <p>To which my response is that...it's in your interest, on some non-financial level, for society to not be like that. It will cost you more if standards of living fall to that level. The idea that we should expect improved standards of living over time means that, inevitably, future generations will see as necessities what you saw as luxuries. In the short term, it's annoying, but in the long-term, it's what success looks like. No one wants to go back to pre-modern standards of living even if they could survive. </p>
      <p>I doubt this was very convincing, but there you go.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>