<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2020-04-12T04:29:54Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fwbvi6/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_5/fn5iizq/</link>
  <title>The History and Increasing Nationalism of Israeli Democracy</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>And yet the intelligentsia, too, can suffer from the feeling of betrayal – and one of the most excuisite kind. Many among its members are naively admiring of foreign critics – until they notice those foreign countries experiencing similar problems and try to "helpfully" point it out to their betters, often in a cringeworthy way of suggesting to "not be like a filthy Ruskie" (for the politically-minded, the entire world is an extension of local conflicts... maybe this post is another example). The violent blowback they receive for their efforts commonly leads to some disillusionment, and sometimes causes conversion to unhinged patriotism. There were many such "awakenings" in 2014 when young liberal Russians realized that some of the wittiest anonymous critics of «Pidorashka» (Russia, basically «'Murica» only worse) were just tribal Ukrainians all along, the type who'll approve of Neo-Nazis in their own Parliament and partake in the basest displays of patriotism they would be expected to mock. I also went through that stage. I'd rather not repeat the whole dance now.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Fascinating. I know Karlin writes a lot about how even Russian liberals have slowly become (since 2010 or so) nationalists when it comes to foreign policy - perhaps simply nationalists who want a slightly more liberal society at home. </p>
      <p>It reminds me a lot of what happened in Israel, especially since 1973 but really on a slower level since the foundation of the state. How did so many anarchists and communists, who believed in freedom for all men, abandoning religion and primitive superstition, no borders and no capitalism, end up forming a conservative, religious, nationalist-capitalist ethnostate? Now of course the far rightists will likely say that general critics of jews are right, all the Jewish anarchists were really just ethnic activists, they only cared about communism as long as it served their ethnic interests , didn’t really care about liberating the world, and so as soon as they found Israel they simply turned it into another western nationalist post-1848 capitalist oligarchic-Democratic society just like the ones they had left in Europe, except this time with them in charge. And certainly, there <em>was</em> always a bourgeois, capitalist, nationalist Zionism, such as that typified by the Rothschilds and other very wealthy Jews in Britain, America, Germany, France and so on. </p>
      <p>But to say that’s the whole story obscures the fascinating and bizarre decline of the Israeli left intelligentsia. I think a lot of them really were true to their convictions, believed in socialism and peace with all men. Most were willing to accept the 1947 partition plan that would have left Jews a minority in the new Israeli state within 20 years, even (and demographic projections were not a new science even then). Many hoped, publicly and privately, that eventually there wouldn’t even be a border between Israel and Palestine, that Jew and Arab would soon coexist, that perhaps Israel would even become part of some broader regional democratic confederation, with open movement and trade. These were widespread positions on the Israeli left in the early years of Jewish settlement in the 1940s. Even those on the Jewish left (the Bund etc) who were explicitly zionist weren’t really ethnonationalists in a way that Israelis are today. Often the Israel they envisaged had an Arab majority and was ruled democratically, or wasn’t even really Jewish at all, but a ‘beacon of democracy’ that might attract all peoples - kind of like how pro-immigration liberals think of America. </p>
      <p>Wealthy Western European capitalists, religious zionists, and mercantile Sephardic Jews were all minorities in Israel’s early days - it was the shtetl intelligentsia who ruled. And over time, as the reality of living in a truly dangerous new neighborhood became more and more clear - as it was pounded into their head, death after death, bomb after bomb, war after war, what the fargroup (Arab states) actually wanted or appeared to want - the outgroup (domestic capitalists ie. class enemies but at least not people who wanted to exterminate them, kind of like in your nuclear war with Russia hypothetical) began to seem more and more amenable.</p>
      <p>Today Israeli democracy is still raucous, spanning everything from gay marriage activists who head floats at pride parades to religious extremists who refuse to allow pictures of women in their newspapers, but all of them - even traditional anti-nationalist groups like the far left and the ultra-orthodox (who believe israel is illegitimate because it isn’t a Jewish Kingdom established by the Messiah) are strongly nationalist. Their world has made them so. I have a feeling Russians might be similar.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>