<post>
  <author>conquerer7</author>
  <date>2020-04-12T06:43:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fvsrae/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_06_2020/fn5rx0f/</link>
  <title>Facing a Senator's Racism as a Chinese-American</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>A sitting Senator pointed directly to you, a small child, and called you out as an individual to be a national security threat? Are you certain that's what was going on? What did he say, exactly?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>When I was 15 I won some awards and went to D.C. with a bunch of similar people and teachers as part of a feel-good delegation to promote science education. It was pretty well organized, too; we had over 10 private audiences with representatives and senators scheduled. </p>
      <p>My group consisted of me, another Chinese guy, and a white guy, all with identical awards, identical dress, and similar physical features. We showed up to the senator's office, and before any of us got a word across, he motioned for the white guy to sit in the chair next to him, and pointed for us to sit on a couch ten feet away. He proceeded to spend the entire meeting pointedly ignoring anything we said, refusing to even look in our direction. He concluded by praising my white friend for his creativity and brilliance, because "we need minds like yours to help fight Chinese cybercrime", shaking his hand, and then waving us away.</p>
      <p>It's not sensational; most real stories aren't. And it wasn't that hurtful. We all had a good laugh about it, and I figured that was just how politicians were. Years later I helped organize these trips, and the same things would keep happening. Groups with more Asian students would have their prescheduled meetings abruptly cancelled without explanation. On one particularly bad year, the only group that avoided this was the one that was, by chance, all-white. And across all my trips to Congress, I never met a single Asian working there, not even to fetch the coffee. It was more depressing and predictable than anything else.</p>
      <p>The problem with all this isn't that it's "racist" or that my feelings are hurt, because they're not. The problem is that if one group is completely excluded from the work of governance, then when the next Red Scare comes along, there's going to be nobody in the committee room that can say they're being insane. The committee members will not be Asian. The aides and staff will not be Asian. For god's sake, it's possible that none of the aides' <em>friends</em> will be Asian. It will simply be impossible to have <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8llS0ZkLVGA">the kinds of moments</a> that stopped McCarthy's momentum. Who the hell is supposed to do that? Some maniac like Sarah Jeong?</p>
      <p>Incidentally, a descendent of the original McCarthy administration still exists, and even meets in the same room today. Its main purpose is to set up sting operations on Chinese-Americans. (I learned this from an academic who occasionally consults for them; he is, of course, white.) These happen <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/10/business/accused-of-spying-for-china-until-she-wasnt.html">all</a><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/09/12/us/politics/us-drops-charges-that-professor-shared-technology-with-china.html">the</a><a href="https://www.navytimes.com/news/your-navy/2017/01/22/the-strange-case-of-lt-cmdr-edward-lin/">time</a>, and generally go down like this: you wake up on some Sunday morning, go downstairs to make coffee, draw the curtain, and see 20 FBI agents with guns pointed at your face. Then you get thrown in jail and read a list of charges that don't make the slightest sense. Luckily this is not common, but there's nothing stopping it from getting much more common in the next decade, because <em>there is no counterweight</em>. We're a political liability to both Democrats and Republicans. Campaigning against this will be about as politically appealing as campaigning to release pedophiles from prison. And obviously, any intervention by China itself will make the situation much worse. </p>
      <p>So that's why I'm pessimistic. There's no way for the situation to get better, there's plenty of reason it will get worse, and every slide towards persecution begins in the same way: a ratchet of increasing suspicion.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, I know that one can write this kind of narrative for literally any group in America... so I guess we'll just have to agree to disagree, and wait and see.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>