<post>
  <author>FCfromSSC</author>
  <date>2020-04-15T03:09:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fng1ky5/</link>
  <title>Reflections on Media Narratives</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I would like to thank you for presenting these arguments, it's exactly the consensus point of view on the press that I was referring to, and having a solid example at hand is most helpful.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The press still has a large amount of influence, I agree, but they do not have much control.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>They have sufficient control that an extremely weak accusation against Kavanaugh turned into a six-week national circus, while a stronger accusation against Biden generates no conversation worth noticing. That is an absolutely jaw-dropping amount of control, easily enough to be a decisive influence on national politics.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>But they did not have much control, because they were fighting against Trump. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The fact that Trump won an extremely risky gamble does not prove that the press lack control. Especially since the Press intentionally put him in a position to make that gamble.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The press are capitalist businesses, and seek to profit maximize for shareholders without concern for longer term self-interest or morals.  </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Treating Biden the way they treated Kavanaugh would have destroyed his candidacy and his political career. It would have been one of the most dramatic political reversals of the last 50 years, turned the democratic nomination from a slog into an actual horse race, and ignited a firestorm of controversy. It would have made any media organization that participated an absolute heap of money. If the press were indeed seeking to maximize profit without concern for longer term self-interest or morals, why didn't they run with it?</p>
      <p>From where I sit, your thesis is directly contradicted by the available evidence.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I don't think by any semantic definition there's a monopoly, even if you only focus on the big mainstream media.  </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Taboo the word "monopoly".</p>
      <p>The left-wing press was able to force a major controversy over Kavanaugh, which the right-wing press was not able to smother and was forced to respond to.</p>
      <p>The left-wing press has refused to cover the accusations against Biden, despite clear risk to reputation and strong financial incentives, despite a whole lot of potential defectors. Further, the right-wing press has not been able to force the the controversy, and the left-wing press has consequently not had to respond.</p>
      <p>Again, what your model predicts is not what we are seeing. The common model of Fox News says that they should be salivating to run wall-to-wall coverage of this issue, but they've run nothing much at all.</p>
      <p>You are repeating a prediction that has been made many, many times before, and I am pointing out that the prediction has been falsified by the actual results of the experiment. The press does not work the way you are saying it works.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>There isn't a head of the New York Times calling up the head of MSNBC to collaborate on who they want elected and to plan out how to get that person elected, let alone collaboration between all the outlets. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This statement is wrong in every detail.</p>
      <p>We know for a fact that there are "heads" of the NYT and MSNBC; there are people in positions of power who decide what gets printed and broadcast.</p>
      <p>We know for a fact that these people very frequently have professional and personal relationships with each other.</p>
      <p>Thanks to Journolist, Cabalist and the Hillary campaign email leaks, we know for a fact that people in similar positions in the press have in fact called each other up and collaborated on "getting people elected", or more precisely on coordinating their news output for partisan political advantage.</p>
      <p>I am not claiming that lack of Biden coverage is actually the result of a series of secret phone calls, but that explanation is plausible and can actually fit the evidence.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The news media pushes partisan stories because that's what earns them money these days.  </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The left-wing press was happy to run sexism allegations against Bernie Sanders, one of the most rabidly popular of the democratic candidates. This didn't seem to hurt their income any. Why were accusations against Biden different?</p>
      <p>Further, this would make an amazing partisan story for Fox News, only Fox News has barely touched it. Why are they leaving money on the table?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>But I think that's the effect of the editors of each media business independently saying to their writers, "Write on Kavanaugh, it'll earn us lots of money! Don't write on Biden, it won't get many views." </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Your explanation appears circular. The media editors declare that the Biden story isn't juicy, so they don't cover it. We know that their decision is just business, because no one is covering the Biden story. But no one is covering the Biden story because the editors have declared that it isn't juicy.</p>
      <p>I'm asking why the story isn't juicy. I mean, it sure as hell looks juicy to me. Biden himself is on the record saying that this sort of story is always juicy, and the media are collectively and extensively on the record agreeing with him. The media has no satisfying answer to that question, and are now quietly embarrassing themselves trying to avoid it as much as they can. You don't have an answer either, from what I can see.</p>
      <p>I think I do. I think the media is 90% progressive/leftist/blue-tribe, whatever we're calling it these days. I think that journalists mostly believe that that their side is always in the right, and that doing their job well and advancing their partisan interests are two sides of the same coin. I think this belief shapes every decision made in the industry, top to bottom.</p>
      <p>So the right-wing journalists try to push their partisan advantage, and the left-wing journalists try to push theirs. But there are nine blues to every red, and quantity is a quality all it's own. Further, journalists are some combination of lazy or overworked, which means they consistently go for the easy way out. And the easy way out, in journalism, is to talk about what everyone else is talking about.</p>
      <p>There are nine blues to every red. If journalists write about what everyone is talking about, they're going to write about what blues are talking about. If rare journalists buck the trend and try to do real work, there will be nine serious blue piece for every serious red piece. Further, since ideas build on each other, a greater proportion of the blue pieces are going to be pushing blue ideas further, and a greater portion of the red pieces are going to be responses to blue ideas, rather than novel red ideas. There's only so many good ideas on each side, of course, so the blues hit diminishing returns much more than the reds do, but with a nine-to-one advantage they can afford the inefficiency and still win handily.</p>
      <p>Reds suck at pushing narratives, even easy narratives like this one, because they've overspecialized in responding to blue narratives rather than pushing their own. They've overspecialized because pushing a new narrative means a fight over framing, and the quantity gap results in blues winning most of those fights through sheer volume of fire. Reds are going to sell papers either way, so why do the hard digging for no result? And so they get sloppy and weak, unable to chase even easy stories like the Biden accusations, or the Gosnell case. The blues decline to cover the issue, because they think it'll hurt their cause. The reds don't cover the issue, because they're mostly there just to argue about whatever the blues bring up, not to actually do the hard work of digging up a story themselves.</p>
      <p>Hence, the blue media declines to cover Biden, and the red media mostly just shrugs and plays along, and the market doesn't work the way everyone knows it's supposed to.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>