<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-04-11T11:33:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fwbvi6/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_5/fn2vew5/</link>
  <title>Your Adversaries Are Not Paid Shills</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I have this... primal urge, almost. I wonder why</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This debate is a superstimulus. Scissor Statement, Toxoplasma of Rage, tribalism etc., all our friends are here. It would be surprising if you didn't feel so agitated. Hardly anything except disengagement from social media will help. Importantly, there's the unique sense of urgency to arguing with "shills": you suspect them of subverting the gullible to advance their evil overlord's agenda, and so there's virtue in protecting the flock with "debunking" and "calling out". Ask yourself: are they winning? Is your help really necessary?  </p>
      <p>But I'd like to discuss a broader point.</p>
      <p>Among many other delusions COVID-19 has broken was my faith in general value agreement with the culture of this sub. I made a few rather unpopular (and, to be fair, low-quality) posts only to see myself not getting through, and gave up. But here's the thing: I am very certain that Mottites are neither paid shills nor simple-minded brainwashed rubes – or, at least, their brainwashing is as authentic as my worldview. This was liberating because it allowed me to stop engaging in hopeless bouts. Suppose you hate Communism because of what it did to your nation, and you see a guy proclaim: «hey, me too, what a monstrous inhumane ideology!» and before you high-five him, he adds: «would have been better to eradicate your people in a nuclear holocaust – to stop the Commies, that is. Oh, by the way US numbers do not indicate criminal neglect of the threat, China lied to us that's why we tarried, and also China totally hid millions of COVID-19 cases, because Commies, man». How do you reply? <em>Do</em> you? </p>
      <p>Some people do. In BNODesk comments, I notice the defenders of freedom and truth: smug, shallow herd animals bravely posting #ChinaLiedPeopleDied hashtag, imagining themselves some tough no-bullshit men like "Die Hard" John McClane, beating down a random Chinese account who dared to make a common-sensical observation, with vitriol and memes and slogans – <a href="https://twitter.com/realXiaolan/status/1247829383735160832">case in point</a>. This Chinese joined in February, has a cookie-cutter pro-China account, tweets nothing but Coronavirus, is accused of being a bot... guess what I believe about him? I'm inclined to believe he's genuinely thinking what he posts, because I think the same, and I assume he's registered to argue on this topic because he feels the way you do about social media. I didn't go through all posts, but I woudn't be surprised to see attempts to "fix", as you say, the "dumbshit" westerners post – not least the timeline Americans habitually fudge to protect their delusion of living in a functional country.<br />
On this note, for me, the program was mostly clear by Jan 23, and notice how rationalists were apparently so immune to dastardly Chinese lies as to <a href="https://putanumonit.com/2020/02/27/seeing-the-smoke/">not even notice them</a>, and in retrospect I see the idiocy of the assertion that China consciously allowed the preventable pandemic to spread in a way "free" country wouldn't – an assertion made with <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/amp/2020/04/andrew-sullivan-time-for-conscious-uncoupling-with-china.html">ever-increasing conviction</a> (I even wonder: if this virus originated in USA, would we learn about it at the point there were a thousand or a hundred thousand cases?); still, all I'll get arguing is the label of brainwashed/Chinese shill. </p>
      <p>There's a natural tendency to use evidence of astroturfing to discredit every unpleasant opinion that to some extent agrees with it; and personally, I go as far as <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/fo3q5e/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_three/flm2hli/">to suspect astroturfing without evidence</a> when I simply notice some suspicious synchrony in disagreeable takes. Every pro-Trump poster on the Interwebz since 2016 is a Russian bot, after all. How often is that label a false positive, what do you think? 99.99%? Higher? By the way, why is there no comparable HillaryBot accusation damaging the other side, despite evidence of ShareBlue and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Correct_the_Record">Correct The Record</a>? Maybe because the Dem-conttolled narrative allows us to recognize that most people who supported Clinton did that "out of their own free will", and thus astroturfing can be safely memoryholed?</p>
      <p>Anyway, my point is that this tendency is most often wrong. And it's a bit sad.</p>
      <p>Edit: <em>Doot Doot</em> award? Since... when is this a thing? Is it a dog-whistle for moving to Mastodon? Thanks, I suppose.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>