<post>
  <author>mokoroo</author>
  <date>2020-04-11T03:51:03Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fvsrae/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_06_2020/fn23rlp/</link>
  <title>The Inherent Advantages of Extraversion</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>So first I want to heavily scrutinize your post, as it could come off to some as a contrarian hot take.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>To be entirely honest, I took it as a hot take. </p>
      <p>But before I mention anything on that front at all, I want to talk about why.</p>
      <p>When I see trans people bitch about cis people, I don't take it as hatred, I take it as jealousy. Cis people don't need to deal with dysphoria, get the genitals they're happy with, get to pass, easier time getting into relationships, etc, etc, etc. To me, I don't mind. It is frustrating that a few trans people on Twitter seem to be dictating public discourse in increasingly weird ways, but I expect in a few years we'll realise that Twitter actually has very little power and return to more sane norms.</p>
      <p>When I see poor people bitch about rich people, likewise. No worries about car registration, rent, phone bills, etc, etc.</p>
      <p>Usually when you see one group bitch about another and the bitching is unidirectional you pattern-match to 'the bitching group has gotten the shit end of the stick and therefore has the right to complain because they didn't get anything else'.</p>
      <p>You rarely hear extroverts talk about introverts. There was a post here (or in SSC) some time back where a fairly accomplished poster talked about introverts as though they were essentially failed extroverts. I was furious. I'm an extrovert myself, but it felt incredibly cruel. Why kick the introverts when they're down <em>already</em>, I thought? </p>
      <p>This might seem like idle talk, but the one trait that correlates the best across both genders (more than <em>attractiveness</em>) to social status is extroversion. </p>
      <p>Whenever I see introverts complain about extroverts, I usually filter it through that lens first. It doesn't really bother me, but 'low status group complains about high status group' is a cliche for a reason. </p>
      <p>But in reality, some things are almost <a href="https://magic.wizards.com/en/articles/archive/making-magic/strictly-superior-2014-03-03">strictly superior</a> to others. </p>
      <p>The OP did anecdotes, and I think it's useful to share. Interesting, maybe, if not necessarily informative.</p>
      <p>Anecdotally, I was a tremendous extrovert in college. I went to a residential college of around ~500 people, and within 6 months I knew ~450 or so of them by name, and vice versa. I would stroll around interacting with people, having good times, going on road trips with friends - I certainly had a core group of friends (huge introvert nerds, incidentally, have always been my gang), but knowing people has a sort of power all of its own. It means you're outcome independent of what your friends do or don't do with you. You can be alone all you want (being alone when you're the big nexus on a graph of social relations is incredibly easy - people always accept you being busy), but life is essentially a big all-you-can-meet buffet.</p>
      <p>Don't want to hang out? No worries, my buddy Marco is headed down to the coast on the weekend. Girl stops sleeping with you? Not a worry, I know a few hundred more cute single girls. Want to do something with me? Sure, I'm game. We're going hiking a hundred kms? Sounds cool, you set up the gear and organise. Cute girl calls me up and wants to get back together? I can back out with zero penalty, people know I'm busy.</p>
      <p>High social status and lots of social connections are <em>incredibly</em> rewarding and it's difficult to describe how rewarding. People like you, look up to you, ask you for advice (I was a decidedly average pure maths student but routinely my classmates asked me for help - they would have been better off asking the weird fat girl with terrible teeth who aced everything), there's a halo of attraction that surrounds you, and everything just sort of manipulates itself in your favour. </p>
      <p>I missed two exams in my first semester (my internet at home went out and I mixed up the days and times and didn't realise until I'd missed two) which is normally a failing offence but I knew a guy who's girlfriend's mother who had the power to make a decision on this, and I got a free resit, no harm no foul. I am objectively not tremendously attractive but getting laid was beyond easy. Making new friends was a compound interest situation - if you know everyone, everyone wants to know you. If you wanted something (weed, booze, money, etc), it would just be provided. Social capital is real and can be converted into other kinds of capital with relative ease.</p>
      <p>Towards the end of college I was very ill. I find it difficult to talk or write about it directly, but I spent the better part of two years in bed, or with doctors or in hospital for repeated surgeries. Low energy kinda guy for a long time. Being miserable and chained to my bed of course disintegrated most of my social networks and friendships, and I moved <em>heavily</em> in the introvert direction - interacting with people was exhausting and difficult. I had to watch what I did, and simply saying 'yes, let's go do this' was never an option. Constant thought and care was required to guard my health, which made me constantly on-guard which made socialising exhausting.</p>
      <p>Thankfully my health has improved. However, I now find people more tiring, more difficult, and I enjoy meeting new people less. My experiences have shaped my personality. I tried navigating social situations in similar ways and I was punished heavily (spending social capital when you have infinite amounts is fine, but I was an ordinary person using debt to live like a Kardashian), and I found people now disliked me. Not all people, but the halo was gone. Part of it is wealth begets wealth, and popularity begets popularity, but those things are strongly correlated with extroversion. </p>
      <p>This isn't a typical extroversion tale (I suspect I was probably in the top 2-3% for extroverts and now am on the top, say, 20-30% of said scale), but it's telling to me that while my brief <a href="https://youtu.be/IUdG1emDb_A?t=43">popular phase</a> was in play I was the most extroverted I'd ever been. It's not to say that there aren't popular, high-status, attractive, etc, etc introverts. I've known plenty of introverts who were high-status and attractive. But the correlation between status and introversion ain't positive.</p>
      <p>Most people I know with tremendous social capital are extroverted as well. My social strategy these days is literally 'make friends with the most connected vertex on the graph', and these people are happy, interesting, intelligent people. They have deep friendships and great lives. They genuinely care about people because they really enjoy being with them. </p>
      <p>The most extroverted person I know (we're buddies - my main problem is whenever I go out to hang out with him of a night I can hang from like 6 to say 9 because eventually the girls will start texting and one usually shows up by 10) is the sort of person who you can pour your heart out to and he'll just keep your secrets and understand. He likes you because he <em>likes people</em>, but as it turns out being liked isn't one of those things where being genuinely liked is undermined by the fact that your friend has a lot of other friends.</p>
      <p>I don't doubt that there are advantages to introversion, don't mistake me, but they seem similar to the advantages of being, say, 5'4 as a man versus being 6'0. Admittedly plane seats are more comfortable, you live longer (height and lifespan having a negative correlation), and you spend less on food, but it strikes me as incredibly unlikely that you'd <em>want</em> to be a 5'4 man over a 6'0 one if you'd experienced both.</p>
      <p>Swinging back around to the original point, the OP says extroverts have inferior quality relationships, are driven by shame, low levels of introspection, don't think, and are obedient and domesticated. Speaking in generalities, it's difficult to look at that post and not think 'well, sour grapes much?'.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>