<post>
  <author>NUMBERS2357</author>
  <date>2020-04-14T07:54:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fncxonb/</link>
  <title>Sexualization and Social Pressure in the Market</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm not sure how much this is supposed to be a stylized version of what Weinstein did for purposes of a theoretical discussion, vs a discussion of what he actually did.  But it should be pointed out that Weinstein did not simply offer movie roles for sex.  He physically forced himself on women, he threatened women who turned him down with ruining their careers, and he harassed anyone who tried to discuss any of this publicly.</p>
      <p>Even using the stylized version of Weinstein's acts, two points I want to add:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>the systemic nature of the problem of women facing these tradeoffs</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>the difference between this free market conception of the world, and most people's actual lived experience</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>On the first, once you allow men to offer this choice to women, how often would women face it?  Men hold a very disproportionate share of positions of power in this country, and it used to be much more so.  Basically any occupation that women traditionally held has been sexualized by men - the sexy nurse, the sexy teacher, the sexy maid, the sexy flight attendant, the sexy secretary.  You may soon find that an attractive woman in her 20s is almost always given this choice.</p>
      <p>I know you want to say that the free market will ensure that someone will come along to offer those women who are therefore shut out of employment, a job with no sex tradeoff.  But I'm not so sure.  "The free market" is the collective actions of many people, and those people just so happen to all be men, and perhaps it turns out that if it's an accepted norm of society that you can give young women this choice, those men will mostly let their businesses suffer a bit in order to have this control over hot girls.</p>
      <p>Theoretically in a free market an attractive woman would be better off - she can get a job on the same terms as anyone else, or she can work at the place that only hires attractive women who will, e.g., wear revealing clothes.  But if enough men in positions of power want to make that tradeoff, then those women might be <em>worse</em> off - most businesses hire young women <em>only if</em> they wear revealing clothes, and there aren't enough that don't do this to make up for it (especially when <em>men</em> are more likely to want to work at (or patronize) the former; <em>especially</em> if there are social norms for men to run their business that way for the benefit of men everywhere).</p>
      <p>I think lots of people will scoff at this hypothetical world - but as far as I can tell it was how things really used to be.  Historically, the world where you can tell women you'll only hire them if they give you a blow job but women are still treated equally is the hypothetical.</p>
      <p>Briefly, on the second, I'm reminded of the <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/109/3/">Civil Rights Cases of 1883</a>.  Libertarians sometimes claim that the Civil Rights Act of 1964 was wrong because it prohibited private discrimination.  This was the question in that 1883 case.</p>
      <p>To quote the majority in that case:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Innkeepers and public carriers, by the laws of all the States, so far as we are aware, are bound, to the extent of their facilities, to furnish proper accommodation to all unobjectionable persons who in good faith apply for them. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>and the dissenter (quoting an earlier case):</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The innkeeper is not to select his guest. He has no right to say to one, you shall come to my inn, and to another, you shall not, as everyone coming and conducting himself in a proper manner has a right to be received, and, for this purpose innkeepers are a sort of public servants, they having, in return a kind of privilege of entertaining travelers and supplying them with what they want.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The idea of everyone acting as consenting adults, including businesses accepting and refusing customers or employees, is not how things have ever worked.  It would be one thing to switch totally over to a system like that, although I think it would upend society more than people might think.  But to have the "the innkeeper is not to select his guest" model as a default, and then switch to "consenting adults" when an attractive 22 year old woman wants a job, is a problem.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>