<post>
  <author>ZeroKelvinCorral</author>
  <date>2020-04-13T20:31:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fnb64pl/</link>
  <title>Merging and Separating the Four Spheres of Modern Activity</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <em>Modernity</em> can be defined as the separation of the four domains of activity (political, economic, social, religious) into distinct spheres. (I forget who came up with this definition but I think it might be Max Weber.) On one extreme, a hunter-gatherer society is by necessity fully-integrated, because you're spending 100% of your time with the same group of people. On the other hand, in contemporary America for the most part, any given person will do activities in each domain with different groups of people. (Well at least this was true before lockdown began...)</p>
      <p>In this framework, the "free market" can be understood as advocating that the economic domain be fully disentangled from the other three. The separation from the religious and social domains had already taken place by the Industrial Revolution, and so free market advocacy in the 20th century had focused on separating the economic from the political domain - i.e. reducing the extent to which political bodies are making economic decisions. This is what we usually think of as "free market libertarianism."</p>
      <p>But your Rule 815 represents a re-merger of the economic and social spheres. Libertarianism as such, being a <em>political</em> ideology, has nothing to say about this. If you want to advocate for the free market against a social/economic integrationist view, you would need to make an argument from within one of those domains. It might look something like this:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Economic vs. social virtues are not necessarily held by the same person, so we gain by allowing for specialization in one or the other. A certain rice farmer may be a scumbag, but we all gain by having more rice on the market rather than less. Or, a more concrete example: the Twitter blue checkmark began as a simple verification that someone is who they say they are, which is mostly a technical problem that Twitter-the-company is well poised to address. But when they started treating the blue checkmark as a mark of prestige or trustworthiness, then there's no reason to believe that they're any better at judging these virtues than anyone else.</li>
        <li>Social/economic integration corrodes society by creating a "dictatorless dystopia" where people's social competence is taxed by having to keep up with a constantly changing set of rules. If people weren't fired for social faux-pas, then there would at least be more room for experimentation.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>(You can probably come up with better arguments; that's just what I thought of now.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>