<post>
  <author>CriticalDuty</author>
  <date>2021-06-08T04:08:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/nu5kvj/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_07_2021/h0ztj9z/</link>
  <title>Part 2</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>2/2</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Why did I watch this film? Why did I write this review? I knew these people were whackadoodles going in; I didn't expect that they would change my mind, and they didn't manage to do so. It's undeniable that one of the reasons I watched this was simply to sneer. I don't have any particular fondness for homosexuals, nor any inclination to defend them from Tariq Nasheed's sociology. But I am interested in the social processes that necessitate the creation and maintenance of these views, how they stay alive despite being both facially and structurally ridiculous, and the enduring influence they have in certain circles.</p>
      <p>A lot of modern Afrocentrist thought is rooted in a particular historical approach advocated by the Senegalese historian Cheikh Anta Diop, who constructed the ideological justifications employed by the likes of Molefi Kete Asante and Leonard Jeffries. Diop's approach cast European scholarship on Africa as inherently suspect and steeped in colonial biases (which, to be sure, a lot of it was), and advocated for an African history as promulgated by Africans. Ultimately this just meant he promoted a lot of pseudohistory and revisionism with little basis in fact, and dismissed non-African critics as limited by the European perspective:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>It is the difference in intellectual attitude between African and European researchers that is often the cause of these misunderstandings about the interpretation of facts and their relative importance. The scientiﬁc curiosity of the European researcher toward African data is essentially analytical. Viewing things from the exterior, often not desiring to develop a synthesis, the European researcher essentially attaches himself to explosive microanalysis that is more or less tendentious as regards the facts and indeﬁnitely puts off the stage of synthesis. The African researcher mistrusts this ‘scientiﬁc’ activity whose goal seems to be to dissolve African collective, historical consciousness in the <strong>pettiness of details</strong>.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>(emphasis mine)</p>
      <p>Diop was hardly the first post-colonial scholar to push revisionism as a cure for colonial history, but in the Africanist context, the influence of his approach has been considerable. What's notable is that Diop was making his arguments in the texts and journals of French academia, and he was met by what he himself called "a qualified silence" - a lot of French academics knew his arguments were nonsense but simply refrained from comment, because organizations populated by Marxists from top-to-bottom are not inclined to call out shoddy African scholarship. In other words, the academy had no memetic antibodies to counter this kind of work.</p>
      <p>As time goes by, I am less confident that American institutions have the memetic antibodies necessary to counter similar thinking, or that they will continue to have such antibodies in the future. If you had told me ten years ago that a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kristen_Clarke">woman</a> who <a href="https://www.thecrimson.com/article/1994/10/28/book-sparks-campus-debate-pmental-physical/">believes</a> melanin makes black people physically and intellectually superior would be the head of one of the most powerful divisions of the Department of Justice, I would have doubted that very much. Would I have believed that prominent <a href="https://www.masslive.com/politics/2012/08/elizabeth_warren_gets_nod_of_s.html">Democratic</a><a href="https://www.masslive.com/politics/2013/02/rep_ed_markeys_senate_campaign.html">Senators</a> would court the endorsement of a <a href="https://twitter.com/TalbertSwan/status/1398987010560385026">man</a> who thinks "the white world was built on plagiarized Black knowledge"? Swan, incidentally, is one of the experts on the white homosexual agenda featured in Tariq's film.</p>
      <p>I feel like there is an ecosystem of similar thought in the black community, practically a world of its own and completely alien to me, and while it is easy to laugh at Tariq and to call him an idiot, it is also sobering to consider that his views enjoy a certain vogue with people who wield power over my life. On the other hand, perhaps this is how gay people feel about Tony Perkins. How the turntables turn.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>