<post>
  <author>Artimaeus332</author>
  <date>2020-01-16T19:07:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/fekk001/</link>
  <title>On the Problems With Narratives</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I notice a lot people on this forum put a lot of effort into trying to rationally interpret the conduct and messaging of high-profile people within the "left" and "right" with the goal of telling a coherent story about what the movement as a whole wants (and how this has changed over time). </p>
      <p>Greyenlightenment is hardly the worst offender here, but I'm becoming increasingly convinced that this sort of analysis is doomed to be shallow and un-insightful if it's not framed specifically as a shift in the relative size, strength, influence, or character of specific constituencies within the broader coalition. Size alone prevents political coalitions from having a coherent, non-contradicting ideology and goals. Analysis is generally useful in so far as it can connect highly visible changes in movement leadership (with leadership broadly defined as anybody who is high profile with a large platform/following) with less visible trends how the people in the coalition are organizing themselves.</p>
      <p>A few examples of the sorts of stories in this vein that one could tell:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>Preferences of people in the coalition have changed, which causes people to flow between constituencies, strengthening some and weakening others (e.g. over time, people on the right have shifted from constituencies defined by evangelical Christian devotion and towards "America First" patriotism)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>New constituencies have emerged and entered the coalition, creating their own set of leaders (e.g. A constituency built around Jordan Peterson and other IDW personalities has joined the right coalition)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>One constituency acquires a new way to organize effectively (e.g. an individually talented leader or a new technology, like social media), increasing its relative power within the coalition (e.g. activist students and academics on the left had the skillset necessary to leverage social media WAY more quickly &amp; effectively than other left constituencies, leading the the rise of wokeness on the left).</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>One could question the details of any of these stories, but I think that if you aren't talking about the struggle between constituencies, you haven't understood what's going on.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>