<post>
  <author>Capital_Room</author>
  <date>2020-01-17T12:12:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/femmy9o/</link>
  <title>Cancellation as Cultural Imperialism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>(3) The problem is the arbitrary and capricious nature of the enforcement.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is actually something I've argue a bit, and have kind of mixed feelings on.</p>
      <p>One the one hand, police and courts and trials with presumption of innocence and rights to defend oneself are certainly superior to vigilatism and mafias and clan feud when it comes to enforcing rules against murder, theft, etc. And whatever the problems of the inquisitions (often exaggerated, and usually found, in greater degree, in the contemporaneous civil courts), they were definitely superior to both what came before — illiterate local lords having to adjuticate when an angry mob of peasants condemn a neighbor as a heretic — and to the various witchhunts that would break out (multiple inquisitors left writings skeptical of the very existence of "witches"). An inquisition can (and often did) acquit; how often do angry mobs do so? An inquisition can issue varying degrees of penalties, and then declare the matter settled. An inquisition can accept a recantation, but an unorganized mass of "cancellers" can not — which point Yarvin was making when he (facetiously) offered to "recant" if only those pushing his "deplatforming" would point him to a body with the authority to accept such a recantation.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, I think there's something to the Confucian case that the laws and "lines" should not, in fact, be clear and sharp and broadly known to the public, but generally opaque and uncertain. Because when the rules are explicit and written, people will "rules-lawyer" them, obey the letter rather than the spirit, dance right up to the very edge, and generally be <em>lawful</em> rather than <em>virtuous</em> — that is, doing <em>what they can get away with</em> rather than doing <em>what is moral</em>. When the cliff edge cannot be readily seen until one has likely gone over it, one keeps a safe distance from the general area; see also the idea of "building a fence around the Torah."</p>
      <p>I guess, it somewhat comes down to me being more of a #2 guy, in a way that also makes me a #1 guy, and which also explains the bit about self-selected ideological communities. Because it's one thing for a "self-selected ideological community" to enforce norms <em>broadly shared</em> within that community, it's <em>quite another</em> for a bunch of outsiders to invade your space and start imposing <em>their</em> foreign values on you. Who enjoys being on the wrong end of cultural imperialism, whatever the scale?</p>
      <p>Polls consistently show that the "woke set" are a definite minority, with distinct demographics, forming a distinct subculture (within Scott's "Blue Tribe"). One that is able to wield outsized institutional and political influence, and do so in the cause of enforcing their particular culture, values, and, yes, non-theistic religion, upon all the rest of us.</p>
      <p>While, I add, denying that's what they're doing. Because every single Christian missionary who set out to convert the heathen (by the sword, if need be) for the sake of said heathen's own soul <em>also</em> did not see themselves as imposing their particular culture's values, but Universal Moral Truth valid for all mankind. And the same with every colonialist who took up the "White Man's Burden" of the <em>mission civilisatrice</em>. Napier's whole 'your custom is to burn widows, our custom is to hang such who do so' bit. People on the receiving end have rightly resisted such imperialism, up to and including independence movements and force of arms. </p>
      <p>And on all those past examples, the "Woke Set" acknowledge this, and agree with the correctness of such resistance. But when it comes to their own <em>mission civilisatrice</em>, it's totally different. Because while all past missionaries and cultural imperialists mistook their parochial values for universal ones, they alone possess the <del>One True and Universal Faith</del> correct understanding of "Universal Human Rights" and what they entail for all people, everywhere.</p>
      <p>(While I see resisting <em>their</em> cultural imperialism against <em>my</em> people as just as valid as all those past resistances… yes, including independence movements and force of arms.)</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>(4) The problem is that the norms being enforced vary all the time and from community to community.</p>
        <p>My problem here: this sounds like an advertisement for a social credit system.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Or for pillarization or separation, whereby we each all stick to our own communities and mind our own business and <em>tolerate</em> other communities engaging in their repugnant local practices and stop trying to enforce our rules on them. But, no, because "Wokeism" is a totalizing, universalist faith that cannot allow the heathen to abide unconverted (and thus, so long as it stays so, it remains an existential threat to every other culture on Earth).</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>But given that commitment, what kind of constructive solutions can liberals like myself offer for anomie, assuming we grant it's a problem?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>And if the answer is "absolutely none"?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>But even if we reject hardline liberalism and abandon any commitment to strict values-neutrality, as long as we still reject collective norm enforcement, is there any remaining way to structure society so as to provide moral pathways and role models for people?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>And, again, if the answer is "no, there isn't"? What if this is simply liberalism reaching the end of its lifespan as it proves long-term unworkable? What if your "commitment" is one that simply cannot be maintained?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>