<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2020-01-22T11:30:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/er8kug/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_20/ff8r2vd/</link>
  <title>How the Opinion Section Took Over the NYT</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>From Jesse Singal on <a href="https://twitter.com/jessesingal/status/1219346191932108803">Twitter</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Covington was also a useful example of how Twitter absolutely radicalizes journalists. Because they are on it, all day every day, watching how their friends respond to every news item in real time -- always emphatically -- that has a profound effect on shaping coverage.</p>
        <p>The publication of <a href="https://theconcourse.deadspin.com/dont-doubt-what-you-saw-with-your-own-eyes-1831931203">this</a>, was a Holy Shit moment. The whole point was to name and shame journos/pundits who acted <em>correctly</em> after the long video dropped. (And yes I miss Deadspin dearly and read it daily and want it back -- but still!)</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is likely a case of media organizations responding to incentives.  As you say, "the short-term benefit is to cater to your partisan audience at the expense of long-term credibility."  </p>
      <p>However, I think a bigger point may be this: <em>long-term credibility no longer matters</em>.  Hits to your credibility only matter insofar as they impact your subscriber numbers, but what if subscribers simply want reporting that flatters their sensibilities?</p>
      <p>Op-ed sections are a new thing.  The NYT didn't have an op-ed section until 1970, and around 1980, only 5% of New York Times readers ever opened the op-ed section.  (I can't find a citation for that number but I've heard it multiple times at conferences in conversations with people in the publication industry.) The op-ed page was developed mainly as a place to sell "premium" advertisements that were written/disguised to look like part of the op-ed section.  </p>
      <p>You may recall the story from several weeks ago where Teen Vogue published a story titled "How Facebook Is Helping Ensure the Integrity of the 2020 Election," then it later came out that this "article" was <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/teen-vogue-story-on-facebook-prompts-sponsored-content-questions-vanishes-2020-1">actually sponsored content</a>.  John Oliver has attacked <a href="https://gawker.com/john-oliver-has-had-enough-of-ads-disguised-as-news-sto-1615693046">the practice of websites running ads that are disguised to look like news stories</a>.</p>
      <p>This "modern" business practice of selling ad space but framing it to make the ads look like actual content was <em>the entire business model on which the NYT op-ed section was built.</em>  The op-ed page was started in 1970, and while its intentions may have been noble (a sort of Vox-like goal of <em>explaining</em> things to reader, and <em>teaching them how to think</em>), it grew because it was immensely <a href="https://digitalcommons.library.umaine.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=1001&amp;context=cmj_facpub">profitable</a> thanks to sponsored content:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The newspaper's executives developed a place for outside contributors with space reserved for sale at a premium rate for additional commentaries and other purposes. ... A review completed in mid-1971 revealed that the first six
months of op-ed operation produced a net profit of $112,000 on $264,900
of revenues. ...  The Op Ed page's premium advertisements, usually written like the adjacent editorials and essays, accounted for $244,400 in revenue in the first six months.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>(This was at a time when NYT's entire net revenue was 7-digits, so that op-ed revenue was pretty substantial.)  And thus, the op-ed section was immensely profitable thanks to "sponsored content," despite the fact that it had relatively few readers: around 1980 (ten years after the birth of the op-ed section), only around 5% of NYT readers ever opened the op-ed section.</p>
      <p>In short, NYT readers did not care about the op-ed section.  The op-ed section was there for companies like US Steel to run ads-masquerading-as-editorials praising their companies for treating their workers well and being bastions of the economy or whatever, the 1970's equivalent of Facebook paying Teen Vogue to run a story titled "How Facebook Is Helping Ensure the Integrity of the 2020 Election."</p>
      <p>Things have changed a lot since then.  In 1980, only 5% of NYT readers ever opened the op-ed section.  Now, look at the "<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/trending/">trending</a>" page of NYtimes.com: as of this moment, 30% (4 out of 13) of those articles are from the opinion section. The opinions section is now a <em>substantially</em> bigger part of what draws people to the publication.</p>
      <p>As its readership has grown, the NYT's op-ed section is now there less to sell premium advertising and more as a service to the readers who pay $10 a month for a basic subscription (or $17 per month for an "all access" subscription).  And the line between opinion and news has grown thinner: it used to be that the op-eds were located in a <em>physically separate section of the newspaper</em>.  Now, everything is content on NYtimes.com, and the only thing that differentiates the news from the op-eds is the word "Opinion" located at the top of the page.  (The word "opinion" is located in the top-left corner of the page, in gray text that is a lighter color than the rest of the text on the page which is in all black; look carefully or you might miss it.)</p>
      <p>This has led to the annoying trend of media-illiterate people on Twitter sharing stories from the NYT opinion section <em>as though they are news</em>, because hey look, it's a link to NYtimes.com, and the story is about news-y topics like Trump and Nancy Pelosi.  The NYT banner is at the top of the page, it's about things that are happening in the news, so therefore it must be news.  (Note that both sides are guilty of this: people on the left will share a "Trump bad" NYT opinion piece as though it is fact and factual evidence that Trump is bad when in fact it is just an opinion piece, while people on the right will share a "Trump bad" NYT opinion piece and point to it as an example of "biased reporting" even though it's not a news article the person who wrote the article is not a reporter.  Famous troll <a href="https://twitter.com/ComfortablySmug/status/1219108625979002881">@ComfortablySmug</a> has even suggested taking advantage of this common misconception to undermine the credibility of NYT's reporting, responding to the NYT endorsement by saying: "Remember, anytime a NYTimes journo says anything bad about Trump, it's because their board ordered them to try to elect Warren and Klobuchar.")</p>
      <p>(Of course, it's hard to lay the blame for this solely at the feet of media-illiterate people on social media; the NYT itself is guilty of failing to distinguish news from editorial.  If you look at the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/trending/">trending</a> page on the NYT website, all you see is the headlines, without any indication as to which headlines are for news stories and which ones are from the opinions section.  Not everyone is going to click-through on each one of those headlines to discover whether it is an opinion piece, which may lead to people seeing headlines from the opinion section and parsing them as news reporting.)</p>
      <p>The NYT used to be a newspaper that happened to have an op-ed section.  (We've gone from the NYT not having an opinion section in 1970, to only 5% of readers touching that section in 1980, to opinions now making up 30% of the "trending" e.g. most-read content in 2020.)  Opinion now makes up a substantially large component of what people come to the NYT for.  Will trends continue further in this direction?</p>
      <p>The possibility of a news outlet shifting away from reporting and toward opinion/commentary is not unprecedented.  Good reporting is expensive and takes time, while an opinion piece can be cranked out in a single morning, and if either will suffice to sell issues, good business practice says you should fire the reporters.  That's exactly what <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newsweek#cite_ref-16">Newsweek</a> did after the economic downturn in 2008; in 2009, the publication "restructured" to place less emphasis on reporting and more on commentary and opinion.</p>
      <p>Do you really need credibility to be profitable?  Alex Jones has basically zero mainstream credibility, he is a literal conspiracy theorist, but he doesn't need to appeal to the general public, he doesn't even need to be advertiser-friendly, because all of his revenue comes from followers who go to his store and spend money on "male vitality pills" and prepper gear like radios and emergency rations.  (He's not selling space to advertisers who sell these products; he sells them himself and his viewers pay money directly to him.)  Is his model really so different from the NYT charging dedicated readers $120 a year for a basic subscription or $204 a year for an "all access" subscription?  (I'm guessing that NYT's revenue mainly comes from selling subscriptions, but hardcore fans can also head to their store to spend <a href="https://store.nytimes.com/products/truth-hoodie">$85 on a "truth hoodie"</a> or <a href="https://store.nytimes.com/collections/best-sellers/products/the-custom-birthday-book">$145 on a custom birthday book</a>, which is the best-selling item on the site.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>