<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2020-01-18T15:26:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/fes45bl/</link>
  <title>Gaming, Articulating, and Gatekeeping Oppression</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>One of the things that is interesting about woke circles is that they reward you for being skilled at articulating how you are oppressed, which is at best orthogonal to actually being oppressed, and sometimes inversely correlated.</p>
      <p>For example, suppose a college admissions officer wants to select the candidate who can best write an essay explaining how they were a victim of systemic racism.  Who do you suppose is going to be better at writing that essay: a black kid who grew up in a low-income neighborhood and was raised by a single parent, or someone like Cory Booker whose parents were IBM executives?  (Hint: it's probably going to be the kid whose parents can afford to hire a coach to tell them exactly how to write that essay.)</p>
      <p>If you just reward people for being good at articulating why they are being oppressed, and the definition of "oppressed groups" is so broad that it includes the majority of the population (after all, women are oppressed and already make up half the population), then at a certain point your "reward people for being good at articulating why they are oppressed" is just going to turn into "reward people for being articulate," and that seems like the kind of thing that would correlate with attaining high levels of education, being upper-class, and all of the other things associated with "privilege."  The most marginalized people in the world, who are dealing with problems like malnourishment, probably couldn't tell you the first thing about "microaggressions."  (In fact, <em>micro</em>aggressions seem like one of those things that, by definition, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Princess_and_the_Pea">you must have a certain level of privilege to notice</a>.)</p>
      <p>I think some people on the left have already caught onto this, which has led to gatekeeping oppression so as to keep oppression from being too ubiquitous that it becomes devalued.  (See: <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/think/opinion/white-gay-privilege-exists-all-year-it-particularly-hurtful-during-ncna1024961">White gay privilege exists all year, but it is particularly hurtful during Pride</a>, <a href="https://verysmartbrothas.theroot.com/straight-black-men-are-the-white-people-of-black-people-1814157214">Straight Black Men Are the White People of Black People</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QntGEb-KgXo">Why 'Passing Privilege' Is A Problem In The Trans Community</a>...)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>