<post>
  <author>dedicating_ruckus</author>
  <date>2020-01-21T02:08:57Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/er8kug/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_20/ff4u6rz/</link>
  <title>Gun Control Laws as Seen by Gun Owners</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>As others have said below, the core problem is that no one -- not even the gun control activists, really -- believes that this is about anything other than going "fuck you" to gun owners and the gun culture.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>"Assault weapon" is a content-free category. Under US law, it's typically defined with reference to a bunch of cosmetic or ergonomic characteristics that make absolutely no difference to how "dangerous" a gun is. Three features commonly definitive of "assault weapons" are forward handgrips, barrel shrouds and adjustable stocks. So, if you want to shoot without crimping your wrist around on the foregrip, or avoid burning yourself on the barrel, or have one gun that can fit people of different sizes -- well, then fuck you. There is no conceivable public safety justification for this kind of law; it's purely for griefing gun owners. (And, as a note, it targets by name the single most popular rifle in the country, the AR-15. Which is no more dangerous than any other semi-auto, just more pleasant to use. Griefing, griefing, griefing.)</li>
        <li>Suppressors. They're a safety/comfort feature that makes it possible to shoot a gun indoors without instant, permanent hearing damage. They don't impact public safety any; a suppressed gunshot is still extremely loud and still obviously a gunshot. No conceivable public safety justification; purely about griefing people to like to shoot.</li>
        <li>Background checks on all transactions. Private citizens can't access the NICS system, so this effectively makes private sales illegal. There is a theoretical public safety justification, but in practice it seems that ~all illegal guns come from the black market anyway; it's hard to imagine this having any particular effect on the availability of guns to criminals. Plus, these laws are often written such that they criminalize wholly normal conduct like temporary loans; I haven't read Virginia's particular proposal, but all the rest of these laws are about griefing gun owners, so I assume this one is too.</li>
        <li>One handgun purchase a month. Again, purely about griefing collectors, or people who are training with a .22 clone of their larger-caliber carry gun. You only need one gun to commit a crime; this doesn't even have the flimsy potential justification of a more conventional waiting period law.</li>
        <li>Allow municipalities to enact stricter ordinances. In practice, this leads to municipalities being able to pull a guy over and drag him to jail for having a gun in the back. Various leftist cities are constantly trying to do this anyway, and getting slapped down by the courts over the kinds of preemption laws that this is trying to repeal. In theory it could have a public safety justification, but in practice it's just another excuse to grief gun owners.</li>
        <li>ERPOs, or "red flag" laws. These have already been applied (in other states) to letting the government show up and confiscate people's guns for disfavored (rightist) political speech. Given this precedent, this is an obvious step toward the leftist goal -- already a staple of their rhetoric -- that goes something like "if you want a gun, that already disqualifies you from having one". There is a potential public safety justification, but without any trust in the people implementing it, no one is going to accept it.</li>
        <li>This one you didn't mention, but it's among the list of bills they're considering: ban indoor ranges in a public building with more than 50 employees inside. This is particularly blatant, because there's precisely one range in the entire state that would be affected, that at the NRA headquarters. It's practically ex post facto; it's a fuck-you to the NRA.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>It's difficult to understand, from the outside, just how purely culture-war-loaded the gun debate has become. It's possible to imagine a gun control proposal that served some public safety ends and was narrowly tailored to achieve them without causing undue disruption to gun owners. But none of these are like that at all; they're fairly blatantly targeted at law-abiding gun owners, with the intention of making life difficult for them, and the justification in terms of public safety not even specified.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>