<post>
  <author>greatjasoni</author>
  <date>2020-01-16T20:09:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/fekq8tv/</link>
  <title>Jesus and The Hierarchy</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I don't know that he is exactly saying Jesus tells us how to climb the hierarchy. Jesus is more like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eye_of_Providence#/media/File:Dollarnote_siegel_hq.jpg">eye</a> above the hierarchy that watches over it. His whole life an inversion of hierarchy, essentially to prove that it's meaningless in the face of God. The Jews are expecting the messiah to be a royal warlord who conquers their enemies. Instead the messiah is born in a dirty feeding trough for pigs to some no name couple. He dies betrayed and abandoned by his followers, poor, humiliated, and tortured to death. In doing so he shows he is God. </p>
      <p>If you go by any sane interpretation of a Dominance Hierarchy, Jesus is clearly at the bottom as he dies. Yet he is also (arguably) the most famous and influential person that ever lived. It's something of a contradiction, but I think Jesus is much deeper than just a hierarchy climbing mechanism, within the framework of Peterson's own understanding. (Although I think Peterson is missing a lot of the story too.) Maybe you could say he's at the bottom of a dominance hierarchy but top of the prestige hierarchy?</p>
      <p>I think the Resurrection is where you see the direct hierarchy-climbing approach to things. Here we get into more of the mythology and Peterson's (idiosyncratic) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IXZc6spUImI">psychological interpretation.</a> He essentially says Jesus is the top of the hierarchy, simply by definition going by western mytho/psychological norms. </p>
      <p>This is really complicated and I don't have time to fully flesh it out, but Peterson's representation of Christ, is something like: "The thing that watches and corrects the hierarchy." Which in psychological terms is "The thing that watches and corrects your own self understanding." So think of Scott's <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/09/05/book-review-surfing-uncertainty/">"Surfing uncertainty" review</a>. You have a top down theory about the world, Peterson might call it your ideological map of reality. It's full of heuristics and biases and blind spots that you're not strong enough to deal with. Your senses take in data, your higher brain makes a top down prediction of what the data ought to look like based on the theory; they usually line up or only disagree a little. Every once and a while you encounter some bottom up sensory data that is so contradictory to your theory that you can't make any easy adjustment, so your brain enters a depressive state where it questions its own theory ruthlessly until it can figure out a better one. (spouse cheating, fired, death in family, didn't get into harvard, horrible disease, etc.) Peterson calls this the underworld. While in the underworld you need to tug at all those things you were willingly avoiding, to make a more sophisticated top down model of the world that can account for such anomalous data. Eventually, through bayescraft, your brain makes a better theory and your worldview is "resurrected." In Christian mythology Christ <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harrowing_of_Hell">literally descends into hell</a> while he is dead.</p>
      <p>The life of Christ, in Peterson's psychological terms, is an algorithm for willingly carrying out this process. If you want the truth, ruthlessly critique your own self understanding, find all the things you're most afraid of, and WILLINGLY DIE. Then you willingly descend into hell and "rescue your father from the belly of the whale." This strange phrase just means tradition is smarter than you, but also changes slowly, and thus when you get a really sophisticated mental model you're synthesizing the best ideas from culture with some new thing you're bringing to the table. You have to go to the underworld to find truth because all the stuff you don't know just happens to be the exact same things you're most afraid of learning about. (The Sequences are full of warnings about this.) At the end of this process you end up "resurrected" which just means you have a better map of reality that better fits the territory. This would let you climb the dominance hierarchy better, since that's what we mostly use our maps for, but that's more like a side effect. According to Peterson this algorithm, for some strange reason, just happens to line up with what your conscience usually tells you to do. That's what these (often mocked) <a href="https://imgur.com/r/destiny/R24Vv">diagrams</a> are supposed to represent. Although they go a bit further by adding a recursive and mythological element to it all. Essentially this process is fractal, repeating itself across all levels of reality and happening over and over again. It maps very strongly onto anti-fragility, the scientific method, and lesswrong rationalism in general.</p>
      <p>Note that this is not a standard christian message. It's psychology wrapped in mythological language, although it can map onto it just fine. Christians focus more on how, in light of the Resurrection, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7iqHPH_P7lw">the hierarchy is rendered meaningless</a>, (every lecture this guy has is amazing) and how Christ reveals that selfless love is the true nature of reality, going much deeper than the hierarchy ever could.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>