<post>
  <author>j9461701</author>
  <date>2020-01-21T02:09:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/er8kug/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_20/ff4u7f7/</link>
  <title>Manic Pixie Mary Sue Inflation</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Mary Sue and Manic Pixie Dream Girl. Both are examples of a broader trend I've noticed of terms for specific female characters becoming over-broad to the point they are used against all women everywhere. </p>
      <p>The Manic Pixie Dream Girl was a type of character criticized for having all the zaniness of a bar of zanes and no actual personality or inner life for herself. Her sole and only reason to existence on this Earth was to get the protagonist out of his shell, and beyond that she had no other objectives in life. When she's not on screen interacting with the brooding male lead she might as well enter cryogenic suspension for all she gets up to.  </p>
      <p>The Mary Sue was a criticism of self-insert fanfiction, which tended to insert vapid and ridiculous wish-fulfillment versions of the author into tv shows. The term comes from a parody of this trend, about a Lt. Mary Sue (the youngest Lt. in Starfleet history at 15 and a half!) joining the crew of the Enterprise. She instantly seduces Kirk, impresses Spock with her logic, and reveals she's half-Vulcan (she's just that special). She wins the Nobel Peace Prize for piloting the ship (somehow), before dying in sick bay surrounded by the men of the Enterprise weeping over how awesome she is. Seriously <a href="https://www.revolvy.com/page/Mary-Sue">read the story</a> the term comes from, it's like 200 words long. </p>
      <p>But over time the meanings devolved. Any woman who was a little strange or offbeat started getting blasted with the manic pixie label, even if they actually were fully fledged characters. It became a stick to beat weird women with, even translating bizarrely to real life. Zooey Deschanel strummed a ukele and got accused of being a real life manic pixie, which doesn't even make sense (it's like accusing a real human being of being 'poorly written'). The term became an absolute monster, a Frankensten that <a href="https://www.salon.com/control/2014/07/15/im_sorry_for_coining_the_phrase_manic_pixie_dream_girl/">even its inventor has come to disown</a> as a toxic concept. What was originally "Hey there's this one type of very specific one-dimensional girl character that shows up as basically a humanoid plot device in male-written fantasies" evolved into "Any kind of quirky girl interested in a man is a pixie dream girl". To quote Zoe Kazan:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.vulture.com/2012/07/zoe-kazan-ruby-sparks-interview.html">
          <em>I think that to lump together all individual, original quirky women under that rubric is to erase all difference. Like, I’ve read pieces that describe Annie Hall as a manic pixie dream girl. Katharine Hepburn in Bringing Up Baby. To me, those are fully fledged characters that are being played by really smart actresses. I just think it’s misogynist. I don’t want that term to survive. I want it to die.</em>
        </a>
      </p>
      <p>Mary Sue has also undergone a similar widening. The original Mary Sue is about a very specific fan fiction thing of absurd self-inserts, and that's it. It's mocking one exact kind of character. The only reason the parody didn't have Gary Stu instead of Mary Sue is <a href="https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/MostFanficWritersAreGirls">most fan fiction writers are female</a>, and so the mountains of garbage fanfic being pumped out tended to have female self inserts because the writers could relate to them more. The Mary Sue's primary traits are being a special snowflake (she's a half-vulcan), being supernaturally beloved \ beautiful (Kirk can't keep his hands off her!), and being implausibly intelligent. Notice no where in any of that did I mention power or strength. The Mary Sue outwits the alien menace rather than defeating them in combat, and in the end she dies of the Space Plague or whatever. Yet the term has absolutely exploded in meaning, and at this point can encompass almost any character who is not actively being beaten to death by a baseball bat. Somehow it tends to be women who have the term thrown at them, even when they fail to meet some or all of the criteria. For example Captain Marvel - she's barely tolerated by everyone around her, isn't particularly bright, and although lesbian reddit died of attraction when she revealed her short hair in Endgame she's not noted in-universe for being especially attractive. She's also not anyone's self-insert fan fiction character. She's an overpowered fantasy character sure, but so are Superman or Batman - none of them are Mary Sues under any sane definition of the term. </p>
      <p>So why do these tropes, that initially described very specific female characters, undergo a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inflation_(cosmology)">great inflation</a> until their definitions cover half the known universe? I think perhaps it's an example of pop culture telephone. One person invents a term, and it gets mangled slightly upon transmission. Then the next person repeats it, and it gets slightly more mangled. Until 100 people in you have <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o_o7UfqkNuU">purple monkey dishwashers</a>. The reason female tropes tend to be the most vulnerable to this is due to the low proportion of female writers and critics, which means purple monkey dish washer might pass through a hundred ears before it reaches the ears of someone who knows to correct it. Meanwhile a similar mangling of a male trope, say '80s action heroes are silly -&gt; Action Heroes are silly -&gt; Any man who picks up a gun is silly, gets corrected well before it ever gets so badly deformed from its original point. </p>
      <p>Thank you for coming to my pointless TEDTalk.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>