<post>
  <author>Karmaze</author>
  <date>2020-01-21T20:50:12Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/er8kug/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_20/ff72i84/</link>
  <title>GamerGate's Threat to Network Privilege</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Hoo boy. Some jumbled thoughts. I don't know how to write a single clear line through it all. First of all, I actually agree with what you say about the closing, that if you take it broader, and make it apply to more than just GG, there's some sense there. But, I think that's the point, to NOT allow that. </p>
      <p>First of all. It's not just young men. That's important to note. There were a lot of women involved in GG, some of which received pretty vicious abuse by opponents of GG. (Like my wife as an example, so it's somewhat personal, let me say) Trying to force down the idea that this is just Men vs. Women, and that the abuse was all one-sided, quite frankly, is just pure tribalism. </p>
      <p>Second, the timeline is wrong. GG wasn't "built" upon recruiting for the alt-right. It's the opposite. Some people in the alt-right saw an opening after people in the gaming journalism and elite communities told non-DudeBro gamers to go fuck themselves. I mean that's what happened. I'm a pretty strong opponent to the alt-right, but I can't begrudge them from doing that. I'd like people on the left to be making the same attempt going towards the right, and I support when they do. </p>
      <p>Third, I think there was some element of reaction to growing Progressive politics involved. Stereotypes about games and how gamers interacted with them, assuming all gamers were brutish DudeBros (both positively AND negatively. This is very important. I think the positive assumptions were just as damaging here) were bubbling up more and more in the media, which offended a lot of the core gaming player base, who simply don't identify in those traditional masculine tones in a lot of way. It's not that we're not men. It's just that...well..we're OK with playing an emotional jRPG or something like that. That's what we grew up with, that's our fondest gaming memories. Don't pave that over by trying to appeal to the monogamers. (My argument is that there's a segment of the gaming market who only plays 1-2 games a year, that's the most mainstream segment, and that's where a lot of the toxicity comes from. It's also clear that a lot of the gaming press wants to be like them) </p>
      <p>Fourth...</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>1) Police have to learn how to keep the rest of us safe from internet mobs</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You don't want that. Really. You don't want that. I still stand by the argument that there was a huge amount of false flagging going on during that whole thing. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>2) Businesses have to learn when online outrage is manufactured</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I.E. when it's not our tribe. </p>
      <p>This is the one that I think really reveals the game. I'm focusing largely on the ArenaNET example, with a writer who was absolutely shitty to a big streamer and promoter of the game, and got fired because of it. But going back up to the top, and back to probably IMO the quote that most drove GG forward in opposition against...</p>
      <p>No Bad Tactics, Only Bad Targets. </p>
      <p>I'll stand by this. I think GG touched a third rail by challenging social and network privilege. I think the idea that people with some social standing had to be under the same rules as the rest of us, was galling and threatening. Especially at the time, where YouTube and Twitch were growing and taking away more brainspace in that field. The big weapon the entrenched media had was...their connections essentially. And GG, unwittingly, was undermining that weapon. </p>
      <p>This is what IMO it's all about and it's still all about. It's about ensuring that this sort of privilege goes uncriticized. It's why static models of identity-based power dynamics that do not include things like social and networking status were widely embraced. It's why people who are of a lower perceived social status were widely perceived as an anchor preventing mainstream acceptance and status. </p>
      <p>The rules are for the little people. </p>
      <p>That's it in a nutshell, I think. Everything is reduced to social status hierarchies. That's the goal, the ideal. Things you can lock in, and entrench. That's what GG took a piss on, and why it still remains the poster child for evil to this day. And it's why people can't even GIVE AN INCH on this. GG has to be horrible and evil and terrible and disingenuous and liars and thieves and horrible in every single way bar none. Zero room for daylight on this. Because we cannot in anyway question this sort of privilege. It raises too many questions.</p>
      <p>REALLY REALLY LATE EDIT: I've been thinking about this for a while. And it really just occurred to me how important it is that last part. That not even a millimeter of space is given. Not even a nanometer. Absolutely zero. More actual credibility is given to White Supremacists than to GG-related or even neutral people. When framed that way, this becomes a super radical position that we're talking about here, kinda obviously. It should be a hint that there's something going on here underneath the surface. I stick to my argument that it's all about network privilege and social hierarchy and being wary of criticism of such, because of the potentially toxic implications of such criticism. </p>
      <p>If it's a thing, what we're looking at here is objection to being dunked in a vat of impostor syndrome, essentially. Which is what makes it so...existential I think. Now, I don't think this is unique. I actually think all forms of privilege theory and criticism have the same effect on some people. But it's a place where people are not willing to go, I think. Truth be told, not incorrectly, but still. But still. It's not like there's often hesitation about inflicting that on others.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>