<post>
  <author>Rabitology</author>
  <date>2020-01-20T23:36:37Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/er8kug/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_20/ff4h0c6/</link>
  <title>The Tribal Violence Hypothesis as Alternative to the Lead Hypothesis of Crime Rates</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I've always liked the lead hypothesis (along with the abortion hypothesis) as an example of creative thinking, but it's always just going to be a matter of correlation, and in general, the evidence for it looks best primarily when you only at it, and ignore everything else that was going on at the time.</p>
      <p>The most significant and obviously causative factor [1] is, and remains, the rise of globalized narcotics trafficking and distribution networks driven on the supply side by technological changes in transportation and communications infrastructure and on the demand side by the social revolution of the postwar generation in Europe and America.  This, combined in America with high rates of gun ownership and the after-effects of white flight from urban centers following the Civil Rights Movement is sufficient to account for most of an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Prohibition-era_gangsters">entirely precedented</a> increase in violent crime.</p>
      <p>The lead hypothesis is tempting to political left not only because, as you demonstrate above, it provides a narrative in which they are the heroes, but because it caters to a certain subconscious bias common on the left [2] in which the default human nature is reasoned, controlled and empathetic, and violent behavior when it occurs must be the result of some kind of defect, either in biology or, more commonly, socialization.  This cause - lead, poverty, racism - is always extrinsic to true human nature, distorting it and driving it to unnatural violence.</p>
      <p>Conservatives, I think with better historical and anthropological support, operate with a different perspective in which violence is a part of normal human behavior.  Humans, with their natural tendencies to violence, must be constrained in the expression of those tendencies not just by empathy (which is tribal), but by strong moral indoctrination.  Violence is not best explained by an extrinsic force that malforms the human soul, but rather by the opposite - by a <em>failure</em> to extrinsically mould a person to behave in prosocial ways.</p>
      <p>This is, I think, a better explanation for the rise in violent crime in the latter 20th century, which was not, overwhelmingly, sporadic violence inflicted by individuals with impaired self control, but targeted violence executed by criminal organizations with complex hierarchies, themselves enmeshed in larger territorial and political structures.</p>
      <p>In short, the violence was much more like that emerging in a series of conflicts between multiple tribes or small nation states than individual actors.  In this context, the conservative position that a failure to impose universal civic and familial norms resulted in localized reversions to more tribal forms of organization (and an honor culture) makes at least as much sense as lead poisoning.</p>
      <p>[1] In the sense of measurably leading directly to the most violent deaths.</p>
      <p>[2] Dating back to Rousseau.  The left has also inherited his concept of education, in which children are not to be constrained or indoctrinated.  Obviously, this also leads to conflicts with the right.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>