<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-01-22T15:59:58Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/er8kug/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_20/ff9awc5/</link>
  <title>Inherent Inequality: A Christian Perspective</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I don't know how any Christian who accepts the inherent equality of dignity of human beings could endorse this position. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>How they could endorse it? Well, it's a fundamental assumption of Christian theology. </p>
      <p>I'm in a theological mood today, and I actually still love this topic, so let's dive in. Remember, first off, the <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/01/31/the-parable-of-the-talents/">parable of the talents</a>. Linking Scott's take because it's simply one of the best out there, and it's true to the original parable:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And this is part of why it’s important for me to believe in innate ability, and especially differences in innate ability. If everything comes down to hard work and positive attitude, then God has every right to ask me “Why weren’t you Srinivasa Ramanujan?” or “Why weren’t you Elon Musk?”</p>
        <p>If everyone is legitimately a different person with a different brain and different talents and abilities, then all God gets to ask me is whether or not I was Scott Alexander. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Given the assumption of variations of inherent ability, even goodness, how can Christians jump to equal moral worth?</p>
      <p>Simply put: because everyone sucks. Sticking with talents as a measure, one person has 1, one person has 2, one person has 5. But the goal isn't 5, or 10, or 20. The goal is... well, I'll let the book of Matthew <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matthew+5:48&amp;version=KJV">present it</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Be ye therefore perfect, even as your Father which is in heaven is perfect.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Keep in mind that the instruction isn't "be a perfect human." The instruction is "<em>be as perfect as a being who is defined as the epitome of all goods</em>". And you're not doing that. So, no matter how much progress you've made and no matter where you are... you suck. You megasuck. You ultrasuck, really. You're just the worst.</p>
      <p>Now, people might object that such a goal is literally impossible. To which, canonically, God will shrug and say, "Well, it's still the goal." <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Romans+8&amp;version=ESV">After all</a>: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The Spirit himself bears witness with our spirit that we are children of God, and if children, then heirs—heirs of God and fellow heirs with Christ, provided we suffer with him in order that we may also be glorified with him.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Which parent would want their children to do worse than them?</p>
      <p>Oh, and speaking of parents, that gets to the third point, the whole "God loves you" thing. Scriptures are littered with references to the idea that God loves all his children, God is love, so on, so forth. Christianity, then, proceeds from four starting principles:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Everyone has different levels of inherent talent/goodness.</li>
        <li>Unfortunately, those differences are tiny relative to the chasm between you and God, and you all still suck.</li>
        <li>Fortunately, God loves you.</li>
        <li>...but he hates it when people suck, so you're going to need to stop sucking and become as perfect as he is.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Which is basically why Christianity puts so much emphasis on Christ's Atonement. Want to stop sucking? Cool, too bad the second- and third-order effects of your actions have still played a major part in making the world rubbish. No matter what you do, you won't be able to undo all those harms. Fortunately, someone literally perfect somehow became the primary injured party. For everything. And then he said that he'll help you become literally perfect as long as you... well, you all know the rest, and it varies between denomination. Jump through x, y, and z hoops, unless you're evangelical, in which case you just jump through x hoop.</p>
      <p>You get quite a few parables on this whole thing throughout the Gospels, often centered around debt:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Luke+7:41-43&amp;version=NIV">A creditor forgives both a massive debt and a small one. The one with the massive debt is naturally more grateful.</a> That is: Big and small sin can be forgiven.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matthew+18%3A21-35+&amp;version=NLT">Someone who owes a massive debt to the king shakes down another dude over a tiny one. So he's tossed in jail until he pays the massive debt the king had been ignoring</a>. That is: If you want to call someone out for sucking, be prepared for God to call you out for sucking infinitely more.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>So, in short, the answer is: Because ultimately there are massive differences between people, and they all pale in comparison to the biggest difference of all, which we'll help you overcome if you just sign here. Oh, and the one who's already perfect loves you even though you suck, so go ahead and love everyone too even though they suck worse.</p>
      <p>The ultimate goal is perfection. Nothing else is adequate. Until then, which other differences really matter?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>