<post>
  <author>4bpp</author>
  <date>2020-07-09T23:11:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fxh44qw/</link>
  <title>Male vs Female Socialization Regarding Bounded Conflict</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Good post, but there is one thing in it I want to push back against, and really would want to tell the author and anyone else in her position, because I think that it's an aspect of the male perspective on the "women are supposed to be demure and conflict-avoidant" view that is very opaque from the outside.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In meetings and 1:1 interactions, people get disproportionately upset with you if you bring a similar level of intensity, directness, or aggression to a discussion because it violates their held perception of how women ought to be on a subconscious level. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Everyone seems to be taking for granted that the "intensity, directness or aggression" in question is actually similar, or more specifically that there is a one-dimensional axis of intensity, directness or aggression that you just need to hit the right level on for perfect symmetry. The way I see it, though, this is not the case, and when women aim to go for a similar level of "intensity, directness or aggression", the result almost always comes across as as something between <em>antisocial</em> and <em>scary</em>. Now, it could be that this perception I have is just a consequence of me being socialised to perceive any female aggression in that way (I imagine that this is the most likely explanation from a feminist-informed female perspective, even), but I believe this is not the case bceause I have encountered (rare) women who can be aggressive without creating that perception in me, and it is not obvious to me what would exempt those individuals from this putative programming.</p>
      <p>So why is this? My theory on the matter is that in most societies we are familiar with, men, and largely only men, grow up from a young age developing and reinforcing social norms that enable them to engage in something like <em>bounded conflict</em>. This happens via playground fistfights, verbal one-upsmanship and silly competitions that can involve absolutely anything, from hitting a window with snowballs during recess to trying to see how much deliberate disturbance you can get away with during class before you are sent to stand outside. (All of these things, as I understand, are very far from anything that girls would ever be encouraged to also engage in for gender equality; in fact, the typical girl still would get praised for dismissing them as stupid boy behaviour.) However, even when these competitions are painful or objectively humiliating for the loser, boys' social norms strongly circumscribe the recourse available to them: you'd get ostracised for sneakily vandalising the locker of the guy who beat you up in an upfront fistfight, or for retaliating against someone who made you look stupid in a board game by making them look stupid in front of a teacher, or for inappropriately escalating even in a situation where a peer group makes you the perpetual low-status butt monkey of their jokes in a way that is seen as underhanded.</p>
      <p>Way down the line, this has the practical effect that if a male coworker viciously rips into the quality of the code you've written with a Linus-style rant, and you respond by digging up a bug in some script they've written up 2 years ago, and it's clear to both of you that the conflict is really about status and determining the team's common knowledge of which one of you is the better coder and most likely the next raise and therefore a bounty of multiple 100k$ is on the line in this context, you still both have a reasonable expectation that neither of you will escalate this by, say, planting a remark about your CEO being incompetent in the other party's slides for the next presentation or sending an anonymous tip to HR containing the username you use to post on <a href="/r/TheMotte">/r/TheMotte</a>. In fact, I can think of multiple instances in my own past where I had <em>vicious</em> professional disagreements with someone (being told things along the lines of "your theory is a load of crap and I bet you'd never dare trying to actually write up a proof of concept lest it be revealed that you are talking out of your ass" in a semi-public setting) that didn't deter either of us from getting drinks together afterwards in a perfectly amicable setting (without a PoC ever being written up or me ceasing the ass-talking).</p>
      <p>This expectation is probably reinforced by a myriad of subtle cues that were learned over those years of playground conflict. In my experience, women who try to be aggressive almost never convey any of those signals; and indeed, most people have heard second- or third-hand stories of aggressive women who did <em>not</em> in fact adhere to any code of bounded conflict, and retaliated against someone dunking on their code not by dunking back but by one or another underhanded move involving upper management. If I had to guess, the basic circumstance that you are signalling a willingness to engage in stand-in competition/"games" at all (as a clichéd example, would it occur to you to settle the preceding hypothetical conflict by proposing a two-stage process where you speed-write some code, like say a Minesweeper game, and then race each other to find a bug in the other person's code?) itself already goes a long way. Indeed, one common quality to all the women I've encountered who stood their ground without at the same time signalling that they might be willing to burn down my apartment and drown my cat before they lose was that they were avid video gamers (top &lt;1st percentile of time spent gaming among women, if I had to guess); I could imagine that this either trains bounded conflict norms, or at least selects for them.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>