<post>
  <author>ceveau</author>
  <date>2020-07-13T12:06:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fxx70fa/</link>
  <title>The Nazis Really Are to Blame and Other Thoughts</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The Holocaust was a consequence of the war effort. That's relevant, and it's not relevant as something that ameliorates Nazi culpability but rather worsens it. The Nazis were who marched on Poland. The Nazis were who marched on France. The Nazis were who bombed London and torpedoed ships in the Atlantic. The Nazis were who so foolishly marched on Russia. If their government had only expelled the Jews, and perhaps kept their word at the Sudetenland, or even only kept their word at Poland, this world would indeed look different. Their belligerence killed millions upon millions on the fronts, and it lead to the deaths of millions in camps. </p>
      <p>If the worst of the antisemites are right, it would be a terrible truth. If Jews were fundamentally incapable of living alongside the civilizations of Europe without attempting to destroy them, <em>that's a bad thing</em>, not only on the obvious level, but on the cruel hand dealt to all of us by fate. This is what I try to explain to people about the understanding of differences in biology. These are not good things. These are not things to be happy about, or smug about, or anything other than remorseful. If it is true it is a damned fact that there are dangerous biological differences between ethnic groups and it is our moral duty to change them - through the transhumanist promise of genetic engineering or technological enhancement. </p>
      <p>This isn't what I see in modern antisemites, and I believe it is the first indicator of their intellectual deficiency, something that started with the Nazis. They were not invaded first. They started the bloodshed. The same head that found the ideals of antisemitism so reasonable as to preside over the construction of concentration camps was also responsible for the extreme belligerence that lead to the Allied Invasion of Germany. Remember: they weren't doing it to save the Jews, they were doing it to stop Hitler. The Neonazi threads that post the line "No more brother wars" completely ignore that Nazi Germany started the biggest brother war of all time. </p>
      <p>We move to the present-ish.</p>
      <p>The Ashkenazim average IQ is 115, and I went to school where the minimum was 130. While I would describe a handful as actually intelligent, I would describe all but a handful as driven. This was a school of students who were the best-in-their-class types. They did their work and they did well. They went to schools, some prestigious but mostly average, and got jobs and are doing well for themselves. The 115 average means they are more "intelligent" (although I've already elaborated on my problem with that.) It also means they are more hardworking. It means lower outliers are ahead of our farther outliers, and it means their very far outliers are some of the best and brightest to ever live, and we know that to be true, just look at physics in the 20th century. There's a seminal piece of Japanese media called Ghost In The Shell: Stand Alone Complex. The Stand Alone Complex is the simulacrum, the copy without an original, the behavior of many, disconnected actors who unknowingly arrive at the same or similar goals. In the United States this meant Jews who grew up hearing about the Holocaust would each believe in "never again" and enough of them would achieve power and status to broadcast "never again" so that independent actors appear coordinated. I think this happens in many other places. </p>
      <p>I do believe there is a culture of quasi-nepotism. I believe Jews have high implicit trust of other Jews, either because in many cases they are vaguely related, or they grew up together and all went to the same Jewish holidays and celebrations, or the simple awareness of same culture: comforting similarities after a long history of persecution. If you're a Jewish person looking at resumes, and you see one other Jewish person, and you know they're from New York, and maybe you know something about a cousin or uncle of theirs, you know the similarity, and you're probably going to be more trusting, even before you consider that they'll know that Jewish resume person is statistically likely to be more intelligent. This culminates in the feedback loop: winners win, Jews hire Jews. When they all seem to push the same political agenda, it seems like a conspiracy, but I don't think it is one. </p>
      <p>This returns us to my point about Eisenhower. There is an issue I see constantly in debates, it's a failing I've taken to labeling the Fallacy of Lost Consequences, but it might be better described as the cognitive equivalent of the off-by-one error.<sup><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Off-by-one_error">2</a></sup> It's where someone misses a crucial step in the consequences of their plans to save the world, or their hypothesis about a world-running conspiracy. They're off-by-one. If a global conspiracy controlled Eisenhower, it runs the world, and it <em>deserves to</em>. If a global Jewish cabal dictates society, including controlling Trump, they <em>especially</em> deserve to rule the world. Now, more than ever, the idea of a shadow group secretly running the show for decades, and this all still being their plan, means there's nothing that can be done to stop them.</p>
      <p>But I don't think it's that. I think it's the simulacrum, I think it's pathological altruism and I think it's the motivation of popularity and the inclination to "sheepishness" that plagues the intelligent-but-not-intelligent-enough. Therein lies what I call the danger zone of IQ. Smart enough to do well in school, smart enough to get a good job, smart enough to be a good mover in a PAC, but still so unintelligent that they don't recognize their own inadequacy. They forge their convictions into dumb steel, firmly believing that they are right and any who oppose them are either ignorant or evil. Because of the significant amount of Jews between 100 and 140 IQ, I believe this must affect them more than any other ethnic group, and given that altruism will naturally affect more women, a culture with such prominent women will have that effect exaggerated even further. </p>
      <p>This makes for a highly skilled but still malleable core of useful idiots, and that makes it simple. They are the ones most visibly controlled by the wealthy. This is simple, it's not even a conspiracy theory, really. Jeff Bezos is worth 180 billion dollars. Bill Gates has variously floated at around 100 billion dollars in net worth. Why wouldn't you expect these men to have great issue with the knowledge that any random person on the street theoretically has as much political effect as them?: one vote each. Elon Musk started a company that's now launching rockets to resupply the ISS and researching sustainable space habitation, why wouldn't he think of a critical journalist as a pathetic ant in the grand scheme of human history? </p>
      <p>So this is my answer.</p>
      <p>• Antisemitism seems to consistently occur with other intellectual failures and I do not trust anyone who does not understand that if it's true, it's damnable </p>
      <p>• People in the danger zone of IQ are particularly vulnerable to pathological altruism. A higher number of American Jews than other ethnic groups are in the zone, and Jews are also culturally inclined to some vulnerability. This is why they appear to have so consistent political leanings.</p>
      <p>• American Jews have good structures in place in this country to get into schools and jobs, meaning they are more likely to be in a position where they can do 
something with that altruism. This is why they seem to be so "present."</p>
      <p>• They're still footsoldiers (again, useful idiots) for the people actually controlling everything, which only includes Jews because it includes the wealthy, of which there are many Jews for reasons explained above</p>
      <p>• The debate on the solution for this could take up an entire culture war thread worth of comments</p>
      <p>• Assuming society doesn't fall apart, Humans are probably going to be bizarre, engineered and synthetic things in probably 100 years, let alone 1000</p>
      <p>• Oh, and astronomical engineering is still an extreme meritocracy, and as long as society stands and people like Elon Musk have adequate control of their corporations, there won't be an issue of corruption of their efforts</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>