<post>
  <author>georgioz</author>
  <date>2020-07-13T16:55:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fxy1gku/</link>
  <title>WWI: A Generation that Lost More Than Just Their Lives</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>That makes a figure like "roughly 7/8ths of soldiers were able to return home alive" become worldview upending for me.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>While technically true, this at least does not do justice to the two main belligerents - Germany and France (and in part Russia). There was literally whole generation up there in trenches of horrible offensives and counteroffensives in West and East. Majority of them got killed or wounded. Others saw their friends literally evaporated  by artillery fire. This caused unimaginable scars, PTSD and other horrors. I hate to do this but in the past when I studied this topic I was most disturbed by mental toll the war took on its victims. There is this video about PTSD/Shellshock and I have <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SS1dO0JC2EE">this</a> short video imprinted in my mind. But I am most horrified by sight of the guy around 42 seconds into the video. This is the face of pure terror. This is what you could encounter among the 7 of 8 soldiers returning home on daily basis in France or Germany. And I also studied some sources and the truth is that vast majority of people just could not live in those conditions. Even the most brave were grounded to smithereens mentally after 100-200 days. It is not about your resilience or bravado. You will eventually be grounded to horrible state in one way or another. This is another side of the lost generation - even if you return with all limbs back to home. </p>
      <p>And they did not return to some paradise. They returned to countries in economical collapse, with radicals on left and right vying for power. Not to even talk about millions of orphans and limbless veterans roaming the cities before social security was widespread. This was truly life-changing experience. </p>
      <p>I also think that it was era changing experience. The old world was dead and modernity took hold. Art, politics, science and everything was on fast forward from then on. Everything was in flux and people scrambled for scraps while at the same time new opportunities awaited this grizzled generation that went through such a hell. </p>
      <p>In many ways the trench warfare in the west in my mind is akin to what it has to look like in hell. I remember listening to one of the podcasts where a soldier is about to attack over the top. And he was the lookout for the artillery barrage. The cadence of artillery grenades took to crescendo level. You had explosions - bam ... bambambam - bam - bam - bambambambam - going for hours. He saw an old tree trunk thrown into the air by artillery grenade only for it to be hit by yet another grenade grounding it to splinters. He mentioned it as if God played with matchsticks. He was in fear and awe at the same time. And then the whistle was blown and thousands of soldiers went into that hellscape as sheep many not to return. His legs moving as if on their own accord - like when you are at stadium of 50,000 and all people start to cheer. </p>
      <p>I do not think any war movie can do it justice. On august 27th 1914 there were 27,000 Frenchmen killed in one day during the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_the_Frontiers">Battle of the Frontiers</a>. That is half the combat deaths USA saw in whole Vietnam war just in one day. All the French casualties in Battle of France during WW2 were 300,000 dead missing and wounded. In a way WW1 was order of magnitude more deadly - at least for western allies. The Germans and Soviets is where the tragedy lies for WW2 and nobody pays that much attention to the war casualties of second "lost generation" in the chaos that ensued.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>