<post>
  <author>INH5</author>
  <date>2020-07-11T05:29:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fxlzrhj/</link>
  <title>Deplatforming in the Wake of 9/11</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I found <a href="https://fair.org/press-release/some-critical-media-voices-face-censorship/">this article</a> from April 2003 while researching media censorship and self-censorship in the aftermath of 9/11, in an attempt to see how it compares to similar issues today. It turns out that things were even worse than I had remembered. The article describes multiple examples of reporters getting fired for expressing opposition to the Iraq War, including from liberal outfits such as MSNBC and (I assume) the San Francisco Chronicle. It wasn't just a "right wing" thing.</p>
      <p>The most interesting part, to me, is that apparently even some websites had difficulties with web hosting companies due to publishing anti-war content:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The website YellowTimes.org, which featured original anti-war reporting and commentary, was shut down by its Web hosting company on March 24, after it posted images of U.S. POWs and Iraqi civilian victims of the war. Orlando-based Vortech Hosting told Yellow Times in an e-mail, “Your account has been suspended because [of] inappropriate graphic material.” Later, the company clarified: “As ‘NO’ TV station in the U.S. is allowing any dead U.S. soldiers or POWs to be displayed and we will not either.” As of April 3, the site was still down.</p>
        <p>The Qatar-based Al-Jazeera news network’s attempts to set up an English-language website were foiled by unidentified hackers who launched a denial-of-service attack. Al-Jazeera is expected to try to relaunch its site in mid-April. The station’s reporters also had their press credentials revoked by the New York Stock Exchange, and were unable to obtain alternative credentials at the NASDAQ exchange: “In light of Al-Jazeera‘s recent conduct during the war, in which they have broadcast footage of U.S. POWs in alleged violation of the Geneva Convention, they are not welcome to broadcast from our facility at this time,” a NASDAQ spokesperson told the Los Angeles Times (3/26/03).</p>
        <p>Addendum, 4/7/03: Al-Jazeera‘s English-language website is, at the moment, available at english.aljazeera.net/, despite losing their contract with their U.S. hosting company (New York Times, 4/4/03).</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The average person wasn't impacted as much back then, because there was no equivalent to Twitter and so on, but I still think that we can say that we've not only been here before, we've been here before in living memory. Hopefully our current "moment" won't turn out as badly as the last one did.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>