<post>
  <author>JustAWellwisher</author>
  <date>2020-07-14T04:08:19Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fy05wod/</link>
  <title>The Key Elements of Cancel Culture</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I've been thinking a lot lately about this too and I think there are a few points which I regard as the key elements to cancel culture or the "new" and "interesting" part of it that makes it a thing.</p>
      <p>1 - The disproportionality of the social ramifications for faux pas.</p>
      <p>This is pretty simple. You say something people disagree with, it's open season on your character, your platform, your source of income. Trying to destroy someone's livelihood is not just freedom of expression or acquaintance, it's an active effort to take away someone else's freedom of expression and acquaintance by leveraging social power against institutions and people. It's not just a person's decision to boycott; it's the collective pressure on everyone to boycott. This brings us to...</p>
      <p>2 - The new level of social coordination of large scale mobbing.</p>
      <p>Places exist now where people can go to discuss and organize their brigades. I'm going to draw on comparisons with cancel culture's predecessor in online terms - anonymous. 4chan and anonymous had a norm they could implement whenever anyone wanted to start a fight somewhere. "We are not your personal army". There is no comparable internet social norm on twitter or on reddit etc. today.</p>
      <p>3 - Growing internet identitarianism.</p>
      <p>The internet has moved away from anonymity or pseudonymity and towards identity. Who you are online today is supposed to be a persona or a representation of who you truly are. It used to be that people online would use the term "IRL" (In Real Life) to refer to their persona and identity away from the internet. Well, people from that generation need to understand that the new generation grew up already learning that social media is real life. What they do online isn't a game avatar, isn't a persona. The person on the other keyboard or the phone matters. Not in the fluffy idealistic way that sounds like someone forcing their morals on you, in the hard, rubber meets the road realistic way where this is the way the new generation of people in online spaces developed their norms on the internet. The internet is real life now. People who have never understood anonymity don't understand that a death threat from a random anonymous stranger online is generally speaking utterly meaningless and just an impotent expression of anger. Which brings us to...</p>
      <p>4 - Norms around doxxing have weakened considerably.</p>
      <p>This isn't about the new internet being anti-privacy or anti-anonymity. This is about the new internet being pro-signalling and pro-celebrity and pro-data. You have to <em>be</em> someone online and people who feel they are someone online feel the need to force others to <em>be</em> online too. When one anonymous, or mostly anonymous person is harassing another mostly anonymous person, then <a href="https://i.imgur.com/Dl1D3vz.jpg">How The Fuck Is Cyberbullying Real Hahahaha</a>dotjpg (Feel the compression artifacts from how much that image has been shared). When an anonymous person is harassing someone with an identity, then anything about that person's real life is at stake and on the table. The anti-doxxing norms of the internet are from an era when anonymous mobs were powerful and we understood they were powerful but also, we understood the power and liberation of anonymity as an individual. Every piece of social progress in the last 20 years I strongly believe pays a massive debt to the liberation of anonymity and pseudonymity.</p>
      <p>The power now flows in the opposite direction. People with identities, people with communities, people with money and real power, not the ddos botnet of thousands of nerds or their shitty individualistic pranks, but the companies in place that provide the systems which protect against the ddos (e.g. cloudflare) are providing vectors of attack for people who want to destroy someone else's online, if not anonymous, mostly private life. <a href="https://medium.com/@jesse.singal/planet-of-cops-50889004904d">It's a planet of cops</a>.</p>
      <p>I want to be clear that I'm presenting two different generations of online anarchism here. I consider Anonymous to be the most successful anarchist community to ever have existed in the history of the world. When anarchists imagine their perfect society, a society where everyone is a cop, where everyone is self-policing to the point where we don't need police, is what they imagine. Anonymous was not like that, anonymous worked mainly because in an environment where everyone is anonymous, you don't actually have much power to do anything against anyone else. But most people wouldn't believe that the 4chan trolls of the last generation are almost entirely left-libertarians and anarchists. If not explicitly anarchist in their ideology, their actions, rules and their community structure absolutely were.</p>
      <p>And here's the hot take - modern 4chan and the alt-right... are also anarchists. At the very least they are the second generations of a still-anarchist system. But to understand that you need to understand that none of them care about real world politics. They don't live in the real world. They live online. They are culture-war anarchists. To normies, they look like they're on the far right of politics, but that assumes these people are actually interested in real life politics. They're not, and if you take your online persona into the real world, they will call you a LARPer.</p>
      <p>"Ignore the trolls" is no longer part of the online culture. Now the trolls are a tool, to be wielded by people with infrastructure and power against the commons. That the trolls are mostly harmless is now a secret. Play up their offensiveness. Play up the harm they cause. Become the fear-monger. You don't have to enforce the new rules, you just need to make people afraid enough of other people, the bad people, to self-police so no bad people ever even think of settling in. That's why dogwhistles and speech codes are so important now. When someone says "X community is a hotbed for Y extremists" usually they're just recognizing that their own speech codes aren't the dominant ones. It can be as simple as the group normalizing the word "sinful" to talk about a communally bad thing instead of "problematic". Or vice versa. They're playing another language game, one that people have intuited has privileged or allowed for the coexistence of a certain other group and moral framework. (Then because of outgroup homogeneity bias people code-match that with their enemies)</p>
      <p>5 - Chilling Effects</p>
      <p>The conversation about free speech online, at least at the meme-level which pervades the culture war, is completely bare of the concept of Chilling Effects. If you're not familiar with a "Chilling Effect" it's the scenario where people are discouraged to exercise their rights due to the <em>threat</em> of legal consequences, not because there actually exists a law against the thing. It's a type of suppression brought about by intended confusion about the broadness and scope of a law. In spaces where free speech is an ideological priority, people aren't just in favor of free speech, they actively fight against chilling effects on speech. People like this new meme "freedom of speech doesn't mean freedom from consequences" - notice how this meme is purposefully vague on the scope of the consequences and how it places this concept as inverted to the scope of the speech.</p>
      <p>So what you get is stricter speech, broader consequences.</p>
      <p>Not just more speech. It's not just more people expressing their own right to associate and speak how they wish. This is the distinction. Cancel culture is in favor of more consequences. More punishment. More shame. More aggressive anti-speech norms. More expressions of power against speech. More speaking power to truth and taking the power of speech away.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Network neutrality is a consumer issue. But it is also one of the foremost free speech issues of our time. Freedom of expression isn't worth much if the forums where people actually make use of it are not themselves free.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Why The Government Must Act To Preserve The Free And Open Internet<a href="https://www.aclu.org/sites/default/files/field_document/netneutrality_report_20101021.pdf">- ACLU, 2010</a></p>
      <p>That would be a pretty radical statement not 10 years later. The forums where people make use of their freedom of expression should themselves be free. Whatever the case, this is not the predominant sentiment. Even among those who would rather go back to days of more freedom, you'll find more people arguing about how [enemy group] deserves to be punished/banned too. There's no sense in which people feel they can fight the tide on the growing predilection for institutions and groups to control and monitor people further.</p>
      <p>tl;dr: The people who can't see that cancel culture is real can't see it because it's the water that they swim in. They never had the experience of their parents doubting the people they talked with online are "real friends", they didn't live through the time when online dating was considered extremely odd. Online dating now is just dating. Online friends are just friends. And what you say and do online is now who you are. That's why speech is now violence and people feel it needs to be controlled.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>