<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-07-16T15:47:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fy9gxbn/</link>
  <title>Pax Americana: 1945 - 2020</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>If just 3 months ago you had said you Expected Autonomous Zones to be declared in Major Cities and patrolled by AR-15 wielding Radicals, Thousands of buildings to burn in dozens of cities, People to die getting shot at checkpoints established by vague groups of political “activists” and others to die under tire as panicked drivers try to run the blockade, armed militias storming state legislatures, young mothers to be shot and killed for repeating a popular (and until 2014 uncontroversial) sentiment... and for there to be ongoing medieval federal buildings a month and a half later?</p>
      <p>I mean most would say you were predicting civil war.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Beyond that if you had predicted any of 2020 in the final weeks of 2019... you’d have been laughed out of the room as having watched too much <em>escape from New York</em>. </p>
      <p>Think of it this way if you had Predicted the Border between Canada and The US to be closed....just that. Something utterly ignored in light of everything else. You’d have been predicting an economic and geopolitical upset in North America unparalleled after the War of 1812, with the Exception of the US civil war (where that border remained open, but another formed to its south).</p>
      <p>It feels like stuff has been dragging, but thats just because so much has happened in 6 months its exhausting... </p>
      <p>To quote Napoleon: “There are decades in which weeks happen, and weeks in which decades happen” we’re really in the latter and thats only going to intensify at-least until election day and probably after.</p>
      <p>It terms of important Years where everything changed... this is probably on a par with 1939. My suspicion is no matter what happens, we’ll probably start referring to  “Post-war Era America” as a period which existed between 1945 and 2020.</p>
      <p>Think of it another way. Before whenever you wanted to poo-poo the culture  war you’d say “America’s seen worse. There were 2000 explosives that went off in 1972” (See <em>days of Rage</em> on the weather underground) now it might well be that that many buildings have burned down, and atleast that many homemade m80 type bombs have been launched directly at the police (far more violent than the weather underground who’d phone in bomb threats so the buildings would be evacuated and no one would get hurt).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>