<post>
  <author>Lykurg480</author>
  <date>2020-07-09T20:42:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fxgmddd/</link>
  <title>Freedoms Political and Metaphysical</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A while ago, <a href="/u/TracingWoodgrains">u/TracingWoodgrains</a><a href="/r/TheMotte/comments/ffprqc/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_09_2020/fk56wj0/?context=3">wondered</a> that radical leftist movements often dont articulate a positive description of the good future after the revolution (BTW, is that book review still coming?). Well, I might have a theory.</p>
      <p>I recently read <a href="https://palladiummag.com/2020/03/26/how-to-find-meaning-when-everything-is-power/">this article</a>. Its the story of the authors psychological struggle with that-which-we-call-postmodernism. I cant really excerpt the part that interests me because its scattered throughout, so Ill just pull a quote and say its the things most related to it:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>All activities, goes the claim, are tainted by the toxic operations of overdetermined systems of oppressive social meaning which speak through us and over us regardless of what little agency we might imagine ourselves to have. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This reminded me of something. You are propably familiar with the Free Will debate: Determinism says that everything we do is ultimately caused by events before our birth or even at the beginning of the world (plus maybe some quantum coinflips. But theyre just that – coinflips, not decisions of the spirit), and therefore we dont have free will. Libertarianism (namespace collision error) says that no, there is an independent causality of freedom which allows us to make our own decisions, and therefore we have free will. Compatibilism says that even though everything is physically caused, some physical processes <em>are us</em>, and so their result doesnt determine our decisions but <em>is</em> our decision.</p>
      <p>Compatibilism is a popular view today, but, I would argue, often incomplete. Compatibilism is generally established only by abstract argument: Its conceivable that the decisions of a physical process might be ours, thats the only way for free will to exist if science is true, and it sure seems like we have free will. The remaining problem, then, is to fully understand the brain and determine which processes are us. </p>
      <p>The problem with this is that there is a big difference between believing in the abstract that everything you do is physically caused, and actually having a gears-level model that allows you to predict which decisions are made. And its not a matter of which model specifically; the mere fact that you are <em>actually</em> connecting outside conditions to decisions instead of just talking about it greatly influences the intuition, irrespective of which connections those are.</p>
      <p>Whenever we understand such a model, even if only for part of our behaviour, our intuition flags it as "mere physical process, not-me". Indeed, this is often how the debate starts off – someone learns of such a model ("the patient occasionally screams when its too bright because of his brain tumor" – but insert something you actually understand here, not something where you only know a one-sentence summary like that) and concludes it is not-me, just a physical process controlling that poor patient. And when they learn more, maybe about brain-functioning in general, that is where the worries start. Uh, so much of behaviour controlled by mere physical processes, it might be all, is there even such a thing as freedom? Its rare that someone immediately understands the abstract statement "all behaviour is physically caused", and comes to the dilemma from just that.</p>
      <p>And when someone is convinced of compatibilism by abstract argument, these intuitions dont just change. It still dings "mere physical process, not-me" whenever you scan a model that you understand in detail. Youve learned that the first part is propably confused and throw it away, but you still listen to that second part - after all, you need to find out which process you are. But that intuition still always answers in the negative once you fully understand something. But you dont know that. You dont have introspective access to your intuitive algorithm, and even if you did, it wouldnt have to be obvious that it does that. So you will keep having a few things you vaguely model, and suspect have free will inside them, and then when you learn about one in more detail, disappointment, and renewed focus on the remaining things. And especially, if I asked you to give an example of a physical process that would make free decisions if it were real, you would only be able to do so vaguely, by describing absences rather than presence, and definitely not as a computable model. So we keep looking for a self in the physical world, even when we can never find it by our current standards.</p>
      <p>Back to the article, I think part of what she is describing is a similar kind of process. She has learned a theory that predicts behaviour (true or not, it doesnt matter here), but it is sociological rather than neurobiology, and so the identified "not-me, mere cultural process" are classed not as a medical condition limting your freedom, but as political circumstance limiting your freedom, oppression in short. (We also dont enter the philosophical/metaphyiscal discussion, because politics is man made, and so it seems ridiculous to go from political unfreedom to philosophical, in-principle unfreedom.) And so a political solution is called for. But we have the same problem as above, were we still feel like any detailed model of our behaviour describes an outside process limiting us. And any concrete something that could be happening instead of the current system is just such a model, when thought about sufficiently clearly. </p>
      <p>Hence the inability to positively describe an alternative: When described in enough detail, it will always be found wanting, and inquisitive minds will naturally push their new idea to this level after having seen an example in the original descriptive theory. Among the less inquisitive, the criticism still can come from somewhere in the movement even if not everyone does it themselves, leading to a constant churn of utopic visions. Some groups might even develop the belief that such visions are always oppressive and will always be in further need of critique, always allowing for a longer list of demanded absences.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>