<post>
  <author>Rov_Scam</author>
  <date>2020-07-09T23:24:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fxh5ixp/</link>
  <title>The Difficulties in Defining and Enforcement Regarding Transgenderism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>You're assuming that "transitioning" in the normal understanding of the term would be required in order to switch teams. If this process is as difficult as you suggest (and I'm inclined to believe that it is), it would seem like the school would be entering quite the minefield if they were to tell minors that the only way they could participate on the sports team of the gender they identify with is to take potentially dangerous drugs. The belief is that trans women are women, period, not that trans women are women, provided they maintain sex-appropriate hormone levels. </p>
      <p>Years ago I worked as an attorney for the disability determination bureau of the Social Security Administration, and at first I was surprised at how lax the rules were with respect to "self help". For example, say a guy is applying for disability because knee problems have made it impossible for him to do his job, which requires a lot of lifting and moving around. His medical records show that he has a relatively common problem that is easily managed through OTC anti-inflammatrories like Motrin and physical therapy. At worst, straightforward outpatient surgery followed by drugs and PT almost always takes care of the problem. But this guy hasn't tried any of it. He would still qualify for disability regardless (assuming the other qualifications were met). There are a number of reasons why a person might not want to take drugs or undergo medical procedures, and the government is generally loathe to condition rights and entitlements upon them. </p>
      <p>Imagine this taking place in any other context. An employer hires an employee who is biologically male but dresses stereotypically female and wants to use the women's restroom. She doesn't pass very well. I doubt trans activists would be okay if the employer started asking for medical records or other documentation, or started delving into her personal life, just to make sure that she was "legitimately" transgendered and not just putting everyone on. That has, in my estimation, been the biggest issue with respect to trans rights generally. When this issue first appeared, I remarked to some left leaning friends that it would be problematic when perverts started wearing dresses and entering the women's locker rooms at gyms and public pools. The response was along the lines of "the rules would only apply to people who are legitimately transgender", but that isn't really feasible. First of all, you would have to define womanhood which would itself be contentious, and then you'd have to institute an enforcement system, which wouldn't only impose a severe burden on trans people but also on cis people who would now have to demonstrate their birth sex. </p>
      <p>I've told this story here before, but it's worth repeating. There's a wealthy suburban school near me that had two boys demanding to be allowed to play girls field hockey. Their argument was that Title IX required equal opportunity, and there was no boys  field hockey team, and the school ruled that they had to be admitted. This unleashed a fury among women's rights advocates in the area (mostly in letters to the editor, but still), and the coach smugly noted that they wouldn't be granted and uniform modifications and thus would have to play in skirts. When this was in the news I assumed, like most people probably did, that the boys in question had played field hockey recreationally and now wanted to play for the school team. My cousin, who was attending the school at the time, told me otherwise: They were two asshats that nobosy liked who had never played field hockey before in their lives and were demanding access more as a stunt than anything else. They were also the best players on the team by far, so the coach was pretty much obligated to play them, and it pissed off opposing coaches to no end. So no, I wouldn't assume that this won't result in scores of boys claiming to be trans to get access to athletic opportunities they might not otherwise have.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>