<post>
  <author>Vincent_Waters</author>
  <date>2020-07-13T16:49:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fxy0oev/</link>
  <title>An Interpretative History of /r/TheMotte and its Predecessors</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The Motte could use some historians, honestly. Someone should dump all the threads before we get banned. At the risk of consensus building, I can tell my own version of history, full of interpretive bias.</p>
      <p>To start off with, it's important to note that the Rationalist community has <em>always</em> been full of rebels-against-the-left. This includes some rightists, but also many leftists who noticed some of the glaring flaws in mainstream left-wing thought (the "Synopsis"). SSC comes from this tradition, and gained much of its popularity complaining about feminists (come for <em>Untitled</em>, stay for <em>Meditations on Moloch</em>). Going back even to Less Wrong, one of Eliezer's main arguments was that the "sanity water line", including and perhaps especially the authorities in left-wing institutions (universities+journalists), was so low as to be sneer worthy. There has therefore always been an inherently reactionary feel to the Rationalist community, that puts it somewhat outside the good graces of the left. </p>
      <p>Now let's consider the state of the culture war itself in the 2010's. There is, essentially, no doubt who the "aggressor" is in this war; it goes without saying that it's the Blue Tribe. But in fact, once you've conceptualized the idea the that what we really have is two tribes competing to impose their values on one another, things immediately start to look very dark for the Blue Tribe. <em>White Fragility</em> is really code word for <em>Red Tribe Fragility</em>, etc. And in fact, you don't really see the inverse, perhaps due to the sheer power differential between the two groups. The right occasionally tries to use similar tactics, but it's mostly embarrassing for all involved. Once you've named the Blue Tribe, it's perfectly obvious that they are almost entirely in power, and that even many Republican politicians are part of the Blue Tribe. The standard argument that Fox News is the most watched news network and that Donald Trump, and therefore the Red Tribe, is in power, really do not stand up to any kind of scrutiny. </p>
      <p>The net result of all of this is that whole idea of the 2010's culture war is <em>inherently</em> red-coded. Most Blue Tribers, if they realized that what they were doing is trying to impose their tribe's beliefs on a weaker tribe, would lose their willingness to fight; the very idea is sort of a contradiction to leftist thought. There is therefore a willful veil of ignorance, and if you try to discuss the idea of the culture war and these tribes with most Blue Tribers, they will simply reject the framing. So again, the framing is inherently red-tribe in some sense, and if you engage with the frame for long enough, you'll find that it lends itself to right-wing interpretations much more readily.</p>
      <p>So what do we make of leftists who accept the framing that they're a member of a powerful tribe trying to enforce their beliefs on a weaker tribe? This is very strange and rare creature indeed. One thing they can do is just be openly mean; this is the Sneer Club approach in a nutshell. Consider the British sneering at the disorderly and untrained American troops during the American Revolution. Warranted, but perhaps they would not be so disheveled if you had allowed them to raise an army whilst you were still in power? The disheveledness of the thought and arguments found in this thread are a consequence of the fact that there is no legitimate institutional training ground for these ideas. As a result, they are clearly far less refined than the ideas supported by extremely large and powerful institutions. Another analogy is early Protestant thought; it was relatively course and sneer-worthy compared to the immensely well-developed Catholic theology. It was easy to prosecute proto-Protestants because they had little power and their ideas weren't very good to begin with.</p>
      <p>Okay, but what do we make of the powerful tribe members who come into the culture war threads and try to persuade us of the Blue Tribe view? To start with, it seems like a fairly hopeless mission from the onset. Most of us are not Red Tribers who have not been shown the light of the one-true-worldview, but are in fact disaffected Blue Tribers with a very strong understanding of leftist thought. It is much harder to bring a Protestant or Atheist back to the Church than it is to convert a barbarian. So it's a somewhat hopeless mission. So anyone who came here with that mission is totally doomed to failure, and if they try, they will quickly get frustrated, ending with a flame-out and a ban.</p>
      <p>What other goals might such a person have? We could try the charitable interpretation: They actually would like to strengthen their world view by exposing it to counterarguments. There are essentially two outcomes that may result. One is that they will actually quietly fall prey to the more popular views here. While the arguments found here are not as sophisticated as Catholic theology, they are probably much higher quality than what you will hear from Trump, Fox News, or that one random conservative Facebook friend, so there is some probability that people will actually experience radical shifts in their worldview over time.</p>
      <p>Another outcome is that this person simply succeeds at fortifying their beliefs. Once these fortifications are built, what is the sense in staying around longer? They may occasionally drop in during major events to refortify. But overall, there will be no major sense of progress. One of the main goals of right-wing posters here is to develop <em>new</em> systems of thought. The thread is sometimes thought of as "right-wing" but this is true only in its opposition to the left; there's not a mainstream system of thought that posters here fall into (nor is there any kind of consensus among posters). The goal of left-wing posters in this category is therefore... to defend an existing system of thought? It's not nearly as compelling of a project. You're not likely to find such a person changing their mind; the outcome is already decided, it's just a matter of deciding the maximally effective argument. This is more like the activity of a lawyer than a philosopher. These people will simply eventually get bored.</p>
      <p>What happens to left-wing posters? They either get bored and leave or flame-out and get banned. The flame-out posts usually involve the admission that they think we're racists and that they hated us all along, or something. To be fair, there have also been many flame-out posts from right-wing posters who either come to accept conflict theory and want to convert this forum to a conflict theory forum, or get frustrated that we're not alt-right enough. That's about it, though. There was no Exodus.</p>
      <p>Well, this turned into 100% interpretation and 0 concrete history. It turns out it's pretty hard to find anything concrete to link to... Who wants to bothering to going through the effort of finding Impassionata's flame-out post, for instance? And there are certainly no secondary sources.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>