<post>
  <note>Another one with missing context.</note>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2021-04-22T15:46:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mtuhyd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_19_2021/gvgfdkd/</link>
  <title>To Interface With Reality Like That, Yuck</title>
  <category>
    <li>knowledge</li>
    <li>culture</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>You are assuming that their job is to "be right" and then get confused when they are not fired for being wrong. But that's not their job at all, and their real job is not necessarily very easy either.</p>
      <p>There are also different levels in this. The footsoldiers who do the low level work of writing up low-readership articles involving trendy narratives are not very high status and their job is not particularly hard. One step above that you need more creative thought and better "doublethink" capabilities, which do require intelligence, foreseeing potential no-no implications, knowing who to praise, who to bash etc.</p>
      <p>These people don't necessarily get explicit instructions on what's the "current agenda", they have to use their social skills, networks and experience to smell the incentives. In some cases, though, especially the lower level footsoldier journalists will indeed get blatant and explicit instruction on how to frame current issues and how not to frame them, what info to emphasize and what to leave out.</p>
      <p>Just like a lawyer isn't "wrong" if it turns out his client was guilty and therefore his argument was wrong. It is his job to argue in favor of his client, whether right or wrong, true or false. This doesn't mean that being a lawyer is easy. Similarly, it requires tactical skill to navigate politics and public opinion leadership. You can't just say random shit, you need to say stuff that elevates the prestige and status of your side. This is what people and corporations will pay big bucks for.</p>
      <p>As a rule of thumb, if you <em>can</em> be unambiguously wrong in your job, you aren't elite/high-status. Political/managerial people will always look down on technical jobs as if they were some kind of janitor stuff. Yeah, of course you can be "wrong" in your job, when you push the wrong buttons or forget to do some step you were trained to do. Just like a janitor is wrong if he forgets to lock the door or fails to scrub off that coffee stain from the table, duh.</p>
      <p>A real high-status person makes sure to never get into such dirty situation where he has to interface with reality like that, yuck. <em>He</em> defines the standard and he gets to <em>re</em>define it the next time.</p>
      <p>You as a sysadmin simply maintain infrastructure, like a sailor who sews up the tears in the sail on a ship. But where the ship goes is decided by others, based on politics and power struggles. Similarly what gets computed (with what business goals) on those servers you maintain depends on the higher level people. When the sail tears again, you know you were wrong. But whether it was a good idea to create a trading alliance with country A as opposed to country B is much more opinion based and involves lots of counterfactuals.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Long story short, my job consists of 4 main things: automating processes (mostly in PowerShell but other languages occasionally), helping our developers get their apps set up, regular sys admin activities, and basically being the tier 3 support that stuff gets escalated to when our help desk can't figure stuff out.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The more time I spend on this planet the clearer it gets: when a top dog reads the above tasks they see it all as "trivial". Not that it requires little cognitive capacity or effort, but in the sense that it doesn't involve power and alliance building and political wresting. You are not a figure on the chessboard, so to speak. He doesn't think "wow, I need to get this guy on my side" or "for my future, I need to make sure I'm in good standing with this guy". No, you just do what you're told, you clean the ship, you replace the ropes when they tear, but you don't influence the destination.</p>
      <p>Having to "be right" is either a luxury obsession/hobby of some elites who just don't give a damn anymore and can afford it, or it's a characteristic of low-status jobs.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>