<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2021-04-23T13:46:33Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mtuhyd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_19_2021/gvkdglc/</link>
  <title>"I don't think it's possible to harbor hatred or even merely resentment toward entire classes of people, and also be a happy person."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This comment is drawing reports because of course it is, but I think your response is very interesting in light of my own perception of the "alt right" as just the white flavor of identitarian critical theory.  My own personal take on this whole discussion is that you are miserable for basically the same reasons as the "woke" are miserable.  I don't think it's possible to harbor hatred or even merely resentment toward entire classes of people, and also be a happy person.  I'm honestly unsure it is possible to be a happy person while genuinely and actively hating or resenting even <em>one</em> other human being, much less a whole group of mostly-strangers.  Fortunately, none of us harbors hate in our hearts <em>all</em> the time, though probably all of us harbor it <em>sometimes</em>.  But building an identity or a lifestyle or an ideology on top of that resentment is, well, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ressentiment">ressentiment</a>.  It's not mentally healthy.</p>
      <p>That said, of course, there is a whole philosophical strain of thought that runs along the lines of "better to be Socrates unhappy, than a pig happy."   I have met many academic feminists and Marxists and similar whose response to "you seem unhappy" is persistently "that's because there's nothing to be happy about, unhappiness is the correct feeling to have."  I don't have a good answer to that; not everyone can be a stoic or a pragmatist or the like, I guess.  But the so-called "alt right" seems to fit that niche on the right column of the political foursquare, for the same basic structural reasons.  To become defined by what you oppose is precisely the thing Nietzsche warned against when he said, "when you gaze into the abyss, the abyss gazes also into you."  Also when he observed:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I want to learn more and more to see as beautiful what is necessary in things; then I shall be one of those who make things beautiful. Amor fati: let that be my love henceforth! I do not want to wage war against what is ugly. I do not want to accuse; I do not even want to accuse those who accuse. Looking away shall be my only negation. And all in all and on the whole: some day I wish to be only a Yes-sayer.</p>
      </blockquote>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>