<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-11-06T23:16:54Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jmhoku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_02/gbedbo7/</link>
  <title>Where is the anti-progressive Borat?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>tl;dr - where's the version of Borat who makes fun of progressives? And more generally, why haven't conservative comedians taken advantage of the amazingly low-hanging fruit presented by some of the silly extremes of wokeism?</strong>
      </p>
      <p>So I finally buckled the other day and watched the new Borat movie. I'd been half-minded not to watch it, because I think it's pretty ugly comedy. <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/nov/22/sacha-baron-cohen-facebook-propaganda">Sacha Baron-Cohen seems to think</a> that he's revealing deep truths about people's indifference to antisemitism or hate, but I agree with <a href="https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2006/11/borat-meets-some-painfully-polite-americans.html">Christopher Hitchens' review</a> of the first movie, namely that it reveals more about how "Americans are almost pedantic in their hospitality and politesse" than the ugly bigotry lurking in the shadows of American life. We already know - courtesy of studies like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milgram_experiment">the famous Milgram Test</a> - that most people are highly agreeable and will go along with whatever circumstances they find themselves in. The fact that Borat, Bruno, and Ali G aren't immediately upbraided and shamed by their interlocutors seems to me to say more about the human tendency to avoid conflict and be agreeable with strangers than any deep bigotry.</p>
      <p>And yet, despite all this - I did find the new Borat movie kind of funny. I guess it's because I like twisted gross-out humour generally, but it was wild and silly and irreverent enough that I laughed a lot. Still, as satire, I thought it felt less interesting and more one-sidedly politicised than any of SBC's previous work. Ali G did very funny interviews with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fOIM1_xOSro">Noam Chomsky</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H-YYroSudUs">Tony Benn</a>; even Borat has <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dWgcPTV2nCA">made fun of animal rights</a> protestors and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mcO4GopVIN4">the feminists of America</a>. But the focus in this movie was squarely on a very small (and I daresay quaint) slice of mostly rural and exclusively conservative America. How many viewers of the movie will know anyone who has <em>actually</em> attended a debutantes' ball in the deep south, or even a crisis pregnancy center? It would be one thing if the movie had been an 'inside job', southerners making fun of southerners in the same way that the Matt Stone and Trey Parker (pbut) make fun of hick mountain towns. But coming from a privately educated Londoner like SBC, and directed at culturally savvy young people, this felt like something more cruelly anthropological; "behold the ridiculous savages with bones in their noses!"</p>
      <p>In any case, all of this led me to reflect on how well the new Borat formula could work when targeted at the silly extremes of the progressive movement. I'm not a conservative, but I like good comedy and satire as much as anyone, and as the Babylon Bee has illustrated there are some very soft targets on the left that it would be great to make fun of. Borat's style of humour - in which people are led to say things they probably shouldn't because of politeness norms, and because they believe they're in sympathetic company - could be readily applied to some progressives. Here are some examples off the top of my head -</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(1) Professor Posad.</strong> A Marxist professor from Columbia (the country? the university? porque no los dos?) who may or may not have once fought for FARC goes to visit Marxist faculty in contemporary American universities. While debating the evils of capitalism with his luckless interviewees, the conversation gets gradually darker, as he e.g. jokes about that time he crushed the testicles of a landlord captured in a FARC raid. Will his interviewees call him out, or will they applaud him for his revolutionary zeal?</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(2) Davide DeGeneres.</strong> A Belgian liberal reformer who meets progressive and liberal activists interested in more liberal policies on drugs, prostitution, and porn. Initially well-meaning conversations about harm reduction quickly turn pear-shaped as he gleefully talks about his threesomes with Italian teenage boys and offers coke to his interviewees.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(3) Kim deKimson.</strong> A sexually confused individual who seeks out the most open-minded sex therapists he can find, and presents increasingly baroque and meaningless claims about his gender and sexual identity, asserting that, e.g., he identifies as a man in a man's body but with a female sexual identity, or as a gay man who's exclusively attracted to women. Will his ridiculous claims be accepted or will he be challenged? (NB: this would be easy to mess up by turning it into a boring 'sexually identify as an attack helicopter' meme; the point would rather be to intelligently make fun of contradictions in ideas like self-identification).</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(4) John Smith.</strong> A tall blond haired dude who tries to get invited to progressive activist rallies where he talks about his experiences of discrimination and the suffering inflicted upon 'his people' and on those who follow 'his lifestyle'. If ever probed about what exactly this discrimination consists in, he responds angrily by saying it's not his job to educate others about discrimination and oppression. How long can he get away with claiming to be an oppressed minority without actually specifying what minority he belongs to?</p>
      <p>Of course, these are pretty crude, and intended to serve as a proof of concept rather than actual material. But I hope they illustrate the basic idea that there's <em>low hanging comedic fruit</em> on the progressive left that almost no-one has taken advantage of.</p>
      <p>It's become commonplace these days to say that comedy involve 'punching up not punching down', but I think it's simultaneously more complicated and more simple than that. It's more complicated insofar as some comedy doesn't really punch anyone at all, and other comedy does successfully punch down. But it's more simple insofar as a lot of the best comedy isn't about social status hierarchies, so much as making fun of the pious, stern, and self-righteous. By this metric, I think that there's ample hay to be made of the silly extremes of progressivism.</p>
      <p>Maybe it's just a matter of time till this happens. I realise there are institutional barriers to producing 'off-message' comedy (RIP Sam Hyde), but as illustrated by the Babylon Bee, these aren't insuperable. Moreover, we live in an age where comedians can get big just on the back of YouTube skits. So I'm surprised we've not seen this already. I think part of the historical problem has been that comedy works best when it's irreverent and degenerate, and these are two traits that are mostly associated with the left rather than the right. When I think of conservative comedy, I think of bland family-themed sitcoms or middle-aged stand up comedians complaining about how their wife is getting fat. And most people these days aren't particularly interested in taking a shot at their own in-group, so the people who would be well placed to make genuinely transgressive comedy mocking progressives aren't interested in doing so.</p>
      <p>In any case, I'd love to hear others' thoughts on this cluster of issues. Why hasn't a Borat-style comedy show targeted at progressives happened already? Could it ever happen? And what are the barriers in the way of genuinely funny conservative comedy?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>