<post>
  <author>marinuso</author>
  <date>2020-11-07T18:43:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jmhoku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_02/gbh4wdp/</link>
  <title>Elections in the Netherlands</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>OK, we have a lockdown here and I'm bored, so I'm going to tell you Americans about how we do elections in the Netherlands, so that you may compare and contrast. Mods, feel free to delete it if, for once, you find I'm not culture-warry enough. </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Registration</strong>
      </p>
      <p>In the Netherlands, everyone who is a legal resident of the country is supposed to register with the municipality where he lives. Not just for elections, mind you, this registration is used for everything from taxes to welfare to the draft, when we still had it, and for official government post. It's a legal requirement, so pretty much everyone is registered. In theory, even the homeless should register, using the address of a homeless shelter in the municipality where they were last registered before they became homeless.</p>
      <p>This same registry is used automatically for the elections. When there is an election you qualify for, you are automatically sent a voter card in the mail. This is done a couple of weeks in advance so you have time to complain if you didn't get one for some reason. Who qualifies depends on the election. For national elections it is all citizens, for municipal elections it is only the people living in that municipality, provincial and water board elections are similar. And if you are a foreigner from another EU country, you can vote in the EU parliament elections. Dutch citizens who live abroad need to register for the election separately, but everybody else is automatically included as long as their municipal registration is in order. </p>
      <p>It follows that there is no such thing as "registering as a Democrat/Republican/whatever". You are merely noted as someone eligible to vote. You can be a dues-paying member of a political party of course, but that's a) uncommon (in fact, it's only ~2% of the population) and b) also not directly registered by the government.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Voting</strong>
      </p>
      <p>A few weeks before an election is due, if you are eligible to vote, you are sent a voter card. They look more or less like <a href="https://www.d-line.nl/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/stempas-02.jpg">this</a>. The voter card is personal and has your name and address on it. It also has the address of the polling station nearest to you, though you can vote anywhere in your municipality (it says that, too). On the back of the voter card is a form you can fill out to allow someone else to vote in your stead. As long as you both live in the same municipality, that is all you have to do, though your proxy will need to cast your vote and his own at the same time, and no more than three votes can be cast at once (to prevent ballot harvesting). Simply fill out the form on the back and give the card to your proxy. You can also vote in a different municipality than your own, but if you want to do that, you have to trade in your voter card for a special, country-wide one at your municipal office beforehand. Accompanying the voter card, you will be sent a list of polling stations and a full list of candidates, so you can look it over and decide at home before you actually go and vote.</p>
      <p>On the day of the election, you bring along a state-issued ID as well as your voter card (plus at most two cards from others). When you go into the polling station, you give them your voter card and show them your ID. They will take your voter card and put it in a sealed box with a slit on top, and hand you a ballot. This is done in the open where everyone sees it. You then take the ballot to one of the little booths they'll have set up, and fill it in in privacy. The booth will have a red pencil for you to mark the ballot. A pencil, to avoid the problems that ink can bring, and red, because that can't be easily erased. 
Once you are done, you fold up your ballot so nobody can see your vote, exit the booth, and put your ballot in another sealed box with a slit on top, again where everyone can see. You are now sure that the fact that you voted has been recorded (by your voter card being in one box) and your actual vote has also been recorded (by your ballot being in the other box). If you have one or two extra cards from other people, you get one or two extra ballots to fill out. Polling places are generally open from 7.30AM to 9PM, though some have wider times. </p>
      <p>Throughout most of the 1990s and 2000s, voting machines were used. This was never without controversy, but in 2006 some hackers proved that it was possible to listen in on votes as they were cast by measuring the electromagnetic radiation. After that, voting machines were discontinued and the red pencil returned. The 'red pencil' has since become somewhat of a cultural symbol of elections, and more generally of the people's voice. (E.g., when Trump was first elected in the USA, there was a cartoon going around that was a hand giving a middle finger, but the middle finger was a red pencil.) </p>
      <p>Postal votes do not generally exist, except for voters who live abroad. </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Counting</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Counting is done individually by each polling station. After the polls close, each polling station counts the votes that they have. They should have the same amount of voter cards as they have ballots, proving that there has been no ballet box stuffing or thrown-away votes. Any citizen is allowed to attend and observe the counting at any polling station. (This was even used to great effect during the EU parliament elections of 2014, when the EU wanted the result to stay secret until all countries held their elections. An Euroskeptic website organized citizens to attend the counts and report the results. It worked surprisingly well.)</p>
      <p>At the end, the results from each polling station are officially recorded, and then added up to form a national total. The results are published in official publications. </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Result</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The Netherlands uses a party-list proportional system. What this means is that the ballot will have a list of parties, and every party will have a list of candidates. A vote for a candidate is both a vote for that party as well as for that candidate. Seats are divided among the parties according to the total amount of votes per party, so if a party wins N seats, N of their candidates get in. By default these will be the first N people on the party list, but the ordering of the list can change if individual candidates win enough votes.</p>
      <p>In the case of a national election, there are 150 parliament seats. The seats are divided among the parties according to how many votes they got, so 1/150th of the vote gets you one seat. 76 seats are needed to form a majority. It has never happened that one party got a majority on its own, so after an election, parties have to form a coalition to get a total of at least 76 seats. Once that is done, they form a government according to their coalition agreement. They then appoint the Prime Minister, who in principle could be anyone, but in practice it is always the leader of the biggest party in the coalition.</p>
      <p>In the last national election, 1/150ths of the vote was 70107 votes. Anyone wanting to make a difference through fraud would've on average need to change about half of that, and even then, there would only have been a change of 1 seat, which is not a big change at all.</p>
      <p>We're not a perfect country. Bad things do happen here, there has been quite some government corruption and backroom dealing over the years. But at least everyone trusts the elections - certainly since the voting machines are gone.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>