<post>
  <author>mister_ghost</author>
  <date>2020-11-09T16:12:03Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jqrmw5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_09/gbqa0o1/</link>
  <title>Things Exist Because People Make Them</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>You're stacking the deck by presuming they have made a discovery. Maybe it's not that they become exposed to something, it's that they cease being exposed to something. University is one of the places most insulated from, in lieu of a cleaner phrase, the material reality of being a human.</p>
      <p>In my undergrad, I moved through a world based on deserving things. It's not that I was entitled and thought I deserved everything, but if I wanted something I didn't need to produce anything in exchange for it; I simply had to deserve it. Want better grades or a scholarship? Show you deserve them. If you have a job, you understand "in exchange for". Otherwise, everything you have, you got by convincing someone that it was good for you to have it.</p>
      <p>This is amped up in grad school. My partner is a PhD student, and the grant-funding system just baffles me. You convince someone that they should give you money for your research in exchange for nothing. If you're lucky, they agree. But then the university decides that you don't deserve <em>that</em> much funding, and takes back some of your base funding, leaving you with what is essentially a symbolic raise. This is, to her, completely intuitive. In my experience, grad students have plenty of complaints about being funded below the poverty line, but have not a lot to say about exactly whose money they should have more of.</p>
      <p>All of this is fertile ground for what Thomas Sowell calls "the unconstrained vision", where society building is based mostly around deciding how things should be: there aren't many tradeoffs, and by making intelligent decisions we can create whatever world we want.</p>
      <p>When people go to university, they are allowed to forget that things exist because people make them. Cars, houses, and toothbrushes simply <em>are</em>, and if they cost too much then it's because some asshole chose a price that was too high.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>