<post>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2020-11-10T17:02:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jqrmw5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_09/gbue2ot/</link>
  <title>Vaccine Production, Release, and Politics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I am a volunteer in this clinical trial. I view it as a civic service to help the approval process move forward as quickly as possible. There is a 50/50 active vaccine / placebo split, so it's a coin flip as to whether I will be one of the first people globally to have vaccine-induced immunity to this pathogen. I am thrilled that preliminary results have indicated such a high efficacy, and am optimistic of what this means for mRNA vaccines both for COVID-19 and other infectious diseases as well as cancer. I am still hoping that Johnson &amp; Johnson vaccine shows similar promise, as it requires only 1 dose and does not need to be kept at -70°C which would make the logistics of mass inoculation more achievable</p>
      <p>However, there's zero doubt that the delay in releasing this report was due to the election.  Pages <a href="https://pfe-pfizercom-d8-prod.s3.amazonaws.com/2020-09/C4591001_Clinical_Protocol.pdf">102-104 of the Vaccine Study Protocol</a> explicitly call for Interim Analyses after "accrual of 32, 62, 92, and 120 cases". From reporting on this, it's clear that no less than 3 Interim Analyses would have been released before the election if Pfizer did not inexplicably change its own protocols and put samples in storage until 94 were allowed to be tested the day after the election. I agree with the perspective that this could have as much to do with not wanting Democrats to politicize and sow doubt about the findings as it did with denying President Trump a major victory right before the election, but it is inarguable that it definitely served the purpose of the latter</p>
      <p>I'd also like to comment on the very false news that the Pfizer / BioNTech vaccine trial was not part of Operation Warp Speed or buoyed by the Trump administration's support, as was the <a href="https://twitter.com/i/events/1325790677838409728">#1 Trending narrative</a> on Twitter yesterday. In actuality, the US Government committed to pre-purchase $1.95 Billion worth of the vaccine under Operation Warp Speed regardless of whether it was effective, with an option to purchase a ~$10B order of 600 million samples (the vaccine requires 2 inoculations). Additionally, the approval process was cut down from 3-5 years to a matter of months thanks to regulatory exceptions provided by the FDA. Dr. Jansen's bizarre attempt to downplay the administration's role in this historic success leads me to believe more strongly that the protocols were changed specifically to influence the election</p>
      <p>Finally, I would like to say that, to my mind, the Trump administration could've done more to get to this point faster. At the most obvious level, the FDA liaisons should never have approved the unwarranted deviation from Interim Analyses protocols. More substantively, the President should've been publicly promoting these trials harder and perhaps providing incentives for enlisted military, federal prisoners, or students with federally backed loans to participate. With a larger sample size, case thresholds are reached faster. If you believe that COVID-19 is a massive civilization-level threat that warrants unprecedented erosion of civil liberties, upwards of $10 Trillion in economic disruption and government spending, and the reorienting of our entire society to center around infection avoidance - which, to be clear, I <em>very</em> much do not - then <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_challenge_study">challenge trials</a> should have been at least debated and considered. But, in any case, I had to proactively figure out how to get involved by Googling and following up with various liaisons. Meanwhile, I received probably several dozen texts these past couple weeks haranguing me to vote. If there had been a similar energy level behind recruiting for these Phase III trials, we'd be at the inoculation stage by now. The vaccine itself has been ready since April, and even with all the regulatory bloat the Trump administration cut, given the stakes there was absolutely a way to expedite things further</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>