<post>
  <author>solowng</author>
  <date>2020-11-08T13:11:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jn8wzm/us_election_day_2020_megathread/gblxieq/</link>
  <title>Examining the GOP history with black voters</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Coming from the other side, agreed, and I think it's hard for many on the left to appreciate how incredibly frustrating it was and remains for the GOP to have been <a href="https://www.govtrack.us/congress/votes/88-1964/s409">decisive in passing the Civil Rights Act of 1964</a> and to have <a href="https://www.govtrack.us/congress/votes/89-1965/h87">overwhelmingly</a><a href="https://www.govtrack.us/congress/votes/89-1965/s78">supported</a> the Voting Rights Act of 1965 only to lose the black vote by  70-80 point margins ever since. Imagine losing the black vote in those margins to George Wallace himself, because that actually happened in 1982.</p>
      <p>There are perfectly reasonable explanations for this, namely having no southern presence to speak of circa 1964 (such that Barry Goldwater was foolish enough to confuse southerners for libertarians) to actually compete for black southern votes, the immense popularity of the Great Society programs, taking the anti-urban side in the post civil-rights culture war, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Mississippi_Flood_of_1927">getting blamed for Hurricane Katrina on steroids</a>, and, yes, some proliferation of witches among state and local GOPs (That's one of the reasons that the AL GOP got <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1982_Alabama_gubernatorial_election">whacked by Wallace in '82</a>, running the mayor and de-facto police chief of Montgomery.) but to the average Republican voter or even politician the seemingly instant marriage of black America to the former party of the Confederacy and the Klan has to be somewhat puzzling. I wonder how many GOP (or Democratic, for that matter) politicians or officials have even heard of the Great Mississippi Flood of 1927. </p>
      <p>With that, among the Bernie and contemporary woke wings of the left there's an underappreciated story of how the southern Democratic parties survived the end of segregation, ditched the Klan for the biracial populist coalition that southern liberals of that recent past like Big Jim Folsom had dreamed of, and black and white southerners came to something of a peaceful coexistence with each other. It was that Democratic Party that produced politicians like Jimmy Carter and Bill Clinton, picked Barack Obama, and put an end to the 2020 clown car. Perhaps Republicans can be forgiven for this ignorance given that the integration era in the south wasn't really part of <em>their</em> history (The Compromise of 1877 on the other hand...) but many college educated Democrats should know better. </p>
      <p>Absent compelling evidence to the contrary I assume that the GOP won't really be competitive with black voters until most with living memory of LBJ are dead (as was required with the living memory of FDR for the GOP to decisively win white southerners) but the Democrats may have trouble finding another Biden in terms of driving black voter turnout in the short/intermediate term (There's a reason they picked him and it wasn't because they were trying to pick someone that old.) given that the party's voters are increasingly concentrated among the college educated, upper class, women, and the west coast and will want a candidate who conforms to their values and priorities. Without a moderate candidate who bulldozes through the primary with a near-monopoly on the black vote (a good omen for black turnout in the general election, I'll add) it's entirely possible if not probable that the next Democratic primary will produce a wokescold or socialist as the candidate for the general which would be a recipe for likely defeat. I think that millennials who came of age under Obama don't really appreciate how hard it is for a party to find a candidate that literally everyone in the coalition can find something to like about and how fragile that unity is. They need only ask the Republicans how they've done finding another Reagan and how long it took that apparent juggernaut to start falling apart.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>