<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-11-07T17:53:09Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jmhoku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_02/gbgyvch/</link>
  <title>Hope for all, a mandate for none: The future is open for those who choose to seize it</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <h1>Hope for all, a mandate for none: The future is open for those who choose to seize it</h1>
      <p>Election Day stretched into two days, then three or four, but the dust is clearing and the immediate future begins to come into view. Joe Biden is poised to be the 46th President of the United States. The Democrats will hold the House, but face an upswell of Republican support making it closer than they had planned. The Senate, meanwhile, will be decided by a battle in Georgia next January. The overwhelming mandate Democrats had dreamed of, and with it dreams of adding states, court packing, and more, has faded. Trump himself lost, but the realignment he ushered in looks to be here to stay. A surge of voters on both sides emphasized the stakes felt in the election. The United States, it's clear, remains as divided as ever.</p>
      <p>What, then, are the takeaways? What is the near future of politics in America? I believe that, in this result, each major political group in the country has both something to cheer and some reason for caution. </p>
      <h2>
        <strong>Leftists</strong>
      </h2>
      <p>While most reluctantly shuffled into the Biden coalition, leftists remain as eager as ever to reach beyond the Democrats and pursue their own goals. If that was ever in any doubt, a quick glance at <a href="https://twitter.com/AOC/status/1324698828944138243">Alexandra Ocasio-Cortez's twitter feed</a> should settle it. For leftists, without a candidate they were more than tepidly supporting, the good news comes in the form of policy. <a href="https://uploads.dailydot.com/2020/11/fox-news-exit-polls.jpg?fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=768&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.0&amp;w=1536&amp;wpsize=1536x1536">A Fox News poll</a> has been making the rounds, indicating strong majority support in the country for a government-run health care plan, leaving Roe v. Wade as-is, tightening gun laws, and expanding the role of government. </p>
      <p>More than just polls, though, you had a chance to see real progress towards their aims. The resounding image leftists should take away from this election: Florida, even as it went for Trump by a substantial margin, passed a $15 minimum wage amendment. Alongside that, four states (Arizona, Montana, New Jersey, and South Dakota)—two of them deep red—legalized marijuana, while Oregon decriminalized all drugs. In these decisions, leftists can claim vindication for one of your core impressions: a selected subset of your policies are increasingly popular with voters.</p>
      <p>That's the good news for you. The cautionary tale can be seen in a quick glance towards California, one of the bluest states in the country, where voters resoundingly supported Proposition 22 and thus allowing rideshare drivers to remain classed as contractors, shot down your attempt to remove a ban on racial discrimination in the California constitution in Proposition 16, rejected Proposition 25 and its proposed elimination of cash bail, and overwhelmingly opposed rent control in its Proposition 21. In Portland, meanwhile, the mayoral candidate who made waves both for wearing a skirt with images of Mao and Che Guevara and for <a href="https://twitter.com/sarahforpdx/status/726995735367929856">casting write-in votes for Mao, Stalin, and Lenin in 2016</a>, fell short in her campaign against the mayor leftists have been lovingly calling "Tear Gas Ted". It's difficult to sort out all the reasons for the red wave in the House and the closeness in the Senate, but one glance at attack ads around the country tying moderates to a Radical Socialist Agenda, full of images of violent riots and burned-out, looted buildings, along with Trump expanding his lead in Kenosha, Wisconsin, <a href="https://www.kenoshanews.com/news/local/trump-loses-wisconsin-but-wins-in-kenosha-county-for-the-second-time/article_ed0e1552-d426-53b3-8564-da82643ba996.html">as the first Republican to win there in 44 years</a>, suggests one part of the picture. Abolish the Police, shockingly, did not prove to be a winning slogan come election time.</p>
      <p>For leftists, then, my own impressions: you're not wrong that, in isolation, some of their policies can draw widespread support. If you're serious about those policies, there's a clear path forward for them. It involves ditching the ideological baggage of labels like 'socialism' and flirtations with extremism, and focusing your message on the parts of your economic and social policies that really do resonate with voters. It means recognizing where you are, recognizing the number of your countrypeople—yes, including the working class—who disagree with you, and long, hard, serious work at convincing people and building coalitions. </p>
      <h2>
        <strong>Liberals</strong>
      </h2>
      <p>Liberals, meanwhile, can breathe a long, deep sigh of relief—your first, perhaps, in four years. Dawn has arrived. The sun is peeking over the mountains. Your boogeyman, it appears, has finally been defeated—much later than you'd hoped, yes, but defeated nonetheless. The sheer chaos of the last four years, the stream of scandals that would have sunk any other president, wall-to-wall coverage in the news, Twitter roulette, and everything else you care to name—I hardly need to, you all have seen it enough—it's fading. In its place stands Joe Biden, with his measured civility, <a href="https://twitter.com/JoeBiden/status/1324926298762870785">pleas for bipartisanship</a>, and a promise to pick up where Obama left off. You did it. You won. The four-year fever dream is over.</p>
      <p>Even as Biden prepares to step into office, though, he finds himself as the first president-elect in recent times to (probably) not have party control of both houses of Congress. The polls, the models, the atmosphere among liberals all pointed towards a landslide victory. In the eyes of liberals, this election should have been an overwhelming repudiation of Trump and Trumpism. That didn't happen. It didn't come close to happening. The liberal bubble, all-encompassing as it can seem at times, remains almost exactly as large as it was four years ago. Expectations, at one point sky-high, must come crashing down to earth. <a href="https://twitter.com/ATabarrok/status/1324047859172343808">Alex Tabarrok put it best</a>, I think:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>My takeaway is that a large number of people HATE the cultural left (not the econ left) and are willing to put up with almost anything, including incompetence, chaos, corruption and bad policy, to signal their views loud and clear.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Everything liberals have hated and feared about Trump for the past four years did <em>nothing</em> to sway half the country away from him. That should be sobering—not just a cause to look <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/jmhoku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_02/gbeksg7/">Borat-style</a> towards an enemy group who wants nothing but evil, but a chance to look inward. You have the most powerful office in the land—and, as conservatives are ever ready to remind, you have the universities, most media institutions, tech companies, all of it. There are two roads ahead, one of ever-escalating all-out attacks against each other, one of a serious attempt to mend what has been broken. </p>
      <p>Worry, attacks, all the tension of the past few years—they make sense when you find yourself faced by an enormously powerful person who horrifies you. When you're unambiguously in power, though? Rather less so. You #Resisted. You don't have to fear a Trump white house any longer. Now you're trapped in charge of a country where half of the people despise you, in the middle of a pandemic, with tensions looming with China and elsewhere. Know what power means?</p>
      <p>It means now it's your job to clean up the mess.</p>
      <p>Get to it.</p>
      <h1>[PART 1 OF 2]</h1>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>