<post>
  <author>WestphalianPeace</author>
  <date>2020-11-10T05:08:29Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jqrmw5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_09/gbsti4l/</link>
  <title>China and the Tragic Universalism of Liberalism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There is a tragic inability of Liberal Democratic states to accept the legitimacy and self-determination of non-liberal democracies. An autocrat can live next to a democracy and not particularly care so long as that government doesn't interfere in the Autocrat's controlled country. But Liberal Democracy often lacks this capacity for particularism and insists that others must copy it. As summed up by John Meirsheimer in 'The Great Delusion: Liberal Dreams and International Realities'. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"Because liberalism prizes the concept of inalienable or natural rights, committed liberals are deeply concerned about the rights of virtually every individual on the planet. This universalist logic creates a powerful incen­tive for liberal states to get involved in the affairs of countries that seriously violate their citizens’ rights. To take this a step further, the best way to ensure that the rights of foreigners are not trampled is for them to live in a liberal democracy. This logic leads straight to an active policy of regime change, where the goal is to topple autocrats and put liberal democracies in their place. Liberals do not shy from this task, mainly because they often have great faith in their state’s ability to do social engineering both at home and abroad. Creating a world populated by liberal democracies is also thought to be a formula for international peace, which would not just eliminate war but greatly reduce, if not eliminate, the twin scourges of nuclear prolifera­tion and terrorism. And lastly, it is an ideal way of protecting liberalism at home."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The United States has largely forgotten that it is possible to live next to a political system that is anathema to what it considers to be good so long as both sides agree not to interfere with the internal dynamics of that nation. When WW1&amp;2 broke the American Isolationism notion of being a City on a Hill and turned it instead into an Arsenal of Democracy on a Crusade Against Militarism we forgot that 'I won't touch you if you don't touch me' is a principle that works.</p>
      <p>An important distinction can be made between normal people and foreign policy elites, broadly defined. Most normal people when pressed arn't even all that liberal, rather they are liberal for their own tribe. 'My tribe's speech is legitimate because i'm right and moral and their tribe's speech should be censored because it disagrees with me and therefor is immoral' is pretty much the default approach of a normal layman. Normal people might find it sad when others nations live in oppression but they do not treat that as the same thing as their own countrymen being oppressed, let alone their local community, let alone their direct family. </p>
      <p>But from a Rawlsian Liberal perspective this is just a failure of bigotry. All humans have inalienable rights and upholding those rights equally must happen regardless of tribe or borders. And it's this Rawlsian perspective that has captured Liberal foreign policy elites. This is Samantha Power desperately trying to get the US to intervene in other nations as much as possible. This is paper after paper pointing out US  bombing campaign in Kosovo and trying to figure out how to do it replicate it. This is the invention of 'The Responsibility of Protect' as something that requires military intervention when lives are at stake. This is Obama preventing the Yazidi's from being genocided &amp; enslaved by ISIS when they were down to one last mountain stronghold. </p>
      <p>It is George Bush declaring the following:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The advance of freedom is the calling of our time; it is the calling of our country. From the Fourteen Points to the Four Freedoms, to the Speech at Westminster, America has put our power at the service of principle. We believe that liberty is the design of nature; we be­lieve that liberty is the direction of history. We believe that human fulfill­ment and excellence come in the responsible exercise of liberty. And we believe that freedom—the freedom we prize—is not for us alone, it is the right and the capacity of all mankind"</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Between the Liberal Democratic impulse to intervention and a Cold War against an Ideology which espoused Global Revolution (and thus a legitimacy in interfering in the internal affairs of another nation) I think a lot of people have come to take it for granted that to advocate for your own system means to advocate that all other nations' governments should be like yourself. But this doesn't necessarily follow. There is another path of respect for Sovereignty. A notion of 'within my territory I have absolute control, within your territory you have absolute control, and while we can negotiate and bargain in the international realm we at least agree to try and not interfere with the internal affairs of other nations. </p>
      <p>In short: Whose realm, his religion. </p>
      <p>It's this notion of Sovereignty that China is focused on. After a Century of Humiliation with it's internal affairs carved up by every Great Power that could manage it, including even Austria-Hungary, it should not be surprising that China would advocate for the norm of 'do whatever you want in your own country but don't touch mine.' So when Syria gasses's it's own population and China veto's intervention it's not because China thinks that gassing your own population is somehow moral or legitimate. Rather it is strictly following to the principle of Sovereignty. Syria gassed itself, not you. Until it gasses someone else you have no legitimacy in getting involved in it's internal affairs. </p>
      <p>When the article states that</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"We sincerely believe that all countries should take the path that suits them most. The diversity of political systems is the result of the political and cultural norms of human society.........The US and West have always fundamentally negated the rationality of the Chinese political system, hyping that China should introduce the Western political system and grossly interfering with China's path........While the US, led by its government, accuses China as a "new tyranny," demonizing China's national political system and major governance measures, and asking China to make changes according to the US and West models, China's counterattack is mainly carried out through the media. Moreover, China has never aimed to change the political system of the West. The US has made no secret of its intention to subvert China, while China has always advocated peaceful coexistence as the key principle in handling its relations with the US. "</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It's not true that China has 'never aimed to change the political system of the West'. Maoist anti-colonial intervention was a real foreign policy. But after retreating inwards and focusing on internal reform it is entirely plausible that Chinese leadership really believes in what it is espousing about sovereignty. If China and the US are exactly the way they are now 500 years from now that is success in China's eyes. Because they haven't collapsed, they havn't been carved up by foreigners, and are fully in control of their own destiny. But if you told most American foreign policy elites that 500 years from now China and the US would be the same there would be a great moaning and gnashing of teeth about how tragic it is that a billion+ people still live under an Authoritarian government. </p>
      <p>There is no fundamental conflict between the governing systems of the US and China. Largely speaking the population of both nations understand this. The Chinese foreign policy elite understand this. Once upon a time the American foreign policy elite understood this. It is only the current ideological concerns of American foreign policy elites, intoxicated on dreams of permanent liberal ascendancy, that prevent this mutual understanding.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>