<post>
  <author>zecaurubu</author>
  <date>2020-11-06T20:39:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/joopge/disappointed_by_the_cult_of_smart/gbdu8dn/</link>
  <title>To Make Jobs that Do Not Crush the Soul</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>What defines a job as "soul-crushing", "meaningless", etc? Low salary? Physical exertion? I have seen these adjectives being used to describe jobs ranging from high-paid positions in FAANG companies to grunt work in the army, but almost never (by people under 50) to describe more "romantic" pursuits like writer/musician/athlete. 
"${BAD_ADJECTIVE_HERE} jobs", at least on my view, is not a concrete category, but some sort of "wink-wink-you-know-what-I-mean" consensus building tool.</p>
      <p>I'll take a page from <a href="/u/Ilforte">/u/Ilforte</a> 's book and share some literature from my country on the subject. All grammar mistakes are my own (corrections are welcome):</p>
      <hr />
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <em>Coffee with sugar, sweetener, and purpose</em> (from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/5040283-qual-a-tua-obra">"Qual é a tua obra"</a> by Mario Sérgio Cortella)</p>
        <p>Two years after becoming the Secretary of Education for the city of São Paulo, Paulo Freire left to do other things and I took the position. I don't want to sound like a demagogue, but I learned under Paulo Freire and I wanted to be a leader for the people working in the Secretary of Education, which is a gigantic machine. At the time, we had 700 schools, one million students, and 45k teachers. São Paulo's largest secretary is Education: the budget at the beginning of 2000 was around R$3 billion (<em>around US$1.6 billion</em>), bigger than the entire budget of some Brazilian states.</p>
        <p>I worked from the 13th floor of a building located at Paulista Avenue. The accounting department was located in the same place, where a girl spent the whole day preparing budget allocation/grant documents. By her side, the copy machines, where a boy would make copies all day long. At the opposite end of the floor you would find the kitchen, where Dona Carmen prepared the coffee and brought it to us.</p>
        <p>What did I notice? That those people weren't lively. Although they were employed in an important activity and I keep telling them Education was something fundamental, they couldn't recognize the <em>work<sup>1</sup></em>. The copy machine boy believed that his work was to make copies. The girl preparing budget grants believed that her work was to prepare budget grants. And the coffee lady believed that her job was making coffee.</p>
        <p>What I started to do? Every time I went to visit a school, inaugurate another, go see a building renovation, go to a party - and those events would happen almost every day - I started bringing one of them with me in the official state car. Brought the copy machine kid with me, brought the budget grants lady with me, brought Dona Carmen with me. </p>
        <p>What was the result? They started to see the <em>work<sup>1</sup></em>. The kid that spent all day long making copies started to understand that his work wasn't making copies, but Education. The lady that made coffee noticed that, just because she spent the day carrying coffee left and right, her life's <em>work<sup>1</sup></em> wasn't making coffee, but making Education.</p>
        <p>That all that stuff would be transformed into children running, into lectures, into happiness, into problems, into solutions. It is at this moment that people start to feel well. Feeling well isn't exclusively about salary, isn't exclusively about material conditions. What matters is how you see your <em>work<sup>1</sup></em>, how connected you feel to it, and how important you believe you are to its progress.  </p>
      </blockquote>
      <hr />
      <ol>
        <li>
          <a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/obra#Portuguese">"Obra"</a> in the original. "Work" is not the best translation, in my opinion - please read it as "the goal of the craft" or "what I am building towards".</li>
      </ol>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>