<post>
  <author>DWXXV</author>
  <date>2020-10-31T18:30:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ji8tv6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_26/gapy2za/</link>
  <title>Meditations on Moderation</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So, I came home today intending to do an effort post on something else but I guess this is what we are doing instead.</p>
      <p>This is less about me and more about me only being motivated to comment after getting smacked by the ruler myself. </p>
      <p>Recent events and moderation have resulted in a drift towards what I want to call tone policing but is maybe better described as “effort policing” and a few other worrying moderation trends.</p>
      <p>There’s a bit of a gap in what requires “effort.” A lot of posters tend to be conspiracy minded about this (aka the leftists get away without…) but I think it’s probably more attentional. Some posts, for whatever reason end up with more reports or eyes and get the shaking fist. Others don’t. Sometimes they are rather egregious. The result is an uneven landscape of frustrated “how did that person get away with it when that other person didn’t.”</p>
      <p>To post here you need to be the kind of person who natively doesn’t say questionable things, is completely okay with getting yelled at by authority (it is telling that most of the people who have been here a long time seem to have significant rap sheets at this point), or have the bandwidth to over explain and contextualize everything.</p>
      <p>My day job leaves me with little free time and requires a saintly amount of kindness and patience, thus I do not like feeling I need to be fully professional here. I am fine with the expectation of baseline levels of respect, charity and so on and I’m also fine with the expectation of effort but I also think it should be appropriate to respond with mediocrity to mediocre comments (but not badly to bad comments).</p>
      <p>Related: Certain types of comments need an egregious amount of framing to be considered acceptable (and often appear to stem from moderator sacred cows more than community consensus, but also topics that trigger certain political groups) and creates an exhausting situation where you just have to create a Darwinesque carefully manicured padding of milquetoast nonsense or wonder if this going to be the time…</p>
      <p>In short, posting here “safely” often requires an amount of diligence that I think is increasingly excessive. I’ve posted probably 20-30 times going “no really, there’s a massive political bias in medicine.” I’ve started wondering when am I going to be short with the person I’m replying to and get a ban as a result.</p>
      <p>You might be saying “well yes, but that’s working as intended,” but I feel it’s gone too far. For years we’ve seen a stream of sneer clubbers and other types walk in, shit all over the place, get banned and then replaced the next day. Meanwhile high effort long time posters slowly get ground down by the rules and people like Darwin thrive. </p>
      <p>I’m not going to say my post wasn’t obnoxious, but if obnoxiousness is going to be a sin it needs to be more uniformly enforced, that thread and the ones surrounding it had tons of other obnoxious comments, why this one? Was I supposed to delete my comment after I realized the mainstream video going around didn’t have the lead up to the event? Effusively apologize? I don’t think posting should feel like a deposition.</p>
      <p>Anyway. </p>
      <p>Hard exits critical of the moderation tend to come from people with a history of multiple bans and a tendency for significant bad action, so I hope doing this serves as something of a canary.</p>
      <p>If you don’t mind I’d like to be banned (for some token amount of time or however much you feel is appropriate for the offense is fine) so I show up in the mod action report next week. Hopefully I won’t be judged too histrionic. </p>
      <p>I’ll leave up the post chain related to this decision for a few weeks but I’ll be scrubbing the rest of my presence.</p>
      <p>Presumably I’ll be going back to lurking. I might someday get drawn back in on an alt, but I think my participation on this account will cease with the end of this conversation.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>