<post>
  <author>greatjasoni</author>
  <date>2020-11-06T18:44:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jmhoku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_02/gbdfucf/</link>
  <title>The Aim and Scope of Classical Education</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The point of classical education, in the spirit of Renaissance, is to cultivate a strong aesthetic sense, so that a person can judge the world for themselves and free themselves from cultural dogma. You immerse yourself in your specific culture to the point of mastery, so that you may be maximally free of its influence. A focus on seemingly useless, but beautiful, things ends up producing people of far more utility than the opposite approach. Otherwise you're a tool capable of a lot of thinking, but are easily possessed by cultural factors beyond your control, like a fast car with a bad driver. If you don't understand your own culture, how can you possibly react against it? The man with bad taste is a slave.</p>
      <p>With that as a rubric I'd say they ought to know beautiful things. I'll keep this anglocentric, but would prescribe equivalents for other cultures:</p>
      <p>A mastery of English. This means knowing your grammar inside and out, etymology, latin &amp; greek root words, emphasis on saxon words, history of the language, rhetoric, good prose style, and a wide vocabulary. </p>
      <p>Tangentially related is the ability to argue persuasively, so that you can properly think and not be fooled by dark arts. This means: logic, more rhetoric, metaphor, statistics, bayescraft, the structure of arguments, charity, etc. (The sequences cover most of this, but need more classical propositional logic, and an emphasis on dark arts and aesthetics to be rounded out.)</p>
      <p>Armed with language one should proceed to consume the best and most influential works ever written. This roughly means reading the western canon, along with most of the important philosophical works, with criticism and commentary for both. One doesn't need to become an expert. At minimum you should know the Greeks and the Bible and Shakespeare and the gist of philosophical history, plus some idea of current trends in philosophy and literature. You can make a list of the top ~50 most influential books in western history and reasonably expect a Renaissance man to have an interesting conversation about any of them.</p>
      <p>As much history as possible. Preferably with a lot of travel and several languages besides english so that one can break out of cultural molds. This includes geography too. Both should involve a lot of rote learning. One should know exact dates of events and be able to fill out a map of countries and capitals with extreme ease. This gives the mind a firm foundation of facts to make connections with, so that one can truly develop intuitions about history for themselves.</p>
      <p>Pure Mathematics and Mental Arithmetic. These teach you how to think beautifully, and how to follow algorithms with machinelike precision. The Renaissance man of old learned classical geometry which was a series of beautiful proofs. Math as taught today is a series of boring and useless algorithms for symbolic manipulation for 12+ years, and only in upper division courses do students see any proofs. This is a travesty as pure mathematics is easily one of the most beautiful human accomplishments. Students should be exposed to proofs as early as possible with an emphasis on the beauty and elegance of math. We are currently so afraid of rote memorization that we end up with the worst of both worlds where students learn to vaguely intuit boring mechanical things. If you're going to do something boring at least get something useful out of it. Children should be able to divide numbers with many digits in their heads with ease. They should be drilled on every speed math trick in the book, that they might have a mastery of numbers and thus be freed from ever having to think about Arithmetic ever again. Instead they can think about topology and analysis.</p>
      <p>Physics and Chemistry. This is by far the most useless of the subjects, at least for everyday use, but they are both beautiful. Beautiful examples that come to mind are: the periodic table, noethers theorem, derivation of the laws of thermodynamics, special relativity, path integrals, etc. Tangentially related is estimation. In undergrad we had estimation competitions. Round everything to an order of magnitude and multiply away and you can get surprisingly close to calculating literally anything. This is an underemphasized skill that can be trained and is almost a prerequisite to statistical literacy.</p>
      <p>Music. It wouldn't be hard to teach every kid perfect pitch, or even just relative pitch, so that they could hear any written music in their heads. Instead we teach them to reproduce sheet music with their fingers like a robot, because it signals to parents better. Sight singing should be mandatory education at a young age, as it used to be when everyone sang in church. This alone makes you as musically literate as you need to be. I'd throw in some basic music history. You don't need to be a snob but at least listen to the <a href="https://youtu.be/lP-8C1UF1mE">Well Tempered Clavier</a> (This is like the Old Testament of classical music.) and be able to hear what is happening. Maybe be able to transcribe simple songs or quickly play a minimal piano rendition of anything you hear by ear. I'd emphasize an ability to improvise but that's probably asking too much on my Wishlist.</p>
      <p>Practical skills and knowledge: weight lifting, anatomy, any team sport, cooking, car repair, drawing competently, small talk, body language, fashion, personal finance, coding, memorized jokes and poems, house repair, impressions, acting, knowledge of spirits and wines, social dynamics, psychology, parenting (being good with kids is enormously high status), evolution, game theory, economics, etc.</p>
      <p>This is both reasonable and a slightly impossible standard. But I think it produces far more useful, and happier, men than what the modern emphasis does. Notice how the extreme emphasis on rote study produces someone disciplined enough to study anything they please, with the taste to truly know what pleases them.</p>
      <p>Most importantly, on this bedrock the Renaissance man should -master- a marketable skill that makes them indispensable to others. Without this they will always depend on others to survive. Without mastery of a skill they won't be free and won't really be respected as a man. They should be able to surround themselves with other Renaissance men in mutual respect, that the community may free its members from themselves. The Renaissance man should as free as humanly possible.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>