<post>
  <author>GrinningVoid</author>
  <date>2020-11-05T11:24:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jmhoku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_02/gb7v1im/</link>
  <title>Giants Will Walk the Land Once More</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Because as the tension increases, restraining factors become less relevant, which clears a path for the best and brightest, or at least the most brutal.
We already saw a preview of this with Trump demolishing the 2016 GOP primary field; the next iteration will be that but meaner.</p>
      <p>This dynamic can be observed during lots of crises: compare how the British liked to assign officer commissions based on connections/social standing right up until the French or Germans started winning too much, at which point the strategy became finding a competent commander and then create them a duke after the fact.
Or the French revolution itself— originally run by the intelligentsia, later by cliques orbiting a minor star, then by the directorie of the most capable (and ruthless) survivors of the first phase, before eventually devolving into another monarchy led by that Corsican overman. </p>
      <p>Or Napoleon's prototype, the Caesars.
Towards the end of the Roman Republic, you had the ancient analogues of our modern day dynasties, where even the best of them, like Cicero, were still kinda puffed-up windbags. 
He checked all the boxes (made consul in his year! a real victory for the debate society over the AV club don'cha see), claimed Mission Accomplished over the Cateline conspiracy (unsure whether this pattern matches to Gulf War II or Russiagate), before getting creamed by the first triumvirate.</p>
      <p>There, you had ol' Julius from a good family and the chad Pompey basically running roughshod over the republic, before Crassus died, thereby initiating Highlander rules.
Caesar ultimately won, but as it turned out he was in possession of information that could put Hilary away, with predictable consequences.  </p>
      <p>Was the Republic saved?
Did Rome end up Retvrning to Trvdition? 
No.
The second triumvirate made first triumvirate/Julius Caesar era look like a <em>Phish</em> concert-- literally. </p>
      <p>Well, okay, not literally, but whereas the original triumvirs tried to do things within the bounds of tradition and the law, their next incarnation (Marc Antony (not the singer), Octavian Caesar (Julius' adopted nephew), and Legolas) were, in contrast, pretty fucking metal.
If you made a triumvir your enemy, you got proscribed, which was basically sentencing you to either exile or death with the bonus door prize of 'all your property is confiscated by the triumvirate'.
When Legolas finally departed for the Undying Lands, it was back to knife-fightin' between Octavian and Antony; Octavian won, annihilated any possible rivals, and then transformed Rome into an Empire that he ruled for half a century.</p>
      <p>Now, there's a certain amount of hagiography and post-hoc just-so storytelling with regards to history, but I think the overall message is pretty clear: instability leads to the removal of things that impede one's meteoric rise/fall.
Furthermore, as shit gets crazier, exceptional people are forced into politics, either as matter of survival or because other avenues for advancement get closed off.</p>
      <p>So yeah, I am expecting American politics to get more intense. 
Giants will walk the land once more, but great men are not necessarily good. 
But hey, at least we get to live in interesting times.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>