<post>
  <author>HavelsOnly</author>
  <date>2020-10-29T02:29:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ji8tv6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_26/gaga3qd/</link>
  <title>The Arbitrary Imperative, or: Kant, Eat Your Heart Out</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>That principle is one of Kant’s formulations of the categorical imperative: “Act only according to that maxim by which you can at the same time will that it should become a universal law.” Another way of putting this is, “Act according to the maxim that you would wish all other rational people to follow, as if it were a universal law.”  </p>
        <p>If you apply this to voting, this means a couple of things. First of all, that means that you should vote as opposed to staying home, even though it is very unlikely that your vote will affect the outcome. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I was going to become a doctor. But then I thought, "what if everyone became a doctor?", and realized that society would cease to function. So the only way to have a functioning society is for most jobs to get done. Therefore, I chose my profession at random (weighted by prevalence of each job). As a result, I work the night shift at the Amazon warehouse.</p>
      <p>My friend who is into philosophy told me I had missed a loophole. You can define actions in all sorts of ways. Shooting a guy vs. putting your thumb on a metal object vs. the other 999 ways to categorize the same action. Or, instead of working at the Amazon warehouse, I could just apply for and accept jobs I wanted and would do a good job at, because if everyone did that we'd still have a functioning society. And then when it came to vote, I figured out that if everyone just voted if they felt like it, we'd still have a functional democracy because about half of everyone wants to vote and the half that don't probably don't care that much anyway.</p>
      <p>Some people thinks this makes "universalizing actions" a confusing and exploitable moral guide. Other people think that interpretation of Kantian categorical imperatives an "universal maxims" is more subtle or at least worded confusingly in the source material. </p>
      <p>Be right back. There's a murderer at the door asking if I am hiding anyone in my basement. I'm going to lie to him because I feel like it. I've reasoned that if everyone lies when they feel like it, we more or less have the world we do today, and that's OK with me.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>