<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-11-05T22:10:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jmhoku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_02/gb9yaxu/</link>
  <title>How to Compete With America, the Unsinkable Ship</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>a win for people who are not thriving in their current country and should be trying something else instead, where they are more likely to be appreciated and to thrive there</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>A phrase somebody ought to have said: «Libertarians always talk of comparative advantage, but why don't we ever hear about <em>comparative disadvantage</em>?»<br />
Come on. The only way this condition can work, in the best case, is by relocating locally non-competitive people to less competitive economies (and, assuming those are to stay solvent, with less of a social security spending per capita). It's not about «thriving», it's about downshifting. Especially so in case of USA. You'll have a hard time spinning your offer against the backdrop of this economic reality, especially if you're unwilling to pay as much settlement as those people would've «drained» by staying.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Speaking of my own country, it seems clear that there is a significant subset of Americans who really don't like America as it is. They seem to strongly believe they would be happier living in countries which are very different from America. They're easy to find on social media, and I believe they have an amazingly toxic effect on American culture.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Be real. </p>
      <p>...You know, I've been thinking about this while jogging a hour ago, and even wanted to create a top-level. My thesis: <strong>America, like <a href="https://nationalinterest.org/blog/the-buzz/are-us-aircraft-carriers-nearly-unsinkable-19144">its signature ship</a>, is unsinkable, for it faces no scalable competition in terms of attractiveness for high-potential people</strong>. Let me elaborate.<br />
All of your intra-American gripes and concerns are detached from the larger context of the world. It seems to me that practically all Americans who emigrate <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emigration_from_the_United_States">are non-assimilated descendants of recent immigrants</a>. Even those unpatriotic liberals you wish to see gone, when they kvetch about exodus to Canada or Good Old Yurope, are ultimately not contemplating this in earnest; it's in-group signaling behavior homologous to far right's talk of secession and ethnostates. At most they'll go visit some exotic country, aww at its adorable little customs, then go back to complain about their uncouth compatriots. I'm not even sure if they could be bribed with anything less than high 6-figure sums.<br />
You sit on the prime real estate of this planet, defended by oceans, loyal neighbors and the strongest military possible with current technologies, your possibilities constantly expanded by the greatest talent pool in history, your prosperity guaranteed by the rest of humanity having invested in your currency, your industry, even reduced, secure by virtue of possession of know-how for all strategically crucial supply chains, with perfect food, energy and information independence... I could go on and on, but there's one killer feature: due to factors of this kind, you're still the best country in the world <em>for a capable person to have a family of four.</em> That's ultimately what people want. That's in our genes. There are places which can surpass you if it's just a hedonistic existence of two; some can compete in terms of environment for a single child family; but above that, you reign supreme. Not even Switzerland or whatever challenges you; okay, maybe there are <em>small</em> enclaves that can, but it's not scalable and they're not looking for immigrants from the US. Your American Dream, the dream of healthy life without downshifting, is universal human dream, even if now it's fading in your brain as you silence the alarm.  </p>
      <p>So there's no scenario where <a href="https://www.unqualified-reservations.org/2008/08/america-vampire-of-world-part-1/">America-the-vampire-of-the-world</a> collapses on itself. Y'all like it too much, particularly the more decent ones of your kind. You'll grumble and put up with its various defects and defections, pay taxes, prevent its state capacity from falling too low, and thus you solidify its lead – while others crash and burn. It's a positive feedback loop. And on the other hand, it allows the government and the entire managerial class to be as corrupt and delusional as possible, so long as the country still retains this advantage.  </p>
      <p>All of the above is very trivial and could've been said in few words, like «USA is too big to fail» or «the rich get richer». But it brings me to the next point: the only way for the world to advance politically is <strong>to create regions where life is better for classical American families than it is in America itself</strong>. The details could be worked out later, but for now suppose China splits a portion of Heilongjiang province (random pick) and establishes a super-special economic zone there. You have to pass a very high bar of productivity to get in, but once you do, you get a special citizenship which entitles you to a land endowment, certain family support and freedoms (to the extent that still keeps you from interfering with politics outside of the region I guess). Also, it's got to have great ecology and be really trustworthy (so, uh, China won't have a good chance to compete with Neo-European Reich in this; but possibly more motivation).  </p>
      <p>In the beginning, it'll be insanely costly, with comparative advantage freaks screaming at the regulatory bodies involved: «don't you realize how many IQ shredders we could've fit in that baby?!» But in the long term, it'll change the rules of the game. It'll preserve local human capital. It'll incentivize American elites to care more. It'll make Americans more critical of their state – critical not in this pathetic grumbling manner of exercising voice, but efficiently critical, because now they will have a viable «exit» too. It'll possibly reverse brain drain, if the aforementioned elites do not renege on their project/don't get their act together. It'll make us all better off. </p>
      <p>I wonder if the bigwigs at World Economic Forum could've come up with this. It certainly strikes me as more reasonable and even less utopian then their Great Reset/Build Back Better buzzword salad. But who am I to judge.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>