<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-11-03T03:02:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jmhoku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_02/gayu5py/</link>
  <title>Nothing Beside Remains: Dreams of a Modern Ozymandias</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I’m fortunate to have a lot of exposure to all sides of the culture war.</p>
      <p>My Grandparents are social distancing CNN watchers (isolated old people have nothing else to do for 4 hour stretches on end) who loath Trump, my parents and it seems an entire generation of rural boomers they know are avowed Qanon followers (it a siren call to boomers, if anything the medias apocalypticism about Q’s followers seem understated, there are at-least millions probably tens of millions of Q people), the non-Q boomers seem divided between people increasing ready to lynch health officials and politicians (I’ve heard people suggest this) on the one hand, and panicking boomers on the other who are getting close to beating the masks onto the “Covidiots” who won’t wear their mask.</p>
      <p>I know 20 something girls who work in hospitals who are terrified of COVID not because they think it would hurt them or their family (who are invariably young), but because they expect social death and unending shaming/dirty looks to follow anyone forever who tests positive within their professional environment.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile I work at a tech company filled with left wing Canadians who mostly roll their eyes at Trump in the way every one in Canada rolled Their eyes at Bush... but with a Blue-collar/energy sector clientele thats getting increasingly cultural distant/seemingly panicky over the insane economic swings they expect any month.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile like 50ish% of 20 somethings I’ve returned to live at home with WFH/initial panic over COVID, and things feel like the end of days...</p>
      <p>I know radical campus feminists who do the regular purgings of each-other from the student union for wrongthink, and I know the MMA bros who listen to Joe Rogan religiously and who just 10 years ago would be dating and, in a few years, marrying the former...</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>I’ve had my kickboxing manager asked me in a hushed voice what I thought of this or that culture war thing, as I gave a non-answer and we spent several minute feeling out that neither of us would try to get the other fired for saying in essence, Jungism is weird but Jordan Peterson doesn’t seem like literal hitler.</p>
      <p>And none of these people can live together... not in the same friend circle, not in the same town, not in the same country, not on the same planet. Many of them are immediate family, who would work together and help each-other fix their house after harsh winters,  and they barely talk now. Things aren’t going back to normal, they can’t, its been made clear that living in a democratic society with each-other, the idea that any of these people have the moral authority to control any of the others or direct their lives has lost legitimacy, pretty-much forever... I’ve heard people say “Oh its just the very online! Normal people who aren’t on reddit have barely noticed this stuff”... and no... that’s not the case. </p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Best hope at this point is democracy dies, maybe the whole thing breaks up into statelets, hopefully some freedoms get restored, but most importantly the feedback loop between normal people and politics needs to break... community, fellowship, and (heaven help us) society just won’t survive another decade of meaningful political engagement and real options that matter on the ballot...</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Im watching a Trump rally now on Fox (parents place)... and the crowd is chanting “WE LOVE YOU! WE LOVE YOU!” To the tune of “U-S-A U-S-A”... most of them are from churches where this decade the men (and many women) would have been embarrassed, or found it “gay” to have been caught expressing such an intense sentiment for Jesus... “I mean ya good guy, literally god, died for our sins...But love? Come on Bob don’t make it weird” Yet for Trump they’ll say it with rapture.</p>
      <p>People believe in the culture wars in ways they haven’t believed in anything else forever... and with good reason, many expect the culture war could destroy them....</p>
      <p>I don’t see how this doesn’t go hot... maybe conservatives and trump supporters are caught flatfooted by a Massive Trump loss and take too long to radicalize to action/stop believing in belief/adjust to world were trump can lose... but otherwise everyone is ready for violence... if Biden loses or its indecisive or its close... well there’ll be violence, recriminations, narrative formation, and radicalization...</p>
      <p>Everyones afraid and everyone expects they could lose everything if they don’t win this one... broadly when people say “Violence would be preferable to the other-side winning” well...this a year where it really seems they’re accurately accessing the outcomes... small business owners face ruin if it re-locks-down, a conservative supreme court threatens pretty much the entire woke industry, one interpretation of a lawsuit by asian students, or internet censorship, ect. Could just kill the entire woke superstructure, a packed court would undo the entire point of 50 years of movement conservatism, Bidens energy policy (or the threat of it) fills my clients with terror, the virus and the “COVIDIOTS” fill my grandparents and the more left wing boomers with a vicious fear and desire to enact literal fascism inmost respects (detainments, forced medical procedures, ect.) ...</p>
      <p>This is going to be fucking ugly...it could really death spiral... and it could keep spiralling downward for years... In urban Canada you meet a-lot of people from different countries that “Used to be really nice” “a true Jewel”... and then they had to flee... Somalia, Lebanon, Iran, Cambodia, the balkans, Armenia, Venezuela, Ukraine, Algeria, Zimbabwe...</p>
      <p>History happens, the sands of history are filled with Empires that were never to end, hell my Grandparents were alive when the sun set on the last one, and my parents remember when they stopped singing God Save the Queen in School...</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>———</p>
      <p>In Montreal stands an office Tower... once the tallest in the British Empire, you walk through massive doors and into halls cathedral’d taller and grander than all but the most glorious heights of the old world, and walking past the art deco entrance  up marbled stairs that echo softly but grandly with each footfall you reach the great hall  from between grand classical columns.</p>
      <p>And on the walls behind you turn about... above the space are carved two great black slates, arched and emblazoned in gold, the alter around which this cathedral was built, written there it reads: <a href="https://greatwar100reads.files.wordpress.com/2019/01/20170816_112005.jpg">IN MEMORIAM MEN OF THIS BANK WHO GAVE THEIR LIVES IN THE GREAT WAR</a>.</p>
      <p>No bank remains. The Royal Bank of Canada fled Montreal for Toronto in ‘76... the victim of another culture war in the last days of another empire. Yet you may see that memorial today in those same cathedral’d halls... and for 3 dollars Canadian and 4 dollars more, you may enjoy a Coffee, and a Scone, from <a href="https://crewcollectivecafe.com/en">The Cafe</a> which resides in the place that was once the Merchant Heart of British North America.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>