<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-10-28T11:54:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ji8tv6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_26/gadea9g/</link>
  <title>What a 6-3 Republican Supreme Court Means</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>First of all, the actions of Senate Republicans over the past five years have been nothing but a barely-disguised grab for power (albeit a remarkably successful one).</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is nonsense, though if you put an "it seems to me" in front of it, at least it would be reporting on your impressions instead of making a dubious claim of fact.  You might as well call an election a "grab for power."  Usually, power-grabbing is the act of enlarging one's office.  FDR is the case study here; his enlargement of the presidency is historically important and well-documented.  The Senate's refusal to confirm Garland was not unprecedented, though it is probably fair to call it "fighting dirty."  Their willingness to confirm ACB was even more precedented, and not "fighting dirty" at all (though the Democrats fought dirty <em>three times in a row</em> on Gorsuch--necessitating the counterstroke nuclear option--Kavanaugh--who was slandered relentlessly--and now ACB).  The Senate's powers have been <em>important</em> throughout Trump's presidency, but they have not been <em>enlarged</em> a single iota.</p>
      <p>I am frankly baffled at the breathless "how will a 6-3 majority change the court!!??" talk making the rounds.  Given that Republican appointees have been a majority of the court <em>since the 1970s</em>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judicial_appointment_history_for_United_States_federal_courts">at one point in the 1990s</a> constituted and <em>8-1</em> majority, what you should <em>expect</em> to happen is a pretty boring continuation of the judicial status quo: mostly letting the legislature do what it wants, so long as it doesn't get <em>too</em> crazy, while mostly permitting progressives to use the Fourteenth Amendment as a blank check for social reform at gunpoint.</p>
      <p>The fact is, ACB's appointment is little more than a (low!) hurdle to clear before progressives can have what they really want: a return to the judicial activism of Earl Warren.  In particular, a direct "wealth tax" is almost certainly unconstitutional (yes, I've read the arguments to the contrary, they are facile) under the Fifth Amendment Takings Clause.  But an activist Leftist Court could probably be persuaded to permit it.  We see California already <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/robertwood/2020/08/17/california-proposes-168-income-tax-rate-plus-4-wealth-tax/#48cf409c19a6">looking that direction</a> and California tends to be the progressive bellwether.  It's not an accident that progressives have been talking about their "Green New Deal" or "New New Deal" or whatever.  FDR's enlargement of the presidency was a grab for power, and though the legislature rebuffed his court-packing attempt, the threat cowed a conservative Court into <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wickard_v._Filburn">reinterpreting matters like the Commerce Clause</a> to essentially grant unlimited authority to Congress, in direct contravention of the "enumerated powers" of the Constitution.  The Tenth Amendment was reinterpreted as a tautology ("whatever is not taken, remains") and the Warren Court ran with the ball.</p>
      <p>The reforms brought about from the 1930s to the 1960s were dramatic.  The size of the federal government ballooned like crazy, the social engineering dreams of 1920s progressives were realized, and... actually, it turned out pretty good for almost everyone involved.  That might be an accident of history, of course; Europe bombing itself back to the bronze age certainly didn't hurt our position on the global stage.  But the expansion of social welfare as directed from DC, the fulfillment of promises made during Reconstruction but swept under the rug for decades, the incorporation of the Bill of Rights against states as well as federal actors, are all developments that few Americans now seek to roll back, or even question.</p>
      <p>And that is, honestly, the single most powerful argument, <em>to me</em>, for not worrying <em>too</em> much about the impending "blue wave."  I <em>do</em> worry anyway, because I know as much about Venezuela as I do about Denmark, and because the 1960s also gave us a new and especially ugly form of identity politics, and I know that past performance is no guarantee of future results.  But this--</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I can only roll my eyes at people who fret about the imminent outlawing of gay marriage, abortion, or the Affordable Care Act </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>--is where you are on firmest ground, I think.  To answer your questions, I do not think abortion is going anywhere; at most we will see some limits on late-term abortions, which are already rare.  The ACA may be struck down but this will only pave the way for it to be replaced, possibly even with a single payer system, and as long as the Democrats pay some fucking attention to drafting the bill properly this time, the Court will not strike it down.  California's wealth tax might get struck down though.  I don't think Biden will try to pack the Court until <em>after</em> it strikes a serious blow to his agenda, but Roberts and maybe Kavanaugh will see that and swing accordingly, likely preventing any actual court packing attempt from even beginning.  In my experience, people get very worked up about Court nominations, but almost never think about it otherwise (everyone knows about Obergefell and Roe, but few could comment on Lawrence or Casey, for example).  I don't think perception will change much.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>