<post>
  <author>XantosCell</author>
  <date>2020-10-31T02:55:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ji8tv6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_26/ganzqx8/</link>
  <title>A 2020 Election Fanfic</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>A 2020 Election Fanfic</strong>
        <em>(Warning: May mildly deviate from reality)</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Saturday, October 31:</strong>
      </p>
      <p>With only days to go until the election, both candidates consult their pollsters.</p>
      <p>“Mister Vice-President, we currently forecast that you win the Presidency<a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2020-election-forecast/"> 89 times out of a hundred.</a> Over the past weeks we’ve been moving in the right direction, and our odds can only go up from here!”</p>
      <p>“Mister President, it doesn’t look great. We are falling behind in key swing states, and our margins aren’t improving. We might have to consider the possibility that you won’t win re-election.”</p>
      <p>The stakes are high. The very future of the nation is on the line! Now is the time for careful consideration, calm strategy, and delicate action... thinks the Biden campaign. Over at Trump Tower HQ though, they can read the writing on the wall. As a grim air falls over the room, Trump prepares to address his campaign staff.</p>
      <p>“Fellas, its been fun. I got my digs in and had some good laughs along the way. But I’ll be damned if I’m going to lose to Quid-Pro-Joe and Where’s Hunter. I’m a winner, and I’m not tired of winning yet. People call me, they call me and they say, “Mr. President you gotta win! You gotta win it for yourself!” I didn’t want to have to do this, but I gotta strike hard. It’s time... for a deal.” </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Sunday, November 1:</strong>
      </p>
      <p>CNN, MSNBC, and Fox drop all existing news coverage to begin reporting on the juiciest story of the year. The President has gone missing. Eyewitnesses recount President Trump entering an elevator in Trump Tower, pressing <a href="https://theweek.com/speedreads/642716/10-floors-are-missing-from-trump-tower">ten hidden buttons marked N/A,</a> and rubbing his hair wistfully as the elevator doors closed. </p>
      <p>The New York Times runs a story claiming that Trump is on the run to avoid the inevitable prosecution that will occur once he’s no longer in office, quoting a source close to someone, somewhere, at sometime. When asked for comment, a spokesperson for the Biden campaign broke out into song, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e5B5kZV0Lrw">“Joe Biden will always be your friend.”</a></p>
      <p>Hunter Biden is seen constantly looking over his shoulder and instructs his people to only make restaurant reservations where he can sit with his back to a wall. Ivanka Trump appears at a campaign rally alongside a Donald Trump lookalike in an attempt to quell supporters fears. The Huffington Post reports that Melania has booked a plane ticket back to Yugoslavia after being told that she cannot outlaw shaving cream by executive order, because she is not the President.</p>
      <p>The country goes to sleep anxious, as voters on the left and right alike wonder the same thing, “What is Trump up to?”</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Monday, November 2:</strong>
      </p>
      <p>FEMA and the FCC issue a national alert through the federal Emergency Alert System. The White House will hold a press conference inside the Oval Office at noon today. Tuning in has been made mandatory by executive order. News organizations are quick to condemn the obviously illegal nature of such an order, but their criticism is tempered by their raw curiosity. </p>
      <p>Mike Pence is seen leaving the White House around 11am slack jawed, repeatedly murmuring “Are you seeing what I’m seeing!” Onlookers, feeling awkward and wishing to avoid a scene, unconvincingly reassure the Vice President that yes, they are in fact seeing what he is seeing. Anticipation is through the roof. A round table of Steve Kornacki, Wolf Blitzer, Brian Williams, and Anderson Cooper is convened to analyze how this as-of-yet unknown development might, possibly, hypothetically, in some instances, affect swing states.</p>
      <p>At the stroke of 12 noon, a video feed goes out to the waiting nation. </p>
      <p>1/3 of all men faint. Anywhere from 1/8 to 1/6 of all middle aged women are reported to have swooned. War veterans across the country instinctively snap into a crisp salute. Almost 90% of babies giggle delightedly and try to touch the television with a few chubby fingers.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://imgur.com/zF6USiq">Donald Trump is now bald.</a>
      </p>
      <p>The trademark cotton-candy blonde locks are no more. A salt and pepper beard completes the ensemble, and projects an air of gravity and competence previously unfelt by even the most die-hard Trump voter. No one knows how Trump pulled it off, but everyone agrees that this changes everything.</p>
      <p>For half a minute, America is a silent nation, her citizens too dumbfounded to speak. Finally, life long Tennessee resident William “Willie” Williamson breathes out a quiet, “Holy fucking shit.” Pandemonium erupts as voters desperately try to make sense of this new information. How does this change things? What should they do? A democrat campaign staffer is caught on tape saying, “You guys, I know this doesn’t really change anything but... the Don’s kinda hot now, right?”</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Tuesday, November 3. Election Day:</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The votes roll in. </p>
      <p>Idaho, Michigan, West Virginia, South Dakota, and Delaware are instant Biden victories. In most counties turnout approaches 100%.</p>
      <p>Virginia, Montana, and Kansas see Trump landslides, with only a single vote being cast for Biden across the three states. A bipartisan investigation later reveals it to be the first ever documented case of voter fraud committed by a <a href="https://www.countrysideveterinaryclinic.org/sites/default/files/styles/large/adaptive-image/public/sphynx-cat-breed-info.jpg?itok=mEBqPkgY">housecat</a>.</p>
      <p>Nevada and North Carolina see similar Trump victories. As does Oregon, in a surprise result that instantly invalidates every pollster’s forecast and leaves election experts across the nation scrambling to find yet another excuse for why they “really definitely almost got it right this time guys, for sure.”</p>
      <p>Data analysts at GQ magazine unearth a<a href="https://www.gq.com/story/facial-hair-trends-across-america"> peculiar pattern</a>, which they claim tracks the shocking results perfectly.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Wednesday, November 4:</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The rest of the election is so close that eyes everywhere turn inevitably towards the Supreme Court. Sure enough, the Court announces that it will hear arguments in Trump v. Biden later that very night, as an emergency case. Legal scholars everywhere debate whether or not this development will confirm that Amy Coney Barrett is secretly homophobic, despite the general public being confused as to how homophobia is even in play in the upcoming case in the first place.</p>
      <p>When the six male justices take their seats boasting hastily grown facial hair of their own, the verdict seems clear. In a 6-3 split vote, the Court finds that the President’s beard is, “Pretty good... Prettaaay, prettaaay good,” and the incumbent retains his office. Reporters describe this as a landmark shift in the court, with the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hyph_DZa_GQ&amp;list=PLIAxMwIXmAAJVXiYmgdjVNRqcSJOT5Y0n&amp;index=2&amp;t=0s">Robert’s Court being less strictly constitutional and more strictly awesome.</a></p>
      <p>A New York based barber publishes a best-selling novel detailing his experience giving President Trump his makeover. The White House continues to deny allegations that Trump refused to tip the man because, “$30 plus tip just isn’t a good deal.”</p>
      <p>Joe Biden takes to twitter for his concession, and reassures crestfallen supporters that he can “definitely, 100% grow a beard,” and that he “just chooses not too.” Twitter CEO Jack Dorsey orders his platform to flag this statement as “dangerous misinformation.” White House Press Secretary Keyleigh McEnaney described the move as quote: "based.”</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>