<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2020-10-27T20:24:26Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ji8tv6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_26/gab5pay/</link>
  <title>Anti-Imperialists in Korea: A Shrimp Among Whales</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I bring up this analogy in part because Park (and a number of his contemporary (South) Korean conservatives) descended from the <strong><em>yangban</em></strong>- basically dynastic relatives from the pre-colonization Joseon dynasty, and Park's (and thus the Korean conservatives) descends from (one of) their cultural/intellectual traditions on what it means to secure the nation.</p>
      <p>The Joseon dynasty was a Chinese tributary that used Confucianism as a state-enforced ideology. At its inception, Confucianism served four roles- politically it enabled the purging/replacing of the preceding dynasty/Kingdom of Goryeo, which was offically buddhist, and diplomatically it brought Korea inline (and in alliance with) Imperial China. But it also served two social purposes- as a self-justifying ideology to organize society with the state (the Confucian patriarch model based around a virtuous patriarch/leadership), but also as a (at the time) modernizing intellectual force. The rise of Confucianism as a secular ideology can be thought of as a 'modernizing' influence against 'superstition' or 'traditionalism'- the same sort of modernizing reformer impulse reflected in modern day aethiesm-tinged movements.' It's from these last two that the yangban tradition grew.</p>
      <p>Crudely, the yangban class can basically be thought of as 'temporarily embarrassed nobility intellectuals'- not necessarily the rulers or officals themselves, but the family and relatives of which who, if not the ruling class, are by their proximity much better than the dirty commoners and menial laborers. The better access to education helped with the airs of sophistication, but even if your family fell from grace/office you could still be yangban if you kept the culture/tradition/intellectual bent. Park was from a poor yangban family, but he grew up reading and admiring Napoleon, for example.</p>
      <p>The concept of yangban differs from your typical paristical aristocratic family reputation (spoiled rich kids who disdain low-class labor) by the relation to confucian/chinese cultural emphasis on virtuous leadership. Confucianism is seen as authoritarian for its emphasis on deferring to the patriarch/king and organizing society accordingly, but the flip side is that there's expectation that the king/ruler is expected to be virtuous, and if he's not then there's karmik/higher righteousness in replacing a corrupt and evil king with a virtuous one. Given that the Joseon dynasty was explicitly confucious, they were at least pretending to claim to public virtue along those lines. Yangban- as a class of relatives of the reigning confucion dynasty- evolved to reflect that, in time self-justifying their existence and intellectualism/aversion to reverting to demeaning work in the framework of nobly holding the rulers to the standards of enlightened virtue (which they maintained).</p>
      <p>Yangban, in other framing, was a form of noble chattering class, with the undercurrent of 'I can't resort to drudgery for base survival- I must maintain my intellectual virtue to advise the ruler or admonish him when he's astray.' </p>
      <p>
        <em>This</em> matters because five centuries later, when it's becoming more and more clear that the Joseon dynasty isn't going to last long in the world of colonialism as the Chinese tributary system is shattered around them and Japan is indisputably more advanced and capable, the yangban are the public intellectuals who are not only the first to recognize the problem, but also debate what is to be done about it to save Korea. As the intellectual class tied to the identity of Korea as a polity-identity, these were the people who considered themselves the thinkers and leaders of what Korean nationhood entailed. </p>
      <p>Park and the Korean collaborators of the Japanese empire- the predecessors of those 'less nationalist' conservatives- are one of those proposed solutions. Not in the sense of 'if you can't beat them, join them,' but rather 'don't fight a hopeless battle against your betters, learn from them and make their strength your own.' Modernize, modernize, modernize, as fast and best as possible from the best... so that <em>in the future,</em> when the opportunity presents itself, it <strong>won't</strong> be a hopeless battle and you can assert yourself then.</p>
      <p>The Japanese imperialists, of course, didn't mind this sort of public intellectual one bit. Local elites telling the public not to resist right now? Telling the locals to learn from you, when you're trying to assimilate/re-educate them? Sometimes being the right sort of yangban probably got you left alone, if not respected, by the Japanese authorities, even if you weren't an explicit collaborator. And thus yangban and their descendents entered into the imperial bureaucracy, and the imperial army, and when the empire crumbled they were best placed and prepared to lead on their own terms. A century later, and the dynamics are certainly different- a century ago Japan wanted, and could, dominate Korea by force of arms and economy. Now, a 3-to-1 economic advantage isn't enough- Japan couldn't, even if it wanted to, which it doesn't. Even if the US wasn't there, Korea is now advanced strong enough to resist at least one of its neighboring whales, and probably two. (China, certainly not... but that's what the Americans are for.)</p>
      <p>Was that a gamble? A bet? Certainly. It was a race against time in a way- about whether the Koreans could learn and adapt and get enough investment and economic development to get strong enough to break free and then resist as an indepedent power, versus whether Japanese occupation and assimilation would sap the Korean will to resist and doom the yangban intellectual identity of Korea. It certainly didn't pan out as either of them intended- the yangban couldn't count on WW2 before WW1 even played out, and the Japanese certainly didn't expect a total defeat and the sundering of the empire.</p>
      <p>But the question more than a century ago wasn't <em>whether</em> Korea should be free and independent, but rather <em>what to do in the face of an overpowering force determined to see otherwise</em>. The popular/peasant left tradition descends from people who didn't want to submit at all/disdain those who did, but they lost their bet too- if the entire Chinese state was ravaged by Imperial Japan, a unified Korea totally behind them would also have been crushed, and they were just as dependent on foreign actors to gain liberation. The Korean right's intellectual tradition derives from the aristocratic intellectuals (and sometimes parasites) who knew what that sort of resistance would entail (for their country, for them), and adjusted accordingly.</p>
      <p>Does that mean they loved Korea less, or were less nationalistic? I think that's misleading. Fighting for independence against impossible odds is valorous, but no less doomed for it, and doesn't address how you'd stay independent even if you managed to fight off one neighbor. Wanting to strengthen your country so it can be in a better position vis-a-vis neighbors, even at the cost of unpleasant- but unavoidable- compromises? That's firmly in the nationalist-territory for me.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>