<post>
  <author>georgioz</author>
  <date>2020-10-27T11:15:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ji8tv6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_26/ga9flhj/</link>
  <title>Horseshoe Theory, Communism, and Fascism in Korea</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>For instance, in Korea, the left are the nationalists.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is one of the key points where the horseshoe theory asserts itself and talking about left/right stops even making sense. On the extremes fascism and communism have many common features. </p>
      <p>Basically the main official differences is that fascist focus on some form of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ultranationalism">ultranationalism</a> - be it religious identity like with Franco's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Falangism">Falangism</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fatherland_Front_(Austria)">Austrofascism</a> or just plain nationalism with irredentist subtones like original <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_Fascism">Italian Fascism</a> or even virulent form of fasism - the nazism - that puts importance on racial identity. Communism historically was based on the idea of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communist_International">internationalism</a> where the focus of fascist national struggle is replaced by international class warfare. On the economy side far-right prefers the idea of national unity including in economy matters. It is often seen as some form of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corporatism">corporatism</a> where various interest groups in economy - especially business owners and labor - are part of the political process where the political national leg enforces the national unity of classes. Communism of course professes the class warfare inside the country with the aim of establishing dictatorship of workers abolishing private property and capitalism.</p>
      <p>Now of course this is only an analysis of authoritarian left/right. There is the other side of political compass where you have leftist anarchists that have much in common with let's say anarchocapitalists. But I will ignore that part of the political compass for now.</p>
      <p>The problem is, that historically traditional communist countries slowly abandoned internationalism and socialization of economy. We have seen it for instance in Soviet Russia where Stalin promoted the idea of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialism_in_one_country">Socialism in One Country</a> eventually turning Soviet Union into basically imperialistic country promoting <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russification#Late_1930s_and_wartime:_Russian_comes_to_the_fore">Russian identity</a> as part of policy of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_communism">national communism</a> and dominating socialists in other countries - or even being outright hostile to other competing socialists in other countries like the hostility between Soviet Union and Yugoslavia or communist China. Some communist movements start with national identity right away. To name a few examples: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hungarian_Soviet_Republic">Hungarian Soviet Republic</a> was even at the time seen as a trojan horse of how to re-establish the Hungary to its pre-war borders hoping that Soviet Union will help with that project. As soon as this dream collapsed former socialists just turned coats and often became adherents of Hungarian Fascism. There are other examples: Mao's China saw communist party as a way to reestablish One China. In Vietnam and many African countries the communism was viewed as a way to fight off colonialism. </p>
      <p>On the economical front we also always saw decay. The state ownership of all production capacities always led to some massive problems and some countries were forced to adopt some sort of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialism_with_a_human_face">Socialism with Human face</a> or in case of China the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_economic_reform">Deng Xiaoping economic reform</a> basically starting privatization of economy - at first small businesses but inevitably successful SMBs turn into large businesses and then they become useful tool and resource in intra-party struggles establishing themselves. On the political side the class warfare eventually leads to establishing the new aristocracy - the infamous <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nomenclature">nomenclature</a> that is also well poised to be the first to truly use the advantages of economic reforms. </p>
      <p>The main point is that communism without class warfare and state ownership of means of production is literally fascism - it does not matter if fascists wave red flags with hammer and sickle. I made that case before <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/jdpvq9/thoughts_on_the_situation_with_china/g9jkzxq/?context=3">elsewhere</a> for modern China actually. Now no all forms of fascism are as virulent as German Nazism - but that was valid even at the time Nazis rose to power. In fact they often saw foreign fascist movements as mortal enemies if they stood in their way. Such as when Nazis assassinated Austrian dictator <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Engelbert_Dollfuss#Assassination">Engelbert Dollfuss</a> to open way for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anschluss">Anschluss</a> or from the other side when members of Polish fascist party - <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Radical_Camp">National Radical Camp</a> - became one of the most effective guerrilla fighters against <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boles%C5%82aw_Piasecki">Nazi occupation</a> to later even use that cred to become influential members of Communist party. </p>
      <p>I think in the end often the left/right distinction loses its usefulness and power as a descriptor.  It is the same here. I believe that if one studied the Korean "left" in their beliefs they would basically came out as right party somewhere else. So in these edge cases just list the properties and have people decide what they think as opposed to relying on such fuzzy categories such as left/right. It is as when Scott Alexander wrote his fantastic <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/11/21/the-categories-were-made-for-man-not-man-for-the-categories/">essay on categories</a>. At some point - especially as we move to the edges - is is useful to abandon the category and just describe things as they are. Planet Pluto is still the Pluto despite us calling it a planet or Kuiper belt object.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>