<post>
  <author>greatjasoni</author>
  <date>2020-10-28T03:40:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ji8tv6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_26/gacivwb/</link>
  <title>A Passionate Defense of Beauty</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>In big 5 personality metrics I have max openness, which is, among other things, a measure of aesthetic sensitivity. Beauty is the only thing I really care about. I think it's more important than morality and truth, or, rather, they're all the same thing, but Beauty is the clearest expression of an underlying deeper reality. If I had a different personality I would probably think about it differently. But as I experience the world, all categories, literally the objects I see in front of me at any given time, are defined first by beauty.</p>
      <p>The true the good and the beautiful is an old philosophical notion. That there are "transcendentals," ultimate expressions of mans desire and the end of being, was western dogma for millenia. Platonists developed it then catholic philosophers narrowed the list of transcendentals down to those three. I reject later philosophys, mostly because they're ugly but also because I think they're all either internally inconsistent or have bad premises, for reasons way too long to flesh out here. I'm not sure what bias drives me towards that other than it looks obviously right to me. I can psychoanalyze myself to see certain cultural factors that pushed me in this direction, but I like to think I'm ruthlessly skeptical of my own beliefs and biases. We all fall short of that ideal but I prune harder than most. Mostly the bias is Beauty. </p>
      <p>The notion that Beauty is only a feeling is tempting but refuted by experiences of Beauty that are deeper than mere feelings. There is a category beyond feeling, where you glimpse a hint of the divine. Sunsets can do this pretty reliably but so can drugs and good art and higher math and people. At this point we'd have to quibble about what we mean by feeling. All of reality is experienced. It makes little sense to posit a reality that isn't experienced by anything. In describing that reality there are objective features of it, things that don't depend on our beliefs, and subjective features like feelings. The experience of Beauty is so far beyond feeling that it justifies itself. The associated feelings are merely a catalyst to glimpsing the deeper form. It's something like logic, which is experienced, recognized, as obviously part of the fabric of reality, but not felt. </p>
      <p>The problem is that we live in an ugly, and therefore sick, culture where we rarely get that experience. Instead we are bombarded with entertainment designed to stimulate us that isn't beautiful. This atrophies our ability to see beauty, as we conflate it with mere feelings the way we conflate love and sex. </p>
      <p>I would say something similar about love, which I will use as an example because it's less abstract. Love is not a feeling; it is the most important principle we have as human beings without which we could not live. "God is love" is literally true. We all value love over truth, and if we pretend otherwise it's out of a love of truth. We love our families, maybe because of circuitry that strongly incentivizes us to, but since reality is experience the circuitry might as well be imaginary. It's irrelevant. Under reality is love, the same way that under reality is Beauty and logic. You don't convince a mother to love her kid. Her love <em>is</em> reality. And that love is beautiful. It's a beauty more real than any meaningless material abstraction or sense perception like atoms or starlight could ever be. That's simply what the world is like. The world is experience and fundamental to the experience are values and truth and aesthetics, with love being an experienced amalgamation of all 3.</p>
      <p>I'm not satisfied with how fleshed out that is, but I hope it gives some idea of my biases. Putting this into language feels kind of silly though and the explanation is itself ugly, like I sullied something sacred. To me this question is akin to asking "why is orange orange?" or "why do causes cause effects?". It's so self evident that it might as well be nonsensical.</p>
      <p>But that might just be a quirk of my personality, and a less aestheticly posessed person could bridge the inferential gap better. Maybe I just have the egomaniacal urge to elevate the importance of my interests, but that doesn't make me wrong. I'd say read <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/plato-aesthetics/#ForBea">Plato</a> to get a clearer picture of this. The cave allegory and analogy of the sun might be helpful. Once you have a shared framework to think about abstractions then it becomes easier to talk about them. Edit: <a href="http://edwardfeser.blogspot.com/2014/02/the-metaphysics-and-aesthetics-of.html?m=1">this article</a> is a well written example of roughly where I'm coming from, although I think it's arbitrarily dogmatic. This <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/080282921X/">book</a> is closer to my beliefs, and one of the best things I've ever read.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>