<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-10-26T15:33:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ji8tv6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_26/ga6b9uu/</link>
  <title>A Steelman of Insane Rambling</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It was fascinating to see people object to you. So, what should be done?  </p>
      <p>I'll try to steelman insane rambling.  </p>
      <p>On one hand, I concur that Kanye is not just insane, but clearly incapable of holding a conversation in the conventional sense. On the other, our notion of sanity may be restrictive: in pursuit of (charitably?) negative-utilitarian welfare or (uncharitably?) Confucian social harmony, we hunt down and brutalise and neuter nascent phenotypes which allow personal expression out of the normal range – even if not all individuals are shown to suffer from living them. Asians are often said to be relatively uncreative and conformist (I've asserted as much too); they're also reportedly more mentally stable than whites. Japanese are famous for picking on students with wrong hair color. Discarding someone like Yeezy is orders of magnitude less irrational, but is irrationality of this action zero? </p>
      <p>I've been awake for 24+ hours (as it not infrequently happens); it has a minor effect. I've been rambling in that first paragraph, just a little bit, layers and layers of dissociation beneath Kanye's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_cuckoo_land">cloud cuckoo land</a>. I could and can do "better", focus my thought, model the modal interlocutor's mind, compress the chain of propositions into a penetrating round, file the rough edges, aim, fire. Is anything lost in the process? A lot, I'd contend. My best-received speeches have all been made in the state of altered consciousness: after a bottle of Crimean wine, swinging around the lamppost and sermonizing about moral imperative, self-important proteins dissolving in the sea and whatever; a three hour long report under stimulants; a cheery confession with LSD in the system... All rambling, all creative, begetting patterns I couldn't come up with in absence of audience. How does it work? On the crudest level, it's mere disinhibition state, the kind that Kanye is prone to enter. Say I have an urge to convey something big and fundamental, involving a plethora of mutual metaphors and inference lines, and an internal censor who says: «you can't <a href="https://twitter.com/0x49fa98/status/1100888518119677952?s=20">correlate these contents</a> and extract their essence; it's part of bigger context than the likes of you can fit, so aim lower». But they are implicitly correlated, their coexistence in my mind is already informative and can arouse insights in another. If only I could share the raw data, even with redundancy and noise, then perhaps... </p>
      <p>"Manic episode", or endogenous disinhibition, is the best tool for dumping raw consciousness logs that we have until Elon perfects his creepy implant. Intelligence is not primarily creative: it is overwhelmingly reductive, an instrument for distilling and pruning mental processes. It is a chisel. There is a famous quote ascribed to sculptor Michelangelo Buonarotti; that his art is merely taking a slab of marble and chipping away everything that is not David. It can be understood (and is told) in two distinct ways: first, as mere humblebrag; second as metaphysical hint that there <em>is</em> David in a formless block of stone, some finished shape waiting to be released. If not for marble, then for contents of one's mind it may well be true. Kanye tries to talk to Joe, but his brain splatters all over the conversation. He's not failing to present a coherent narrative or a doctrine – he's laying it bare, the "Kanye West Thought", interrelated corpus of suspicions and guesses and certainties and knowledge and false positives and spurious associations and hot glue, containing something that he's a couple sd's in intelligence away from grasping and being able to turn into a bullet round, but something he feels <em>is already there</em>, a grandiose paradigm and uplifting lesson, his life's work. Not just Ye but every person is an alchemist, every life a great work, <em>Magnum Opus</em>, and you only get to know what it truly was about in the very end, if ever – so complex and nuanced it is; but wiser men can have a certain inkling, and can try to share it in their own lifetime, use a workaround, sacrifice their conventional sanity and analysis for preternatural synthesis. And occasionally men are born who can't <em>not</em> do this. In the past, those men were probably called seers and shamans. Today we medicate them so that they're more like the rest of us – lest they suffer for being different. In the majority of cases we're justified in doing so, at least within the ruleso of our negative-utilitarian slash Confucian world.<br />
But maybe it's not a tragedy to fail to enforce rules – from time to time.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>