<post>
  <author>iprayiam2</author>
  <date>2020-10-24T01:14:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9txinx/</link>
  <title>Diversity of Opinion Means More Than Two Sides</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>For what it's worth, I replied to your post (actually your follow-up) rather late, but I conceded that I do believe in white privilege, but as a distinction from modal privilege.</p>
      <p>IIRC, in response to your post there were <em>at least</em> these different views:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>privilege is progressive bs</li>
        <li>the privilege you describe is real, but better called modal privilege</li>
        <li>Modal privilege is bunk (granted your view)</li>
        <li>(insert group class) Privilege does exits but its different from modal privilege (mine)</li>
        <li>The fact that you stoop to trivialities is itself representative of "first world problems" style privilege that makes other complaints sound silly</li>
        <li>Yeah that is male privilege but not a big deal, and other privileges make it messy.</li>
        <li>The fact that you notice is a sign of <em>real</em> female privilege.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Of course some of those overlap, but in my view the whole thread created a respectful dialog that included a <strong>wide diversity of opinion</strong>.</p>
      <p>The fact that nobody explicitly came and stanned for the progressive view isn't particularly sad to me. or representative of an echo chamber. (And if theschism wasn't one week old, I'm sure it would have been represented anyway.)</p>
      <p>One of the problems I have with the progressive view,which is likely linked to why they don't post here, is that the tend to collapse the world into untenable binaries (see privilege) on a meta conversational level. Because it is so prevalent, we seem to have accepted the frame that there is the progressive take and the not progressive take, and if the progressive take isn't there, then the whole thing must be an echo chamber. B. S.</p>
      <p>This is also why more liberal subs end up engulfed in progressive takes. It's all a false binary, and that simply isn't represetnative of any nuanced place or discussion.</p>
      <p>No, the progressive take is one of many many many. I'd prefer it to be represented here, but if it's not, oh well. That doesn't make this place one sided. It makes it <em>missing only one side</em>.</p>
      <p>Here in the Motte, conservative Christian like myself has few shared lenses, or frames of reference with the techno libertarians, the classical liberals, the rationalist utilitarians, or the alt-right blackpilled posters that also frequent this place.</p>
      <p>TLDR; I'd love to hear progressive voices here, but they aren't representative of one of only two sides.  Their tendency to frame conversations as an either-or, makes it harder to include them and has tainted the general perception of this place's diversity of opinion.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>