<post>
  <author>Karmaze</author>
  <date>2020-10-24T21:51:57Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9yhc9q/</link>
  <title>Blank Checks Cause Existential Conflict</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So, I think there's two levels of debate here, and they really should be spread apart, otherwise it becomes horribly messy. And I do think there's conflict on both levels. </p>
      <p>The first, is individual level HBD. We don't talk about it much...but this essentially the Blank Slate vs. Biological approach to individual personality and physical characteristics...although maybe we should keep those things separate. Let's just focus on personality characteristics, as that essentially is what we're talking about here, I think. </p>
      <p>The question really does come down to, how flexible are we in terms personality socialization. The Blank Slate argument, is that we're infinite. Do I have to talk about the MASSIVE downsides of that argument, or it plain obvious? </p>
      <p>Truth is, I'm a Nature and Nurture person. Personality traits...some of which certainly affect IQ, we're all born with a set level of them, and from that point, it's like an elastic. The further you stretch it, the more dangerous it can be, the more harm it can do, and the tougher it is to get that one extra "point" of a trait. </p>
      <p>I don't think IQ is the end-all and be all of success anyway. I'd trade 20 IQ points in a HEARTBEAT to get rid of my (largely innate and heredical) anxiety issues. I believe I'd have more success, and have more value overall. (It's possible that losing 20 IQ points would solve the anxiety issues in and of itself) </p>
      <p>But when it comes to group level HBD...first of all, let's just get rid of the absolute racists. The people who think that Obama has a lower IQ than any white person, for an example. (How many are those?). </p>
      <p>But I think one thing has to be recognized. I personally consider this the Charles Murray argument. Group-level HBD as strictly a defensive tool, against the sort of "God of the Gaps" systemic racism that's impossible to have anything close to a rational discussion about. Different results? Must be racism! (or sexism, or whatever). If the "God of the Gaps" argument goes away....how much of the Group-level HBD argument goes along with it? I think that's the real question. </p>
      <p>I suspect most of it, to be frank. How many people absolutely think there's zero racism in the world? My guess is that number is fairly low. Most people are willing to say, when they see something they perceive as actually racist....yeah...that's racist.  But...this can't be a systemic argument. It has to be a systematic argument. You have to show where the racism is, so we can fix it. It can't be just a blank check. </p>
      <p>On that note, I have a new rule: Blank Checks cause Existential Conflict. What that means, is that when causes are seen to be asking for a Blank Check, the incentivized reaction, is to act like the value of that Check is going to be infinite. If you don't want people to react that way, then make sure that Check has an actual number on it, I.E. set clear policy intentions, goals and limits. </p>
      <p>Edit: I just want to add one thing...this isn't a hypothetical. I live in an area that has a very large social justice-type controversy right now, and the whole thing is being MASSIVELY inflamed by Blank Check writing by largely outsiders. </p>
      <p>I think the embracing of this sort of Group HBD, is the reaction to what people see as a Blank Check. I think even if people think that there might be innate differences, it's all going to take an overlapping modal form, right? It's not something that justifies individual level racism, just that we shouldn't freak out over the results. </p>
      <p>I'm not convinced about what level of actual biological differences there are between races. (Sex is a different story, which I do believe is bimodal) BUT. I'm not convinced that's the point either. Again, are there some hardcore racists out there? Sure. But I'm not convinced those numbers are meaningful, and frankly, I think the level of bias they have will make it hard for them to get any sort of real power, because their handle on reality really isn't there.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>which is intuitive because what other than racism would promote bias in social science? I can't think of anything more distorting.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Social status bias. It's one thing that hasn't been tackled at all. One would need to internalize the history of academia, at least in the US, into to how it for a long time (and in some ways still does) signal more about socioeconomic class, and the ability to fit in, rather than actual knowledge obtained.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>