<post>
  <author>Rumpole_of_The_Motte</author>
  <date>2020-10-23T09:56:57Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9qsvmj/</link>
  <title>Lefties: Born This Way</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Sounds like you've been so thoroughly indoctrinated by the man that you don't even know you're being oppressed. We're as born this way as any gay man, and more of us have been subjected to conversion therapy too, yet some how no one cares. Where are our reparations? You pick up a phone at the office, the number pad is to the right of the receiver, no awkward cross-ups or cords in the way for a righty. I look around and even the locks on my office file cabinets are on the right corner. Its disgusting. Most lefties have learned to use their right hand to get by, just like black people have to code switch to get by in a white man's world. </p>
      <p>I have adapted fine in a right man's world. I'm ambidextrous enough to get by except for handwriting and some fine motor skills like cutting and stitching. Some of this is unconsciously trained, but I'm sure there is some biological component to one's ability to be ambidextrous. Maybe some lefties don't adapt as easily. Should they have to? Does that fact that you or I don't think it's a big deal absolve the world from their disgusting anti-lefty bigotry?</p>
      <p>I think its an interesting question in all seriousness. A lot of times space and tech limitations force you to make design choices that hurt lefties. We're a minority, and it makes sense to design against us if there is really no choice. What kinds of innovation would we suppress if we required everything to be ambidextrous? Maybe not much now, but surely a great many things 100 years ago. The tech we allowed to unjustly oppress us (right handed mouses) has lead to innovations that liberate us (universal trackpads). Maybe there is a case for forgiving the past and working towards a better future, but that would take a vision of privilege that seeks progress rather than power and its just way more fun to call people bigots than it is to actually make a difference.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>