<post>
  <author>sodiummuffin</author>
  <date>2020-10-27T22:39:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ji8tv6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_26/gablu05/</link>
  <title>HBD Proponents On Jewish Brilliance</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>On the other hand the same question applied to Jewish people tends to send so many into contortions.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>...really? I would say they they are actually the main proponents of the idea and I've almost exclusively seen support towards it from them. At most I once read an article from a pro-HBD source suggesting that Jewish representation at elite universities is so extreme that it can't only be the result of IQ and location so discrimination/nepotism might also play a role, but even that article took for granted that Ashkenazi Jews are more intelligent and that difference is genetic in origin.</p>
      <p>Kirkegaard, a vocal HBD supporter who has commented in this subreddit, is one of the authors for papers like "<a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/330601752_Polygenic_Scores_Mediate_the_Jewish_Phenotypic_Advantage_in_Educational_Attainment_and_Cognitive_Ability_Compared_With_Catholics_and_Lutherans">Polygenic Scores Mediate the Jewish Phenotypic Advantage in Educational Attainment and Cognitive Ability Compared With Catholics and Lutherans</a>". Gregory Cochran, another vocal HBD supporter, is the lead author for <a href="https://web.mit.edu/fustflum/documents/papers/AshkenaziIQ.jbiosocsci.pdf">Natural History of Ashkenazi Intelligence</a>. Charles Murray, author of <em>The Bell Curve</em>, has written things such as the article <a href="https://www.commentarymagazine.com/articles/charles-murray/jewish-genius/">Jewish Genius</a>. <em>Intelligence</em>, which is the most prominent journal on intelligence research and probably one of the most prominent scientific journals to routinely publish pro-HBD research, publishes studies like <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0160289614000130">Spearman's hypothesis tested on European Jews vs non-Jewish Whites and vs Oriental Jews: Two meta-analyses</a>. Richard Lynn, who as you can tell from his Wikipedia article has been aggressively targeted by anti-HBD people and media outlets as the avatar of "racism infiltrating science" (as if his positions are exclusive to him rather than largely resembling the majority positions among experts on intelligence, it reminds me of the global warming denier obsession with Michael Mann) wrote <em>The Chosen People: A Study of Jewish Intelligence and Achievements</em>, a 400-page book that argues high intelligence is the principal factor responsible for Ashkenazi Jewish achievements. A search of pro-HBD blog Gene Expression finds plenty of coverage for <em>Natural History of Ashkenazi Intelligence</em>. Blogger Steve Sailer has various posts <a href="https://archive.is/wip/hpDZA">supporting</a> it. Blogger HBDchick doesn't seem to have commented on the subject much, but a quick search of her twitter finds a <a href="https://archive.is/Tbz9k">tweet</a> taking for granted that Ashkenazi intelligence is the product of natural selection. I can't search the HBD subreddit because Reddit banned it, but using Google showed they had at least some posts titled things like "The Genetic Origin of Ashkenazi Genius". That's pretty much every notable HBD proponent I can think of at the moment, all of them that I checked supported the idea with some publishing scientific studies, essays, or writing a book devoted to the subject.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>