<post>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2021-01-11T15:21:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/giw11ac/</link>
  <title>How European:nationalism::American:corporatism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Right. The European idea of state is very different from the American one. In America the state (usually rather called "the government" by Americans) by default is seen as an external entity that is somehow there, descended from an alien spaceship, like some pest or disease, some invasive weed that must be kept in check. The government is a "them", an adversary. If it does something good for you, that's just a nice accident, otherwise it's just acting in its own interest of self preservation and resource acquisition for its own growth. It's a patriotic duty of people to protect themselves from the state. </p>
      <p>The default in European democracies is to see the state as "us". Sure, we don't like the politicians all the time politically, but that's a defect, a deviation from the intended way of things. The state is a replacement of a benevolent Mufasa-like king. From our taxes it pays us child care money, organizes free-at-the-point-of-use health care, tuition free education, protects consumers against greedy lying corporations, generally is there to advocate for citizens, it shouldn't have interests on its own, it is supposed to mediate and facilitate people's interests. When it doesn't do this, it's corruption and people are angry and want it to do these things better. In America people who are dissatisfied with govt would rather want it to gtfo and let people settle things without interference.</p>
      <p>We in Europe by default tend to see profit seeking powerful corporations as more dangerous than the elected state apparatus. In America it's the reverse and being ruled by corporations is seen as good because they can't imprison you.</p>
      <p>I'm not saying either extreme is good. Just that the underlying attitude and atmosphere that one grows up in is fundamentally different. Plus the whole deal with positive and negative freedoms. </p>
      <p>Germany forbids Holocaust denial and this is largely backed by the popular consensus. It's defined in the law, and is known to everyone. Again you may not like it, but at least the rules are clear and don't change arbitrarily every week in opaque ways according to profit interests.</p>
      <p>It makes communication across the Atlantic quite difficult and the respective right and left sides often get confused when discussing with their counterparts on the other side of the pond.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>