<post>
  <author>FCfromSSC</author>
  <date>2021-01-09T19:24:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/giom5ab/</link>
  <title>Effortfully grasping accountability for the Capitol riot. (2/2)</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>2/2</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Of course, all this generally leads back to connections to political figures. Usually, this immediately descends into a morass of quibbling over the meaning of denunciations and statements. Did this politician encourage? Did that politician disavow? In my experience, those conversations are useless. I think it is useful to instead look at actions.</p>
      <p>In the few days since the riot, the Republican party leadership has turned against Trump. A massive ban wave has swept the entire social media ecosystem. A new national security bill has been presented to congress. Censorship is being rolled out across the internet. And of course, there's the incidentals: a wave of harassment, doxxing, cancellations, etc, etc, all the normal stuff.</p>
      <p>This is what it looks like when people <em>take an event seriously</em>.</p>
      <p>Show me where people took it seriously when explicitly political riots rocked a hundred cities. Show me a similar level of concern when masked men with guns declared themselves the rulers of a neighborhood that did not elect them and had not requested their presence, and then proceeded to shoot unarmed civilians. Show me a similar level of concern when a politically-motivated gunman attempted to massacre republican congressmen, or when a BLM supporter attempted to massacre cops, or when a gang of thugs openly celebrated the murder of a political opponent in public, on video.</p>
      <p>None of those events, or any of the hundreds of others, were <em>taken seriously</em>. Instead, those events were minimized, excused, or ignored. No sweeping new security laws were passed. Social pressure was not applied. In fact, the exact opposite happened: attempts by government officials and by Trump himself to crack down on the lawlessness were actively opposed. Criticism of the rioters was itself grounds for social sanction. Even calling them riots was strongly opposed by a broad cross-section of the blue-tribe mainstream, all the way up to senior elected officials and, not coincidentally, most of the prominent blues here. Bail was raised for those arrested for criminal violence by Biden's own staff. A major media outlet made a decent attempt at turning a political murderer into a hero. Normal citizens who tried to defend themselves from lawless violence were targeted by the full power of the government and the hate of half a nation, and no one that mattered did a thing about it. No serious attempt was made to moderate BLM and Antifa extremists on social media. Twitter still allows open calls for political violence, so long as they target the right people. No one is calling for Twitter to be shut down or to be banned from app stores or to be denied payment processing.</p>
      <p>Nothing was done, because the truth is that for the overwhelming majority, "who, whom" is all that ever mattered. Sadly, it seems to me that posters here are no exception. I think it is pretty clear that things get worse from this point. It might be slow and it might be quick,  but I do not think the events of the last six years are survivable for our society. Blue Tribe does not believe that anything outside itself should exist, it does not hold itself accountable for its excesses, and it has now secured a stranglehold on both social and political power. It will not accept checks or balances on its powers, and it will never stop pushing until things break down completely. Doubtless Blue Tribers could make an inverse critique of Red Tribe, that our stubborn refusal to accept necessary changes will plunge us all into disaster. All I know is that the same people who argued that a baker declining to cater a gay wedding was necessarily a matter that should be fought to the supreme court, also argue that uniformed gangs of thugs openly celebrating a political murder is simply an irrelevant local issue. They cannot bring themselves to leave us in peace, and they cannot bring themselves to hold their own accountable, and that combination will not be sustainable long-term.</p>
      <p>A great many posters here argued that Biden would be a return to normal, a new dawn of reconciliation and healing. He hasn't even been inaugurated yet, and I think we can safely lay those predictions to rest. The Culture war is not going away, because at the end of the day it is not about internet bullshit, but rather about serious issues in the lives of tens of millions of American citizens. The fact that Big Tech and the federal government are going to be working together to ensure that people like me can't effectively communicate and organize politically matters on an extremely fundamental level. We are not going away, and pretending otherwise will cost us all a great deal sooner or later.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>2/2</strong>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>