<post>
  <author>FCfromSSC</author>
  <date>2021-01-09T19:24:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/giom3iw/</link>
  <title>Effortfully grasping accountability for the Capitol riot. (1/2)</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>1/2</strong>
      </p>
      <p>One of the long-running arguments here has been over appropriate responses to illegal violence. People compare the violence and lawlessness of this recent riot to the BLM riots of last summer, and they compare the responses to those riots by, say, Trump and Biden. People make these comparisons in an attempt to find common ground with those different from them. Speaking generally, they fail.</p>
      <p>First, we can ask whether the violence is comparable. On a purely kinetic level, the question itself is absurd. Last summer saw riots in over a hundred cities, well over a billion dollars in damage, dozens of murders, an uncountable number of assaults and injuries, thousands of buildings torched or vandalized. This recent riot saw some windows smashed, trespassing by a mob, and a police officer murdered. Many individual riots last summer were worse than this event in terms of damage and harm, and the cumulative effect was overwhelmingly worse in those terms as well.</p>
      <p>Riots aren't just about the money and the injuries, though. They are also political acts. The current meme seems to be that this riot is somehow worse, because it targeted congress and the electoral vote counting. By attempting to interfere with the legitimate function of government, relatively mundane violence is elevated into something much more sinister: an attempted coup, insurrection, terrorism, etc, etc.</p>
      <p>Seeing this argument being taken seriously is quite the experience. A very large number of BLM riots have been obviously intended to interfere with the legitimate function of government, by punishing government officials for their actions or intimidating them into acting in a way the rioters prefer. Mobs have previously accosted elected officials in public, at their homes, or within the capitol building itself, often in a naked attempt to either influence or to punish them for their voting. Elected representatives have been assaulted and even shot.</p>
      <p>Variance is fractal, and no two events are perfectly identical. I am not aware of a previous riot entering the capitol building during verification of the electoral college. But if there were an actual principle at stake here, I would expect a roughly similar argument to be deployed in roughly similar circumstances, and it was not, ever, in as long as I've followed politics. Every conversation about race riots I've seen or participated in has operated on the basic understanding that the riot is a political act intended to use lawless violence to exert pressure on duly elected governments. Those sympathetic to the rioters have always started from that assumption, and argued that the rioters believe the law is wrong, dysfunctional, or otherwise broken, and that therefore lawless action is at least understandable. Those unsympathetic to the rioters argue that the law works fine, and the rioters are simply criminals or malcontents.</p>
      <p>Until now, I do not believe I've ever seen an argument that, regardless of the justice or lack thereof of the rioters' cause, officials and official rituals are sacrosanct and interfering with them is a crime against democracy itself. I am highly confident that such an argument would have been laughed out of the room in any other context. Nor do I see any attempt by those making this argument to demonstrate a consistent principle based on previous incidents, especially incidents where their own side was in the wrong. It should go without saying, but if you're going to claim to have principles, it should be possible to distinguish those principles from "my side is always right." It is at least a colorable argument that this riot is the most dangerous riot we've ever had, on whatever scale one uses to define danger. It is not a colorable argument that this riot is the <em>only</em> dangerous riot we've ever had.</p>
      <p>Some have argued that violence against officials is more serious than violence against normal citizens, because the citizens have only very indirect political power, and the officials have direct political power, so attacking politicians will get them to do what you want whereas attacking normal citizens is pointless. This is wrong in two ways. First, whether speaking of riots or terrorism, it is commonly understood that the point of attacking normal citizens is explicitly to influence the decisions of their government, both because the government wishes to keep their citizens safe, and because the citizens will pressure the government to appease those harming them. Second, because attacking individuals directly makes them less sympathetic to your cause, not more. Beating a congressperson is not going to convince him to vote your way. You will go to jail, and he will hate you and your cause much more than he did before. I feel comfortable claiming this is simply common knowledge; if anyone disagrees, I will try and draw examples from the riot discussions of the last year.</p>
      <p>Others have argued that the mob's intention was to seize power directly, that this was a coup. The evident fact that the mob had no way of securing any sort of long-term power or legitimacy, nor even showed any evidence of organization or an actual abstract goal beyond "keep moving forward in physical space" is handwaved away by claiming that their incompetence doesn't absolve their intent, which was to overturn a legitimate election. Again, no attempt is made to connect the claimed principle to previous events, especially bipartisan ones. We've had organized groups armed with rifles take over portions of major cities, deny access to the police and civil authorities, declare themselves sovereign over everyone living inside their perimeter, and shoot people they didn't like dead. We've had numerous attacks on federal agents and facilities, on senior government officials and on their families. Again, no two incidents are the same, but similar incidents should at least suggest similar principles. They haven't, ever.</p>
      <p>The rioters themselves did not believe the election was legitimate. One can argue whether they were right or wrong in this belief, but one cannot claim that their intent was to overthrow an election they themselves <em>knew to be legitimate</em>. If we are judging lawless actions with no accounting for the beliefs and motives of the rioters, but purely by our own assessment of the actual facts, last year's actions take on a very different color. Those claiming the rioters were attempting a coup are making an extremely isolated demand for absurd rigor.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>1/2</strong>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>