<post>
  <author>fIexibeast</author>
  <date>2021-01-11T11:34:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/giv9ono/</link>
  <title>The idea that meaningful freedom of speech should extend *at least* to the leader of the biggest opposition party</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is one of the reasons "freedom of association" and "free market" sloganeering is moot. Interpreting decisions by entities of this size as free market decisions is not possible. It's free association only to the extent that Lockheed-Martin not selling arms to Iran, or Baidu not serving up photos of the Tiananmen Square protests can be interpreted as freedom of association. It's not possible to conclude that an act of censorship is <em>not</em> a state or government entity wielding its power merely because it is done by a private company.</p>
      <p>Nominally, Tencent is a privately owned company freely choosing who they provide a platform to. But in fact they have absolutely no choice but to ban Winnie the Pooh from WeChat, unless they want a state apparatus to come down on them and make their lives incredibly difficult.</p>
      <p>The US companies involved in the purge are not mom-and-pop stores exercising their free association rights in accordance with stated personal beliefs, but big tech companies, multiply intertwined with public authority and the political parties, lobbying and making political contributions on one side, seeking political approval and avoiding threats of regulatory retaliation on the other. They know full well that if they ban the wrong speech and refuse to ban the "right" speech, they face being regulated out of business. Seeing the threat, they scramble to align with the incoming administration. It's problematic to call this free and voluntary association and not government censorship, because with entities of this size, <em>the government is always involved</em>, by its very nature in a coercive capacity.</p>
      <p>We're not talking about people with fringe views having to move to equally fringe platforms. We're talking about the Trump campaign, the campaign of the largest (soon-to-be-)opposition party, being purged from all major platforms en masse, while even people like Navalny, who have significant credibility in matters of free speech, denounce these acts as "unacceptable acts of censorship" (despite being on bad terms with the Trump administration, which took Russia's side in the recent poisoning case). You really don't have to be a free speech absolutist to care: you just have to use the convention, reasonably common, that any meaningful freedom of speech should extend at least to the leader of the biggest opposition party.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>