<post>
  <author>HlynkaCG</author>
  <date>2021-01-11T01:58:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/gitspzj/</link>
  <title>The existence of "inalienable rights" as a point of fundamental political dispute</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Firstly, I'll state that there are no inalienable rights in a practical sense.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>...and right off the bat I'd say you've struck one of the fundamental points of dispute between the Anglo-American right  (what was the old "liberal" order) and pretty much every other intellectual tradition on the planet, including the modern progressive left.</p>
      <p>We do not survey the facts on the ground and arrive at the "rational conclusion" of inalienable human rights existing in a practical / physical sense as you describe. <em>We hold these truths to be self evident</em> from the start. Anyone who disagrees is free to do so, but preferably from somewhere down range. </p>
      <p>The educated cosmopolitan urbanite sees culture as superficial because he can travel from a franchise restaurant in Paris to a franchise restaurant Tokyo without ever leaving his bubble of urban cosmopolitanism or ever having to engage with groups of people in a visceral way. Everything is a re-skin of a re-skin, everything is atomized.</p>
      <p>But this shit does matter. the idea that every individual has rights and agency worthy of consideration is one of those pills of an idea that has myriad downstream effects on how one interacts with people and how groups interact with each other, even if it's something that's never consciously articulated or considered. </p>
      <p>Heck just down thread we have <a href="/u/JTarrou">u/JTarrou</a> and <a href="/u/ulyssessword">u/ulyssessword</a> arguing, in effect, that might makes right. Having dismissed the concept of inalienable rights, can you tell them that they are wrong? Do you want to?</p>
      <p>Edit: spelling / formatting</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>