<post>
  <author>LacklustreFriend</author>
  <date>2021-01-09T18:34:09Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ksxidt/friday_fun_thread_for_january_08_2021/giofpvl/</link>
  <title>Reviewing Cyberpunk 2077</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>In last week's thread I started a Cyberpunk "rant review" that's now finished, and I'm reposting here for visibility. Here it is its ranty, unstructured, unproofread glory. I'm also thinking of writing something a bit more substantial on the themes of Cyberpunk 2077's story if people are interested in that.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>So I finally finished Cyberpunk 2077 and I have got to say I both love and hate (well, strongly dislike) the game. I want to vent my thoughts about the game in a half-review/half-unstructured rant and I feel this is a good place as any.</p>
      <h1>Summary Review of Cyberpunk 2077</h1>
      <p>
        <strong>Positives</strong>
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>Phenomenal character writing (perhaps with the exception of V, ironically)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Strong plot/main story (if rough in some parts)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Phenomenal "side" stories</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Managed to balance the high philosophical elements of cyberpunk with  personal, simple stories reasonably well.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Game looks fantastic, not just "technically", but including art and environment design</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Fantastic soundtrack</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Not really a "positive" but acceptable core gameplay/combat</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <strong>Negatives</strong>
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>The ubiquitous and infamous technical issues, performance and glitches</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>An outdated, at best, progression/perk system. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Absolutely atrocious loot/crafting/gear system</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The awful AI, if it can even be called that</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Complete lack of a meaningful "open world", including customisation </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The huge amount of cut content/ideas and systems left in the game that you can still see fragments of. Presumably due to time constraints, lack of development time, and I assume changing design direction.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>General lack of polish and balance</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <strong>As a Whole</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Cyberpunk 2077 is a game that I couldn't help but falling in love with due to the storytelling, characters and atmosphere. At the same time, there were many times I found myself frustrated and actively hating the game for bizarre game design decisions and the many undercooked elements of game. I would say "diamond in the rough", but that would be unfair to all the games that are the actual rough diamonds. Perhaps "diamond in the rough that also happens to be in a mound of dried dog shit". Many problems the game has go deeper than just technical issues that can be fixed, and I think rushed development and changing design ruined what could have been a "breath-taking" game. I would recommend this game only to people love story driven games and don't mind all the shit, in the vein of Vampire the Masquerade Bloodlines, or Fallout NV.</p>
      <hr />
      <h1>Indepth "Discussion"</h1>
      <p>
        <strong>Technical Issues</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I want to get this out of the way early and quickly. Yes, the game is a technical mess. Yes, it has many glitches, including some potentially game-breaking ones. Yes, basically the bad things said on this topic are true.</p>
      <p>I really don't have much else to say. This is not to excuse the horrendous launch state of Cyberpunk 2077, but rather there is nothing I can meaningfully add to this issue, many other outlets have gone into great detail. Moreover, I think the discussion the actual game past all the technical issues has been lacking, both the good and bad. In fact, I think in some ironic way the technical bugs may have actually worked in CDPR's favour, distracting from the seriously lacklustre gameplay elements. So I'd rather talk about that instead.</p>
      <p>Also as a side note I see a lot of people taking about the "7/8 year development" of Cyberpunk 2077. This is misleading you can find interviews with CDPR stating that development (pre-production, even) only really began after Witcher 3 was finished, and Cyberpunk 2077 probably had closer to a 4-ish year development cycle which makes sense considering how half-baked it feels.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Art and Sound</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I am not a hugely creative individual, so I don't want to spend too long on something I am no expert on. The game is extremely pretty, even if you don't have a fancy, high end RTX card (though you probably do want something like a 1060 at a minimum). </p>
      <p>The art direction and environment design is fantastic. The design and look of Night City goes a long, long way in making it believable (shame it's so lifeless). There is a lot of detail placed into the environment. I have to specifically mention the car interiors, they are honestly fucking awesome.</p>
      <p>The original soundtrack is also fucking awesome. It is one of the best soundtrack's I've heard, and probably better than Witcher 3. I will mention <em>Johnny Silverhand's Theme/The Rebel Path</em> and <em>Never Fade Away</em> (cover in particular) as being near perfect and great pieces of music even outside the game. <em>Mining Minds</em> also has a special place in my heart for how well it's used in the game.</p>
      <p>I strongly suspect the reason the art and sound is one of the best parts of the game is because it had a head start with a skeleton crew before full production, but also because it likely wasn't subjected to the changes in direction I believe the rest of the game had.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Gameplay - Core</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Before I start on the hugely negative parts of the gameplay, I would be mildly positive and say the core gameplay of Cyberpunk 2077 is reasonably solid. Gunplay feels very fluid, firing weapons of all types felt very satisfying and the best part of combat. Melee combat is okay if you accept it's more about moving from enemy to enemy quickly than meaningful melee mechanics. Stealth is also just okay. Quickhacking or "spells" can be pretty clunky to use but can be quite fun when you develop it enough and can combo hacks.</p>
      <p>I can't help but feel the core gameplay elements are undermined by "dripfeeding" some of the fun elements. You know, where a game will only give you the fun toys later in the game but by the time you get them the game's almost over. This applies to both melee and quickhacking. This is particularly prevalent with a lot of movement options. Things like shoot and reload while sliding, or dodge while in air are locked behind perks, when they should really be in the standard game kit. My biggest piece of advice is <strong>get the double jump cybernetic asap</strong>. I can't understate how much this this improves the gameplay. More movement for melee, opens up more creative routes for stealth and exploring, and just makes moving through the world that much more fun. I imagine many players experiences would have been substantially improved the game shoehorned them into getting that cybernetic.</p>
      <p>One thing that I have only realize in retrospect and looking into after the fact is how the armor system works and how terrible it is. Basically, every 10 armor reduces the amount of damage you take by a flat 1 damage. Anyone who has experienced similar system before or interested in game design would probably recognize why this is a terrible system. Simply put, it is an extremely easy system to break (in an RPG without static damage numbers). If the player manages to get too much armor, they become practically invincible, too little and they get one-shot. It also disproportionally affects weapon types - submachine guns become worthless quickly, sniper rifles overpowered. Armor that applies percentage reduction is almost always preferred - even Skyrim manage to get this right. If something more detailed or complex is required then an mixed armor system where different armor types protect against different damage types or weapons is possible, but I guess that would require extensive playtesting and balance which is why it's not in Cyberpunk.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Gameplay - Character Progression</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The progression system, including stats and perks is outdated at best, and horribly broken at worst. The Perks are awful. The vast majority of perk options are meaningless % damage modifiers that increase or decrease X. I seriously thought we had grown past this design for single player, story driven RPGs. And these are the "good perks" in Cyberpunk 2077! Not to mention the completely completely useless ones, the epitome being a perk that reduces fall damage taken by a whopping <strong>5%</strong>. But wait, it gets better! There's perks that are actually <em>hinder</em> you too! A perk that automatically disassembles all junk for you! Why is a QoL feature a perk? Who knows! But wait, you don't actually want to always dissemble all your junk, cause sometimes it's valuable and you want to sell it instead! A stealth perk to throws knifes! Cool! Except it throws knifes from your inventory and permanently destroys them. Oops, goodbye iconic legendary knife!</p>
      <p>A positive of the perk system might be that you take perks from any group and build your character however you want - until you realise you're more or less forced to take perks from all groups because of how many are shit. Also the fact crafting requires serious investment from perks and tech points is so ridiculously stupid (more on this later). Imagine if in Witcher 3 you had to spend 1/3 of your perk points in a crafting tree to unlock crafting witcher gear. </p>
      <p>Part of the problem is that the cybernetic upgrade system is also kind of perk system so many of the options that normally would be in a perk tree (e.g. double jump, slow time, major stat increases etc) are instead in the cybernetic tree, so there's two competing perk trees. I don't know how exactly to fix this but the perk tree needs an overhaul of some kind and possible integration with the cybernetic system (like Deus Ex Human Revolution?)</p>
      <p>This bad progression system also distracts from more "nitpicky" discussions of the stat system like "Is having an evasion stat good for an FPS RPG?" or "Is having stealth and the cold blood mechanic under the same stat a good idea?" But it's sort of beyond the pale for the current state of the game.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>
        <strong>COMMENT 1/3</strong>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>