<post>
  <author>motteolotteo</author>
  <date>2021-01-10T21:30:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ku9u8d/smallscale_question_sunday_for_january_10_2021/gisvfj2/</link>
  <title>Why ex-Mormons seem so much more anti-religious than the median ex-Christian</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm an ex-mormon. I don't <em>really</em> consider myself to be [strongly] anti-christian nor [strongly] anti-religion, but I am pretty solidly atheist. I may not be the most rabid, but I'll try to speculate on possible factors.</p>
      <p>Brainstorming, the possible explanatory factors are:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>An epistemology  of "prove it to yourself"</li>
        <li>"The church is true."</li>
        <li>A culture which may be more puritanical than comparable American religions</li>
        <li>separatism</li>
        <li>edit: identity</li>
        <li>High bar for exit (filtering)</li>
        <li>High bar for exit (self-justification)</li>
        <li>Different demographics than other American religions</li>
      </ul>
      <p>I'll dive in to each of these.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>An epistemology of "prove it to yourself"</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The founding myth of the LDS church is, basically, that Joseph Smith saw multiple competing churches, and wanted to pick the correct one. So, he studied on the question, thought about it, and then asked God directly. God's answer was "none of them. go make your own".</p>
      <p>This seems like a natural progression of the protestant reformation, and you see some similar themes coming out of other churches from the American Restoration era. In modern Mormonism, this idea of "prove it to yourself" and "you can receive personal revelation directly from God" permeates every teaching of the church.</p>
      <p>In a lot of ways, it's a church of "listen to your headcanon" (unless that headcanon is directly contradicted by the published canon of the prophets).</p>
      <p>Edit: Also of note, the church / culture of the church also puts a pretty high emphasis on studying other religions, being aware of their teachings &amp; precepts. I'd expect the average Mormon to be more knowledgeable about specifics of Buddhism, Janism, Shinto, Protestantism, Baptism, Catholicism, etc., than the average American (excepting members of those particular religions).</p>
      <p>Due to this, I'm under the impression that active mormons are more likely to be strong True Believers. Conversely, when people exit, they're going to exit because that epistemology has led them to believe that it's very much and very provably <em>not</em> true. Under an epistemology of "convince yourself", there's less middle ground to believe things only sorta-kinda.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>"The church is true"</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Perhaps more than other mainstream religions, the LDS church spills a lot of ink and a lot of breath teaching its members how their <em>particular</em> take on religion is correct, and others are more or less correct to the extent that they match up with Mormonism. Again, it doesn't really allow for wishy-washy feelings.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>A culture which may be more puritanical than comparable American religions</strong>
      </p>
      <p>This is perhaps debatable, I don't have stats to back this up, just a feeling. Many churches have prescriptions for correct behavior. I think the LDS church has more than average, and there's a strong culture of <em>really</em> believing that one needs to abide by those prescriptions. Off the top of my head:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Ingest no mood-altering or addictive substances. No alchohol, no tobacco, no marijuana. Famously, even caffeine is pretty iffy.</li>
        <li>No premarital sex.</li>
        <li>No pornography.</li>
        <li>Heck, no masturbation on your own.</li>
        <li>And certainly you should never act out on or encourage any same-gender romance or cross-gender behavior. The genders are a direct divine construction from God.</li>
        <li>You should try and only consume media that exemplifies your values. If a movie is rated R, there's a good chance you'll either not watch it, or feel mildly guilty for doing so.</li>
        <li>etc.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Now, to be clear, I'm not going to argue here that any or all of these are necessarily a <em>bad idea</em> as social mores and prescriptions for creating a good society. But, for some people, the sum total of all this behavioral prescriptivism, especially with something as instinct-based as sexuality.</p>
      <p>This can lead to a good deal of mental stress while in the church, reflected as more rabidity once exited.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>separatism</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The Mormon church does a thorough job of teaching how-and-why its different than other churches. Several of the behavior prescriptions are explicitly, said-out-loud to be about marking yourself as separate from society, at least culturally. Also, several of the other more banal points of theology are just notably different than other churches, and incompatible.</p>
      <p>Because of this, after exiting, it's less likely that an ex-member will land in a <em>different</em> christian church, and more likely that they'll just become non-religious, or much more modernly "spiritual but not religious".</p>
      <p>
        <strong>edit: identity</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I think Mormons tend to have their religion as a very strong part of their identity. They're not <em>merely</em> Americans, they're Mormon Americans. On exiting, they can't be "Mormons" any more, so it's not surprising many would take "ex-mormon" as a new identifier.</p>
      <p>Some atheists are of the "well you can't prove or disprove there's a teapot in the oort cloud" variety, and some are more of the "religion is harmful to the fair and just operation of society" variety. i.e., atheists who simply don't believe vs. atheists who need to anti-believe. I think there's an analogy here - after believing, it's hard to <em>merely</em> not-believe Mormonism.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>High bar for exit (filtering)</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Exiting the church is going to be difficult. The church is a very strong social fabric, and really leaving that means giving up a huge social network, lots of events. Plus, the church spends a lot of time teaching and encouraging retention, and encouraging members to justify to themselves their continued membership.</p>
      <p>Because of all this, a wishy-washy member will probably stay in, and only those who overcome a high activation energy exit. This would make exiters more rabid, on average. Sort of the opposite of a social 'evaporative cooling' maybe?</p>
      <p>
        <strong>High bar for exit (self-justification)</strong>
      </p>
      <p>While in the church, a member was continually convincing themselves of its truth, and it was a HUGE part of their identity.</p>
      <p>After exiting, there's bound to be cognitive dissonance. The now-ex-mormon will need to more loudly assert their new identity.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Different demographics than other American religions</strong>
      </p>
      <p>There've been studies that suggest, in America, most churches have an inverse relationship between educational attainment and religosity - the more secularly successful, the less you turn to the church.</p>
      <p>These studies often find Mormonism as an exception to that. From my experience, if I had to describe the <em>stereotypical</em> Morman family, it would be</p>
      <ul>
        <li>The father is white, college-educated, and owns a small business, works his own medical practice, or has some white-collar occupation</li>
        <li>The mother is white, college-educated, and might work part-time, have a serious hobby, or might have a multi-level-marketing side hustle that they <em>really hustle</em>.</li>
        <li>3-8 children. High academic expectations are a baseline, they're probably going to be in at least one focused extracurricular, whether sports, art, music, mathletes, etc. They're expected to go to college (with BYU as a strong default), and move out of the house, be self-sufficient, and married, by ~25ish.</li>
        <li>They live in a <em>nice</em> house in the suburbs. Even if they don't have a lot of money, and they're in a smaller house or renting, their home is well-decorated and well-organized.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>All this to say, that maybe the baseline demographic of Mormonism is one that would tend to be irreligious or anti-religious <em>by default</em>, and Mormonism just happens to capture this demographic more successfully than most. So, when exiting the church, you've got that baseline to fall back on.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Sorry if this is a bit long-winded, and hope it helps. That's my impression of things, anyway. On leaving the church, I think I felt most of these, to greater or lesser extents. For me, it was <em>primarily</em> about the epistemology that had once convinced me to accept the church as true, on further thought, led me to believe it was not true.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>