<post>
  <author>wlxd</author>
  <date>2021-01-11T22:24:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/gixngq1/</link>
  <title>Defending Microsoft against selective application of anti-anti-competition arguments</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is extremely specious argument that's only ever applied to the particular instance of Microsoft and IE. It also misses the sine qua non of the entire argument: that Microsoft enjoyed monopoly market power. </p>
      <p>Consider, for example, car radios: it used to be the case that car radios were standardized form factor, and were easily swappable. You used to have to pay for them separately, and there were entire companies built around car stereos. Today, the radios are included in cars "for free", and they most definitely cannot be uninstalled with significant trouble. Sure, some people might complain that they are no longer able to swap stereo in their car, but I haven't ever had anyone suggest that this new integrated stereo practice is somewhat illegal.</p>
      <p>No, as I said, the sine qua non of the entire argument is that Microsoft enjoyed monopoly power. Without the alleged monopoly power, the practice of bundling the browser with the operating system in a way that "causes trouble" if it's removed, is, according to anti-trust litigators, totally fine. That's exactly what Apple is doing with Safari on iOS, and it in fact goes even further than that: not only you literally cannot remove it, but also all other browsers are <em>forced to actually use Safari under the hood</em>. </p>
      <p>The reason this argument is specious is that the relevance of monopoly power here is completely illusory. Consider, for example, GMail. Google doesn't really have a literal monopoly on anything. However, it has immense profits from its ads industry, which allow it to subsidize their mail product, and run it at a loss, indefinitely. You used to build company around providing high end mail services, up until GMail came up with free 1 GB mailbox, something that nobody else imagined at the time. Today, most of the email product market is captured by megacorps that all subsidize the email products from the profits of other segments (except Microsoft, which actually does seem to make money on their enterprise offerings). How does the fact that there's no monopoly makes it any easier for new market entrant to provide service comparable to GMail at similar cost, i.e. $0? The "monopoly market power" is very much a red herring here, as it is just as hard to compete with monopoly as it is with oligopoly, if they all provide superior service for free, thanks to being able to run a different business model.</p>
      <p>Truth is, Microsoft was just vindictively attacked based on very creative interpretation of anti-trust law. Plenty of companies do the almost exact same thing today, but since they are not monopolists, that's completely fine, despite not actually resulting in a meaningfully different customer experience.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>