<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2020-04-17T21:23:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fnq6j3b/</link>
  <title>Hillary Clinton's Mismatch With Character Archetypes of Female Politicians</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="/u/professorgerm">/u/professorgerm</a> began an interesting discussion about Elizabeth Warren and Democrats' failure to nominate a woman for the presidency until now. I began thinking about why Clinton and Warren seemed, to many - including myself - so jarring.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>So, every politician falls into a character archetype</strong>, whether strongly or mildly. For men, there are perhaps four or five viable ones. For women seeking national office (ie. not novelty or hyperlocal candidates, 35+ years old), there are (in my opinion) <strong>three</strong>. </p>
      <p>
        <sup>[These</sup>
        <sup>apply</sup>
        <sup>regardless</sup>
        <sup>of</sup>
        <sup>specific</sup>
        <sup>circumstances</sup>
        <sup>(being</sup>
        <sup>the</sup>
        <sup>spouse</sup>
        <sup>of</sup>
        <sup>a</sup>
        <sup>former</sup>
        <sup>leader,</sup>
        <sup>racial/ethnic/religious</sup>
        <sup>factors,</sup>
        <sup>political</sup>
        <sup>faction).]</sup>
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>The Young(ish) Reformer. This is the most dangerous category, because it always or at least often comes across as preachy, try-hard, or 'planted' to the opposite political faction. This woman is ambitious, bold, but not 'manly' enough to turn away male voters. May-be-but-need-not-necessarily-be pretty (this forms a sub-category), but probably skinny. Traditional femininity is especially important when young and brash - red lipstick, dresses, blouses, skirts - both to temper 'shrill'ness for male voters, and to appeal to younger women. Examples include Sarah Palin, Jacinda Ardern, Sanna Marin, possibly AOC. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The Caring Matron ie. the "headmistress"/principal. A strict-but-fair, competent figure of broadly maternal age, the matron herself adopts an air of non-corruption; her ministers might be involved in any form of shady business, but she does her best to stay above it. Her beliefs might be contested, but her motives are at least seen as going largely beyond personal gain. May or may not be unmarried/childless (slightly different subcategories), but triggers in voters a warm sense of being looked after. If preachy, then in a way that people respect, as preachiness becomes more acceptable with age. Examples include most major elected women - think Thatcher, Merkel, Tsai Ing-Wen.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The Wisened Old Lady. Most common in the developing world (sometimes seen in Asia, the Caribbean, parts of Africa etc..), the old lady thrives in cultures that revere elders in ways the modern west tends not to do. Projects an image of aged wisdom, stability and a grandmother's cunning. Rumors of corruption are overlooked in ways they would not be for the above two groups. There might be an age overlap with the matron, but the attitude projected is entirely different - that of a sometimes-stern grandmother who bakes you cookies and intervenes with your parents after you get bad grades, versus a mother who tells you to do your homework. Examples include Sheikha Hasina and Golda Meir.</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <hr />
      <p>Hillary's problem is she didn't fit any of the above categories. </p>
      <p>She was too old for the first category. </p>
      <p>The third, the old lady, didn't quite apply either. Occasionally, Hilary's team would try to adopt this persona ('as a grandmother' etc..), but it fell flat in the face of her personal unlikeability. Above all, Hillary didn't seem <em>kind</em> - a crucial component of pulling off this form of popular appeal. People remembered Clinton as a young political operator, and a loud politician and secretary of state. Transformation into a wisened political elder takes time - even The Queen required a decade after the death of Diana to recover her reputation fully, and she doesn't even make political decisions. To be honest, I'm skeptical it would work even if she had all the ingredients - it's unclear this works in America. </p>
      <p>That leaves the matron, and indeed this seemed her initial goal. The problem was that Clinton lacked a core aspect of the Iron Lady and Mutti's charm - their seeming public incorruptibility. Both Thatcher and Merkel (have) presided over governments of astounding corruption, with many ministers implicated, fired or rotated out etc etc.. But Thatcher herself was rarely accused of corruption or graft - despite initiating huge programs of economic liberalization that increased inequality and made many conservative party insiders very, very rich, her public persona seemed uninterested in personal wealth accumulation. When [accurate] rumors about her son trading on her name (and personally making much money off UK-Saudi arms dealings) arrived, she was able to avoid reputational impact because she had never seemed interested in the vulgarities of wealth herself. Similarly, Merkel's career politics are that of an austere chemistry teacher. She has no children and little in the way of a personal legacy beyond being remembered as a politician. The Matron may be misguided, but a majority of the people ought to believe, at least, that she is above personal or petty corruption. </p>
      <p>Hillary's history with Bill, her decision to stay with him after the affair (seen not as self-sacrifice, but as a desire to stay in power even as she was publicly humiliated), her huge income post-presidency, her time in politics thereafter and her substantial personal wealth - almost all of it the product of grafting her time as First Lady and her husband's time as President - meant she was too impure for the matronly role. Hillary was stern, but didn't seem <em>fair</em> in the way that a principal you can respect is.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>