<post>
  <author>cvdailyupdates</author>
  <date>2020-04-19T19:25:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g14usp/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_6/fnws10z/</link>
  <title>COVID-19 Protestors Are Acting Reasonably On Wrong Beliefs</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The pushback isn't because the rules are strict, it's because the rules are inconsistent, arbitrary, poorly communicated, and imposed with force instead of explanations.</p>
      <p>I don't know how many times I have to emphasize this example before anyone else will hear it. As recently as <em><strong>three weeks ago</strong></em>, protective masks were completely off the market by fiat, reserved for 'people who need them', while all of our political, media, and public health authorities were telling us that masks don't work and we are stupid and kind of racist for wanting them. </p>
      <p>Now, in various parts of the country, it is a jailable offense to go outside without a mask on</p>
      <p>(Yes I am aware that the strict definition of 'mask' is different between those two paragraphs. No, it's not relevant). </p>
      <p>Three weeks ago our authorities were telling us not only that masks don't work, but that we are bad people for wanting them. Today our authorities are telling us that masks are mandatory, and we will go to jail if we don't wear them.</p>
      <p>Do you not understand how that level of idea whiplash might be upsetting to people? Do you understand how pulling a complete 180 like that, without any authority at any point in time explaining how or why that 180 happened, might prompt people to be a little skeptical of what else the authorities say? </p>
      <p>And then factor in that this is how <em>all public policy in the us is always implemented</em>. I don't know how it is in NZ, maybe it's the same there and I'm sounding like a crazy person. But look. Contrary to what people on Reddit seem to think, Americans are not stupid. They're stubborn sometimes, yes, but they're not retarded. During this crisis, at every step of the way, at every level of government, in almost every state in this country, policy has been designed and implemented starting from an assumption that the public are retarded children and have to be forced to accept things. All skepticism, all request for explanation, all questioning if any particular policy is a good idea, or worth the cost, is not met with an explanation. It's not even met with respect. It's met with sneering derision and threats. <em><strong>People don't like being noble-lied to and treated like stupid kids</strong></em>. </p>
      <p>As a meta commentary, it is quite telling that, even though we're in a situation where some basic respect, patient explanation, and a bit of give-and-take on policy would completely end these protests, the relevant governments either can't or won't. Does that mean the stakes aren't actually high (because they could do something that would be super effective at implementing the 'needed' public health policy, but they are refusing to for some unknown reason)? Does that mean that the people in charge care more about exercising authority for its own sake than actually achieving their goals (because they are intentionally choosing heavy-handed options when others are available)?</p>
      <hr />
      <p>EDIT: <a href="/u/irresplendancy">/u/irresplendancy</a> in a sister comment points out another element to it</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Based on the supporters I know, the anti-lockdown protests are largely fueled by beliefs that the pandemic is either entirely fake...</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I am sure the overwhelming instinct of the people here would be to dismiss anyone who thinks that out of hand as being stupid. The fact that they're objectively incorrect about facts doesn't help their case. (Although I remain convinced that the pandemic <em>does not matter at all</em> for young, healthy people, and I think there are reasonable questions to be asked regarding the extent to which it is ok to sacrifice the next 50 years of young people for the next 3 years of the old). </p>
      <p>But it is <em><strong>fundamentally reasonable</strong></em> for protestors who believe the pandemic is fake, to think that. Why? Same reason.</p>
      <p>For all of January, for all of February, and for a decent chunk of March, the commentary out of almost every media outlet, almost every public health outlet, almost every political outlet, was some variant of "it's just the flu, brah". We know it's not just the flu. They know it's not just the flu. They don't say that anymore. But from the perspective of someone who <em>isn't</em> obsessively plumbing the depths of 4chan for research papers every night, think about what they saw. For two fucking months, everyone told them it's not a big deal. Then, pretty much overnight, everyone told them that it's a giant deal, and they're all bad stupid people for not taking it seriously. As far as I am aware, the <em>only public people</em> who have actually addressed this reasonably are Drs. Fauci and Birx, who have both publicly stated at several briefings that their initial policies on this plague were underpowered, and they both cite the unbelievably low Chinese numbers as evidence for this; a plague that kills 1k is a lot different from a plague that kills 100k. They claim that in February they thought this was a 1k plague; now they know they're wrong, and their proposals have changed accordingly. </p>
      <p>I have not heard any such acknowledgement from anywhere else. Not the WHO. Not any corporate media in the US. Not the CDC. Nobody. </p>
      <p>So if you're a normie who isn't paying hyper-attention to anything, all you see is "well a month ago they told us it was no big deal, now they tell us it's a big deal now, they were lying before, why should we believe them now?". For that matter, a lot of people don't pay any attention to the daily news. It is entirely possible that the people protesting <em><strong>literally don't know</strong></em> that it's not just the flu. After all, they live in rural michigan, where like <em>zero</em> people they know have died. They don't pay attention to Italy. I personally know someone, a really smart guy, who was in this situation. In February I tried to alert him to this, and he points to all the news authorities saying 'just the flu' and humours me but doesn't take it seriously. In March he flies to NYC to visit his grandmother, who is in poor health for unrelated reasons, and he was like 8 hours short of getting caught in the NYC lockdown. He had no idea. Because he doesn't obsessively read the news every day. </p>
      <p>It is possible that the protestors <em><strong>literally do not know</strong></em> that it is a big deal. And it is possible that they are acting <em><strong>reasonably</strong></em> in light of their legitimate, sincere beliefs. Their beliefs are wrong, but the relevant authorities aren't talking to them and explaining that. They're arresting them. You don't communicate critical public health information to people by threatening to fucking jail them</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>