<post>
  <author>cvdailyupdates</author>
  <date>2020-04-22T20:48:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g5j7zm/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_7/fo820ms/</link>
  <title>Astroturf or Facilitating Community Organizing?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I think one partisan's "astroturf" is another's "community organizing". </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I am fond of telling this story and I am sure you all have heard me tell it before, when I was someone else</p>
      <p>I lived in Berkeley in 2014. Back then, when I went for walks around my neighbourhood, there were signs <em><strong>everywhere</strong></em> that said "Activist jobs! Up to $6000 per month! grassrootsactivism.com" (I don't recall what the exact URL was, but in any case it has long since expired). Aside from the offensive level of doublespeak that it takes to <em>pay</em> someone to do "grassroots" "activism" as a <em>job</em> (meaning it's neither of the above!), I did some digging into them once and between whois records pointing to nonprofits and playing the "which boards does this guy sit on" game, I traced it back to the DNC</p>
      <p>In a very real and very literal sense, protest actions that occurred in Berkeley, CA between 2014 and 2016 were literally organized and funded by Hillary Clinton's campaign. Does that make it astroturf?</p>
      <p>I <em>imagine</em> that if I could find a leftist who would actually believe that the above is true, and not denounce me as a conspiracy theorist, they would say something like the following: every movement needs logistics, and if you think otherwise you're a fool. They're using their resources to organize support for their campaign. What do you think political spending is <em>for</em>? Not to mention, they're paying the organizers, yes, because organizing is a full time job, but it's not like they're paying people to show up. The people who show up, <em>want</em> to show up, and all the funding is doing is facilitating that, enabling them to show the support that they wanted to show all along. There is nothing nefarious about this, nothing artificial about this. </p>
      <p>Of course when the right does the same thing, it's denounced as astroturf, but that's just because in this context 'astroturf' is a Russel conjugation. The facts, that we can all observe and agree on, are:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>This kind of behaviour is <em>common</em></li>
        <li>For each person currently upset about it, there exist comparable circumstances in which they would defend it as legitimate and not nefarious at all</li>
      </ul>
      <p>tl;dr: <a href="https://status451.com/author/davidzhines/">read Hines</a></p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>