<post>
  <author>ggthxnore</author>
  <date>2020-04-22T22:30:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/fo8drqz/</link>
  <title>Should Magical Rome Have Female Legionnaires?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Probably unsurprisingly, I agree with the complainer. Once we've departed from literal history by adding mythical creatures appeals to historical accuracy seem hollow. We already agree we're not really playing a game set in a particular historical period, why should we feel constrained to what things were like in that historical period?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>What is the relation between between mythical creatures and the gender politics of Rome, though? Does gravity still exist? Does math still work the same way we're used to? Is Rome still located in Italy as opposed to, say, Uganda? I need you to make a comprehensive list of everything that differs from Rome as we know it (besides the monsters) so we can be on the same page here. Because when I hear "Rome, but with monsters" I think.... Rome, but with monsters. Obviously the introduction of monsters would change things, but until you elaborate on exactly how they changed which tings, the base rate is still "Rome". It's fine if the monsters brought modern gender egalitarianism with them, but at least to tell me how, please.</p>
      <p>You'd probably be more willing to accept "no, you can't be a samurai, this is Rome", right? Like, the setting has to mean something, it sets some kind of boundaries. Maybe one guy really, really wants to play a steampunk cyborg ninja, but this is not the game for that, and "but there weren't Lovecraftian horrors in ancient Rome either!" rings pretty obviously hollow (I hope, anyway?) as an objection.</p>
      <p>It's not that female legionnaires are the ultimate taboo, somehow far more implausible than vampires and werewolves and cosmic horrors, it's that if you want that, you have to do the work. The base of the setting, before the Lovecraft twist was added, was historic Rome, which did not have female legionnaires. How do you get from A to B? Did the arrival of the creatures so shake the very foundations of the (Republic? Empire?) that all of its institutions are.... still intact and recognizable, but now with women? Are women now at least as capable of being soldiers as men because magic/mutation, and let's handwave away all the social/cultural stuff we don't want to get into? Are humans just not sexually dimorphic in this setting?</p>
      <p>I want to make it clear that, again, it's not that "no female legionnaires" is the hill I want to die on or anything, it's merely this shrugging indifference argument of "who cares it's already ahistorical so anything goes" which is somehow only ever selectively applied to culture war issues that I abhor. No one ever sympathetically deploys such an argument in defense of the weeb who wants to dual-class ninja/samurai in your Civil War game, though they may eventually agree just to shut him up in the way you placate a difficult child. I'm happy to have female legionnaires <em>if</em> they'll just put in the work to show how and why that is now a thing and all the other knock-on effects this has on the setting. I'm even fine if a player just wants to say they're doing a Mulan without making a big thing about how female legionnaires must be a normal and accepted thing and rape and all those other uncomfortable things we don't want to talk about just magically never happen. I just refuse to ever accept the "who cares there's magic therefore there can also be modern gender politics" argument.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>