<post>
  <author>HelmedHorror</author>
  <date>2020-04-17T22:14:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fnqc1fl/</link>
  <title>Ideological Orthodoxy Causes Flawed Survey Questions</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <blockquote>
          <p>Political scientist Brian Schaffner attempted to measure sexism by having pollsters ask Democrats if they agreed with phrases including "women are too easily offended" and "most women fail to appreciate fully all that men do for them."</p>
          <p>"There is a very strong relationship between how people responded to the questions that are meant to measure sexism and whether they were likely to vote for Elizabeth Warren," Schaffner said. "And it was the least-sexist Democratic voters who supported her the most. But her support dropped off very quickly among those who registered higher levels of sexism."</p>
        </blockquote>
      </blockquote>
      <p>There is a pernicious tendency I have noticed in the social sciences whenever researchers devise measures/inventories of characteristics that are especially abhorrent to blue-tribers (sexism, authoritarian attitudes, racism, xenophobia, transphobia, populism, etc.). What they will do is come up with attitudes/beliefs/practices that are in and of themselves not necessarily objectionable, but that the researchers operationalize/code as evidence of a broader phobia/"ism".</p>
      <p>There are many examples of this in social science. For example, researchers might do <a href="https://jspp.psychopen.eu/article/view/835/html">a study purporting to measure right-wing authoritarianism</a> by asking whether respondents agree with statements like:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <em>"The facts on crime and the recent public disorders show we have to crack down harder on troublemakers, if we are going preserve law and order."</em>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Or they might do <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/227636305_A_Cross-Cultural_Investigation_into_a_Reconceptualization_of_Ethnocentrism">a study purporting to measure ethnocentrism</a> with questions like:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <em>"I feel that in general the basic values of my cultural or ethnic group are fairer, more decent and 
more reasonable than those of many others."</em>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The researchers you mentioned who studied support for Warren and "sexism" are another example. <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/polq.12737">The study</a> asked respondents if they agree with these four statements:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Women are too easily offended.</li>
        <li>Many women are actually seeking special favors, such as hiring policies that favor them over men, under the guise of asking for “equality.”</li>
        <li>Women seek to gain power by getting control over men.</li>
        <li>When women lose to men in a fair competition, they typically complain about being discriminated against.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>In all of these studies, the researchers basically just define those who agree with such statements as right-wing authoritarian, ethnocentric, sexist, etc. Often they will attempt to "validate" their questionnaire by observing that it correlates with similar questionnaires by other researchers.</p>
      <p>But it would be like they did a study on "authoritarian Marxist revolutionaries" by seeing if respondents agree with statements like <em>"I think wealth should be redistributed to the needy more than it currently is,"</em> and then "validated" it by seeing if it correlates with the other distinguished researchers of authoritarian-Marxist-revolutionaries whose questionnaires ask about agreement with <em>"there needs to be more prosecution of big bank executives who engage in conduct that is risky to the economy"</em> or whatever. It's preposterous.</p>
      <p>It would be fine if the researchers said <em>"We will define agreement with these statements as 'flurbism' and discuss socioeconomic, political, and other correlates of flurbist attitudes."</em> But, of course, the terms "sexism", "right-wing authoritarian", "ethnocentrist", etc., preexist in the minds of English-speakers, and you can't use the terms without bringing along with them all the associated connotations and other baggage. That is, of course, why they use those terms. I don't mean to imply they're always being insidious about it; I wholeheartedly believe these researchers usually sincerely believe that agreement with their questionnaire items <em>is</em> sexism or <em>is</em> ethnocentrism or whatever. But this is the problem with ideological orthodoxy in academia. It literally. never. occurs. to these researchers that their underlying blue-tribe understanding of these terms is highly biased and disputable.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>