<post>
  <author>Im_not_JB</author>
  <date>2020-04-22T01:23:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/fo56jve/</link>
  <title>How Private Property Enhanced a Socialist Game</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="/u/ZorbaTHut">u/ZorbaTHut</a> recently had what I consider <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/fo0avs6/">a top-notch Quality Contribution</a> concerning socialism in video games. What stood out the most to me was how much the factual statements clashed with my intuitions.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>For example, there's a game called Foxhole that's a massively multiplayer wargame, with the added twist that ammo and vehicles don't spawn; someone has to make them. The end result is that each side in Foxhole includes a bunch of people manufacturing stuff, which mostly just gets left in supply depots so people can grab it and go up and shoot some dudes. There's entire logistics systems in that game that mostly come down to ". . . and then one of the combat people grabs it and shoots someone in the head".</p>
        <p>But then, the combat people aren't really "participating in the economy", aside from converting guns and ammo into headshots. And the producers don't really "need" things, they're just doing it because they enjoy the economic work.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I genuinely struggled to understand this. Maybe part of it was thinking that it's mostly dudes who played video games, and dudes want to grab guns and shoot people. Which dudes are going to <em>want</em> to do manufacturing just to have it pulled by other dudes who get to have all the fun?! I started watching <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCey1Gv1_f1iU1TlJ5d-Ci9Q/videos">Gaming Field Manual on YouTube</a>, who gives instructions on how to do "logi" in Foxhole. His buttery smooth voice describes how to harvest resources ("salvage"), transport them to a central repository ("internal logi"), make the stuff that's needed (no central command), and distribute the resultant equipment to the front lines ("external logi").</p>
      <p>Honestly, I was amazed by this. I admitted to my fiancée that I wasted hours watching his videos in my amazement. She talked me down from the ledge. People play farming simulators and other resource/crafting games all the time, and this is really just a resource/crafting game slammed together with a shooting game. But I kept watching, because in every video, Yung Lion seemed to constantly express bewilderment and dejection concerning how the resources he harvested were being used. 'They're making useless stuff that just blocks the road and makes logi harder.' 'They're making useless, waste-of-resources structures that are just magnets for gas/grenades.' In his videos, he rarely joined in combat; mostly, he ran away when bullets started flying or at the most provided medic support... so it didn't seem like he was ever <em>personally</em> "enjoying" picking up the guns and exploiting the gains made by his logi grind. Several times, he would kindly ask other players, "What's the logic behind doing [this thing that he thought was stupid]?" Very very occasionally, he tried to gently advise them as to how to do things better. Most times, after they basically just ignored him and said, "I think this is good," his response was just a (sarcastic), "Okayyyyyy...." (Then he often sat there, watched, and reveled in their plan blowing up in their face in exactly the way he predicted.)</p>
      <p>My bewilderment could not be completely put down. <em>Why</em> would he keep doing this, especially when he really seemed to think that his efforts were wasted most of the time? I don't MRA or whichever sect uses the "beta" terminology, but I honestly asked myself how this guy could convince himself to keep just grinding in order to provide more canonical "pleasure" to others. Ok... the game has a "ranking" system, which I don't quite understand, but it appears that you can rapidly advance in rank by doing logi activities (I think the game gives you points for depositing various resources, but probably other types of tasks as well). Also, it has a "commendation" system, which is a social reward system (if you like something someone did, you can give them up to three "commendations", up to a max of 100/day) that tries to keep an explicit record of how noticeably useful you've been to others. Maybe these were enough, at least in addition to the sort of mindless peace that playing a resource/crafting game can give... along with the occasional jaunts to the front lines (even if mostly just to see what's happening).</p>
      <p>...and then I got to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tVQu2x9mkDM">Season 2, Episode 5</a>. I honestly have no idea how I managed to watch this much of this random guy's YouTube channel for a game that I have no intention of ever playing, but I'm glad I did. Much of the episode is a lengthy discussion about how he had intended to stop playing Foxhole. He had skipped some wars already, and he was happier <em>not</em> playing it than playing it. Logi had become just a grind. The developers mostly added new combat features, and combined with a bunch of new users, this resulted in <em>massive</em> waste of resources as people experimented and just tried a bunch of stuff that had little chance of working. He openly asked the question that was burning my brain: '<em>Why</em> would I keep doing this, especially when I really think it's a grind and that my efforts are wasted most of the time?' </p>
      <p>His answer? 'At least they gave us private property.' Seriously. The public nature of all resources all the time <em>sucked</em>, and it required time-costly workarounds:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Before the squad storage came along, you had to go find somewhere on the map that hopefully other players did not go, build a box out in the grass somewhere, and hide your stuff and hope that nobody stumbled across it, because people were always searching for that kind of stuff... Too much work. The grind was just... mmm... just thinking about it frustrates me even now. And that was another reason why you just had to give up on the game. It was like, "Uh, can't be bothered. They're not improving this; they're just making it worse."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>At the same time as disparaging the developers for focusing on combat features, he talks about how unenthusiastic they were about private property for logi. He calls out one dev in particular:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Mark seemed like he wanted to vomit at the idea of personal property, or private property, in Foxhole. I'm telling ya, he just looked like he got diarrhea and everything all at once at the idea of <em>personal storage</em> in Foxhole, and he just couldn't wait to let you know that he's willing to take it away... at the drop of a dime, if someone so much as complains about private storage, he's going to take it away. So it was like, "Ehhhhhh, I'm not even sure I want to come back, and then I came in and I tried it, ......"</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>He has an aside about another (unposted) video here, but the point is, they gave him the ability to <em>actually exert some personal control</em> over the things that he grinded for. He doesn't completely disparage making resources public at times. He expects to eventually dump resources into the FOB, where it will become public for front-line soldiers, but</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Giving us the ability to have a private stash where we at least don't have to go all over the place just to have stuff, man that was the best idea ever.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>He could <em>at least</em> make sure that "his own truck" was available to him with the resources he left in it the next time he started the game:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>You know the feeling when you first log back on and it's like, "Oh, I've got to make a truck and then blah blah blah... or I've got to go find a truck first, so it's probably best to spawn on the front lines so you can just find a truck laying around and then take that truck and do logi"? You know how good it feels to just say, "I'm just going to go back and get <em>my</em> truck"? <strong>OH MY GOD! OHHHHH!</strong> Listen, the ability to just say, "I'm gonna go get <em>my</em> truck and continue doing logi is the absolute best.... it is.... you have to understand, in other MMOs and things like that, the fantasy types or whatever, it is normal to have your own thing, like your own mount you can ride or your own weapons stash or whatever. It's just <em>normal</em> to have that. So when you're playing a game that has zero concept of personal property installed within the game intentionally, like this is by design, <em>oh my god</em>, it is like... <strong>mmmmmm</strong>. Such a rewarding... it's energizing, almost, really, it is, because I had given up... but now, here I am back again, trying to revive my love for Foxhole, and I believe that the private stash is going to do that.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I still have complicated thoughts about both inside- and outside-of-game socialism/capitalism. It seems like game mechanics like feeling like you're part of a bigger mission (one that you can connect to the work you're doing) and having a variety of social reward systems (even if they don't correspond directly with economic rewards) are quite important. And some people can genuinely enjoy resource allocation problems (though I still think there are problems if you think your efforts at resource allocation are <em>just wasted</em> by foolish other people). But this was just an in-your-face moment that took a, "Wow, this doesn't mesh with your intuitions <em>at all</em>; what's up?" and ended up solidifying even more, "Private property is an <em>immense</em> motivator in so many ways," I felt compelled to share it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>