<post>
  <author>oaklandbrokeland</author>
  <date>2020-04-19T15:36:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g3x5gj/akrasia_strategies_discussion/fnw3dd3/</link>
  <title>Overcoming Akrasia Through Pleasure</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I've thought about this issue a lot. My thoughts are somewhat jumbled and informal, but I (arrogantly) think I've made significant progress on understanding this issue from how we normally approach it.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>We will always do what is most pleasurable, no matter what, provided we understand pleasure in an <em>expansive</em> sense. The things we aim for, even noble and spiritual things, are all directed toward a pleasure, which is a kind of <em>end</em> or <em>repose</em> of our desires. (This is something I've borrowed from Aquinas' <em>Summa</em>). Let me give some examples. I will not smoke a cigarette even though I greatly desire the sensation of smoking a cigarette. Why? Because the fear of its effect on my teeth is greatly displeasurable and salient. I don't merely know rationally that it has a harmful effect on my teeth: I know <em>saliently</em> (viscerally, emotionally) how painful and annoying it is to go to the dentist and have my teeth worked on. So while the sensation of smoking is desired, the activity of smoking is not desired, because of the salient greater pleasure of abstaining. I will not procrastinate by watching Netflix, even though I really want to. Why? Not because I know rationally that this is negative behavior (we all do), but because I remember all of the painful things in my life that were a result of procrastination. There is an enormous psychological difference between knowing a thing to be bad rationally, and knowing a thing to be bad emotionally, saliently, viscerally, and imaginatively. To defeat akrasia, you need to turn rationality into an intense tangible feeling.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Following this line of thought, to defeat akrasia you need to always remember all of the bad things that naturally accompany the targeted vice (or sin). It's not enough to "know" it's bad, which is another way of saying "remembering I once determined it is bad in the past". No, you need to actually have intense imaginative recollection of bad experiences in your life, or of probable future bad experiences, <em>whenever</em> you think about the vice. It has to be right in the front of your mind. This i functionally identical to remembering the positive that results from abstaining, provided it is an intense enough recollection of the positive and the positive is actually a greater positive than the negative is a negative.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Practically speaking, you can develop this rational salience by <em>always noting, appreciating, and emphasizing higher feelings throughout your day</em>, and "meditating" on all of the ills that are easily abolished by abstaining from the behavior (we pay more attention to avoiding discomfort than finding comfort). By "higher feelings" I mean the long-term "identity" feelings which accompany long-term behavior changes. Pride, gratitude, honor, and hope are long-term feelings (<em>pleasures</em>) because they change your focus to the weeks versus the hours. If your mind has developed the taste for fleeting pleasures only, then it will be impossible to defeat akrasia because quitting will never be more pleasurable in the shortterm than abstaining. When you only notice short term pleasures, your <em>identity</em> becomes short-term pleasures. If you only live for a day, why wouldn't you do drugs? Well, you're only living for the day if you never try to develop a taste for long-lasting leasures. (See: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mS9LCR5P5wI">this is a problem for future Homer</a>). When you continually remember, recall, and look for long-term pleasures (longanimous pleasures), then these are the pleasures your mind will pay attention to, and these are the pleasures that you will desire. This explains a myriad of helpful interventions: Jordan Peterson's Future Authoring Program, Gratitude Diaries, Progress tracking, and so on. It also explains the success of the Marie Kondo method: enjoy seeing order, enjoy seeing organization, enjoy the things you own, and enjoy the act of cleaning: (magically!) you will find yourself cleaning all the time!</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>An adjacent piece of advice: It's almost always better to gradually taper off of bad habits then to quit wholesale. This is because almost no one ever quits something wholesale without significantly changing everything about their life, which you're not going to do. And when you continue to attempt quitting and you <em>fail</em>, gradually you lose confidence in your ability to quit, which is your Will. If your Will is always wrong, why would you listen to it? "I shouldn't eat these cookies" -- ""You say that every time you're about to eat the cookies."" The words lose all meaning. A parent who threatens punishment and never delivers will find that the threat is no longer heeded. You must train your Will by developing an 80%+ success rate in the things that you <em>will</em>, ideally more like a 95%+ success rate. How to do this? Make smaller progress! If you set a plan of progress and you succeed every day, you'll eventually realize that your Will is actually right and is good to follow. And it's shocking how quickly you can taper off of things while hardly realizing it. If you play 5 hours of gaming a day and quit 15 minutes every three days, then you've totally quit video games in two months. Now combine this with other vices, which you can also taper off of. There's also some intriguing psychological reasons for tapering: making pleasures <em>routine</em> will decrease your desire for the pleasure, whereas introducing novelty and anxiety will increase the pleasure. If you get anxious about not eating cake, and you're not sure whether you will cave and have cake tonight or not, you're amplifying the pleasure much more than had you decided that for the next two months you'll just have littler and littler cake.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>You need to feel good about <em>everything</em> that is better than your default state, and feel bad about anything <em>lower</em> than your default state. There are people who don't read, decide they want to read, realize they can only read for 10 minutes, and then get pissed. They have effectively punished themselves for doing better! Even the <em>smallest</em> step above your default needs to be accompanied by good feelings. You should never punish something better than the average. You don't have to have a dance celebration after 10 minutes of reading, but you should feel satisfied. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Our capability to feel intense pleasure is pretty much renewed every couple days or so. A lot of people feel embarrassed about feeling amazing after small progress. "I can't be happy with myself. I only ate two fucking baby carrots, dude." If you felt absolutely amazing after making that progress, it's not as if you lose the ability to feel amazing the next day or the next. You can't "save" your strong emotions -- it's like hunger, it comes back again the next day. You can feel just as amazing while increasing the number of carrots you eat. My point: you can literally celebrate every single small win as if you were winning the fucking Superbowl. Did you know Little League football players and NFL players feel the same sense of victory after each match, weekend after weekend? They don't "save" their happiness for another occasion. Use up all of your joy and happiness every day, you'll get new ingredients for it the next day.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Lastly, and pretty much just clarifying the above: if a step in the right direction feels bad, there's something off with your mental model. Because every positive step should be associated at some level with pleasure. Getting up should feel good, putting on the gym should feel good, getting in the car, arriving at the gym, and entering the gym should all feel good. Don't just feel good after working out, feel good after every step because they're all a necessary part of working out. The proper place for anxiety and disappointment is when you're doing nothing, i.e. procrastinating, not making any small step whatsoever. That's the only time you should feel straight anxiety and disappointment. You can literally decide right now: I can put my phone down and feel good. I can stand up and feel good. I can get a glass of water and feel good, and drink a glass of water and feel good. You can take small step by small step and defeat any vice, and feel good the entire time. Imagine some guy who feels good doing every small thing, and only feels anxiety when he's doing nothing. That will be a 100% productive and happy individual.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>