<post>
  <author>ZorbaTHut</author>
  <date>2020-04-20T19:02:05Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/fo0avs6/</link>
  <title>What Would a Video Game Socialist Economy Look Like?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Couldn't we have a large scale economy in a game that is controlled by the players, not a sharing economy but still a socialist economy? What would that look like? I guess it would have to be opt-in, but then we just need to make it so that players wnat to opt in.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>What <em>does</em> that look like, though?</p>
      <p>For example, there's a game called Foxhole that's a massively multiplayer wargame, with the added twist that ammo and vehicles don't spawn; someone has to make them. The end result is that each side in Foxhole includes a bunch of people manufacturing stuff, which mostly just gets left in supply depots so people can grab it and go up and shoot some dudes. There's entire logistics systems in that game that mostly come down to ". . . and then one of the combat people grabs it and shoots someone in the head".</p>
      <p>But then, the combat people aren't really "participating in the economy", aside from converting guns and ammo into headshots. And the producers don't really "need" things, they're just doing it because they enjoy the economic work.</p>
      <p>So . . . does that count? I don't really know. Maybe, maybe not. It's kind of opt-in because you don't have to dump your ammo in a supply chest and give it to other people, but it's kind of not opt-in because it's impractical to do all the production of your own gear yourself, and it's not really an "economy" either, it's just one group of people providing stuff that another group needs.</p>
      <p>ATITD has plenty of stuff where you need to work together, but at the same time, most people are trying to finish their own projects; having your own private airship is Cool and that's a reasonable endgame goal. So you might help out a group, and you might pool resources to build production facilities, but at the same time many people will be thinking "aha, I can use these production facilities to make a bunch of rubber for my airship!" And that's just kinda expected.</p>
      <p>In the end, people play games to accomplish things, and there's <em>always</em> going to be people who want to accomplish things for themselves instead of things for everyone else. (I think this is true of socialism as well - no matter what you do, <em>something</em> will always be scarce, and there will always be people who really want that thing for one reason or another.) So when you say . . .</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I guess it would have to be opt-in, but then we just need to make it so that players wnat to opt in.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>you will never get <em>all</em> players to want to opt-in, you'll always have some people trying to do their own thing just for funsies.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>As a more concrete example, I played a game called <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/648800/Raft/">Raft</a> a while back. Raft is really intended to be a singleplayer game but that is not how we played it; we had half a dozen people trying to figure out WTF to do, all smashing parts together on a single (rapidly expanding) raft. People eventually started specializing; we had one person who decided he enjoyed cooking, so he started catching fish and cooking up food for all of us. Meanwhile, I kinda fell into being the technology person, so I was the one asking for certain supplies and building new things that made everyone's lives easier. Arguably, this was the "leader" position, but frankly I wasn't doing a lot of leading, I was just saying "can we get a bunch of sand? trust me you won't regret this" and then a few minutes later people started dumping sand into our boxes.</p>
      <p>At the same time, there were people who just weren't doing anything useful. Two people decided they liked shark hunting, so whenever we stopped at an island, they'd jump in the water and start trying to kill the shark, who would respawn, like, a minute later. This was mostly not a useful thing to do (though the cook appreciated the constant supply of sharkmeat) but they were having fun with it and I made sure to supply some metal spears for them so they could keep it up. People would constantly expand the raft (mostly without asking other people if it was OK, I don't even know how many times I had to go hunt down the new location of the water purifier) and it was basically glorious chaos.</p>
      <p>So what <em>is</em> this, economically speaking?</p>
      <p>It wasn't a planned economy because the closest thing we had to planning was me saying "see if you can find some metal at the next island, I really need a bunch of metal", and meanwhile there's people goofing off trying to raise birds and plant pineapples and stuff. It wasn't selfish because almost everything that people made tended to go into the shared boxes if they didn't need it themselves. It was maybe a sharing economy, but then there <em>was</em> a little central guidance thanks to me. And it was enforced by the game, because there's only one raft, you can't build a second raft, but at the same time nobody required us to put things in boxes, so maybe it wasn't entirely enforced.</p>
      <p>I think, in the end, this is a reasonable model of economies. It's not really any specific thing, because you can always find exceptions, but it's a working melange of a bunch of techniques. At the same time, it can be used both in favor of and against any Perfect Economy Model; I could say "we got through the game fine therefore socialism works", or I could say "this one bozo kept hanging out near the research table trying to figure out what to make next instead of helping out, and sometimes he got up and ate some cookies instead of playing the game, therefore socialism doesn't work, he was just leeching off the workers".</p>
      <p>So . . . in the end, I guess my question is what you're looking for in this game. What does "centralized economy" mean in this context? What does "democratically" mean? What prevents people from refusing to give their stuff over? Is it opt-in (in which case some people won't opt-in) or not?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>