<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-02-04T17:32:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l9xgxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_01/gm0eoaf/</link>
  <title>Whether John Gabriel's Greater Internet Fuckwad Theory largely explains radical racial politics in the 21st century</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I wonder whether some proportion of radicalized racial politics among progressives - especially people of color - is due to being exposed to internet racism. </p>
      <p>Let’s say you’re a black or brown hispanic American who grew up in the 90s, or 80s (or 00s for that matter). You grow up in a middle class suburb of a major American city, do well enough at school, get into a top college, get a job at the New York Times.</p>
      <p>You may well have faced racism in your life - the owner of a convenience store following you around in a way you’re pretty sure he wouldn’t for a white kid your age, or an older white or asian woman crossing the street when you’re walking towards her on the sidewalk late at night. Maybe a girlfriend or boyfriend’s dad looks at you or speaks to you in a way that you think suggests he doesn’t approve because of your background. Maybe the girls at school feel they have the right to grab your hair or play with it without your permission, ask you constantly if it’s a weave. </p>
      <p>But, for all of that (and I’m not saying we should dismiss these things, by the way) you’ve never faced the kind of ‘overt’ racism you read about in history books. You may never been called the most severe kind of racial slur by a white person - especially not a young white person, no one’s told you they want all ‘your people’ dead, you haven’t been physically threatened or had your family or life threatened because of your race. You haven’t seen <em>contemporary</em> racial caricatures of your own ethnic group that look straight out of a nazi textbook. No one’s gone on a rant in front of you and told you they want to genocide your race, called the slave trade ‘unfinished business’. You’ve experienced racism, sure, but it’s of the ‘unconscious bias’ kind, not the Quentin Tarantino kind. Even if the woman crossing the street is an example of the intolerant and racist society you live in, it’s clearly - obviously - <em>less terrifying</em> than that (whether you admit it or not). </p>
      <p>The first time you’re called the n-word is in the Twitter replies to one of your first pieces in the New York Times. </p>
      <p>Maybe you write something about race, maybe not. You have a google alert on your name like every other journalist or writer. You get people with pepe or Roman statue avatars claiming you’re proof your race is low IQ, or dangerous, or that you’re proof of how low the standards are for affirmative action at the NYT. Perhaps you click on these people’s profiles, or follow back mentions of you from google to obscure forums where people discuss their affinity for segregation or their hatred of the laws that allowed your parents or grandparents to move to America, advocate your immediate stripping of citizenship and deportation to your ‘ancestral homeland’. Maybe you were a hardcore social activist in college. Perhaps you barely thought about race at all. But it’s not hard to see how that could change somebody. </p>
      <hr />
      <p>To those of us (of all races) who grew up in certain corners of the internet, on 4chan or SA or on parts of other sites where views like this exist in some quantity, seeing extreme, genocidal tier racial hatred like this isn’t shocking. It’s not uncommon - and in any case we can comfort ourselves because we know /pol/ isn’t normal (and is often posturing anyway), and because we know the hardcore racists are a tiny minority. Scott writes this in ‘You Are Still Crying Wolf’ - and he’s not wrong, maybe there are only fifty thousand violent ultra-racists in a country of three hundred million, and their existence shouldn’t radically transform one’s politics if anyone’s thinking rationally. </p>
      <p>But this ignores the visceral impact that people - especially people of the groups that online racists hate, let’s be clear here - feel when they see, for the <em>first time in their lives</em> people actually calling for their genocide or ethnic cleansing. And you can say that it’s irrational because these people are like 0.2% of the population or whatever, but this is exactly what radicalizes people, no less so that someone on /pol/ can get radicalized by a collage of blue check tweets calling for some policy or another. Probably more so, because it’s often directed at them personally.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>I’ve never been progressive, but it would be no exaggeration to say (in fact I’d freely admit it) that the sole cause of my Jewish identity is internet antisemitism. Growing up, I had no concept of myself as Jewish. We had a Christmas tree (<em>with</em> presents), my parents were an atheist and an agnostic, I never had a bat mitzvah (and indeed none of my siblings had any life cycle events), and the only ‘Jewish’ thing we did was go to my grandparents’ for Passover once every few years if we weren’t on vacation, where my grandmother would often serve her famous (pork) meatloaf. If people at school asked what religion I was, I would say ‘atheist’. The summer camps we went to were stringently multifaith, we never went to Israel (or discussed it at all as far as I remember), we weren’t even ‘secularly Jewish’, in the arts and culture section way. I can remember my mother once telling me that I might “decide to be Jewish” one day, in the same way I might decide to get a dog or something. The only great memory I have of my father’s Jewishness growing up is in his favorite story of how he got hired at a Catholic bank by perfectly honestly answering the interviewer when he asked where in Germany his family came from. I’m not saying that we weren’t Jewish in some subconscious, Steve-Sailer-blogpost way, just that I didn’t feel it. I can’t remember ever experiencing antisemitism growing up, although admittedly I grew up in New York. </p>
      <p>From the age of 12, my exposure to the most extreme kinds of internet antisemitism created my sense of being a Jew. When somebody hates you for what you are, you hate them, sure, but you also feel like you can’t hide from yourself - or the version of yourself that they hate. It also makes you feel like assimilation is worthless, which in my case was a pretty heavy blow given I had never had any other identity than generic, wealthy-ish urban American in my own mind. We’re a relatively intelligent people, and there are several almost universal positions that secular-ish Jewish people who get exposed to a lot of this type of dissident right material occupy. There are some people who will dismiss it for various reasons (Moldbug, Scott to some extent), others who will pathetically plead with the people who hate them by trying to expose logical flaws in their reasoning (eg. Nathan Cofnas) and so on, but the biggest group of people are just those who realize that if somebody hates you as a group, you can’t oppose them as an individual. This is true for black people, white people, Christians, Muslims, Jews and everyone else. And it’s why the internet, as this engine of extremism in which many are so frequently exposed to the people who hate them the most (people they’d never ordinarily encounter in life, or perhaps only vanishingly rarely), is so dangerous.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>