<post>
  <author>ChrisPrattAlphaRaptr</author>
  <date>2021-02-05T14:50:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l9xgxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_01/gm4btkr/</link>
  <title>The process and promise of disease eradication</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'd be shocked if we could eradicate covid at this point, or honestly even much earlier in the pandemic as you mention. Let me also distinguish between eradication (no cases in the wild, pathogen either no longer exists on Earth or exists solely in a CDC basement in Atlanta) and elimination (negligible #s of global infections or local eradication).</p>
      <p>The diseases we've eradicated or are on track to eradicate loosely share a few characteristics; they either lack an animal host (smallpox, polio) or the disease is very obvious in animals (rinderpest). We have an extremely effective intervention (smallpox/polio vaccine, ivermectin/albendazole for elephantiasis). And typically diagnosis is very easy to make. For example, we could never realistically eradicate cholera which actively replicates in the environment and naturally grows in hosts (copepods) with anything near current methods. Ditto with influenza which is constantly reproducing and mutating in avian and other hosts before spreading back to humans. Tuberculosis can lie dormant for 5-10 years or longer before reactivation and our current drugs are effective but take 6-12 months and are very inconvenient.</p>
      <p>Like most things in biology, those three characteristics aren't hard rules. The majority of polio cases are actually asymptomatic, but our vaccine is so effective, so cheap and easy to transport that we can easily just carpet bomb a given population. Furthermore, there's no reason they're hard limits and I have no idea what the modern healthcare industry is capable of at this point if we actually made a concerted effort. People take it for granted, but the current scale of covid testing is unprecedented. </p>
      <p>Coming back to Covid, we have a few problems. I've seen at least some reports about <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-54818615#:%7E:text=Denmark%20will%20cull%20all%20its,was%20found%20on%20mink%20farms.&amp;text=Denmark%20is%20the%20world's%20biggest,many%20mink%20cases%20were%20detected.">animal reservoirs of the virus already</a>. Very large numbers of cases are mild or asymptomatic, and the testing we need to do is expensive/relatively complex and just not feasible to do at scale in poor communities or developing nations. Our current vaccines are pretty effective (at least in the short term, remains to be seen if we need regular boosters) but still difficult to distribute, again particularly in developing nations without -80 freezers. Large segments of the public are extremely uncooperative and actively hostile to interventions.</p>
      <p>So, if we had a Manhattan project scale testing apparatus and/or a mandatory, global vaccine distribution program, if we got a lot better about reducing contact between people and livestock/wild animals and if we could somehow restore trust in public health institutions, maybe. But I think there's also the sense that the political capital is better spent elsewhere at this point. I'm pretty sure covid is with us to stay, and I hope people are willing to get vaccinated in Australia because sooner or later you're going to have to reopen and some foreigner is going to bring covid with them.</p>
      <p>Can I also just say, nothing makes me feel warm and fuzzy inside like talking about eradicating diseases? <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/empire_seapower/smallpox_01.shtml#:%7E:text=Print%20this%20page-,The%20scourge%20of%20the%20world,beings%20for%20thousands%20of%20years.">300 million people died of smallpox</a> in the 20th century alone and humanity came together and <em>eradicated it from the Earth, forever.</em> Short of bioterrorism, nobody will ever die from smallpox again. It's one of the purest, indisputable markers of our progress and I'd wager most people are ignorant of that fact or don't care.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>