<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2021-02-04T16:05:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l9xgxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_01/gm014f4/</link>
  <title>International politics: EU and US interests in Germany and Poland</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>PoliticoEU isn't so much an American-run organization as American-selected German. PoliticoEU is/was started as a joint venture with a German publisher Axel Springer SE, one of the largest digital publishing houses/multi-media groups in Europe. It employs Americans, but it's editorial line, hiring, and institutional capture by local (EU) politics, is completely European. It's a project by, of, and for EUphiles, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Axel_Springer_SE#Editorial_bias_and_alleged_ties_to_US_intelligence_agencies">albeit one possibly boosted by the CIA very early in the cold war</a>. (CIA had a history of recruiting pro-American Europeans to start American-friendly buisnesses that'd cooperate with the US government, but those were person-centric arrangements. Axel Springer the man/founder died in 1985, and the US typically let insitutional inertia rather than active direction take over to let such relationships quietly fade away.)</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>You've probably never heard of Axel Springer SE, but if you're an American who's only awareness/exposure to Poland in media for the last several years has been the occasional english media blitzs condemning the conservative Law and Order Party, Axel Springer is a significant part of why.</p>
      <p>First, Axel Springer is very much the sort of media group who's owner/directors feel they have a right/role in influencing European politics, be it refusing to carry Left Party election advertising in Germany's 2005 election (the election that brought up Merkel, who's the PoliticoEU line has constantly supported), or it's PoliticoEU slants. But Axel Springer <em>also</em> owns some significant Polish media interests (<em>Fakt</em>, one of the largest daily tabloids), and has Ringier Axel Springer Polska, which is it's Polish arm, which has been a bit more... well, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Axel_Springer_SE#Accusations_of_editorial_interference_in_Poland">paternalistic in its editorial bias</a>?</p>
      <p>Well, to quote the wiki...</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In 2017, <a href="https://pl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ringier_Axel_Springer_Polska">Ringer Axel Springer Polska</a>  was accused of editorial interference, when the head of the joint  venture Mark Dekan wrote a letter to the company's Polish employees in  which he disparaged the head of the conservative <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_and_Justice">Law and Justice</a> political party, calling the Polish politician <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaroslaw_Kaczynski">Jaroslaw Kaczynski</a> a "loser" for opposing the candidacy of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Tusk">Donald Tusk</a> as President of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Union">European Union</a>,  stating that "...we should never forget about the basic values that we  represent... Here is the moment where free media, such as ours must be  active. We speak for the ideas of... a United Europe." In the letter,  Dekan also raised his concerns that European integration was least  supported by the youngest generation of Poles and vowed to take  appropriate action, suggesting "Let's tell them what to do to stay in  the fast lane and not end in the parking lot."<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Axel_Springer_SE#cite_note-36">[36]</a><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Axel_Springer_SE#cite_note-37">[37]</a></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Probably not controversial in a lot of people's minds, if you agree the EU is an unambiguous good and that calling major opposition figures losers is decorum. Tusk was a died-in-wool EUphile and generally reliable German ally who broadly supported EU institutions and had no issue with German media's disproportionate role in the Polish media environment. (<a href="https://notesfrompoland.com/2020/12/07/polish-state-energy-giant-buys-hundreds-of-local-media-outlets-from-german-owner/#:%7E:text=Another%20deputy%20prime%20minister%2C%20Jaros%C5%82aw%20Gowin%2C%20has%20previously,national%20level%2C%20most%20media%20outlets%20are%20Polish%20owned">One German-owned company, the Polska Press, owned 20 of Poland's 24 regional newspapers, as well as 120 regional weeklies.</a>)</p>
      <p>If, on the other hand, you're on the other side- a side that comfortably thrashed Tusk's coalition at the voting block with wide voter support despite the slings and arrows of a hostile European media coverage- then massive (and hostile) foreign owners of your national media is a problem to be addressed. 'Re-Polanizing' the media has been a Law and Justice Party theme since it's 2017 election, the same as reforming the Supreme Court system (another EU-compliant institution, but one who unlike most countries selects its own judges/successors, which has direct continuity from the Soviet era and has never-addressed roles in public corruption in the de-communization turmoil).</p>
      <p>Donald Tusk had the indignity of being the first European Head of State who got one of the highest honors of European politics- graduating from national politics to President of the European Council in 2014- before his ruling party coalition he left behind got one of the biggest indignities of not just losing to the Law and Justice Party, but in doing so to such a degree that they got the majority of the polish legislature, letting them make laws on nearly party-line votes. Given that Donald Tusk was a long-term enemy/opponent of the Law and Justice Party (he beat them to become the ruling party in the first place), and that the Law and Justice Party is often derided for being religious/conservative/backwards nationalists...</p>
      <p>The American political equivalent would be if, say, Obama had stepped down from being President a year early to become head of the UN, opting to have Hillary replace him and run for President, and <strong><em>then</em></strong> Trump and the Republicans won the 2016 tri-fecta.</p>
      <p>Basically, Tusk turned into a EU politician with no meaningful domestic power base, who often was lobbying against his own country's ruling party in sympathetic, often german-owned, European media. Kind of like a government in exile, but instead of losing a war he lost an election so public repudiation.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>Or- to re-arrange various contexts for why this matters-</p>
      <p>-American-linked German interests own a <strong><em>lot</em></strong> of Polish media</p>
      <p>-German-owned media are far from dispassionate, neutral, non-political actors, and are institutionally pro-EU from the top</p>
      <p>-German media are the de-facto conduit of Polish politics into European and American media consciousness (providing, among other things, not just the context but literal translations)</p>
      <p>-The Polish Law and Justice Party in 2017 won significant margins on 3 planks that put them in conflict 3 separate EUphile allies: the Polish Supreme Court (reliably defferential to EU institution), Donald Tusk (one of the highest ranking EU officials with established relationships), and German media conglomerates (pro-EU, pro-Tusk, and stood to lose economic and political interests in re-Polanization of polish media).</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>Add in the chain of information flow from Polish politics to American ears- Polish-language news produced and translated by the German companies facing economic and political challenges from the Polish government, reporting to and appealing to political allies in the EU, with media partnerships to mainstream (Democrat-aligned) American media in the US, where a largely Democrat-aligned media environment regularly coordinates/shares themes in the age of Trump, who that pesky Polish government also happens to like and all Orange Man Things Bad apply...</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>American media coverage of Poland is less reflective of an unpopular regressive regime destorying democracy, and far more reflective of scorned EU allies and German media interests fighting to preserve or reclaim their own influence and providing the framings to allies in the notoriously parochial American media.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>(Which doesn't make Polish government ownership of Polish media any better, but the alternative to Polish government media bias wasn't media free of propagandizing bias, but German/EU government-aligned propagandizing bias. Not the take anyone would read in the New York Times of Associated Press.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>