<post>
  <author>grendel-khan</author>
  <date>2021-02-03T04:40:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l9xgxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_01/gltrezm/</link>
  <title>The continuing saga of San Francisco housing politics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Heather Knight for the <em>San Francisco Chronicle</em>, <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/heatherknight/article/San-Francisco-is-one-of-California-s-most-15891810.php">"San Francisco is one of California's most conservative cities - when it comes to housing"</a>. (Part of a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/neoliberal/comments/8a9o5i/on_the_nimby_subject/dwx6oef/">series about housing</a> in California.)</p>
      <p>Knight is reporting on the City Council of Sacramento voting unanimously to <a href="https://www.sacbee.com/news/local/article248544635.html">allow fourplexes on any residential lot</a> in the city, and decrying San Francisco for not doing the same. The Bay Area Council, the region's business association, describes the city as "a suburb masquerading as a city". The city's eleven supervisors (city council members, essentially) gave generally noncommittal comments.</p>
      <p>This cuts to the heart of the issue where self-described progressives are terrible at producing progressive outcomes. A lot of people don't want to live in bikeable, dense neighborhoods that are welcoming to immigrants; none of this is about those people. This is about people who profess to, and seem to, want those things, and yet do not create them. I've quoted <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ijs526/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_31_2020/g4dsl77/">Ezra Klein on this before</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>A lot of the progressivism in California is phony. It's just... you hate Donald Trump, and you put a thing in your front yard, about how in this house we believe science is real and refugees are welcome and Black Lives Matter and da-da-da-da, and everybody's a person, and trans people are people, and the whole thing... but you can't build a house. And so people can't live there. It's exclusionary progressivism. It kinda makes me sick--I am very mad at California. You can't tell people progressive governance works when it doesn't work. And here, it is not working.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Among the YIMBYs, it's blamed on an "Unholy Alliance" between wealthy landowners and progressive activists, in which the activists get money and favors, and the landowners get credibility and boots on the ground. The downside is that the city gets worse and progressivism as an ideology is discredited--sort of the opposite of <a href="https://pedestrianobservations.com/2016/10/26/sewer-socialism-or-sewer-neo-liberalism/">sewer socialism</a>. The YIMBYs have been engaged in a very clumsy process of attempting to break that alliance, largely by convincing those activists that it's better to build than not. (Noah Smith <a href="https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/the-left-nimby-canon">summarizes the intellectual underpinnings of left-NIMBYism here</a>.) Here's the Sacramento City Council, backed by <a href="https://twitter.com/SacYIMBY">House Sacramento</a>, on the change:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>One of the reasons why many of Sacramento’s higher-resourced residential neighborhoods remain largely racially segregated is because many of the “desirable” neighborhoods remain zoned exclusively for single-unit homes, a more expensive product type. Past discriminatory practices of racially restrictive covenants and government-sponsored redlining have created barriers to homeownership and intergenerational wealth-building for many minority families, and subsequent single-family zoning in high opportunity neighborhoods has reinforced it. The exclusion of lower-cost housing types (e.g. duplexes, triplexes, and fourplexes) prevent lower-income residents from moving to neighborhoods with the best parks, schools, and other desirable amenities. Allowing a greater array of housing types in Sacramento’s residential neighborhoods will help create more equitable and inclusive neighborhoods by addressing the remnant forces of government policies of exclusion and racial segregation.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Meanwhile, <a href="https://twitter.com/abettercambma?lang=en">A Better Cambridge</a> (a Boston-area YIMBY group) is, along with <a href="https://twitter.com/SunriseBoston">Sunrise Boston</a> (a leftist youth group nominally focused on climate) proposing to <a href="https://twitter.com/ABetterCambMA/status/1352235207739518977">legalize three-story multi-family housing with no parking minimums</a> throughout the city. Compare <a href="https://twitter.com/yanisatech/status/1352666314523992065?s=19">this thread from Yanisa Techagumthorn</a> of Sunrise Boston with <a href="https://twitter.com/mikeleyba/status/1352377909181378567">this thread from Mike (@mikeleyba)</a>, a local leftist who she engaged with. Items to note:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Everyone is <em>excruciatingly</em> polite, which seems unusual for leftist activists disagreeing with each other: "this disagreement is coming from a place of respect and strategic difference", "I want to express how much I respect [Mike]", and so on.</li>
        <li>Yanisa describes her experience immigrating as a child, and moving from apartment to apartment with her family--being part of the rental market, and not in a "finally found a rent-controlled place; time to never move" way.</li>
        <li>Mike distinguishes between local control being exercised by the powerful (right-NIMBYism) and by "working-class communities of color" (left-NIMBYism): "Is the developer pushing for increased density to maximize profits OR b/c they're trying to increase affordable housing?"</li>
        <li>Yanisa voices some aspirations about wanting new people to be able to live in the better parts of the city, and to live in places that don't require commuting by car.</li>
        <li>Mike doesn't address any of those, but does make some empirical claims: that rent in new buildings is high, and that rent in old buildings does not decrease even with new building. (The latter is <a href="https://research.upjohn.org/up_workingpapers/316/">false</a>.)</li>
      </ul>
      <p>This is a remarkable thing to see from the left, or from anywhere, really; Sunrise Movement chapters are pretty autonomous, which is why you saw <a href="https://twitter.com/NYJohnSanchez/status/1339232533498781697">the New York group signing on to oppose upzoning in SoHo</a>, <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/j5dqwd/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_05/g82ech3/">the Bay Area chapter backing Jackie Fielder</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/Sunrisemvmt_sea/status/1351282319055720450">the Seattle group opposing cap-and-trade</a>. There <em>is</em>, historically, no third-party group that shows up to advocate for more housing. Anecdotally, I've talked to developers (both market-rate and subsidized), and I hear, repeatedly: "I've been in this business for twenty years, and I never, not once, had someone show up to a public hearing in favor of a project until the YIMBYs came along." It's not unusual that leftists would sign on to NIMBYism. <em>Everyone</em> signs on to NIMBYism. What's surprising here is that some of them <em>didn't</em>. Maybe the Sunrise people are just impressionable kids, and it matters who gets to them first.</p>
      <p>I'll close with a bit from <a href="http://berkeley.granicus.com/MediaPlayer.php?view_id=5&amp;clip_id=4418">the January 21st meeting of Berkeley's city council</a>, at around 1:43:20, included staff reading the following email intended for public comment. It was part of a follow-up to <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/i2r8qo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_03_2020/g0eu6dh/">the Robert Reich "Payson House" kerfuffle</a> (the City Council rejected the appeal to landmark the house):</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Please do not hesitate. Move forward to preserve the historical Payson home and greenspace garden at 1915 Berryman Street. Please respect our past. Please respect our Berkeley heritage. Respect trees, animals, people and their works. Down with the running dogs who serve the capitalist burghers and developers seeking profit by creating <a href="https://www.zillow.com/berkeley-ca/sold/?searchQueryState=%7B%22pagination%22%3A%7B%7D%2C%22usersSearchTerm%22%3A%221915%20Berryman%20St%20Berkeley%2C%20CA%2C%2094709%22%2C%22mapBounds%22%3A%7B%22west%22%3A-122.28262710063693%2C%22east%22%3A-122.26707028835055%2C%22south%22%3A37.87886063965991%2C%22north%22%3A37.888795079261946%7D%2C%22regionSelection%22%3A%5B%7B%22regionId%22%3A16992%2C%22regionType%22%3A6%7D%5D%2C%22isMapVisible%22%3Atrue%2C%22filterState%22%3A%7B%22fsba%22%3A%7B%22value%22%3Afalse%7D%2C%22fsbo%22%3A%7B%22value%22%3Afalse%7D%2C%22nc%22%3A%7B%22value%22%3Afalse%7D%2C%22fore%22%3A%7B%22value%22%3Afalse%7D%2C%22cmsn%22%3A%7B%22value%22%3Afalse%7D%2C%22auc%22%3A%7B%22value%22%3Afalse%7D%2C%22pmf%22%3A%7B%22value%22%3Afalse%7D%2C%22pf%22%3A%7B%22value%22%3Afalse%7D%2C%22rs%22%3A%7B%22value%22%3Atrue%7D%2C%22ah%22%3A%7B%22value%22%3Atrue%7D%7D%2C%22isListVisible%22%3Atrue%2C%22mapZoom%22%3A16%7D">million dollar yuppie housing</a>. Let a thousand parks bloom. Let a thousand historical buildings be restored. Let many poems be written and flowers planted. Let the oak trees live. Preserve Berkeley. There is only one. Signed, A Native Berkeleyan.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In a world that contains Maoist-Landlordist Thought, who knows what might be possible?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>