<post>
  <author>JhanicManifold</author>
  <date>2021-02-10T12:28:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lgslx8/gratitude_walking_through_walmart/</link>
  <title>Gratitude on a Walk Through Walmart</title>
  <category>
   <li>economics</li>
   <li>personal</li>
   <li>flux</li>
  </category>
  <body>
   <div class="md">
    <p>Yesterday, I cried of gratitude while walking through Walmart.</p>
    <p>My parents grew up in communist Romania, for my mom eating bananas was something rare and special, she was ecstatic every time her family was able to buy some. As a young boy, my dad would spend hours waiting in line (and defending his position against other young boys) for the privilege of being allowed to exchange money for food. Some people were luckier and happened to be friends with the food store clerks (or used bribes): they got advance notice when new items were in stock. Money wasn't the problem (the Party, in their infinite benevolence, understood that the people needed to be able to afford bread, and so kept the prices low), everyone had money, the problem was finding food to exchange against that money. If your family had a car, it was the same state-manufactured <a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/proxy/w6o5BV8HuTNfS0FeE9enJ8VYv7Ev5T-aLOqBJt-FHPsLMhWHLQ25QqKRe9UF8ecdcI57Y11IwRcBNpKlZff0AeYi2-age1hYzrkkc7CMqemlZcR9rw">car</a> , in the same gray color as everyone else's, my grandparents spent 3 years on a wait-list (having already paid, of course) before the State deigned deliver it to them. When my grandfather came to a Canadian suburb to see the house his engineer son had just bought, he asked how many other families we were sharing it with. When he saw the sapphire-blue pool in our backyard, he started crying.</p>
    <p>I've also recently started reading The Gulag Archipelago, detailing the forced labour camp system in the Soviet Union. This book is making me feel the most intense emotions I've ever felt reading a book: blood-boiling rage, bone-deep indignation and strongest of all an overwhelming sense of duty to value the freedom that I have. I can feel the 60 million people who would have liked nothing more in life than to have the chance to experience what I would consider abject failure. What I fear happening to me in life, they would have hailed as a miracle from god. What I would consider a mediocre outcome isn't even in the set of possibilities for them, they would have hoped for it if only they knew it was possible, but they didn't. I suspect that they would have passed out from sheer disbelieving joy walking through Walmart. Most of all, I can feel them crying out "Don't you fucking dare waste your freedom out of fear!"</p>
    <p>So I'm walking through Walmart, seeing the 30 different choices of chocolate bars, wall-to-wall offerings of chips, perpetually-filled bread-racks and meat counters, all the eggs, milk and butter that I could ever want, giant multinational corporations fiercely fighting for the right to sell me the tastiest food from every part of the world at the best price possible. I start to smile and this great sense of gratitude radiates from my upper-back. Suddenly my problems don't seem so large anymore, and I know that everything is going to be alright.</p>
    <p>Discussions of the culture war here can get quite depressive and hopeless, and its good to sometimes remember just what the stakes are, just how bad things can get, and how good they are right now.</p>
   </div>
  </body>
</post>