<post>
  <note>Removed a user ping.  Not sure if you want to keep the reddit link opening.</note>
  <author>Lykurg480</author>
  <date>2021-02-07T22:08:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lewuzb/emergent_coordination/</link>
  <title>Coordination As an Emergent Process</title>
  <category>
    <li>economics</li>
    <li>civilization</li>
  </category>
  <body>
   <div class="md">
    <p>Ive been thinking about this for a while, but u/AncestralDetox's <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/l9xgxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_01/gma5msu/">recent</a> <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/l9xgxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_01/gmbzxxq/">comments</a> have helped to crystalise it. The summary is that I think even ordinary coordination is closer to emergent behaviour then generally considered.</p>
    <p>The received view of coordination goes something like this: First, people act uncoordinated. They realise that they could do better if they all acted differently, but its not worth it to act differently if the others dont. They talk to each other and agree to the new course of action. Then they follow through on it and reap the benefits.</p>
    <p>There are problems with this. For example we can imagine this exact thing happening up until the moment for the new action, when everyone continues with the old action instead. Everyone is acting rationally in this scenario, because if noone else is doing the new action then it hurts you if you do it, so you shouldnt. Now we are tempted to say that in that case the people didnt "really mean" the agreement – but just putting "really" in front of something doesnt make an explanation. We can imagine the same sequence of words said and gestures made etc in both the successful and the unsuccessful scenario, and both are consistent – though it seems that for some reason the former happens more often. If we cant say anything about what it is to really mean the agreement, then its just a useless word use to insist on our agreement story. If we say that you only really mean the agreement if you follow through with it... well, then its possible that the agreement is made but only some of the people mean it. And then it would be possible for someone to suspect that the other party didnt mean it, and so rationally decide not to follow through. And then by definition, he wouldnt really have meant it, which means it would be reasonable for the other party to think he didnt mean it, and therefore rationally decide not to follow through... So before they can agree to coordinate, they need to coordinate on really meaning the agreement. But then the agreement doesnt explain how coordination works, its just a layer of indirection. </p>
    <p>If we say you only really mean it if you believe the others will follow through, then agreement isnt something a rational agent can decide to do. It only decides what it does, not what it believes – either it has evidence that the others will follow through, or it doesnt. Cant it act in a way that will make it more likely to arrive at a really meant agreement? Well, to act in a way that makes real agreement more likely, it needs to act in a way that will make the other party follow through. But if the other person is a rational agent, the only thing that will make them more likely to follow through is something that makes them believe the first agent will follow through. And the only way he gets more likely to follow through is if something makes the other person more likely to follow through... etc. You can only correctly believe that something will make real agreement more likely if the other party thinks so, too. So again before you can do something that makes it more likely to really agree to coordinate, you need to coordinate on which things make real agreement more likely. We have simply added yet another layer of indirection.</p>
    <p>Couldnt you incentivise people to follow through? Well, if you could unilaterally do that, then you could just do it, no need for any of this talking and agreeing. If you cant unilaterally do it...</p>
    <blockquote>
        <p><a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/07/30/meditations-on-moloch/">The two active ingredients of government are laws plus violence – or more abstractly agreements plus enforcement mechanism. Many other things besides governments share these two active ingredients and so are able to act as coordination mechanisms to avoid traps.</a></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>... then you end up suggesting that we should solve our inability to coordinate by coordinating to form an institution that forces everyone to coordinate. Such explanation, very dormitive potency.</p>
    <p>People cant just decide/agree to coordinate. There is no general-purpose method for coordination. This of course doesnt mean that it doesnt happen. It still can, you just cant make it. It also doesnt mean that people have no agency at all – if you switched one person for another with different preferences, you might well get a different result – just not necessarily in a consistent way, or even in the direction of those preferences. So this is not a purely semantic change. The most important thing to take away from this, I think, is that the perfectibility associated with the received view doesnt hold. On that view, for any possible way society could be organised, if enough people want to get there, then we can – if only we could figure out how to Really Agree. Just what is supposed to be possible in this sense <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/fx9fnb/why_wonkism/">isnt clear either</a>, but its still subjectively simple, and besides, its <em>possible</em>, which lends a certain immediate understanding. Or so it seems at least, while the coordination part of the classical picture is still standing – each of them has to be true, because the other part wouldnt make sense without it. I suggest that neither does – they only seem to, in the same way the idea of being invisible and still able to see doesnt immediately ring an alarm bell in our head.</p>
</div></a>
  </body>
</post>