<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2021-02-09T13:45:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lf6ihw/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_08/gmp2ndi/</link>
  <title>Whether or not men ""really"" value motherhood, and how</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Thanks for writing this.  I am minded of a certain Chesterton quote, from <em>What's Wrong With the World?</em>--</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>But when people begin to talk about this domestic duty as not merely difficult but trivial and dreary, I simply give up the question. For I cannot with the utmost energy of imagination conceive what they mean.  When domesticity, for instance, is called drudgery, all the difficulty arises from a double meaning in the word. If drudgery only means dreadfully hard work, I admit the woman drudges in the home, as a man might drudge at the Cathedral of Amiens or drudge behind a gun at Trafalgar. But if it means that the hard work is more heavy because it is trifling, colorless and of small import to the soul, then as I say, I give it up; I do not know what the words mean.</p>
        <p>To be Queen Elizabeth within a definite area, deciding sales,  banquets, labors and holidays; to be Whiteley within a certain area,  providing toys, boots, sheets, cakes and books, to be Aristotle within a certain area, teaching morals, manners, theology, and hygiene; I can understand how this might exhaust the mind, but I cannot imagine how it could narrow it.</p>
        <p>How can it be a large career to tell other people’s children about  the Rule of Three, and a small career to tell one’s own children about the universe? How can it be broad to be the same thing to everyone, and narrow to be everything to someone? No; a woman’s function is laborious, but because it is gigantic, not because it is minute. I will pity Mrs. Jones for the hugeness of her task; I will never pity her for its smallness.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I endorse this quote wholeheartedly.  And to your question--</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I get such rapid agreement from the anti-blank-slate crowd, it scares me. Are they actually agreeing with the all-important caveat?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>--I would respond with my own question: why does it scare you?  I am certainly anti-blank-slatist.  I find our cultural devaluation of motherhood disturbing.  I think it is only part of a larger trend, however, toward a downright Platonic antagonism against the institution of the family.  What many people don't notice is the extent to which fatherhood had been wrecked by the one-two punch of office culture and government welfare.  The separation of home and the workplace took fathers out of homes long before it took mothers out of homes.  This is a long and complicated emergent trend that weaves through urbanization, industrialization, the rise of the suburbs... and brings us back here, to pandemic-wracked America.  We have forgotten how to <em>work alongside</em> our children in those moments when it is impossible for one person to focus solely on their care.  We have smaller families and so cannot (or will not) place some of the burden of care on older children.  We have gotten paranoid (rightly or wrongly) about allowing children to look after themselves and one another.</p>
      <p>I recognize that the largeness of the phenomenon means it cannot be fixed by clamoring <em>only</em> for stay-at-home mothers to do what they have done for all of human history.  But I think the pandemic may have given us a chance to move <em>forward</em>, if only our politicians could be arsed to see it.  How many people, if they could simply exit the "workforce" and stay home to raise their families as they saw fit, would do so?  Why don't we enable this?  Well, the answer is complicated but it probably has the letters "GDP" somewhere in the report.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Or is it just a quick CYA that they toss off before returning to a comfortable belief in their own greater importance and worth?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't know any heterosexual men who actually believe that they have more worth than women.  Many think they are smarter than women, or stronger; many object to the ways that women value things, preferring more masculine approaches to the world.  Many are downright misogynistic--but almost always because they have been <em>denied</em> something that they want at such a deep biological level that they cannot help but hate <em>someone</em> for it.  If there is anything our society is willfully blind about (probably there are many such things, <em>but</em>) it is the absolute biological imperative (young) men feel to <em>have sex</em>.  Yes, yes, hashtag-not-all-men, but really: almost all men.  Women--<em>all</em> women--have a path to worth by possession of their primary and secondary sex characteristics, but also via their caring nature.  Men who <em>feel</em> this, even if they don't <em>realize</em> it, may feel it is unfair for women, who already have so much value built right into their existence, to deprive men of opportunities to win some glory for themselves.  Conversely, women who prefer to be valued in <em>other ways</em> beyond merely being feminine will find such jealousy a maddening hurdle to their own projects.</p>
      <p>I think men are foolish to treat those kinds of opportunities as a zero-sum game, but particularly for low-status men I'm not sure how we can reasonably expect anything <em>but</em> foolishness; we haven't given them any attractive alternatives.  Men are willing to suffer, bleed, even die to provide for a family, conditional on a partner who is willing to round out the equation through childbearing and childrearing.  Filling out the ranks of the social elite with equal-opportunity employment does not help the majority of humans who will never be the social elite.  Providing single women with the means to raise children absent any need to also cooperate in providing their father with sexual fulfillment gives us a two-tiered society in which wealthy children have it all--two parents, ample resources, positive masculine and feminine role models--and poor children are relegated to a world where most of the men they see are reduced to perpetually-frustrated beasts-of-burden and the women in their life are mostly wards of the state (either through welfare or government employment).  </p>
      <p>I don't know how to fix this, and I am sufficiently opposed to growth in government power that I am reluctant to go all-in on a welfare state.  But assuming (I think a good assumption) that my political preferences will never, ever be implemented in the United States ever again: I'd much rather a welfare state that incentivizes and <a href="https://cointhoughts.co/is-this-why-everyone-hates-tucker-carlson/">enables family life</a>, than a corporatist state that incentivizes maximum employment.  Children are a long-term project, but they are not a lifelong project.  Take it from someone who knows: your kids won't be toddlers forever.  I know you know that, but you can't know it in your bones until you get there, I think.  Your season will come, and your efforts will be rewarded.</p>
      <p>Anyway, sure--there are probably some men who make noises about the value of motherhood while secretly harboring a sense of superiority.  But <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XJlBVlVAaUc">you can ask Lonestar</a>--they may be clumsy at expressing it, but a lot of men <em>absolutely</em> value motherhood, perhaps above every other possible human role.  Perhaps, if society would stop shaming them as sexist for expressing their appreciation, however clumsily, you would hear it more often, and have less reason to doubt it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>