<post>
  <author>Shakesneer</author>
  <date>2021-02-09T03:52:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lf6ihw/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_08/gmntcv4/</link>
  <title>The Evergreen Greatness of Wii Sports</title>
  <category>
    <li>personal</li>
    <li>media</li>
  </category>
  <context>
    <p>Why not Ring Fit Adventure? </p>
  </context>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Wii sports breaks down into 5 games: baseball, boxing, tennis, bowling, and golf. Taking them in that order:</p>
      <p>Wii baseball is a nullity and can be mostly disregarded. Good for curiosity.</p>
      <p>Wii Boxing makes for a good match or two with a friend. It can be a little hectic and so gets a little physically tiring. (At least compared to other things people do in their living rooms.) Fun for bragging rights. Makes an OK tournament.</p>
      <p>Wii Tennis is an immediate hit at parties and casual social settings. Anyone can play with nothing more than a good arm and a good sense of timing. It is also some success as a single-player game for about 15 minutes in suite with the rest of the games. But more than that, Wii Tennis offers doubles with 4 players. This makes it not only a perfect game for duels, but a perfect team game. Wii Tennis makes for great tournaments, and unlike Boxing is light enough that people will gladly play many, many matches.</p>
      <p>Wii Bowling is also a diamond. For some people, Wii Bowling is Wii Sports. This game was so popular that it spawned hundreds of viral articles about people breaking their TVs by accidentally throwing their wiimotes. With the different angles and styles of throw, Wii Bowling has a surprising amount of depth. And, truly a rare quality for video games, Wii Bowling is almost as good as the sport it attempts to replace. At least, I've been to bowling parties, I've been to Wii Bowling parties, and it's at the latter that people had most fun. There are many famous games for other sports, FIFA and Madden and Pro Golf and Mario Tennis -- but Wii Bowling is the only bowling game immediately recognizable to people of all sorts. </p>
      <p>Finally, there's Wii Golf, which alone might be one of the best games on the system. Wii Golf is not as casual as the other games here, and can't be played as quickly, but might be the deepest. Even without the complexities of other golf games with curved shots and stamina and special effects, Wii Golf is deep enough for both single contemplation and simple enough for friends and family. Sessions can take hours, and this game puts the lie to the idea that Wii Sports is merely "casual". Wii Golf, like Wii Bowling, is incredibly sensitive to the motion controls. But when they work, they actually enhance the game -- there's a sense when playing that "I screwed that up" or "I nailed it". Here Wii Golf, unlike Wii Bowling, doesn't replace the original sport, which is too outdoors to ever be replaced by a game. But in my experience Wii Golf creates its own itch, so that years later friends and family still want to play it.</p>
      <p>A word also about Miis. Wii Sports wasn't the first game to use digital avatars, and properly the Mii is part of the console and not the game. But the Mii is the face of the console, a core part of the game, and can be great fun in its own right. The secret is that the Mii is a little too goofy, and so people don't mind that their Mii is a little too silly, doesn't look quite right. In the right crowd a few minutes making Miis for players has the same effect as giving everyone a shot of something to drink. </p>
      <p>When I say Wii Sports is one of the greatest games ever made, I don't mean to just be contrarian. People think I'm joking. But even now the game holds up. It is, really, just stupid silly fun. And it is fun. When I say Capture The Flag is a great game, I'm not criticizing Poker or Chess. Likewise when I say Wii Sports is a great game, I'm not denying the virtues of Zelda or Halo. Those latter games, though, aren't "hardcore" and mature as Wii Sports is "casual" and dumpy. These games just have different ideals to live up to. I like Zelda fine, and I could play Twilight Princess and beat the 8th dungeon from memory. I couldn't even draw the 8th course of Wii Gold from memory. But I can remember playing Wii Golf with my Dad for hours and hours, and I can't remember anything about most of the times I've played Zelda or any game.</p>
      <p>Wii Sports is one of the best games ever made. It contains 3 or maybe 4 of the best sports games on the Wii or any system. It can be played as a party game, more meaningfully with friends and family, or even sometimes as a serious solo endeavor. I've played it with girlfriends, mates, grandparents, acquaintances, catholic priests, children, coworkers, and total strangers. It can even be played by people who are greatly disabled. </p>
      <p>Wii Sports is now a little rusted out and worn and the craze is over, people don't play it the same way anymore. But the same can also be said for Tetris or Pac-man. And those are great games. So is Wii Sports, except that it has been neglected by the myth-makers, dismissed as "casual," and been deliberately forgotten by the people who think about this sort of thing.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>