<post>
  <author>Slootando</author>
  <date>2021-02-04T03:07:33Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lbmozu/a_vast_web_of_vengeance_the_new_york_times/gly0qc8/</link>
  <title>The fragility of a comfortable lifestyle and the strength of those with nothing to lose</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Yeah, I think I saw this article previously in the main thread's bare links and/or other crime-think corners of the interwebs, but didn't have a chance to respond yet. I'm glad you brought it up again; it is relevant to many of ours' interests.</p>
      <p>It’s like asymmetric warfare. How can you even begin to defend yourself against someone who’s willing to set themselves on fire just to burn you? What’s worse is that often times, they don’t even need to set themselves on fire, if they have sufficient institutional and/or social backing.</p>
      <p>Truth can be a woefully insufficient defense against libel.</p>
      <p>Suppose you’re a regular, law-abiding citizen doing well in life, earning five-to-seven figures a year at a white-collar job—or you’re a student on the path to doing so. Maybe you’re a (future) regular office drone, or something more esteemed like a doctor, lawyer, investment banker, or software engineer.</p>
      <p>Your income and net-worth allow you to live a handsome lifestyle, but you’re still not rich enough to whimsically deploy a squadron of lawyers and publicists to defend a false accusation on your behalf without damaging your quality of life, your life savings—much less have the ability to have someone “disappeared” or… deplatformed from life via a mostly peaceful helicopter drop. You’re just a normie citizen.</p>
      <p>If things go south you have a lot to lose. Your lifestyle is fragile in the Talebian-sense: Anti-<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antifragile">antifragile</a>. Your life is a continual-rolling of short out-of-the-money options. A false accusation could de-rail your marriage, your retirement plans, your ability to payoff your mortgage, your ability to pay for your kids’ private schools, cost you your job (and your ability to find one afterward)—and as we see from the article, potentially those of your friends and family, as well.</p>
      <p>Someone with less to lose doesn’t have to worry about any of that. After falsely accusing you, they can return to working the under-the-radar jobs they worked before—perhaps in the grey or black markets—and/or return to living off the government’s (that is, your) largesse. Even an accuser with something to lose may have institutional forces to protect them and/or help persecute you, e.g. academic tenure, Title IX kangaroo courts, HR and Legal departments, activist lawyers and judges.</p>
      <p>It’s a form of emergent anarcho-tyranny... where the earnest, productive, law-abiding have to constantly tip-toe around, walk on thin ice—being careful not to rock the boat lest you somehow trigger someone enough to try ruining your life. Although this is nothing new, the signal-boosting via platforms like Twitter or Google increases the probability of suffering such tail-risks. We’ve seen this well-before the 24/7 social media age, but somehow we’ve still yet to develop the cultural antibodies against it. For example, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_lacrosse_case">Duke lacrosse case of 2006</a>.</p>
      <p>Three young white men of the Duke lacrosse team were falsely accused by a black stripper of rape—a single-ish mother with a… curious… past, especially when it comes to accusations, to say the least. Nonetheless, the Duke Three were rail-roaded by an activist prosecutor, mainstream media, and shoved <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Group_of_88">under the bus by their professors</a>. Their lives were thrown into mayhem, their futures de-railed; they and their families spent a small fortune on their legal defenses.</p>
      <p>The stripper’s life hummed along as usual—actually better than usual, becoming an overnight celebrity with the full faith and backing of mainstream media and academia. In the aftermath—after her accusation was ruled fake and... well, false—this story was quickly dropped and forgotten from the news-cycle. The lovely young lady returned to <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/latarian-milton">doing hood-rat stuff with her friends</a>, eventually culminating in a 2013 murder conviction.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>