<post>
  <author>Stefferi</author>
  <date>2021-02-09T20:32:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lf6ihw/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_08/gmqlg2r/</link>
  <title>"Cultural appropriation" as a matter of being territorial about status indicators</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There's a lot of non-racial/non-ethnic/non-religious cultural appropriation accusations flying all around, even though the accusers might not call them such, or might do it ironically (but still in a way where irony obviously masks real dislike of something). Metal fan sees a teen girl wearing a Behemoth shirt and angrily demands her to list all the albums in order. A working-class punk sneers at rich kids playing punk with immaculate expensive barbershop Mohawk haircuts. A gamer complains about the fucking casuals going "OMG I'm such a gamer!" when they play Candy Crush and Farmville. And so on.</p>
      <p>It's pretty obvious where such reactions come from, at least in part - you've been in some subculture, you've taken your lumps from people who just don't understand, and suddenly there's a new class of people just trying to easily glide in, kind of like they're just wearing a costume. However, more than that, there's real risks involved in all cases. If you've been into metal specifically because you like the abrasive sound and the obscure nihilist/Satanist philosophies, all indicators that it's becoming more popular are alarming, since it's probably going to lead to all those things you liked getting watered down. People richer than you colonizing your subculture gentrifies it - suddenly you're getting pushed out because gigs and merch suddenly cost more because the bands and clubs can charge more. And so on.</p>
      <p>In case of yoga, if there's a lot of people who are not into it for religious reasons, and you are into it for religious reasons, if the culture just sees it as a bunch of postures for getting into shape (and implicitly also something kind of silly for bored housewives), it opens your religious practice up for mockery, and religious people don't tend to want that, especially since it's the kind of mockery that doesn't really even lead to noble suffering for your faith, it's just kind of annoying. (It's telling that the other group that would want Westerners - that's what "white people" means here, essentially - to stop practicing yoga would probably tend to be Christians.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>