<post>
  <author>cantbeproductive</author>
  <date>2021-05-25T17:35:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/njr5h0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_24_2021/gzey4wa/</link>
  <title>Donald Trump, Fake New Yorker</title>
  <category>
    <li>coteries</li>
    <li>culture</li>
    <li>media</li>
  </category>
  <context>
    <p>I've never lived in New York City. But I've always been pretty bullish on Andrew Yang. He strikes me as a generally thoughtful person and as the sort of politician who, if I do not exactly want to offer him my full-throated endorsement, I can at least imagine as a successful governor (in the literal sense of one-who-governs).</p>
    <p>So I was disappointed to see his campaign (well, his wife, but there appears to be more to come) playing the "race" card on a cartoon that ran in the Daily News. Here's the story: the cartoon depicts Yang as a tourist. The criticism is clear: "Yang isn't a real New Yorker." That criticism seems pretty stupid to me. Yang has obviously spent a lot of his life in New York, and furthermore, New York is substantially a city of immigrants anyway. But creating the impression that Yang is a carpet-bagger has been his opposition's chosen tack, so, the cartoon seems like a pretty anodyne expression of that.</p>
    <p>Evenlyn Yang, Andrew's wife, took to Twitter the totally reasonable and proportional take that this is a racial caricature on par with (or maybe worse than?) a buck-toothed guy named Chin-Kee saying "HARRO AMELLICA!"</p>
  </context>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There’s no shortage of progressive periodical calling Donald Trump a fake New Yorker and a tourist.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/daily-comment/donald-trump-tourist-trap">http://www.newyorker.com/news/daily-comment/donald-trump-tourist-trap</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Donald Trump’s kind of obnoxiousness has always seemed to be atypical of New York values, and even, to put it bluntly, a kind of tourist trap for people from Texas who think his is anything like the real New York obnoxiousness. </p>
        <p>It goes without saying, or should, that the New Yorkers issuing these judgments are invariably not-very-long-ago émigrés from elsewhere, whose roots are still in a small town in Jersey or a luncheonette in Kansas City or a farm in Ontario.</p>
        <p>Donald Trump, an interloper whose spiritual home is someplace in midair, aboard that private jet—accompanied by his Slovenian-model wife</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Can you believe that? Donald Trump married a <em>foreigner</em>. Disgusting. No real New Yorker would ever think of doing such a thing, according to <em>the New Yorker</em>. How much more irony can we attach to this, but that the anti-Slav writer is a Russian Jew named Adam <em>Gopnik</em>! Ouch. /u/Ilforte can perhaps tell us a proportional demographic breakdown of those responsible for the kulak Holocaust. Talk about sensitivity!</p>
      <p>Anyway, enough about the Gopnik, what does Mehlman say in <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/11/donald-trump-was-never-real-new-yorker/601324/">the Atlantic</a>? Anything close to this?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And the truth is, Trump, the lifelong New Yorker, was never a New Yorker. He was a tourist.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Oh, well. Way too close to this. </p>
      <p>What did Cuomo say about Trump?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I don’t believe he was a New Yorker, anyway,” he said. “Living in New York does not make you a New Yorker. To be a New Yorker is a state of mind. It’s a set of beliefs that you live by.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>If they can write this stuff about Donald Trump, so synonymous with New York that he had a cameo in <em>Home Alone</em>, born and raised by a father raised in New York, whose name is writ large on the skyscrapers, then let us please have <em>one</em> comic about Yang’s California values. Just one, without being called racist by the “Asian Victory Alliance”, a totally normal name for a totally normal racial advocacy group.</p>
      <p>Anyway, a bit more to the point,</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Some bit of context I've missed?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Yes. Asian racial networks were given hundreds of millions of dollars to advocate racially last month. This is the fruit of their labor — or really, your labor, because the corporations we work for footed the bill.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>