<post>
  <author>Nouveau_Compte</author>
  <date>2021-05-26T22:44:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/njr5h0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_24_2021/gzkl1s1/</link>
  <title>Crime and the Security Hypothesis</title>
  <category>
    <li>civilization</li>
    <li>flux</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <h2>The security hypothesis</h2>
      <p>Looking into crime research, a theory that apparently explains the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crime_drop">crime drop</a> is <strong>the security hypothesis</strong>. This theory states that:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>change in the quantity and quality of security was a key driver of the crime drop.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It posits that crime has become harder because of better security measures (more locks for instance) and that in consequence people do less crime.</p>
      <p>It matches a few observations:</p>
          <a href="http://irep.ntu.ac.uk/id/eprint/11021/1/205359_7515%20Tseloni%20Postprint.pdf">The drop in vehicle theft</a>:</li>
      <blockquote>
        <p>From evidence relating to vehicle theft in two countries it is concluded that electronic immobilisers and central locking were particularly effective.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <a href="https://crimesciencejournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s40163-017-0064-2">The impact of locks on house burglary in the UK:</a>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The causal role of improved security is strongly indicated by a set of interlocking data signatures: rapid increases in the prevalence of security, particularly in the availability of combinations of the most effective devices (door and window locks plus security lighting); a steep decline in the proportion of households without security accompanied by disproportionate rises in their burglary risk; and the decline being solely in forced rather than unforced entries to households. The study concludes that there is strong evidence that security caused the decline in burglary in England and Wales in the 1990s.</p>
      </blockquote>
          <a href="https://popcenter.asu.edu/sites/default/files/123-mayhew_clarke_elliott-motorcycle_theft_helmet_legisl.pdf">The impact of helmet laws on motorbike thefts</a>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In  London,  motorcycle thefts  fell by 24% on the introduction of helmet laws on 1 June 1973,  from 5,280  in  the  twelve  month  period  prior  to  the  legislation  to  3,997  in  the subsequent  twelve  months  (Mayhew  et  al.  1976).  In  Holland,  a  drop  in motorcycle  thefts  following  the  introduction  of helmet  laws  in  February 1975 was  noted  in  national victimisation survey results:  the  percentage  of people  who  had  experienced  a  theft  fell  from  10.0%  in  1974  to  6.4%  in 1975,  with  even  lower  levels  in  subsequent  years  (van  Straelen  1978). These  declines  were  presumably  the  result  of opportunistic  thefts  being made  more  difficult  by  the  need  for  the  thief to have  a  crash  helmet  in  his possession;  otherwise,  he  would  quickly  be  noticed  and  be  suspected  of stealing  the  motorbike.</p>
        <p>the  introduction  of penalties  for  riding  a  motorcycle without   protective   headgear  had   the  same   unintended   result   in   the Federal  Republic  of  Germany</p>
      </blockquote>
          <a href="https://popcenter.asu.edu/sites/default/files/28-bowers_et_al-closing_off_opportunities_for_crime_an_eval.pdf">The impact of backalley gates on house burglary in Great Britain</a>:</li>
      <blockquote>
        <p>A new situational crime prevention measure recently introduced into Great Britain involves the fitting of gates to alleyways running along the back of terraced properties to restrict access to local residents and reduce opportunities for offenders. (...) in the City of Liverpool. The results demonstrate that, relative to a suitable comparison area, burglary was reduced by approximately 37%</p>
      </blockquote>
      <hr />
      <h2>How does it compare to other explanations for the crime drop ?</h2>
      <p>The authors of the security hypothesis <a href="https://crimesciencejournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/2193-7680-2-5">say that a crime drop theory should pass 5 tests</a>:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>Are there reasonable empirical grounds to consider the theory ?</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Can the theory be applied to different countries (i.e. explain why the crime decreased in all developed countries) ?</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Is the theory compatible with the fact that crime was previously generally increasing for several decades?</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Is the theory compatible with the fact that some crimes such as phone theft and e-crimes were increasing while many crime types were decreasing?</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Is the theory compatible with variation in the timing and trajectory of crime falls both between countries and between crime types (some crime types decreased earlier than others) ?</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Out of <a href="https://crimesciencejournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/2193-7680-2-5/tables/1">15 common theories</a>, the security hypothesis was <a href="https://crimesciencejournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/2193-7680-2-5/tables/3">the only one to pass all 5</a>.</p>
      <hr />
      <h2>TL;DR: <a href="https://sites.nationalacademies.org/cs/groups/dbassesite/documents/webpage/dbasse_164572.pdf">A powerpoint presenting the topic</a></h2>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>