<post>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2021-05-26T20:25:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/njr5h0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_24_2021/gzk2u32/</link>
  <title>The Costs of Taking COVID More Seriously</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Pretty interesting graphs - drawn from the Oxford Covid-19 Government Response Tracker (OxCGRT) - that show <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E2Mg08XWQAM6TjH?format=jpg&amp;name=medium">virtually no relationship between COVID deaths per capita and unemployment rate</a></p>
      <p>* <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E2MU4eGXIAcI39X?format=jpg&amp;name=small">No relationship between restriction stringency and COVID deaths per capita</a></p>
      <p>*  <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E2MU4eGXsAAjYVu?format=jpg&amp;name=small">Meaningful relationship between restriction stringency and unemployment increases</a></p>
      <p>* <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E2MaEiaX0AAcsXX?format=jpg&amp;name=small">Meaningful relationship between Democrat vote share and unemployment increases</a></p>
      <p>* <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E2MWryxX0AAxjMt?format=jpg&amp;name=medium">No relationship between Democrat vote share and COVID deaths per capita</a>, even when <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E2MdGt7WYAQI35v?format=jpg&amp;name=medium">excluding the early hit states like NY, NJ, CT, and MA</a></p>
      <p>* Virtually no relationship between COVID deaths per capita and <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E2Ngje8X0AEv3lJ?format=png&amp;name=small">median age of state</a>, <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E2NgldwX0AIXJdz?format=png&amp;name=small">population per square mile of state</a>, <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E2NgoJBX0AQcWFG?format=png&amp;name=small">urban population percentage of state</a>, or <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/E2NgpD4XMAEonKr?format=png&amp;name=small">income per capita of state</a></p>
      <p>It honestly blows my mind that - in addition to the completely expected conventional wisdom of the Reddit, Twitter, and the mainstream media bubble - polling reflects that voters broadly believe that Democrats handled COVID better than Republicans. We <strong><em>know</em></strong> that Democrat voters massively, histrionically overstated the risk of COVID to the point that they estimated the hospitalization risk at more than <a href="https://www.washingtonexaminer.com/news/americans-overestimate-hospitalization-covid-study">an order of magnitude</a> over what it actually was. We <strong><em>know</em></strong> that the benefits of any restrictions / Non-Pharmaceutical Interventions (NPIs) was so weak as to be statistically indiscernible, whereas the economic costs were clear, unambiguous, and statistically significant. We <strong><em>know</em></strong> that the resistance to school openings was <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2020/11/20/covid-19-schools-data-reopening-safety/">misplaced</a> and <a href="https://nypost.com/2021/05/01/teachers-union-collaborated-with-cdc-on-school-reopening-emails/">political</a>, and that <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/04/22/opinion/covid-vaccine-kids.html">children are at virtually no risk from COVID</a>. We <strong><em>know</em></strong> that states with Democrat governors had slightly <em>more</em> deaths per capita than their counterparts, while also having significantly higher unemployment than their counterparts, and that the <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/stimulus-no-republican-in-congress-voted-for-biden-stimulus-package-2021-3">strictly partisan</a> “American Rescue Plan” stimulus bill <a href="https://www.manhattan-institute.org/massive-1-9-trillion-bill-is-a-bailout-for-blue-states">allocated funds based on unemployment</a> (creating windfalls for NY, CA, NJ, MA, IL, etc at the expense of red states). We <strong><em>know</em></strong> that Biden did virtually nothing different from Trump on COVID, has overseen as many deaths at this point as Trump did prior to the election, didn’t even increase performative / virtually useless metrics like mask compliance or lockdown stringency, and that the entire time he wore a mask as president was completely unscientific grandstanding given he was already vaccinated. Yet somehow, misleading media convinces the masses that <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/coronavirus-polls/">the difference was night and day</a></p>
      <p>Now that COVID seems to be largely resolved domestically, we can see with a bit more perspective. <a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#datatracker-home">There are currently about ~600,000 deaths attributed to COVID</a> (via somewhat dubious methodology), which reflects about 0.18% of the population. <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/ng-interactive/2020/dec/22/lost-on-the-frontline-our-findings-to-date">The median age of death (from/with) COVID is ~78</a>, compared to a <a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/263724/life-expectancy-in-the-united-states/">US life expectancy that averages between 78.04 and 78.84 over the last decade</a>; nota bene that <a href="https://globalhealth5050.org/the-sex-gender-and-covid-19-project/the-data-tracker/?explore=country&amp;country=USA#search">56.5% of US COVID deaths have been among men</a>, who have a <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data-visualization/state-life-expectancy/">lower life expectancy averaging ~76</a>. The second highest risk factor after age is obesity, <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/70/wr/mm7010e4.htm?s_cid=mm7010e4_w">with 79% of those hospitalized with COVID being overweight or obese</a> and  <a href="https://www.webmd.com/lung/news/20200805/obesity-ups-odds-for-severe-covid-19-but-age-matters#1">morbidly obese COVID patients 60% more likely to die or be intubated, and moderately obese COVID patients 30% more likely to die or be intubated</a>. Additionally, <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/covid-19-comorbidities-are-the-elephant-in-the-room-7d185bd6cfe2">94% of COVID deaths involved one or more comorbid conditions</a> with an average of 2.28 comorbidities per decedent, and <a href="https://www.ucsf.edu/news/2020/05/417411/smoking-nearly-doubles-rate-covid-19-progression">a history of smoking nearly doubling the risk of disease progression</a></p>
      <p>In totality, the end result of COVID in terms of mortality was that, generally speaking, the oldest, fattest, sickest, least risk averse, 1 out of every 550 Americans would die before mass availability of vaccinations, at a median age of death on par with our average life expectancy. For those under 18, it was decidedly less deadly than the seasonal flu. For the ~85% of the population under 65 - and especially the ~66% under the age of 50 - there was extremely little risk (and even overall there was less than 1/10th of the risk that polled Democrats seemed to think). If you had told people that in March 2020, I struggle to imagine how anyone could've used this to scaremonger the innumerate masses into an outright existential panic that was used as a pretext for everything from massive wealth redistribution to radical changes in election laws to drastic expansions of the power of the state to disrupting a year and a half of many children's education and socialization, and so on</p>
      <p>In retrospect, it's clear we should've adopted polices proscribed in <a href="https://gbdeclaration.org">The Great Barrington Declaration</a> and centered on Focused Protection of the vulnerable instead of ineffective, dysfunctional universal restrictions that treated everyone the same - despite vastly different risk profiles. Instead, we did a poor job of protecting the vulnerable, disrupted the development of our nation's children for a year, cratered small businesses, let the government run roughshod over civil liberties, and spent <em>insane</em> amounts of money to exceedingly little benefit. It was very convenient that this virus was only a meaningful risk to people who were a very tiny component of the workforce; our utter failure to take that into account, and to try to treat all people as interchangeable, is breathtaking. By back of the envelope calculations, going with the GBD approach + Operation: Warp Speed while foregoing all of the other ultimately ineffective NPIs would've <strong>easily</strong> resulted in national savings of $6 Trillion - or 3x the cost of the similarly doomed and quixotic Iraq War. Even if this had resulted in a <em>doubling</em> of COVID causalities - which beggars belief and is a <em>wildly</em> generous overestimation of the (demonstrably ineffective!) NPIs' efficacy, this would put the marginal cost of life saved - of, generally, very sick and very fat people <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/william-shakespeare-covid-vaccine-first-man-uk-died/">at the very end of their lives</a> - at $10M, <em>or more than 10x the lifetime earnings of the average American.</em> (My actual estimation is that it's closer to $30-60M per septuagenarian death avoided)</p>
      <p>All of this said, the idea that we should have taken COVID <em>more</em> seriously is so alien to me as to be barely comprehensible</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>