<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2020-12-30T05:05:29Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kllo5n/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_28/ghgyznd/</link>
  <title>/u/DeanTheDull on the importance of the UK as an ally</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>​</p>
      <p>As a demonstration of the EU's political muscle on the international stage, Brexit has... not been impressive. 'The UK is more diminished' does not mean the EU appears stronger or more competent, especially given the EU's obvious attempts- and failures- to keep the UK in its strategic orbit.</p>
      <p>The UK, as an international polity, is a prize/high-value ally for whoever it aligns with because the UK is a capable partner in so many fields that no matter what your diplomatic/strategic context, the UK can help you more than most. It's not big enough to fight and win your wars for you, like the US, or subsidze your economy in its entirety, but it's a significant boon. It has a tier-1 intelligence and analysis capabilty, in case you have domestic terrorism concerns. It has world-class academic and economic assets for helping develop your economy, and the financial center to help allocate funds. (This will be decreased by, but not ended by, diverence with EU.) The UK also has a very credible and professional military0 not enough to win your wars for you, but more than enough to train, equip, and assist across the globe. With France bogged down in Africa, and the German military increasingly a bad punchline that fails to have armed drones in 2020, the UK is THE Western alternative to partnership with the US, even as the UK has more influence with the US (and many other places in the world) than most EU countries aligned. This isn't even touching on UNC veto ability, cultural soft power in the anglosphere, or a very well established diplomatic corps actively engaged across the world.</p>
      <p>With the UK as a member, the EU was a credible future global power even without German militarization. Without it, the EU won't be a great power until Germany militarizes, and quite possibly not even then. That the UK itself is less valuable as an ally without its influence within the EU doesn't change that.</p>
      <p>This was known beforehand, and so the strategic grand strategy move would have been to keep the UK as close as possible- close enough to hopefully re-integrate/admit the UK in the future once the Brexit political coalition passed (a matter of age and possible mear years), or at least in the EU orbit rather than, say, the American economic/regulatory orbit. And that is what the EU was at least trying to do, via the May deal and the Irish regulatory alignment hooks and 'level playing field' tactics.</p>
      <p>But they continually fucked it up by trying to use economic coercion levers against a country that- in multiple electoral contests- chose sovereignty-at-the-cost-of-economy over economic-maximization, and in doing so burned all the Europhile members of parliament (and Prime Minister who sympathized with them) to be replaced by a crushingly strong new political coalition that will quite likely define the UK for decades to come as the EU-phile Labor Party loses its northern heartlands. </p>
      <p>So now the EU has no sphere of influence over Britain, just regular economic influence on a country that repeatedly prefered sovereignty to economic threats, and now it's Biden and the US's move to lose strengthening the US-UK alliance to great American benefit. </p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>About the main avenue the EU succeeded in was making the process a punishment enough to deter other EU countries from seeking their own exits. This makes sense, in that institutions that don't prioritize their own survival eventually don't survive, but it's also a mark of a weak and insecure power that relies on coercive fear to maintain cohesion. If the EU wasn't strong enough to be able to give the UK a sweetheart deal that would keep it aligned and in position for future re-integration, that's a demonstration of its underlying fragility.</p>
      <p>It also comes with its own problems, as when dissidents can't leave a system they become more committed to changing it from within. After Brexit, not even Poland or Hungary want to leave the EU, for example... but that just gives them more incentive to focus more time (and accept more costs) on challenging the notional shared values and establishment elites they disagree with. When exit is unthinkable, the nature of conflict inside the space changes- the La Pens and ADPs and other populists of Europe aren't going to become establishment technocratic neoliberals just because even they believe leaving the EU isn't worth the hassle, they'll just continue to seek power to smash the parts of Europe they don't like from the inside. Brexit has deterred Exit, not European populism, which now can't even be distracted by the phantasm of exit politics that would probably defeat them on its own.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>In so much that Brexit was a contest between the UK and EU, the UK may well have gotten the worse of it relatively. As a demonstration of the EU's strength as a wannabe great power alternative to the US, the EU lost the most in losing influence, a good part of itself, and shat should have been its prized ally.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>