<post>
  <author>heywaitiknowthatguy</author>
  <date>2020-12-29T21:44:19Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kllo5n/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_28/ghfm8ou/</link>
  <title>/u/heywaitiknowthatguy explains why children *at least* should not be allowed on social media</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think Instagram and Twitter should be illegal outright. I don't think there's anything salvageable with Instagram, it fills part of the niche of Facebook but then turns it into a spectator affair, that's bad. Twitter might be salvageable if it were legally prohibited from banning accounts for anything but a specific category of illegal content (illegal porn, copyright-violating content sharing,) and additionally prohibited from maintaining any sort of "trending" category or having such information extricable via API, and prohibited from any sort of artificial feed manipulation. Facebook has problems but I think its positives outweigh its negatives, while I don't think there are <em>any</em> positives, <em>at all</em>, about Instagram and Twitter. </p>
      <p>The other day someone whose username I do not remember posted a comment on overpopulation. I figure people are smart enough to come up with the necessary engineering to cover Earth in arcologies and transform the whole planet into an ecumenopolis. A whole host of Norman Borlaugs engineering the semi-dwarf wheat of whatever logistical problem.</p>
      <p>The problem is we've had a bad version of that. We've found a force multiplier and given it to things that are socially destructive. What semi-dwarf wheat did for ending hunger, Instagram (and even aspects of YouTube and TikTok) have done for attacking humility and life-contentedness, and Twitter has done that for foolishness. Before, for something to get the sort of attention an <em>average</em> Twitter controversy might, it'd take someone extremely charismatic, or an extreme issue. Now Twitter higher-ups can insert something in their trending column, causing fools to pile on, and companies to listen. Fake trending should be the sort of thing that Twitter got sued to death over years ago. </p>
      <p>I don't know the resolution of the trans controversies surrounding Cyberpunk 2077. If serious claims of boycott persisted past its release, I don't know of them. I do know the game broke 1 million concurrent players on Steam. So if a corporation was making decisions because they saw Twitter and thought nobody would be playing it, yet it tops the charts, that's a big problem. But maybe CDPR greased the wheels and the opposition cooled off. </p>
      <p>That's not going to happen with Hogwarts Legacy, the Harry Potter-verse RPG coming out next year. There is a vocal group of HP fans with seeming strong support (high upvotes) who say they won't purchase it because they oppose Rowling's stance on trans issues. So unless there's a total sociopolitical shift against trans issues or Rowling turns a 180, there are going to be loud cries for boycott increasing to its release. I think those cries are going to do nothing, I think the game's going to be as much of a success as everything else Harry Potter is. I don't even think it will be because of some group of people buying it specifically because of trans-activist opposition. I think a lot of the activists will be the ones playing it, because video games are great and people want an escape and it's easy to rationalize just <em>yourself</em> doing something, and also probably because WB will make some nominal donation to a charity and the "developer team" (HR) will make a statement. But even if none of that happens, even if every person who says they won't buy it doesn't buy it, I still figure it will sell well, because I know for a fact a lot of people who say they won't buy it <em>don't play video games</em>. </p>
      <p>This gets us to the point, two paragraphs about vidya that exist because there's a website that offers <em>no economic product</em> except giving dumb people megaphones so they can bully companies into changing products said dumb people never had any intention of buying, and still won't buy once it's changed. Adam Smith's ghost is screaming.</p>
      <p>Now for the meat on Instagram:</p>
      <p>Wapo: <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national/health-science/suicide-attempts-using-poison-have-surged-among-young-people/2019/04/30/a980c98c-6b8d-11e9-a66d-a82d3f3d96d5_story.html">Suicide attempts using poison have surged among young people, particularly girls</a></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“It’s not going to be any one thing that explains these troubling trends,” Moutier said. “And the impact of social media on youth mental health is complex, but the research we’ve seen so far suggests heavy screen time does have an impact on mood, sleep and suicide risk.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Forbes: <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/nicolefisher/2019/06/30/neuroscience-explains-why-instagram-is-so-bad-for-teen-girls/?sh=9e130746eba6">Neuroscience Explains Why Instagram Is So Bad For Teen Girls</a></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>As of 2018, Instagram has more than 1 billion users worldwide, and more than half (over 500 million) are daily users. Of those, about 60% are females under the age of 34. This is not coincidental. In fact, the software has been engineered to keep them engaged longer and coming back for more. Bottomless scrolling, tagging, notifications, and live stories tap into the fear of missing out (FOMO) that give teens so much anxiety. Or as We The Internet posed in a YouTube video, the site has “engineered addiction.”</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>Functional MRIs have shown that how many likes (which are often fake, purchased or manufactured) an Instagram post has alters the appeal of that photo to viewers. <em>For example, when girls see a highly rated image, their brain (most likely the nucleus accumbens, or reward circuit) instinctively associates it with being better, no matter the content. Their brains literally can’t help but prefer images that have more likes than images with less likes.</em> As researchers at UCLA put it, teens react to what they consider “endorsements” of content.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Repeated for mega, mega emphasis: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <h4>
          <strong>For example, when girls see a highly rated image, their brain (most likely the nucleus accumbens, or reward circuit) instinctively associates it with being better, no matter the content. Their brains literally can’t help but prefer images that have more likes than images with less likes.</strong>
        </h4>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Instagram should be banned on this alone!</p>
      <p>Make it illegal for minors to use the sites, then continuously raise the penalties until the sites figure out a way to ensure their age-gating works. Someone came up with a system that can guess birth sex with extreme accuracy based on email address. Was it Google? Sounds like their forte. I bet Google can figure out if someone's a minor in like 10 clicks.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>