<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-12-25T04:11:54Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/khcdwb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_21/ggymjn8/</link>
  <title>/u/Ilforte on the plasticity of preference in the face of social pressure</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I really don't buy the entire shame/guilt dichotomy, likewise for other self-serving and bafflingly un-self-aware typologies WEIRD people invent in their "study" of social phenomena (such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hofstede%27s_cultural_dimensions_theory">Hofstede's</a> model). What does "shame culture" even mean? It means tendency to avoid showing behaviors that are frowned upon. But it does not happen in a vacuum: you're supposed to feel "guilt" instead, a dread of behaving in ways that are inherently immoral, even if unseen by others. This is tied to the notion of East Asians "saving face" instead of following their conscience, and supports the implicit hope that Christianity really is the only Truth and Salvation after all.</p>
      <p>(For added hilarity, see Zvi's <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/CHtwDXy63BsLkQx4n/covid-12-24-we-re-f-ed-it-s-over#Face_Saving">"we are a face-saving culture now" bit</a>.)</p>
      <p>But I digress. Thing is, in practice, you can define what is or isn't moral by manipulating consensus that operates by shaming. Maybe not instantly, but in a generation or two, the answers children get will transform into common sense defining right and wrong internally, and the answers are affected by cheap insincere signaling that's driven by low-stakes incentives you can very easily hijack if you get to media and education (and that's still only the low-effort, guaranteed-success pathway). "Individualist dogma" is brittle, and in fact is largely an old white males thing; even with them it's most brittle when it can be attacked by appealing to previously established theory of common good, and to irrational empathy. No mask? Are you willing to kill grandma in the name of your "freedom"? Maybe you are. Be prepared for social boycott. </p>
      <p>I'd be the first to acknowledge deep cultural and indeed biological differences between human populations that affect their reasoning. But we all descend from social primates who feared exile the most, and since then we've only become more socialized – perhaps <em>over</em>socialized. Ain't any individualist dogmas that can oppose that. </p>
      <p>The reason Trump faithful are generally unfazed by liberal shaming is precisely because they are confident in having a tribe to belong to – maybe they tell themselves a story of it being a tribe of rugged individualists, self-interested yet cooperative patriots who'll raise a rifle behind each blade of grass, indeed <em>a pack</em>; but the calming feeling is every bit as "herdish" as on the other side. In fact Trump's team devoted a great deal of effort to projecting this tribal feeling, thus the accent on massive rallies and emergence of Qultist sect-like ultra-Trumpian narrative about some Plan that the true and legitimate power structure is hiding (come to think of it, it's not so different from early catacomb Christians). If anything, the attacks only brought them together.</p>
      <p>
        <em>True</em> individualism was defined by Pobedonostsev, in his rebuke to liberals: «Do you even know what Russia is? A frozen desert, where a reckless man wanders». You don't build WEIRD societies on something like that.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>