<post>
  <author>nicolordofchaos99999</author>
  <date>2020-12-28T21:24:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kllo5n/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_28/ghbregx/</link>
  <title>/u/nicolordofchaos99999 notices the parallels between cancellation and crab mentality</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Sure, I guess my point is less that Groves is “virtue signaling” or a “woke scold” or anything, but more that I doubt Gilligan would have released the video at all if not for Groves’ initial Facebook post. </p>
      <p>I mean, at my college there were a few well-meaning white people organizing fundraisers for BLM in the wake of George Floyd’s killing. One got raked over the coals on social media for apparently once <em>singing along</em> to a song with the n-word in it. (Note: I’ve done this accidentally many times in very liberal company without getting any sort of condemnation for it.) He had to make a public apology for it and took down the original fundraiser post. Another person got some blowback — though not universally —  for being associated with the fraternities which are “agents of white supremacy" now. </p>
      <p>It’s incredibly obvious to me that they were “cancelled” not because of their actions, but because they were perceived as reaching for status they weren’t entitled to. If I created the same kind of fundraiser, I would pretty much 100% be cancelled for the same reasons. Even my more liberal friends, some of whom have privately donated fairly sizable amounts to BLM, seem to understand this, although they would probably phrase it differently and say something like “I don’t want to be seen as stealing the spotlight from marginalized people.” Groves did steal the spotlight from marginalized people, thus she was justly slapped down to her proper place. </p>
      <p>My point here is really that people like Gilligan aren’t “psychopaths” who go around ruining people’s careers for no reason. Woke scolds are often pretty friendly to get along with, and I’ve found in practice they are surprisingly tolerant of heterodox and conservative views — until you are perceived as competing with them for virtue / status. THEN the claws come out. It’s a very human kind of monstrousness, really. The leaking of this video wasn’t the random act of a vindictive psychopath, but a perfectly legal move in a game that Groves might not have realized she was playing. And IMO once you understand the game you realize “the only winning move is not to play”.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>