<post>
  <author>OrangeMargarita</author>
  <date>2020-12-23T12:55:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/khcdwb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_21/ggsk4ww/</link>
  <title>/u/OrangeMargarita thinks Marx was right about class</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>My two cents (which turned out to be more like ten):</p>
      <p>It's not really that simple.  Marxists are right about one thing:  Class is always salient.  Go back as far as the Reformation.  As a German, surely Marx would have been familiar with Luther and his 95 theses.   For all the other criticisms of the Catholic Church that Luther would levy later, these theses are interesting in that they are just chock full of class-based themes.   Whether that was intentional or not, to front-load that I don't know.   The Reformation doesn't end up doing much about class, their other criticisms become broader.  The Reformation gives Europeans a new way to be tribal though - are you Catholic or Protestant?  And humans gravitate towards tribalism.</p>
      <p>The Enlightenment isn't totally unconcerned with class, but it's also concerned about this religious tribalism, and the consequences when one tribe wields too much institutional power over another.   Their answer to this is a concept for national governance whereby the people rule themselves via representative democracy, with a religious and intellectual pluralism that allows for debate and dissent.</p>
      <p>But class is still salient.  And people are still tribal.  So I think what Marxists were noticing was that things like nationality or ethnicity or religion can be really powerful tribal alliances.   People seemed to see their interests just as often in these non-material concepts, things like belonging to a community that shares a common set of values and traditions.   Marxists say no, you don't need belonging, or religion, or tradition or any of that.  Your needs are material, you need food, you need clothing and shelter.   All that other stuff is merely distracting you from uniting to pursue your material needs more effectively.</p>
      <p>And it doesn't quite turn out like Marx hoped.   From Luther to the Founding Fathers to Marx, the running theme is that the people in charge are screwing over the little guy.   But it turns out that materialist and collectivist approaches don't actually rectify that problem.   The people in charge still find ways to screw over the little guy.  And the less pluralistic and more authoritarian regimes that were supposed to stomp all that non-material hokum out only made it harder for the little guy to fight back when things went south.</p>
      <p>But what Marx does give us is this analysis of substructure and superstructure, and this structuralism, combined with some Hegelianism  is what Foucault and others are picking up on in the mid 20th century.   And this isn't occurring in a vacuum either, post World War II, in an era of increasing technological progress, specialization, expertise, in a world of Cold War and competing propaganda and an age of mass communications with newspapers and radio and film and television, etc.    Foucault is very interested in power dynamics.  And he's very interested in how they affect knowledge production and what we perceive to be true.  And you can throw Derrida in there too, he's just way more abstract about it all.</p>
      <p>This is where you start to see a shift across the pond and we've got to talk more about American thinkers.  In the late twentieth century in America Marxism/socialism/communism has all become kind of culturally radioactive.  But the Civil Rights movement has put issues of racial and gender identity front and center.  The postmodernists aren't wrong for being able to put two and two together here and saying hey, look, turns out that yeah, power dynamics do affect what we perceive to be true.   Feminism's talking about that.  Said's talking about that with Orientalism.   Representation then becomes very important.</p>
      <p>But then we have this weird split.   Classical liberalism is actually cool with all this because it can actually coexist pretty well within an Enlightenment-based pluralist framework.   But for some of those once unfashionable Marxists, this is actually kind of a problem because now we've got tribalism based on non-material social constructs like race and gender trying to shove class and material needs on the back burner again.   Critical theorists try to square the circle by saying we can talk about material needs as long as we only do so from within an identity-based lens.</p>
      <p>But now the critical theorists are running headlong into Foucault's problem again.  When they were not in control of the systems of cultural knowledge production they operated as a coalition of the oppressed.  Now that they control these systems, they do their own gatekeeping, they silence other voices, they enforce other "truths", and they can't reconcile their power as a socio-political-religious coalition with their static conception of themselves as the righteous oppressed.</p>
      <p>And the classical liberals, which includes both liberals and many conservatives, are bashing their heads against the wall because from their perspective all this reifying of binary thinking and of superiority/inferiority based on identities, all this gatekeeping and stereotyping and silencing of dissent is, to them, several giant steps backwards.   So you see more and more left-liberals asking themselves where is the line, in my own personal conscience what's the point where I am uncomfortable enough where I have to speak out against this.</p>
      <p>In the meantime, American culture is a pretty big export.  And neither Canadians nor Europeans are any more immune from those human instincts towards tribalism.  So of course this is spreading back out to the broader West.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>