<post>
  <author>Stefferi</author>
  <date>2020-12-25T15:15:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/khcdwb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_21/ggzq5b8/</link>
  <title>/u/Stefferi provides an insider look at Finland's COVID-19 response</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>From what I've followed from Finnish debates, and knowing some of the high-level figures in Finnish government personally, in some cases quite well, I've seen no indications of anything but great levels of reticence regarding the restrictions we've had and currently have. </p>
      <p>For context, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COVID-19_pandemic_in_Finland#/media/File:COVID-19_Finland_timeline.en.svg">restrictions amounted to a less-than-a-full lockdown</a> for two and a half months (mid-March to the end of May), then essentially almost no restrictions for summer, and for the autumn and winter a tiered set of restrictions which, in my home town (second biggest urban area in Finland), amounts to bar opening hours restricted, 10-person gathering limit, gyms and other such places closed and a mask recommendation in buses and shopping centers that is not enforced by law (I'd assume that about 2/3 of persons I generally seen on buses would be wearing a mask). Of course, Finland’s COVID situations has been one of the best in Europe, with current numbers showing 524 dead out of population of 5,5 million – 89 dead per million inhabitants, compared to America’s 971 per million or Sweden’s 785 per million.</p>
      <p>Throughout this process, the government and the parliament have considered the validity of whatever legislation from both <a href="https://yle.fi/uutiset/osasto/news/govt_lifts_state_of_emergency_in_finland_further_relaxing_coronavirus_restrictions/11402495">public health point of view</a> (ie. are the restrictions absolutely necessary for preventing rates going up, “Based on the epidemiological and legal assessments we received, it can be stated that the conditions no longer exist for the emergency measures to be in use.”), <a href="https://newsnowfinland.fi/finland-international/ministers-easing-travel-restrictions-paves-the-way-for-coronavirus-new-normal">economic point of view</a> and the <a href="https://yle.fi/uutiset/osasto/news/constitutional_committee_calls_for_changes_to_govts_restaurant_restriction_plans/11367751">constitutional point of view</a>. It has generally been the rule that ministers have been the foremost advocates in <a href="https://yle.fi/uutiset/osasto/news/education_minister_start_easing_restrictions_in_schools_first/11315040">ending restrictions in their own sector</a> first, which is the opposite of what you would expect if it was all about them grabbing power to their own ends.</p>
      <p>In almost all cases, the public pressure (as well as what the center-right and right-wing opposition parties have wanted) has been for more restrictions than what that the government has enacted. Of course, there are exceptions – people rarely want restrictions to be too onerous for themselves (such as bar owners opposing bar restrictions), but this has not translated to some large general anti-restrictions movement. Whatever such efforts there are have been the province of far-right and alt-medicine fringe figures.</p>
      <p>The more I think of it, the more whole idea of COVID restrictions as a government power grab just seems a libertarian cope – a way to avoid the fact that, in general, the populations have been far more likely and willing to demand the enactment and maintenance of authoritarian health measures than politicians have been willing to do so.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>