<post>
  <author>Syrrim</author>
  <date>2020-12-24T13:40:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/khcdwb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_21/ggwb87s/</link>
  <title>/u/Syrrim ponders the importance of myth in protecting and developing fragile psyches</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The argument would usually be to the effect that believing in fantasies is a nice thing, since fantasies are usually better than the real world. So as a service to children, we allow and even cause them to believe in certain particularly idealistic (if implausible) fantasies, under the assumption that this makes their life more enjoyable. </p>
      <p>As adults, we often do not reflect on, and sometimes purposefully ignore, the more horrible parts of the world. In part, we fail to ignore certain of these detestable portions because we cannot; our minds deny us the pleasure. The rest of our failure is a conscious decision, as we consider ourselves to have some responsibility to pay attention to these more horrifying aspects, in order that we might be an element in rectifying them. In either case, there is little reason to demand that children be given a complete education in these gory details, since they are still dumb enough to be able to ignore them, and are generally not considered morally responsible for making the world a better place. The natural conclusion is that if we can at all trick children into believing an even more beautiful and idealized version of the world, then of course we should.</p>
      <p>We might go even farther, and suppose children to have particularly weak constitutions and sensibilities. At which point, exposing them to the horrible parts of the world would be a quite terrible thing, because it might lead to a great deal of anguish which an adult would not suffer in the same situation. Furthermore, we can imagine instances where the santa claus myth hides one of these details liable to cause children anguish. Suppose there was a badly off family. Suppose the parents of this family went through a great deal of trouble - taking on second jobs and so on - to purchase worthy christmas gifts for their children. The children, who are capable of perceiving the considerable difficulty the family has making ends meet, might reasonably wonder where these gifts came from. To that end, an explanation is posed: a large man wearing a red suit flew around in his sleigh pulled by reindeer, alighted on the roof, dropped down the chimney, and delivered then below the tree. "Ah!," the child says, "I should have known." Thus, knowledge of the considerable pain their parents have undergone to their benefit is avoided.</p>
      <p>One supposes that a considerable fraction of families are in this group, and therefore presumptively benefited by the myth. Of course, a niggling question arises regarding what actual benefit it creates. Suppose we lived in a world without the santa claus myth. What would these parents do instead? Presumably, they would forgo presents at christmas, or give smaller gifts to their children instead. (Or, heaven forbid, come up with their own ridiculous folk myth to explain away lavish giving.) They are therefore, in effect, forced to give their children lavish gifts at christmas under threat of destroying their children's feeble constitutions. In this sense, we perceive the santa claus myth, if not to have been invented by, to have been heavily exaggerated and promoted by a consumerist hegemony in order to increase spending and production. Parents were/are threatened with insufficiency and with ruined children if they fail/ed to meet this standard.</p>
      <p>Compare, for example, the tradition of giving an expensive diamond ring as part of a marriage proposal; supposedly invented whole-cloth by the De Beers company, for the very purpose of driving demand for their diamonds. The nakedly consumerist aspect of this does little to reduce its pull in popular culture. Comparing the role of women in driving demand for diamonds, we might go as far as to suppose that children are "in" on the whole santa claus charade - they know in their heart-of-hearts that the whole myth is a ridiculous lie, yet suppress this knowledge in order to ensure they receive more presents. Finding out that santa claus isn't real is a terrible and traumatizing event, because this marks the end of the age where one can continue pretending to believe in him, and therefore marks a steady decline in the number and quality of presents to be received. </p>
      <p>Reflecting on this perspective, yet another view of the myth is generated: There are certain cases where a person will offer a gift to a child, but gate it behind the child performing some ridiculous action. They might ask the child to pull their finger, or to look for the gift which has been hidden, or to put on whatever other display necessary. A gift that the child will quite enjoy is relatively easy to acquire, since children are easy to please. The ridiculous action is easy for the child to give away as well, since children have no shame. And the parents (or whoever), revel in watching their children behave in interesting ways (indeed, this is the entire draw of the occupation of parenting). We might describe the santa claus myth as a case of this sort of interaction. The child is asked to believe in a man who lives at the north pole, and delivers a present to every child in the world on a single night (never mind that the vast majority of those children are unaware of this tradition). If the child manage to put on the requisite display, including posing for photos on the mall santa's lap and so on, then they will receive gifts in return. They are only too happy to comply.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>