<post>
  <author>Timthe7th</author>
  <date>2020-12-28T16:13:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kllo5n/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_28/ghaqtv7/</link>
  <title>/u/Timthe7th on the hypocrisy of locking down weddings, but not particular political protests</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>See, I’m on the right, but it looked like a huge threat to me since late January. I spent a couple of weeks then and in early February stocking up on food items. I (stupidly) listened to professional medical advice that masks don’t make a difference, and when I couldn’t find one, I just stopped looking. In early March, I got sick and responsibly quarantined myself just before the entire nation started locking down (I learned several months later that it was indeed Covid). I was fine with all of it and generally regarded myself as a responsible citizen. Most other right-wing people I knew were behaving the same way, ready to cooperate with what the experts were saying. </p>
      <p>A few things happened, though. You’re right about the China travel lockdown; I actually wanted Trump to go further, but at that early stage Democrats were saying it was no big deal and that the lockdown was racist, which was just incoherent to me (how do they know the motivation was race and not just good sense and, furthermore, how did it matter from a policy perspective?). </p>
      <p>When the lockdown protests started around early May, my first reaction was that they were irresponsible but it was their constitutional right. Over the next couple of weeks, though, I started learning that in many cases, the people protesting were from communities that had not been hit as hard and maybe didn’t need draconian measures. I thought this might be a talking point at least in the media, but instead, the protestors were just derided as idiots wanting a haircut by every major media organization. This made zero sense to me, and told me the press and media was once again simply lying and being disingenuous. They also stopped showing the press conferences, which I found informative. Then Fauci outright admitted the medical community lied about mask usage, which made me feel like a sucker for ever listening. It reminded me to use my own head, my own intuition, rather than just following advice and being led by the nose. </p>
      <p>Finally, I saw a few things happen in blue cities. One, Democrats started to argue that prisoners—even in some cases violent ones—should be set loose. Two, they started treating religious people, particularly the Jewish people in New York, especially harshly,<em>including threatening them with prison!</em>  Practicing a constitutional right to protest was out, now, even practicing your right to assemble for church was an act worthy of nothing but derision!  I had put off my own wedding, for good reason, due to this pandemic, but if we were setting criminals loose in blue cities, I saw no reason why religious people should then be arrested. </p>
      <p>Still, I encouraged cooperation. Still, I disagreed with e lockdown protestors. </p>
      <p>Then George Floyd happened and from where I’m sitting, the mask came off. Democratic politicians and media personalities and who had persecuted people practicing their first amendment right to worship were now marching arm-in-arm with protestors who were not practicing social distancing, who were screaming into megaphones. There was also a widely-attended funeral for George Floyd. And the greatest insult was doctors, nurses, and other medical professionals signing off on the protests, saying they concerned a greater health crisis than the pandemic. </p>
      <p>Why I should put off my wedding, why other people should have to avoid funerals for their own family members, and why people with deeply held beliefs should have their constitutional rights suspended, but for some reason these protestors, just because they agreed with some left-wing group, should be exempt, was completely beyond my understanding. I was immediately so indignant about this—it seemed like such a violation of basic morality, so shamelessly manipulative—that I dropped any concern about anyone following the rules. I still do, myself, because I have at-risk family members (and I may well adopt some of this more careful attitude around flu season every year, because it’s prudent and no skin off my back). But that is my own responsibility and concern, and if the people with the power to <em>suspend my constitutional rights</em>show any degree of favoritism, I no longer feel compelled to listen to anything they have to say. </p>
      <p>Post-Floyd, every ounce of left-wing indignation about mask wearing and lockdown protests and restrictions on freedom of religion looked like pure virtue signaling to me. Essentially, the requirement that you abide by the rules is bound entirely to ideology.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>