<post>
  <author>withmymindsheruns</author>
  <date>2020-12-28T03:23:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kjixaz/conspirituality_explains_why_the_wellness_world/gh95eql/</link>
  <title>/u/withmymindsheruns on signaling, status, and focus</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>They're both doing the same thing. Seeing a pattern, then extrapolating it into a very high level explanation for everything.</p>
      <p>A feature of both stories is that they allow you to dismiss the status signals from your social environment because the value hierarchy is corrupted. Furthermore, both stories tell you that the corruption of the social hierarchy actually generates that low-status signal for you in particular, irrespective of your behaviour. Which means that there is no practical method for advancement other than to tackle this corrupting influence.</p>
      <p>This is appealing if you're low status. </p>
      <p>The connection with New ageism is very good because it can be used to illustrate the problem, although I don't think the article manages to do it (although I admit I started skimming about 1/2 way through).</p>
      <p>The New Age community (in my experience with it) is already living within this dynamic . </p>
      <p>One basic premise of New Ageism is that they're playing a superior game that normies are too crass to recognise and so all the usual status signals that emerge out of mainstream society aren't applicable to them. Often new agers see themselves as <em>choosing</em> not to play, <em>I could if I wanted to</em> being the subtext. <em>I'm just as good as the neurosurgeon out sailing his yacht with his family, the fact that I'm unemployed, have no assets and don't have a stable partner is irrelevant because I'm not playing that game</em>.</p>
      <p>That's not to say that there isn't a basic truth in the new-ager's belief system, but that they are using it as a crutch. They aren't cultivating spirituality, they suffer intensely because they are unable to even reach the level where that is the important factor in furthering their development. They pretend that they are learning to fly before they can even crawl.</p>
      <p>There's a similar problem with the woke and the awakened (although I have to admit that I've had much less intimate contact with the woke, but they look the same from the outside). They're focused on the furthest point they can see rather than what is immediately at hand, they suffer and blame their suffering on that top level problem, and because all their concern with those top-level problems, they get to say that all the status signals coming from the low-level problems that they aren't addressing are irrelevant. But the social hierarchy isn't just a random configuration. Those status signals aren't all cunning manipulation (although in fairness some may be). A large part of what is being signaled is being shaped by millions of people trying to fulfill their needs. If you decide that the whole game is corrupt and all the signals are therefore false (which is functionally identical to the new-age idea of transcendence of mundane, materialist values) then your needs won't be met and your life probably won't be very good. </p>
      <p>So if your life is getting worse and worse, and you have this super high-level, abstracted explanation of why you are suffering, the more desperate you you are going to be to solve that problem. It's a vicious cycle of radical activism.</p>
      <p>So possibly it's a problem of the super-ordinate goal eclipsing all the subordinate ones. New agers are too focused on enlightenment, the woke on bigotry, and the awakened on elite parasitism. All seemingly legit things but focused on in a pathological way.</p>
      <p>And then there's a subsection of the activism which is 'awareness raising' which both tracks of the waked up really focus on. If we accept that there is a big motivation to chase status signals then 'awareness raising' could be seen as the project of building large scale buy in to a new value hierarchy which signals high status to the people doing that 'awareness raising', thus reifying that new status signal. And we can imagine how neatly social media with it's very overt signalling economy turbocharges the process.</p>
      <p>(as a disclaimer I want to say that I'm talking in generalisations about the pathological versions of these systems here. I'm not saying that every new ager/wokenista is just a failure trying to mask their shortcomings, or that this even comprehensively addresses the different ways that things like new ageism are a vehicle for negative personality traits to express themselves.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>