<post>
  <author>Artimaeus332</author>
  <date>2019-12-27T16:37:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eeg1xx/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_23/fc5s5mp/</link>
  <title>Liberal vs Progressive - Differing Political Strategies</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm happy to see a critic of anti-racism actually quote the prominent anti-racist scholars.People like Robin DiAngelo (whose entire career, as far as I can tell, is built upon popularizing the phrase "white fragility") are very easy to criticize, and I wish people took to it them more often.</p>
      <p>But here is how I imagine a debate on these subjects actually going:</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Liberal:</strong> I'm nervous about the increasingly authoritarian tendencies of anti-racism. As the baseline level of racism in society declines, anti-racist campaigns need to be more costly and disruptive to move the needle, and at some point, the cure becomes worse than the disease. Anti-racist activists routinely advocate a zero-tolerance, all-or-nothing, with-us-or-against-us mindset, and I have every reason to believe that they'll blow way past the point of diminishing returns (if we aren't past it already) into totalitarianism if they're ever given any real power.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Progressive:</strong>  Look, I know some activists go overboard, but their passion is motivated by the very real and very profound injustices that are ongoing in our society. We're currently nowhere near the point where anti-racism worse than racism, as evidenced by the fact that, in the US, the wealth of the median black household is something like 1/8th to 1/10th that of the median white household (need to look up that source), and that even the black people who are not themselves poor are much more likely to live in communities with high rates of poverty and accompanying social ills. This has barely changed since the 1960s. Fixing this is the ultimate goal of anti-racist activism. When we've made some progress, then you can start talking about diminishing returns of activist tactics.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Liberal:</strong> Sure, I agree that less wealth inequality is a meaningful long-term goal. But this is a challenging problem that's actually difficult to solve. It might not even be tractable to policy. But more to the point, why should I think that endlessly interrogating my whiteness and buying books by Robin DiAngelo, which is what progressive activists are mostly telling me to do, has any impact on the material conditions of black Americans?</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Progressive:</strong> It's important because it will make people more willing to support policy interventions because [reasons]</p>
      <p>I have a hard time continuing the discussion past this point, because it becomes a question of political strategy. Do you think, for example, that creating a cult of anti-racism among a segment of the upper-middle class is a good idea (because these people will be strong advocates for beneficial policies) or a bad idea (because the backlash from the normal people will empower white identitarians and anti-progressive demagogues).</p>
      <p>I'm not a political strategist, so I have no idea. The liberal might say that the cult is unnecessary because they already support policies that will reduce the wealth gap, provided that they are actually effective and can withstand some sort of cost-benefit analysis. The progressive may reply that mere support isn’t enough, and that without a passionate, committed base with very strong moral convictions, nothing ever actually gets done.</p>
      <p>A lot of the disagreements between the liberals and progressives hinges on the details of their theory about how activism influences policy.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>