<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2019-12-30T07:03:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ehhmq2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_30/fcjizb3/</link>
  <title>2019: Year in Review</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Several weeks ago, I posted my <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fbfyi3r/">"Winners and losers of the democrat primary December debate"</a>, which I found enjoyable and some people seem to have found useful, as not everyone has time to watch a 3 hour debate and might want a highlight reel.  So, I had some free time and was ruminating over some of the fun times we had this year, and I thought I'd do the same thing, but for the whole of 2019, because a lot happened.  Here are some of the highlights and lowlights of 2019:</p>
      <p>
        <strong>The men who ruined black history month, and the men who saved it</strong>
      </p>
      <p>During Black History month, Liam Neeson broke new ground by being perhaps the first person to get canceled for a hypothetical hate crime.  Liam Neeson, who may be best known for being the action star of the "Taken" films (which are basically dad revenge fantasies, a man attempts to track down the men who kidnapped his daughter), attempted to illustrate the dark and not-so-entertaining side of revenge by sharing a story from his past in which he harbored a revenge fantasy of hoping to beat down a black man after his friend was raped by a black man.  Clearly, for Liam Neeson to come forward with full contrition decades later and express his regret over having entertained violent fantasies is a cancel-worthy offense.</p>
      <p>Also on the subject of people getting canceled during Black History Month for hate crimes that did not actually occur, actor Jussie Smollett faked a hate crime, paying two men to act as assailants so that he could gain sympathy as a victim. Cardi B summed up everyone's thoughts on the matter, saying, "I'm really disappointed in Jussie Smollett, or whatever the fuck his name is...he fucked up Black History Month, bro."  Of course, individuals are flawed and always will be, so perhaps the real story here is about how the media (and plenty of politicians) credulously lapped up his story and pointed to it as clear evidence of America's problem with bigotry and the sad state of America during the Trump era, until the police discovered that Jussie Smollett was not very good at creating the facts to support his fake narrative.  Some might see this as a chance for reflection by the voices on the left who had credulously leapt to Smollett's defense, but according to Vanity Fair, the real story not to be missed here is about how republicans are always <a href="https://www.washingtonexaminer.com/opinion/republicans-pounce">pouncing</a>: "A rush to judgment was endemic on the left. <a href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/2019/02/why-the-right-wing-media-is-so-furious-about-the-jussie-smollett-affair">But the Smollett episode also exposes a complementary phenomenon on the right"</a>.</p>
      <p>There's probably a culture war argument to be had here, but the real moral of the Jussie Smollett story, according to the esteemed Charles Barkley, is this: "America...do not commit crimes with checks. C'mon, man. If you’re going to break the law, do not write a check."  Better yet, according to Barkley, Jussie could have achieved hate crime victimhood status without spending a dime: "Jussie, you wasted all that damn time and money! You know what you should've did? Just went out into Liam Neeson's neighborhood! Could've solved all your damn problems."  Charles Barley is a world-class entertainer and a text transcription cannot do justice to his fine delivery, so I implore you to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=D824ese7n-8">watch the video</a>, I am biased because Charles Barkley is one of my favorite people (and the video is only enhanced by Shaq's appearance), but it was definitely the highlight of black history month for me.  And while you're watching online videos of people providing their commentary on the Smollett story, check out <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H0xAGnVWv2I">Chris Rock's remarks from the 5th annual NAACP awards</a> (spoiler: he begins with the sentence, "They said no Jussie Smollett jokes," and he is Chris Rock, so you can probably predict what follows.)  Dave Chapelle also covered the Jussie Smollett incident in his special <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wZXoErL2124">Sticks and Stones</a>, though you might not find the jokes very funny as this special scored only 35% on Rotten Tomatoes (a bit higher than its 7% score the day of its release), it has a 99% audience score, but what do the unwashed masses know about what makes them laugh.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Teenage Greta getting some much-deserved recognition</strong>
      </p>
      <p>2019 was a good year for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greta_Van_Fleet">teens who go by the name Greta</a>, who won the 2019 Grammy Award for Best Rock Album.  From the Fires is an EP fully deserving of that award, give it a listen if you haven't already.</p>
      <p>On a complete unrelated note: The most disturbing trend of 2019 was people attacking 16-year-olds who get politically involved, particularly the people who couldn't criticize on substance and <a href="https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/xweabw/trolls-attacks-on-greta-thunbergs-appearance-are-sadly-predictable">chose instead to focus on the 16-year-old's appearance</a>.  Wait, no, I lied: actually, the most disturbing trend of 2019 is <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2019/01/19/us/teens-mock-native-elder-trnd/index.html">16-year-olds attending political rallies and then having the audacity to make the wrong facial expression when confronted by older men who are intimidating them with slurs/epithets and/or drumbeats</a>. Covington High School closed for the day amid threats following the "smiling teenager at a pro-life rally" incident, reopening the following day with police presence.  Still, not everyone was threatening the kids with physical violence: Kara Swisher of Recode/Vox believed that a lifetime cancelation would be sufficient punishment for the crime of smiling: <a href="https://twitter.com/karaswisher/status/1086733996988469254?lang=en">"I hope this follows these truly awful teens for the rest of their thus-far pathetic lives."</a></p>
      <p>Wait, no, I lied again, actually Kara Swisher is very sorry that she said these things.  To be clear, in her apology statement she makes it clear that her mistake that she reacted <a href="https://twitter.com/karaswisher/status/1087443815269584897?lang=en">"without waiting to see the whole video of the incident."</a>.  <em>Some</em> 16-year-olds might be deserving of lifetime cancelation for making the wrong face at a pro-life rally, but not <em>these</em> teens, says Kara Swisher!   What an incredible show of charity on her part. She also apologized for a tweet in the same thread where she said <a href="https://twitter.com/karaswisher/status/1087444442498433024">"go fuck yourself,"</a> because <a href="https://twitter.com/karaswisher/status/1087444442498433024">cursing: bad</a>. The problem with her response is that she gave it <em>before learning all of the facts</em> and <em>used offensive language when doing it</em>.  It's good to know that permaently un-personing teenagers for making faces at a pro-life rally is still on the table; we just have to save that punishment for the teenagers who <em>really</em> deserve it.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Biggest victim of seasonal affective disorder</strong>
      </p>
      <p>You know that feeling: toward the end of the year, when the stores start playing Christmas music and our hearts turn toward impeachment, sometimes you find yourself down in the dumps.  Pour one out for Nancy Pelosi, whose life seems devoid of joy during this holiday season.  "This is a very sad time for our country," she said in <a href="https://www.msnbc.com/morning-joe/watch/speaker-pelosi-impeachment-is-no-cause-for-any-joy-this-is-a-sad-time-for-our-country-70066757846">September</a>.  <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/sad-day-pelosi-house-votes-trump-impeachment-probe/story?id=66663715">"It's a sad day,"</a>, she said in October.  In November, she said that going toe-to-toe was <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/transcript-house-speaker-nancy-pelosi-on-face-the-nation-november-17-2019/">"sad, you know."</a>  And on the last day of work before taking off for Christmas after impeachment, she chided cheering democrats, telling them that it was <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2019/dec/18/pelosi-applause-impeachment-vote-democrats">"a sad day."</a></p>
      <p>Poor gal.  In 2020, I just want one thing: to see Nancy smile.</p>
      <p>[Reddit character limit reached, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ehhmq2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_30/fcjj0rg/">2019 recap continued in part 2</a>]</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>