<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2019-12-23T01:36:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fbt0e19/</link>
  <title>Yang Vs Beto: How a Message/Signal Changes Depending on the Speaker</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Now as far as I can tell, none of Yang’s policy positions are conservative, and of late he’s given lip service to leftwing idpol as well, albeit without using the standard vocabulary. (He said men become “morons” without women in the latest debate.) He wants to ban assault weapons, make gender identity a protected trait, legalize marijuana, provide a pathway to citizenship, etc. etc. His centerpiece UBI plan may be the largest increase in taxes and federal spending ever proposed, and yet you find supposed libertarians and fiscal conservatives saying they have been converted by Andrew Yang.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'm reminded of Scott's remarks about how Trump is an expert on tribal signaling:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Your role model in this (and in nothing else) Donald Trump. Think about it. He supports Planned Parenthood, doesn’t want to cut entitlement programs, condemns Dubya and the Iraq war, supports affirmative action, supports medical marijuana, etc. If somebody were to tell you last year that a man with those policy positions would not only be leading the Republican primary, but leading even among the most conservative voters, you’d think they were crazy. The rest of the country has been trying to convince conservative Republicans to be more comfortable with those positions for decades, and we’ve failed miserably. Now Trump just waltzes in and everyone is like “Yeah, okay, sure”?</p>
        <p>The secret of Trump’s success is that most conservative Republicans don’t really care about medical marijuana (or whatever) for its own sake. They care because opposing medical marijuana symbolizes membership in their tribe, they feel like their tribe is persecuted, they have a fierce loyalty to their tribe, and darned if they’re going to support somebody who doesn’t use the right shibboleths.</p>
        <p>Trump throws them a bone. He says things like “illegal immigrants are rapists” that no moderate or liberal would ever say, things that would horrify them. He uses all the affectations of being working class. He may not quite prove he’s “one of us”, but he very effectively proves he’s not Just A Typical Outgroup Member. When Trump says “Legalize medical marijuana”, they don’t hear “I’m yet another RINO liberal pansy who hates Christian values and wants everybody to become reefer-smoking hippies”. So they only hear something boring about the regulations around pain relief medication – and who cares about those?</p>
        <p>Trump’s Law is that if you want to convince people notorious for being unconvinceable, half the battle is using the right tribal signals to sound like you’re one of them.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>When Beto says "we need to provide a pathway to citizenship," conservatives hear "<a href="https://www.azcentral.com/story/opinion/op-ed/2019/10/15/beto-orourke-immigration-open-borders-hurts-angel-moms-like-me/3986552002/">he's one of those crazy nutjobs who opposes deporting illegal immigrants who have committed violent crimes</a>."  When Yang says "we need to provide a pathway to citizenship," conservatives hear, "we should allow the <em>good</em> immigrants to stay.  You know, the ones who are going to be productive, law-abiding citizens who learn to speak English and behave like proper Americans"  They are probably not wrong for thinking this, because Yang implies exactly that when he says things like "<a href="https://www.scmp.com/news/china/diplomacy/article/2163756/us-needs-more-immigrants-says-presidential-hopeful-andrew-yang">I would staple a green card to the diploma of any international student who graduates from an American university</a>," which is quite a bit different from what Beto seems to imply when he stands on the debate stage and says on national television on front of millions of viewers, "<a href="https://www.lataco.com/ranking-the-spanish-of-the-2020-candidates/">Necesitamos incluir a cada persona en el éxito de esta economía</a>."</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Is this a blatant textbook example of tribalism over substance?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>What do you mean by "tribalism over substance?"  When Beto speaks in Spanish on the debate stage, that's tribal signaling, but it also tells me substantive things about him, like: the fact that he seems to care more about serving the interests Mexican immigrants than, say, Chinese or Indian immigrants, and the fact that Beto is more likely to be in favor of things like, say, removing the English requirement from the citizenship test.  Those seem like very substantive things to vote on: most conservatives would probably not support a presidential candidate who believed that English fluency should be optional for US citizens, but would be willing to support Yang's plan to give green cards to international students who graduate from American universities.  That doesn't make them hypocrites, because even though both candidates claim to be "pro-immigration," you're making judgments about two very different things when you say "I like Yang but don't like Beto."</p>
      <p>You look at Yang in shock and say, "How could conservatives like him?  He's in favor of legalizing marijuana!"  Perhaps it is not marijuana that conservatives dislike, but stoners and potheads, in the same way that most conservatives are not fans of  drunkards and bar flies: just so long as you can keep the idea of alcohol divorced from the drunkard identity, conservatives will be fine with cracking open a beer after a long day of working in the sun, toasting at weddings, and maybe even having a little too much to drink on special occasions like New Year's Eve.  Likewise, if you can divorce the term "queer" from the idea of "deviant," an increasingly large number of conservatives will be perfectly content to welcome a gay couple who pays the property taxes on their suburban home, goes to church on Sundays, attends PTA meetings, and shakes their head in disgust when they see hedonistic displays at the Pride parade.  After all, why should a conservative have a problem with Peter Thiel's sexuality?  They agree with Peter Thiel on all of the important things!  And yet, when someone puts pronouns in their bio, a republican might react by saying, "Oh, this person has <em>very</em> different values and policy goals from me," <em>even if that person is a straight cis person</em>, and they will probably be right!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>