<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2019-12-20T07:10:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fbfyi3r/</link>
  <title>Humorous Thoughts on the WInners and Losers of Democratic Debates</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Winners and losers of tonight's debate:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>This debate's biggest loser: wine caves.  Warren says "Billionaires in wine caves should not pick the next president of the United States."  Klobuchar says "I have never even been to a wine cave."  Yang pitches his 'democracy dollars' plan by saying "you'd have many, many more women who would run for office because they don't have to go shake the money tree in the wine cave."  All of this is upsetting to California's democratic governor Gavin Newsom, whose multimillion-dolar business enterprise includes many California wineries.  Said Newsom of California's wine industry, "Having a wine cave --  it's my business. It's how I started. It's a point of pride, it’s one of America’s great exports...I don't know that it's helpful to have those kinds of debates."</li>
        <li>Previously, I noted in that in October's debate it seemed that the stage had shifted from treating Warren as the frontrunner to Buttigieg as the frontrunner.  Tonight, Warren went after Buttigieg.  Buttigieg looked like a young, innocent schoolboy; Warren looked like the sort of stern old lady who makes it her business to antagonize young innocent schoolboys.  I'm not sure if Buttigieg won that argument, but Warren definitely lost, and I think the results in Iowa and New Hampshire will bear that out.  (Warren polls 4th in New Hamphire and 3rd in Iowa; Buttigieg is polling at number one in both.)  My bold prediction: Warren loses two those two states and with that seals her fate as her trajectory from here certainly doesn't seem to be going upward.</li>
        <li>Elizabeth Warren defended herself against attacks on her age by noting that if elected, she would be the youngest woman ever nominated.  That reminds me of the time 4 years ago when Hillary Clinton said, "<a href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/video/2015/06/15/hillary_i_may_not_be_the_youngest_candidate_in_this_race_but_i_will_be_the_youngest_woman_president.html">I may not be the youngest candidate in this race, but I will be the youngest woman president.</a>"  It's easy to see why Warren would want to copy Clinton's homework, considering that Clinton seems to know so much about appealing to voters and winning elections.  Winner: whoever it was that won the previous presidential election.</li>
        <li>Pete reminding us that he has the lowest net worth of anyone on stage, which probably says more about the fact that he's 37 years old than anything else.  (What was Biden/Sanders/Warren's net worth when they were Pete's age?)  Winner: boomers with home equity and 401k's.</li>
        <li>Tom Steyer wanted to take credit for impeachment, noting that he started the impeachment movement two years ago, before Trump did any of the things he's currently being impeached for.  A good appeal for a Steyer presidency, if you're a big fan of having a president who says "show me the man and I'll show you the crime."  Winner: Lavrentiy Beria</li>
        <li>According to Biden, "the middle class is getting killed."  He later updated his remark to say that "the middle class is getting crushed."  And to further add insult to injury, we also found out that "the middle class is not behind the eight ball."  Warren suggests that the middle class are not only getting killed and crushed and bested at the pool table, but also disemboweled.  ("America's middle class is being hollowed out.")  What is going on with America's incredible shrinking middle class?  <a href="https://www.cato.org/blog/middle-class-shrinking-households-become-richer">According to Cato, the middle class is "shrinking" as many middle class households have been moving up and now making too much money to be considered middle class</a>.  Winner: all of the ascendant households that are getting kicked out of the "middle class" club.</li>
        <li>Most uncomfortable moment of the night: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SX_iAYlIkDk">Joe Biden imitated a stammering child</a>, leaving us unsure of whether he was having a stroke or trying to mimic a stammering child's speech.  Said Biden: "My wife and I have a call list of somewhere between 20 and 100 people that we call at least every week or every month to tell them, I'm here. I give them my private phone number. They keep in touch with me. The little kid who says, I-I-I-I-I-I-I-I can't talk, w-w-w-hat do I do?"  I honestly couldn't believe it was happening when I watched it.</li>
        <li>Runner up for most uncomfortable moment of the night: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fGuZhF_SO_M&amp;t=28s">Yang left speechless</a> when the final debate question of the night required him to get in the holiday spirit and tell the other candidates what gift he would give them.  Saved from winning "most awkward moment of the night" only by Andrew's unflappable affability.  After a few moments of stunned silence, Yang answered that he'd give all of them a copy of his book, which is full of data.  Loser: all of the gift recipients who will be disappointed on Christmas morning when they unwrap their gift from Yang to discover a book instead of a $1000 check.  Winner: Buttigieg, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fGuZhF_SO_M&amp;t=1m44s">who is a big fan of both data and books</a>, and absolutely "excited" at the prospect of getting to read Yang's book.</li>
        <li>Last week, Noah Rothman published in Commentary Magazine (a Jewish neoconservative publication) that <a href="https://www.commentarymagazine.com/politics-ideas/liberals-democrats/bernie-sanders-has-a-big-jeremy-corbyn-problem/">Bernie Sanders' camp, like Jeremy Corbyn's, has an anti-semitism problem</a>.  Earlier this month, old tweets were uncovered from Bernie Sanders' newly hired deputy director of constituency organizer Darius Khalil Gordon which made references to <a href="https://freebeacon.com/politics/new-bernie-sanders-hires-tweets-include-homophobic-slurs-references-to-jew-money/">"jew money"</a>.  (Gordon was fired after these tweets came to light, though the Sanders campaign declined to comment on the reason behind the firing.)  Of course, the assertion that Bernie Sanders' campaign has an anti-semitism problem seems pretty odd considering that Sanders himself is Jewish, and at tonight he laid to rest all fears that he might be a secret anti-Semite by proudly embracing his heritage in a moment when he loudly declared, completely unprompted and in response to a question that had nothing to do with race, <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/video/sanders-brushes-off-age-m-024727960.html">"I am white."</a>  He was so enthusiastic to get that out that <a href="https://twitter.com/sarahedolan/status/1207847387752009728">he interrupted the moderator to say it</a>.  You might think that I am unfairly divorcing his comment from its context to make it look weird, but I swear that even with context it was the weirdest thing I saw all night.</li>
        <li>Underrated sleeper pick: Amy Klobuchar.  It's hard to point to a specific moment in the night, but throughout the night I got the impression that she was the lone remaining adult in the room, and that seemed good on a night that was chaotic thanks to debate moderators who let the candidates trample all over the moderators and a few moments that actually descended into shouting matches.  (There was one moment when the moderator tried to cut Buttigieg off with a "thank you..." and he just steamrolled her no fewer than <em>four times</em> for a single monologue of an answer.)</li>
        <li>Sanders says: "Amazon and other major corporations pay zero in federal taxes."  Wow, I wonder if Amazon somehow figured out how to avoid paying any federal payroll taxes, or if this is a case of a politician getting away with repeating a blatant falsehood that nobody in the media is ever going to call them on for some reason.  It's not just politicians who say that Amazon pays no federal taxes: <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2019/06/18/politics/fact-check-aoc-amazon-wages-bezos/index.html">according to CNN, "Amazon paid zero federal taxes in 2017 and 2018."</a> CNN is clearly a reputable media organization that doesn't lie, so maybe I'm just a stupid ignoramus and federal payroll taxes are just a made-up thing that only exist in my head.  (Or maybe this is what Yang was talking about tonight when he said, "Americans don't trust the media networks to tell them the truth.")  Loser: me, who clearly picked the wrong hill to die on.</li>
      </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>