<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2019-12-25T01:25:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eeg1xx/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_23/fbz72xg/</link>
  <title>Richard Jewell - Orphan of the Culture War</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Awhile back there was a discussion about "orphans of the culture war," causes that aren't clearly aligned with one side of the culture war, and thus wind up in the unfortunate position of having no defenders when they fall under fire.</p>
      <p>One such victim may be Richard Jewell.  (The film, not the man.)</p>
      <p>For those unfamiliar with Richard Jewell (the man, not the film), in 1996, a bombing attack at the Summer Olympics in Atlanta Georgia was discovered by a security guard named Richard Jewell who called for an immediate evacuation of the area. One person was killed (the evacuation was not completed by the time the bomb went off), but Richard Jewell's discovery is believed to have saved hundreds of lives.</p>
      <p>The bombing was the first of four bombings by Eric Rudolph, and being that it was the first, Eric Rudolph (a terrorist who lived off the grid) was not yet a person of interest and not on the FBI radar; the only suspect that the FBI had for the first bombing was Richard Jewell, suspected because he was the one who discovered the bomb.  This information was leaked to Kathy Scruggs (a pioneer of clickbait journalism in an era before the web), who wrote a story for the Atlanta Journal-Constitution with the title, "FBI suspects 'hero' guard may have planted bomb," which led to Richard Jewell becoming a villain in the public eye, despite the fact that he was a hero whose only "crime" was being the only person of interest that the FBI had.</p>
      <p>Richard Jewell (the movie, not the man) is Clint Eastwood's attempt to set the record straight and tell the story of how a national hero was wronged by the media and the law enforcement who leaked to them.  It debuted earlier this month to a box office open of $4.7 million, a "flop" by pretty much any measure.</p>
      <p>Richard Jewell is a story about journalism, and about how you can tell a misleading story or paint an inaccurate picture while still accurately reporting the facts.  So, with that in mind, here are three facts:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Clint Eastwood is a republican (you might remember his <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/morning-mix/wp/2016/08/04/clint-eastwood-explains-and-regrets-his-speech-to-an-empty-chair/">nonsensical, rambling speech at the 2012 Republican National Convention</a> where lectured an empty chair which served as an efigy for the incumbant Obama), and his movies have a right-wing viewpoint to roughly the same degree that 80% of movies and TV sitcoms have a left-wing viewpoint.</li>
        <li>The "villains" in Richard Jewell are the media (who attacked a hero and turned him into a villain), and the FBI (who handled the investigation unethically)</li>
        <li>You might note that there are many republicans who believe that Trump is a hero who has been turned into a villain by the media and treated unfairly by an FBI investigation</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Viewing these three facts, the bluechecks were quick to <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/movies/story/2019-12-10/richard-jewell-ajc-lawsuit-reporter">rally the troops</a>: clearly, this film was conservative propaganda attempting to smear the sacred institutions of the media and the FBI, all in the name of defending Trump.  Most notably, the media was concerned with the fact that Kathy Scruggs (the reporter who broke the story) was treated unfairly: the film portrays her as someone who is disliked by her coworkers (which was true, by all accounts), someone who was more obsessed with her own career than reporting the facts or telling an accurate story (which also seems to be accurate), but more critically, "she slept with a source."  The Atlanta Journal Constitution <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2019/dec/10/atlanta-newspaper-ajc-sues-clint-eastwood-olivia-wilde-reporter-richard-jewell-film">threatened a lawsuit</a>.  They hired lawyer <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/22/business/22singer.html">Martin Singer</a>, who makes his money by menacing the media, protecting his clients from reporters, which you might find a certain amount of irony in.</p>
      <p>From this, you might surmise that the film is about a female journalist who slept with a source in order to obtain information.  (That is the narrative being told by the mainstream media).  If you watch the film, you might note that 1) the source wanted to leak the information even before Scruggs showed up, 2) the whole sex thing happened only after the information was exchanged.  In fact, it almost seems like the "cause and effect" chain implied by the reporting in this movie is actually the reverse: one plausible reading of the film is that Jon Hamm's character was interested in having sex with Scruggs because she was willing to publish the information, not that he was willing to leak information because she offered him sex.</p>
      <p>I'd also say that the movie has a lot more to say about institutional failure than the actions of specific individuals, but like most movies, it tends to use people as totems for institutions, because it's easy to portray humans in a movie and hard to portray abstract things like institutions, and having a reporter and an FBI physically entangled is a great way to use the language of cinema to portray the idea that the media was literally in bed with the FBI.  (It's the same reason that in Avatar, the main villains are "evil corporate bad guys" and "the military," but we get Colonel Quaritch who serves as an avatar for the military, and administrator Selfridge who serves as an avatar for corporate interests.  Yes, Quaritch may be a xenophobe who wants to trample all over the natives, and Selfridge may be greedy, but we're meant to understood that these are characteristics that Cameron wants to ascribe to the military/corporate interests on an institutional level; it's not as if the conflict in Avatar would be suddenly resolved if both of these characters were killed.)</p>
      <p>It's interesting (but not surprising) to see so many bluechecks insisting that Eastwood's portrayal of Scruggs is unethical.  I wonder if there was a similar level of handwringing over the scene in The Social Network where Mark Zuckerberg is shown having sex in a bathroom.  Certainly, Zuckerberg stood to suffer more damage from this depiction, given that he was (and is) still alive, while Scruggs is not.  (Is Clint Eastwood being hypocritical in attacking the media for telling an inaccurate story by telling a story in a way that plays fast-and-loose with the facts?  I don't know, is there a difference in the purpose of movies which people pay $10 to see on a Saturday night and a story that appears in the local newspaper?)</p>
      <p>If anything, I think that the movie's portrayal of Kathy Scruggs is incredibly charitable: a more accurate portrayal would have made her appear far more villainous and self-serving than what we see in the movie, where she is conflicted over whether it's worth it to damage her subject to advance her career.  That, I think, may be the problem.  Richard Jewell (the movie, not the man) had a $4.7 million opening, a dismal performance for a Clint Eastwood movie with an estimated budget of $45 million.  The movie is not the "pro-Trump" anthem that the media seems to think it is.  It approaches it with all of the subtlety and nuance demanded of its subject matter. It treats its "villains" with far more charity than they deserve, and it treats its hero as a flawed individual.</p>
      <p>Richard Jewell's story is one of a man who was worshipful of authority who believed in the inherent goodness of law enforcement and waived his rights because he believed that the FBI's investigation would exonerate him and the truth was the only defense he needed.  This man's blind faith in law enforcement was his undoing.  And we're sort of led to believe that only a schlubby loser like Richard Jewell who lives with his mom and is incredibly awkward and uncharismatic could believe in the inherent goodness of law enforcement.  He's a hero for his actions, but unlikely to be anyone's role model.  Nobody wants to be like Richard Jewell. That's what we see in the film, and that a message that you'd think would be a bigger hit with blue tribers.  Certainly, it's not the kind of thing that red tribers would consider a "rah rah, go us" anthem.</p>
      <p>As much as Richard Jewell was dragged by the left-wing media, it never became a story for right-wing media.  Fox News had basically zero reporting of it.  It was a villain for the left, but not a hero for the right.  Could this explain why it was such a flop at the box office?  Certainly, a movie like Richard Jewell is a hard sell to begin with, but the media controversy did more to hurt it than to help it.  Richard Jewell was far too nuanced to be a film that you could watch to "own the libs."  (Compare to Joker, a movie which was maligned by the left-wing media but has obvious appeal to a comic book nerd fanboy, or whatever you want to call the demographic that the media likes to castigate for harassing Kelly Marie Tran.  Yes, Joker was nuanced and morally ambiguous, but buying a ticket to see it is clearly something you can do to "own the libs" while I don't think the same can be said of Jewell.)</p>
      <p>To me, the biggest story to take away from this is that Richard Jewell is a film about how a man was treated unfairly by the media, and the media managed to turn it into a story about how the <em>media</em> is being treated unfairly.  (Yes, a man who should have been a national hero had his reputation and career destroyed because of a newspaper story, but the journalists are the real victims here!)  It's easy to see the incentives for this, as victimhood is the highest status that one can claim. In this, I hear echoes of the constant drumbeat that has been playing ever since the first time I was told that Trump's attacks on the media were the greatest possible threat to our democracy.  One would think that if journalism was such a linchpin of our democracy, it would be a good idea to hold journalistic institutions accountable every now and then to make sure that they were doing their job properly.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>