<post>
  <author>greatjasoni</author>
  <date>2019-12-20T15:19:29Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fbgoxjg/</link>
  <title>Stereotypes, Ideal Stereotypes, and Treating Everyone as Individuals</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>You can acknowledge that sterotypes tend to be true in the aggregate while also not thinking that people need special treatment based off of them. This is predicated on people having inherent worth as human beings.</p>
      <p>I was thinking about this yesterday. I saw Trans-Siberian Orchestra many years ago and they interrupted the cool music to have a guy dressed up as a homeless man give an eloquent speech about the spirit of Christmas for 45 minutes. It was very moving I'm told but I didn't appreciate it at the time. That homeless man is an ideal. The gentle honest man who is just down on their luck and deserves your charity in the spirit of <a href="https://youtu.be/hox8RW408iM">Christ.</a> It teaches us not to judge off appearances and to be more open and tolerant. Through poverty his spirit has been made in the image of God.</p>
      <p>But that's not how homeless people actually are at all. I'm sure some of them are like that man. Largely it's criminally insane drug addicts who are far less likely to be a good person than a well adjusted normie working a cushy do-nothing job. They simply wouldn't be in that situation without some kind of massive personal issues, often chosen. Chosing to have them around your family is both dangerous and immoral. They'll likely spend any money you give them on drugs and be mad you didn't give them more.</p>
      <p>Does realizing that, and having statistics and numerous anecdotes to back it up, mean that they aren't worthy of a Christian compassion? No. Obviously they deserve charity and the same basic human dignity as everyone else. That they are in such awful material conditions is undeserved, regardless of what they did, and the moral thing to do is to take them into your home and give them pork, at the table with the rest of your family. That's the message of Christmas. Jesus hangs out with the worst of sinners, not because they're somehow just as moral as everyone else, they're the worst sinners! They have inherent worth as human beings.</p>
      <p>This is a somewhat reductive take on the story but the contradictory memes you're dealing with have religious roots anyways. It rests on an irrational metaphysical principle that all people are equal in a supernatural sense. This principle has no material basis because people aren't equal on any material level whatsoever. Pick literally any attribute and we all vary on some kind of hierarchy. The religious idea is to go beyond the hierarchy, not that the hierarchy doesn't exist. Christ shows that the hierarchy is utterly meaningless, revealing himself to be God by dying a humiliated tortured slave, the lowest position. Christians wave the cross around ironically; the torture device that killed their savior becomes mocking proof that the material world has no power over them. The left here seems to want to correct the hierarchy until it resembles the ideal, while the right thinks the ideal is divorced from the hierarchy. Both can be accused by the other of not believing in equality, but the two aren't really supposed to contradict. One way of putting it (in an overly poetic and unsubstantial manner) is that the left doesn't believe in the resurrection and the right doesn't believe in the crucifixion.</p>
      <p>You have to look truth in the face, have your naive presuppositions shattered, then do the right thing anyways. The very geometry of the cross symbolically represents this by intersecting heaven and earth, but so does the contradiction of the incarnation (God/man), virgin birth, death and resurrection, king born in a feeding trough for pigs, etc. The whole narrative is a wrestling with these contradictions. I'm not sure of a better language to approach equality from since it's not a rational concept. Merry Christmas.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>