<post>
  <author>j9461701</author>
  <date>2019-12-23T11:55:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ee931u/quality_contribution_roundup_for_the_weeks_of/fbty9vp/</link>
  <title>On Artillery</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <a href="/u/funobtainium">/u/funobtainium</a>
 on: A first hand account of paralysis</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>That whole thread is some of the most depressing stuff I've ever read. I desperately feel the urge to go into medical research, just so I can contribute in some small way to alleviating that kind of abject suffering. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Apologia for the Ruinous Powers - Even Space Marines Need Artillery</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I actually forgot to mention Marine artillery in this post. They rely on the <a href="https://warhammer40k.fandom.com/wiki/Whirlwind">Whirlwind</a>, which is intended to even the odds somewhat when the marines face overwhelming hordes or are about to assault heavily entrenched positions. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <a href="/u/KulakRevolt">/u/KulakRevolt</a>
 on: What We don't Teach</p>
        <p>A-lot of people found this argument un-compelling but I was actually reading a work at the time about a school in which the reverse was true: HPMOR.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Wait, why HPMOR specifically? This is also true for regular Harry Potter. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>So why don’t our education systems actually teach those skills? And why does it seem like they used to?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'm surprised no one mentioned this, but hard skills tend to be temporary and useful only in a narrow range. Soft skills are longer lasting and more broadly applicable. Knowing how to 3D print isn't really useful to anyone, and the specific techniques and principles involved may all be invalidated in 10 years time. Meanwhile learning the basics of food webs is something that, more likely than not, will always be true and will pay many small dividends over the student's life time. Focusing on soft skills gives students a bedrock of generalized knowledge they can build on to pursue other things, that suit their own personal interests and situation. </p>
      <p>I remember <em>despising</em> every last minute of shop class, while you seem to have wanted more of it - a good compromise then is we spend our mandatory in-school time learning generic knowledge, and then after school we go pursue our own hard skills on our own without forcing the other person to get involved. </p>
      <p>But this really ties into the fact that pre-university schooling isn't about education, but mostly about being big daycares. So the fact that the logical thing to do would be mostly scrap the one-size-fits-all 5 day a week current system in favor of more individualized programs is largely ignored. </p>
      <p>Responding to <a href="/u/barkappara">/u/barkappara</a>'s <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/e4u7a6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_02/f9j512p/">comment</a>:</p>
      <p>
        <em>Small arms, specifically massed rifle fire, had been the greatest killer in
previous wars. In the Franco-Prussian War, 91.6 percent of casualties among
German soldiers were caused by infantry rifle fire, and only 8.4 percent by
artillery. This ratio changed drastically in the Great War, despite the introduction
of the machine gun. According to autopsy reports, 58.3 percent of deaths were caused by artillery, and 41.7 percent by small arms.</em>
      </p>
      <p>-Whalen, Bitter Wounds</p>
      <p>Estimates from the Civil War indicate similar percentage of casualties attributable to artillery as happened during the Franco-Prussian war, if slightly higher in some specific battles. But the primary killer of infantry was other infantry, going back centuries. Indeed, in a 1762 survey of admission causes to the Invalide in Paris swords accounted for more wounds than artillery (Christopher Duffy, The Military Experience in the Age of Reason). </p>
      <p>I think people don't quite appreciate just how novel WW1 artillery was. Let's first look at some modern artillery:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aAd5SO22ivo">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aAd5SO22ivo</a>
      </p>
      <p>Now let's look at some Civil War artillery:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2BJ6ZhUVcMo">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2BJ6ZhUVcMo</a>
      </p>
      <p>A lot changed in between those two, so let's go down the list and name some of the most important ones:</p>
      <p>First, breech-loading. The first breech-loading cannon debuted in the 1830s, but it was expensive and dangerous to operate. Improvements came in the 1850s and 60s, until it completely replaced muzzle loading. Breech loading greatly increases the speed at which the artillery piece can be fired, with trained crews able to output truly staggering firepower - on the order of 20 rounds a minute!</p>
      <p>Rifling. Most cannons at the start of the civil war were smooth bore, which is to say the inside of the barrel was smooth and had no rifle grooves. The industrial capacity to mass produce rifled cannons was just starting to come online as the conflict began however, and we would see both sides scramble to rifle their own artillery during the conflict. This process would've gone far faster if Army Ordnance had not been of the opinion rifled artillery were an expensive indulgence.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dyiCHI87KHQ">Hydraulics</a>. Civil War cannons, as you may have noticed, fly backward on their wheels each time they're fired. This makes consistent shot to shot accuracy nearly impossible, and the idea of "walking" your fire onto the target almost impossible. The gun is 5 feet back from where it started after you shoot, let alone your sights still being lined up as they were before. The introduction of a hydro-pneumatic recoil compensation system changed this, and allowed every shot to land just precisely where the precious shot had gone. Only the barrel moves on a modern artillery piece, recoiling back and then returning exactly where it was prior to being shot. Nothing else moves, not the gun carriage, or the sights, or anything that might throw off aim. </p>
      <p>Precision-timed shells. In the Civil War version they had a hollow metal ball full of blackpowder, and the fuze was a piece of cord cut to a certain length. X length of cord means the shell explodes Y seconds after it leaves the barrel.  This was hopelessly imprecise, as you can imagine, given the vagaries of burn rates a piece of cord might have on a hectic battlefield. But technology, as it often does, improved. The crude cord-length-fuze was replaced by contact fuzes and wonderfully steampunk <a href="https://qph.fs.quoracdn.net/main-qimg-addb8c9bba16c11ca20f10f52c92819c.webp">clockwork fuzes</a>, which allowed trained crews vastly more precision in where and how their shells detonating. With access to the proper charts (more on this later), they could even get their shells to detonate just before hitting the ground - and thus inflict maximum causalities. </p>
      <p>High explosive shells. The above Civil War explosive shell had a 2nd large flaw: Its explosive charge was black powder. Black powder is not a high explosive, and so when you set it off in has a tendency to rip the shell casing into large pieces. This may sound great, but it's actually kind of terrible. A shell that explodes into 5 huge chunks can kill only 5 enemy soldiers, barring some <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M6PbdJiAK84">sick collaterals</a>. By contrast, a shell that explodes into 500 chunks can potentially kill 500 enemy soldiers. The invention of modern high explosives, which have the detonation speed to shatter steel into thousands of pieces, solves this problem and dramatically increases the killing power of explosive shells. The M107 shell, for example, explodes into something like 2000 fragments on average.</p>
      <p>The gun-howitzer. In the Civil War, the two most common types of artillery were guns and howitzers. Howitzers had short barrels, fired indirectly and had low muzzle velocities. Guns, by contrast, had long barrels, high muzzle velocities, and fired directly. But going into the 20th century the two types had begun to undergo <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6OWq38TikzU">fusion</a>, producing the weird wacky wonderful hybrid the gun-howitzer. This was an artillery piece that combined elements of both types, having high muzzle velocities, long barrels, and usually employed in an indirect fire capacity. The combination of high muzzle velocities and indirect fire allowed artillery to achieve truly absurd range - 10km was perfectly normal for standard heavy artillery by mid-WW1. By contrast 1.5 km was extreme range for a Civil War artillery piece.</p>
      <p>Smokeless powder. Reloading a Civil War cannon is a messy, involved process. One of the key reasons is black powder is a very messy substance, that does not burn cleanly. You need <a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/01/VAFO929worm_exb.jpg">a worm boi</a> to clean out the gunk that inevitably starts building up. Black powder is also less powerful, giving you less bang for your buck. Smokeless powder solves both of these problems, being clean burning and much more powerful. This simplifies the reloading process considerably, and almost lets you fire the cannon as fast as you can cram fresh propellant and shell into the breech. </p>
      <p>Telecommunications. One of the key problems with indirect fire of artillery is you don't know where you're hitting until someone who saw the shell splash down runs back to your position and tells you. This was a slow, error prone process, as you might expect. Enter telephones and radios. Now the gun crews can directly talk to someone sitting 11 km away from them, and get active feedback. The gun crew can correct their aim with up to the second information, and even 'walk' their fire toward targets called out by forward observers. </p>
      <p>Finally, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HBsdV--kLoQ#t=1m21s"><em>science</em></a>. Scientific precision! Due to all the above improvements, it was now possible for the army to go out, fire a bunch of shells on one of their guns, and compile charts that detailed all the relevant statistics the crews for that particular artillery piece would need. These charts were remarkably accurate, as contrasted against their Civil War forebearers that tended to be a bit questionable. America was especially notable for their skill in this avenue, having some of the scariest artillery in the world in WW2.  Bloody yanks and their love of guns :/</p>
      <p>
        <strong>CONTINUED BELOW</strong>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>