<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2019-12-22T03:21:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fbmjx8x/</link>
  <title>Tales From the ~~Gas Station~~ Grocery Store - Who Get's The Boot</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Couple days ago I had me an experience that has deepened my general resentment against modern society and left a bad taste in my mouth twice over. I’ve been chewing on it since, and I think I’ve digested it enough to spew out words on the subject.</p>
      <p>I’m currently working security at a grocery store while doing college. It’s chill post. Mostly I tell beggars to fuck off, try to discourage shoplifters without getting sued, and generally keep the store’s insurance premium acceptably low by wearing a cheap uniform while possessing a pulse.</p>
      <p>It was early in the morning. Not many people had shown up. I saw a homeless dude wedged in the corner of the parking lot all wrapped up in blankets, struggling to keep all his body covered up and snug. It’s Southern California, so it isn’t, like, <em>freezing</em> or anything. But 45 degrees Fahrenheit is deeply unpleasant when you add in a stiff breeze and a layer of dew.</p>
      <p>I could see the logic of how he emplace himself. He was right at the right angle of two brick walls- a perfect wind break. The issue is that he’s a fucking street person and this was private property. As the designated “tell trespassers to fuck off” guy, it was clear that my job was to trudge on over and tell him he needed to bounce.</p>
      <p>It was a bitch of a morning. The sun hadn’t risen yet. The wind was being a vicious little bastard, cutting through my clothes and sucking the body warmth out. It was not a good moment in time to have to wake up unless you had to. I knew exactly how much it would suck for him to sit up and expose himself to the elements he’d been fighting off all night.</p>
      <p>So... I chose not to see him. It’s only my job to shuffle him off if I know about him, after all. There ain’t no proof I noticed him.</p>
      <p>I want to be clear. I really don’t like homeless people. I used to be highly sympathetic towards them, but years of life fixed that. I have all the time and empathy in the world for working stiffs who get fucked by chance and are struggling to get their shit together again; I am not talking about such people. I’m talking about professional street persons who never intend to to abandon the life, if it would require even an ounce of accountability and effort. The people who ruin every program meant to help them by being aggressively nonfunctional and who default to defect-bot given even half an inch.</p>
      <p>I want to be absolutely clear that if I met that poor, freezing son of a bitch, I probably would not have liked him very much. I just didn’t want to make him suffer for no valid reason. It would be one thing if he was panhandling or harassing shoppers or jerking off in front of kids or whatever. But he wasn’t bothering anybody, so I felt no moral compulsion to fuck with him.</p>
      <p>So while I stood by the entrance and greeted customer and very carefully did not look at the far off corner of the parking lot, a dude shoplifted. I kept my eye on him, but there really wasn’t much I could do about it. The store policy is shaped by the law, and the law doesn’t look kindly on security guards who harass people for being potential shoplifters. As such, I could not accuse him, could not order him to fuck off, could not ask him what he had there tucked down the back of his pants; I really couldn’t do much but scan him and hope my presence would make him lose his nerve (he did not lose his nerve).</p>
      <p>Basic math, you see- better to let a hundred shoplifters steal and get away with it than confront the one guy who’ll scream about harassment and disrespect and then sue you. Or worse, some dysfunctional junkie who will pick a fight and get someone stabbed to death over a six pack of beer (can you imagine how embarrassing it would be to explain to St. Peter at the Pearly Gates for what cause you fought and died?)</p>
      <p>So as the shoplifter went off on his merry way, it struck me as obvious that everything about this was bass ackward.</p>
      <p>By what screwed up moral framework does it make sense for me to be called upon to harass, bully, and possibly even call the cops on a vagrant who is minding his own business trying to escape the freezing cold (again, I did not confront him, but if one of the workers had officially brought it to my attention I absolutely would have), but which gives every legal protection to the thief?</p>
      <p>I could get fired just for <em>following</em> the shoplifter around, but I could also get fired for <em>refusing</em> to budge the sleeping man into the chilly morning air. Had I approached the sleeping man and told him he needed to leave before I call the police, he could have utterly disarmed me by trundling over to the entrance, making a beeline for the beer aisle, grabbing a case of Coronas, then flipping me off as he waltzed off. Until he physically left the building I would have had no recourse, and once he swished past the checkout counter he would have been in the exact same legal situation he was in before- trespassing but able to leave.</p>
      <p>Why does breaking the law automatically confer benefits that do not apply to anyone else?</p>
      <p>I don’t have a larger point. This isn’t really CW either, because the relevant laws that shape the incentives are not under attack by any faction.</p>
      <p>I just find it absolutely morally dissolute that society is organized to be harsh and cruel to small people, and absurdly kindhearted and chivalrous in defense of bastards. Say what you will of the barbaric creeds that demand a thief’s hand to be cut off, you can’t deny that at least the hand to be removed belonged to a thief and not an honest peasant.</p>
      <p>The sleeping dude left of his own accord about an hour after the sun rose and the temperature spiked up to a pleasant 70.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>