<post>
  <author>anti-intellectual</author>
  <date>2020-01-31T09:10:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eujcbl/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_27/fg2yml3/</link>
  <title>Always On Camera, Never the Cameraman</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Intellectually, I can vaguely understand why some people hate it, but I can’t really empathize. This is despite me consuming a lot of anti-establishment content in the past year, and being sympathetic to the view that the elites are often out of touch, and play games of class warfare more often than they realize/admit.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>That’s perfectly par for the course IME. Blue teamers tend not to “get it.” In fact, the only people I see on Reddit who get what it’s like to be on Red Team are Eastern Europeans and Israelis. The common thread there is one where you’re fighting a neverending battle to  defend your team’s honor (not goodness, not correctness, just honor)  in the face of resources you can’t compete with. </p>
      <p>It’s not unlike being the subject of a rumor in high school, if you’ve ever had that happen to you. The difference would be that new acquaintances <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/redscarepod/comments/eut2p3/just_talked_to_god_he_told_me_that_kobe_went_to/ffw698j/?context=3">also casually use your name as a slur</a>, as if to assume that  you can’t possibly be the eponymous basis of that slur. I say “as if” because it’s not so much that people are surprised to meet you; it’s that upon realizing who you are, they don’t get embarrassed—they instead proceed to denigrate you mercilessly. </p>
      <p>I know you can’t empathize with that. I understand. Your political beliefs aren’t bywords for stupidity. Swedes on the internet don’t hear you say what area of the US you’re from and, on that information alone, call you trailer trash and insinuate that the reason you disagree with them is that you’re trailer trash. </p>
      <p>Where would Swedes get the idea that that sort of behavior was acceptable? Where did they get the idea that every man, woman, and child in Ohio is trailer trash? That sanity exists only on the coasts? Why do Danes have back-and-forths with me about the economic worthlessness of “red states” despite the fact that, as we all know, Republicans carry the greater tax burden? I didn’t tell them these things. Who told them? Who went around spreading rumors, and why aren’t they putting out the fires they started? </p>
      <p>To bring the point about Eastern Europe and Israel home: there is something pernicious about only ever being the subject of the camera and never the cameraman. It’s like being on Big Brother, only you didn’t agree to it and the show producers are trying to make you look bad. It’s an unequal relationship. Blue Team will tell you night and day that you’re not allowed to punch down, and then they cackle on cable TV, associating accents with stupidity. It’s enough to make a man vote for anyone who doesn’t bend to them. A-ny-one.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>