<post>
  <author>AshLael</author>
  <date>2020-02-02T00:33:29Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/exbynl/meta_just_keep_swimming/fg7wzht/</link>
  <title>Protect the Player Going for the Ball</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Basically, I think there’s a “weight of numbers” effect. Even if everyone arguing with you is super nice, the fact that you can reliably know ahead of time that if you post opinion X it will be you vs 10 other people, that’s enough to make you reconsider if you actually want to post it.</p>
      <p>Iterate a few times and people have clearly inferred a set of opinions that they can safely express, a set they can argue over on a reasonably even basis, and a set that will get them dogpiled.</p>
      <p>Like, when is the last time a top level comment in the CW thread came from a clearly left-wing perspective? I think it was the guy who was tearing down “It’s OK to be white” posters at his university. That guy got dogpiled by everyone (including me) and left never to return. I don’t regret anything I said in that thread, but the feeling he must have had was one of being overwhelmed. </p>
      <p>It’s not like we have no lefties here, but they know posting a top level comment that inflames the righties is going to get them <em>swarmed</em>. And again, even if everyone plays by the rules, that’s intimidating.</p>
      <p>In Australian Rules football, there is a well known umpiring philosophy: protect the player going for the ball. The rules are routinely interpreted in a way that favours the player attempting to take the ball and make things happen and disfavours the player trying to stop him and slow things down. This has two purposes: it keeps the game fast moving and fun to watch, and it gives players the confidence to go all out with no fear or sense of self preservation - after all, if they do get wiped out by an opponent they’ll probably get a free kick. It makes it a spectacular sport.</p>
      <p>I would like to see a moderation philosophy that “protects the player going for the ball”. The person who is championing the unpopular viewpoint is the one creating the discussion and making thing interesting. That doesn’t mean the rules don’t apply to him, but that his opponents don’t get away with the minor things that are normally ignored. If they want to take him down, they have to do it by the book.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>