<post>
  <author>Capital_Room</author>
  <date>2020-02-02T23:06:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eujcbl/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_27/fgdooih/</link>
  <title>Examining 'Amerikaner' Culture</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Gotta break this into parts:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The label "white" is an extraordinarily vague measure in a global context.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Indeed, but the usage in question developed in the <em>American</em> context, particularly in the white vs. black that remains the country's most prominant ethnic division (as has been discussed many times, even as Asians, Hispanics, and others make the actual situation more complicated).</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>So consider this a request, from a cultural outsider, to explain what your culture is and what's distinctly "white" about it.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Well, for the latter question, it's that Amerikaner is pretty much a subset of "white" — as you note, many whites aren't Amerikaners, but Amerikaners are pretty much all white. At most, there's maybe a bit of Native American, often at Warrenesque level (there's purportedly a tiny smidgen of Huron a way back up my family tree). That, and the fact that it's roots lie mostly in Christian Europe. Its language is English — a distinct set of related English dialects, with their own vocabulary and features, including a mix of both archaicisms lost in the UK and new, distinctly American features (like Webster's successful spelling reforms).</p>
      <p>Warning: the rest is going to be rather rambly.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>What's your ethos? Where does your morality stem from?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>"Judeo-Christian values," the phrase goes. Ceremonial deism. The kind of low, superstitious folk-Christianity, both Catholic and Protestant, that is fine with maypoles and Easter eggs and Christmas trees (most people miss that Dickens's Ebenezer Scrooge is, down to his name, a <em>Puritan</em> caricature), with beer and brawling and missing church for deer season, with throwing salt over your shoulder, sometimes down to the level, to paraphrase another online commenter, of "a paganism where the local folk deity is Oily Josh."</p>
      <p>An ethos of concentric loyalties — "me and my brother against my cousin" and all that — and family first. One that puts a lot of weight on friendship, as opposed to mere acquaintances. "A good friend will help you move… a dead body" and all that. A bit clannish. Remeber Hatfields and McCoys.</p>
      <p>A culture where, when you score a moose, or a caribou, or do well  salmon dipping, you share a bit of the resulting mooseburger, or caribou andouille, or home-smoked salmon, with family, and friends, and coworkers, and the families of your kids' school friends, and your kids' teachers — like the "gift economy" of a hunter-gatherer tribe.</p>
      <p>The culture that prefers space, prefers rural to urban, loves the outdoors… and killing and eating the wildlife. And thus supports the conservationism of Teddy Roosevelt, of Ducks Unlimited, so as to preserve those practices for future generations.</p>
      <p>And thus, guns. Lots of guns. Multiple safes and lockboxes, literal scores. My dad and middle brother once took the time to properly count whether they had more guns or bottles of scotch. (The latter won, at near a hundred.) Nobody since my paternal grandfather smoked, but otherwise we all agree with the sentiment that if you take the B off BATFE, you have the finest things in life.</p>
      <p>The kind where, when I see one of those ads on tv saying "if you own a gun and have kids, you have to sell it now, or else lock it in a safe and bury the safe in concrete until the kid is 21 or else they'll find it and shoot themself or someone else when they inevitably treat it like a toy," I feel something like the way left-wingers feel about abstinence-only sex education. Because we grew up around guns, and never once would have treated them as a toy. Because we learned gun safety from the earliest age — never point it at anything you're not willing to kill, always treat it like it's loaded — including seeing what even mere birdshot can do to a grouse (before seeing Dad wring its neck to put it out of its misery, then having it for dinner — with admonitions to chew carefully lest you bite into a piece of shot that was missed when the rest were picked out of the meat).</p>
      <p>Per that last point, the kind of culture where you're practicing gutting trout before age 10. Where you understand that meat doesn't come "from the store." And that Bambi's Mom is <em>delicious</em>.</p>
      <p>The kind that believes not so much in <em>self</em>-reliance — no man is an island, and all that about kin — but more that your family and associated "tribe" should collectively be as self-sufficient as possible. Which ties back to guns again, because when seconds count, the state troopers are hours away — when you're out in rural nowhere especially. And because the state, in all capacities except military and border security, is at least a little suspect, disputes are perhaps best settled without police or lawyers if at all possible (including duking it out — or maybe, at the direst, "shoot, shovel, and shut up"). And revenue agents are the spawn of Satan.</p>
      <p>Frontier people. Descendants of people who, when the going got tough, picked up and moved away. Or were thrown out. There's one great-great grandfather whom we can't trace the family tree any further past, because the only name we have for him is not his birth name, but the identity he stole before fleeing out West to escape the hangman. The Irish ancestor who gave the surname was pretty much told he had a day to be on the next boat across the Atlantic if he wanted to keep breathing. The earliest ancestor we can trace, the only one confirmed to have come over pre-Revolution, did so as an indentured servant. We're the descendants of the flotsam and exiles of Europe. One of my German ancestors came from Elsass-Lothringen, another from Prague. Another came from, if not Danzig, then somewhere in the "Polish Corridor."</p>
      <p>Think cowboys and mountain men and the Gadsen flag. Too willing to pick up and move for proper "blood and soil," too clannish and communal for proper "rootless modern."</p>
      <p>The kind where how other people raise their kids is none of your business… until those kids start wandering onto your property and getting into your stuff because the parents are too permissive (or maybe because they're corrupting your kids, but even then you just tell your kids not to hang out with them). We were never spanked, but nor did our parents oppose the practice in general, or as something that could be resorted to in extremis. You don't poke too much into other peoples' business, so they don't poke too much in yours. Where schooling is generally accepted as a necessity… but suspect when it goes beyond "the Three R's."</p>
      <p>The kind where you might spend a few weekends one teenage summer helping your social studies teacher with some work around his cabin on a lake, because his wife is a friend and former coworker of your grandmother, and because he's "paying" with a free meal. Where you can be in your 30s, living in your own place, and your mom can still call you up any given day and assign you chores around her house. And you do it without talking back.</p>
      <p>The kind where you can — and should when needed — prevail on family and friends for help, but you "ask for a hand up, not a handout," and are expected to "pull your weight" as much as possible. And where working poverty is more dignified than than being less poor but on welfare. (I've been wracked by guilt and self-loathing since I first went on disability.)</p>
      <p>We — those who are male — do not have "careers," we have <em>jobs</em>. You don't do what you do for a living because you enjoy it, or because it's a "calling," or anything like that. Work is the curse of Adam, and you labor at a job you hate, for over a third of your day, from whenever you first become old enough until you're either to physically broken or you die, for no other reasons than that you have to so as to put a roof over your family's head, clothes on their backs, and food on the table, and because it's morally superior to being the sort of vile, lazy parasite who leeches off other such workers' tax dollars.</p>
      <p>"Mom and apple pie." Women work outside the home when the financial situation demands it, or the kids are all grown. Mom was a couple months out of high school when she married Dad (who was only a couple years older), and she first started working, as anything other than a homemaker, after my youngest brother graduated. But both parents cook. Me and my brothers all cook. Youngest brother and I come over to our parents' place pretty much weekly, and generally alternate on who makes dinner — unless middle brother, the one with the culinary arts degree, is home (rather than at his job selling guns), in which case he takes over the kitchen and kicks everyone out. (Mom is still quite jealous of Dad's ability to make pie crusts.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>