<post>
  <author>genusnihilum</author>
  <date>2020-02-02T18:55:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/exbynl/meta_just_keep_swimming/fgc6wca/</link>
  <title>How Forums Self-Select by Writing Style</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I agree, and feel like these posts are too close to the "<em>Outgroup, boo!</em>"-posts that drive even mentally healthy progressives away, so I don't really like these posts. These healthy progressives want to <em>maintain</em> that mental health, and since it isn't healthy to be in an environment (digital though it may be) where they get signals like this all the time, they take off to somewhere else instead.</p>
      <p>But... humans are <em>really good</em> at picking up on this stuff, even if they can't consciously articulate it.</p>
      <p>So, one big problem is, even something as simple as the choice of prose can strongly signal "progressives, be gone!", even if that's not the intent. We adopt these styles intuitively without consciously considering their effects. It's subtle enough that I can't identify it in my own posts (though presumably it is still there, and quite conspicuous to everyone primed to see it). But I can definitely identify it in the posts of a lot of progressives. The conspicuous culture-signaling written disfluencies, the quirky onomatopoeia, the word-choice, the jargon, the academic references, and so on. It's like they wear their tribal affiliation on their sleeves, their every word dripping with poison aimed in my direction (implied through past experiences). I assume they do not do this consciously either, and that they might just as well not be aware of it. This is just how they talk normally.</p>
      <p>But that's one of the theories for why we have so many languages, right? Not to be able to communicate better, but to be "able" to communicate <em>worse</em>. Signaling constantly to the out-group that they don't belong, whether we intend to or not. Verbally, in the form of dialects, this is baked into even the simplest utterances we make.</p>
      <p>Interestingly (maybe?), I suspect the sidebar rules might be weeding people out for this reason. If progressives (along with various other groups) get banned (or just have it signaled that they don't belong, so they leave on their own) for talking what is normally among their peers, they do not see these rules being enforced as enforcing "niceness" or any such thing, but as enforcing a form of cultural hegemony within the sub. I definitely feel this effect on myself. I do not normally talk (or write) the way I do in this sub. I like to be a lot more aggressive, to use a lot more invectives, but also to be a lot more relaxed. You can call a guy a retarded dickhead whose opinion is objectively shit, but then continue the conversation with him just fine because he (being part of the same culture) understands that these are relaxation signals (i.e., it is okay for me to transgress normal social taboos on direct personal insults - indeed, powerfully so, as demonstrated by my hyperbolic insults, just like it's also okay for him to transgress by having opinions I or the group disapproves of; this is a relaxed environment where these things are tolerated). And if <em>I</em> turn out to be the one with the "objectively shit" opinion, then no big deal. The expectation is that we're all idiots here anyway, or so the pretense goes, so it's fine. You laugh it off. It was totally a joke anyway, haha... But that requires the person be part of the culture, or at least put the effort in to understand it. So it's necessarily 'gatekeeping'.</p>
      <p>But... you gotta choose <em>some</em> language to speak, and the people who made this sub presumably speak polite, so that's the language they went with. But this necessarily weeds out a lot of people. And if progressives can't speak polite well because they normally speak progressive, then the rules of the sub (unintentionally?) weeds them out - along with the people who want to speak like me. It may just not be worth the effort of rejiggering your brain, if nothing else.</p>
      <p>I wonder that we underestimate the power of these subtle social signals; that tribalism is built into us at a much more intrinsic level than we're probably comfortable with admitting. I similarly wonder if this problem isn't a lot more intractable than we give it credit for. If we literally can't have a conversation anymore without implicitly adopting the "other side"'s language, and thus ceding the advantage to them, then any arena that adopts any speech codes will necessarily be (or at least be perceived as) biased in favour of whoever's side those speech codes come from.</p>
      <p>Presumably, assuming this is correct, we could attract a lot progressives by mandating progressive speech codes instead. Y'know, put a big fat "no racism, no transphobia, no white supremacy dogwhistling, no criticizing feminism or you'll get a ban" etc., up on the sidebar; the kind that's in progressive subs. (Or whatever less-caricatural rules they might approve of in lieu of these suggested by my poor mental model of them). That'd make them feel real at home. And we could still have the same arguments we have now in spite of these rules, it would just be a harder. I know, because I have these arguments in those subs and as long as you frame them <em>just right</em>, you can get away with it. Even the HBD stuff passes just fine if you frame it right and avoid stepping on landmines, and then merely <em>imply</em> your intended argument. Though it's real exhausting; way more exhausting than talking polite, at least to me. But would you still wanna post here at that point? I probably wouldn't. Got other subs for that. And I suspect they feel the same way about the sub as it is now as I would about that hypothetical version of it. The language alone might be enough to drive them away.</p>
      <p>But, meh, well... I must admit my bias is I don't especially like writing in this style (though I like the conversations here, so it's not so intolerable as not to be worth it; it's just frustrating). So I'm heavily biased against this language. Likely, I'm seeing this as a much bigger problem than it truly is a result. So take everything written here with a huge pinch of salt. Feel free to read that as a pun as well.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>