<post>
  <author>georgioz</author>
  <date>2020-01-30T09:57:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eujcbl/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_27/ffzgq16/</link>
  <title>A Brief History of Islamic Conquest</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I am by no means a historian but I like to listen to history podcasting, I read some history on my own time and I also am fan of Paradox games.</p>
      <p>To cut things short, the history of early Arab conquest can be summarized as Roman expansion on fast forward. Prophet Muhammad can be seen as Marcus Furius Camillus, Jesus Christ and Emperor Constantine in one person. Within a few decades Muhammad united Arab tribes, founded the new religion (originally viewed as another Christian sect), and established the religion as state religion of the conquered nations.</p>
      <p>The success of early Arab conquest can be attributed to many factors. The most important ones were the exhausting war between large neighboring empires: Byzantine Empire and Sassanids between 602 - 628. This war put Byzantine Empire on its last leg where legendary general Heraclius miraculously turned it around with literally the last army Byzantines were able to muster. The second huge factor was the spread of devastating Justinian Plague that heavily affected populous regions of established empires - the desert tribes were much less affected. The third issue - especially for Byzantines - was long-term religious infighting between Chalcedonian orthodoxy (based on Concil of Chalcedon in 451) and Monophysitism. As a result Arabs basically swooped in, won just one decisive battle of Yarmouk in 636 and gained control over vast swathes of the land from Byzantine empire that was too weak to retaliate. Then they turned their attention on weak Sassanid empire and Abu Bakr conquered it basically in two decades consolidating his gains and establishing Rashidun Caliphate. The power of caliphs peaked with Umayyads which was the succesion Caliphate in 750. So the whole peak of Arab conquest took approximately 130 years give or take. </p>
      <p>Around this time however the internal pressures started to build up.  One major move was the revolt of non-Arab Muslims that relied on the power of Persian nobles and bureaucrats. They overthrew Umayyads and establishing succesor Abbasid dynasty in 750 also resulted into moving of capital from Damascus into Baghdad. Continuing with the analogy with Roman Empire imagine it as establishing the Constantinople. In a sense this is quite a good comparison. Similarly as Romans adopted ancient Greek culture into their own empire Arabs adopted ancient Persian culture into their own empire. But in the same way as Roman empire was for the whole time split between Latin speaking west and Greek speaking east - the basis on the split of the Roman empire - Muslim caliphate had similar split between Arabic speaking Arabs (and some other nations) in the east and Persian speakers in the west. Similarly to split between Catholicism and Orthodoxy the counterpart of this divide in Muslim is the split between Sunni and Shia. </p>
      <p>What follows for Abbasid  is period of various civil wars and eventual disintegration of caliphate into semi-autonomous regions. But in truth this was a gradual process that started even earlier under Umayyads. One should not be fooled by maps. The actual power and ability of people from Damascus and Baghdad to control affairs as far as Spain was always very limited. For insance the conquest of North Africa and Spain in 7th and 8th century by "Umayyads" this was done by coalition of Arabs and non-Arab Moors - the latter being basically the Berberic tribes that gave a lot of grief even to Romans for centuries. This coalition destroyed dislodged Vandals from north Africa and Visigoths from Spain. However there was infighting between these two groups basically since the beginning that resulted eventually resulted in establishment of separate Berber dominated successor states of Almoravids and Almohad Caliphate ending the power of Arabs in that region. </p>
      <p>The analogy with Romans continues. In the same way Romans started to rely on Germanic and other tribal mercenaries to fight their wars the civilized Muslim states started to rely on Turkic mercenaries. This resulted in Ottoman conquest but also some of the other entities. For instance the Mamluk sultanate established in Egypt in 1250 was actually a coup of elite Cuman and Kipchak mercenaries - member of Turkic tribes from Eurasian steppe. </p>
      <p>Anyway I would not say that historically Muslims are especially bent on world conquest. Or to be precise not to such and extent as some other cultures or ideologies. For instance Mongol culture and religion was much more aggressive in this way. In their view all the world belonged to Mongols - the foreign nations just did not know it yet. Also if one looks into the historical period of 6th-9th century one can find a very apt comparison with expansion of Franks. Thanks to the succession of very capable Frankish military leaders: Pepin of Herstal &gt; Charles Martel &gt; Pepin the Short &gt; Charlemagne the Franks were able to expand over the Europe in just about 130 years or so. The strategy was actually quite brilliant. Charles Martel created indomitable war machine that operated on very simple process: every year all tribal leaders under him were obligated to gather for that year campaign season. If somebody did not come to swear allegiance he could count on being the first target of the host for that year. Franks did this year after year for generations aggressively expanding and subjugating neighbor nations - including remnants of Gallo-Romans in nowadays France. And later on after the Roman influence in France manifested in unique French language and culture that was different from Germanic Frank conquerors. So you end up with Carolingian Empire ultimately split into France and related duchies speaking romance languages and Holy Roman Empire plus some other states speaking Germanic languages. </p>
      <p>Similarly to Muslims, Franks - and especially Charlemagne - used christian ideology as an excuse to subjugate pagan nations (e.g. Saxons) but also to keep conquered population in check. Chalemagne greatly supported by Catholic church and helped to enforce official Catholic dogma combating various heresies and syncretic Pagan/Christian practices. This is the period where we can see the Europe transforming from the patchwork of various tribes with different chieftains and customs with various relation with Christianity and Catholic dogma into the much more religiously and to some extent culturaly homogeneous Catholic blob one associates with middle age Europe. In this sense Charlemagne is not unlike let's say Abu Bakr in that regard - a military leader that uses tribal war machine forged by his predecessors to expand political and military power using religion to maintain cohesion of the newly created entity. In fact Franks and Arabs share also the "unfortunate" relict of tribal societies where the inheritance tends to divide lands between multiple successors which can lead to devastating civil wars for inheritance of land and power.</p>
      <p>Also some closing thoughts - even Muslim conquest was not some total war. In the end we have Greece and Serbia and Bulgaria and Croatia and all other nations that retained some of their identity despite being for centuries under Ottomans. For instance in 1897 Istanbul had total population of around 1 million. But only about 570 thousand were Muslims. There were around 200,000 Greeks and 170,000 Armenians. Ottoman empire was always a patchwork of religions and ethnicities. </p>
      <p>Anyway to conclude I'd say that historically Muslims were not some extreme when it comes to aggression. You had many more examples of aggressive expansions of empires starting from Assyrians, through Greeks, Romans, Franks, Mongols and many others. You had large expansion of christian states - the prime example is definitely Duchy of Mucovy that went from small area around Moscow to rule over large swaths of Eurasia pushing against steppe nomads to the souht, siberian tribes to the east but also against Christians to the west. Christians expanded and exported their ideology into America that is now basically homogeneous when it comes to religion. I'd say that if one rates religions then Christianity more successful than Islam - especially when it comes to conversion and export of that religion around. The key thing to consider is that during the 20th century Islam gained adherents mostly by demographic explosion in the Muslim world that by that time was stagnant (in terms of geographic expansion) for centuries.</p>
      <p>EDIT: some grammar changes and also some additions/corrections.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>