<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-01-29T17:11:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eujcbl/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_27/ffx505g/</link>
  <title>Where Does Moral Responsibility for Bigotry Come From?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Where does Moral Responsibility for Bigotry come from?</strong>
      </p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>So this came up below and got kind of derailed  by a bad analogy on my part among other Factors but: where does moral responsibility for beliefs come from?</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>In <em>Terminator 2</em> Sarah Connor (Linda Hamilton) starts off in a psych ward. </p>
      <p>Following her discovery in the first film that Skynet, a rogue AI, will go live in 1997 and kill 90+% of humanity with a nuclear attack, and that said AI is able to influence the past through the use of time travelling humanoid killing machines (the titular <em>Terminators</em>), Connor does the sane thing: she becomes a terrorist.</p>
      <p>This is genuinely the most rational thing to do. She engages in industrial terrorism to try and take out the systems that will become Skynet and if she needs to kill a Programmer or two....well what’s one life compared to billions.</p>
      <p>Now Connor cannot prove any of her beliefs and, as they’re quite out there, when she gets captured the courts come to the most plausible conclusion: Connor is delusionally insane and is not morally responsible for her actions. Thus they send her to an asylum where therapy might cure her and allow her to reintegrate with society, as opposed to prison where exclusion from society might serve as a suitable punishment.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>We generally consider this quite rational and moral on the part of the courts.</p>
      <p>Assuming Connor is wrong, demonstrably wrong, even delusionally and dangerously wrong beyond what any reasonable person could ever plausibly believe....well she acted sanely with regards to what she genuinely believed: if SkyNet was going to go live and Terminators were coming back through time to kill her and ensure humanity’s destruction, then ya terrorism is the sane responsible thing to do.</p>
      <p>It is not Connor’s Moral Judgement or Ethical Character the courts take exception to, simply her delusional beliefs and the resulting dangerous behaviour. If Connors beliefs were 100% accurate she’d be acting in self defense and defense of humanity: a Moral Exemplar (as evidenced by her role of hero in the films)</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Likewise the courts tend to look less than favourably on the Mentally Ill who do betray a flaw in moral judgement. If Bob, a paranoid schizophrenic, murders a man because “He insulted my mother”, well even if defense council can show that the victim said no such thing and the “insult” was demonstrably a schizophrenic delusion,  prosecutors would still have a strong case that Bob should face criminal penalties because irrespective of the delusional belief, Bob had an intent to murder someone without just cause. If everything Bob believed were true, he’d still be a murderous psychopath.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Which brings us to sane or “sane” beliefs.</p>
      <p>Religious and conscience exemptions are often handed out to ordinary sane people for their sincerely held beliefs.</p>
      <p>Sure the official position of the US government might be that gunning down the Vietcong as part of the 101st airborne is a right and noble thing for an American 18 year old to do, but if your religion forbids any violence at all on penalty of Hell or Moral ruin....while the US government vehemently disagrees with your conclusions (the official position of the US government remains that God protects the United States and those that kill in her name)... they will respect your sincerely held beliefs as, given what you believe to be the case, you are behaving correctly. You can serve you country in other ways:  by working in logistics or by serving as <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2693176/">Test Subjects</a>.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Now for Racism, bigotry, sexism, etc.</p>
      <p>Racism and Co. are sincerely held beliefs. Indeed admissions that it is not a sincerely held belief: “I’m not a racist i just have a twisted sense of humour”, “I’m not a sexist I just think its funny to tell women to make me a Sanmich”, “ I’m  not a nazi I just find holocaust jokes funny” are treated with the utmost suspicion! </p>
      <p>You may say you were joking, but how do we know you were <em>really</em> joking about fitting 6 million Jews in your ashtray!?</p>
      <p>This is bizarre! Both Anti-racists and their opponents seem in pure agreement that MERELY acting racist, but not actually believing the ideology would be a profound moral improvement! </p>
      <p>“Don't worry! He doesn’t have a sincerely held beliefs about the facts of the matter, he’s merely a dishonest actor.”</p>
      <p>This would be as if Sarah Connor admitted at trial that she doesn’t really believe this SkyNet bullshit, she merely enjoys blowing up tech companies. Only for the prosecutor to fire back insisting that her actions and behaviours betray a true belief in a threat to humanity and her need to defend herself and everybody else, and her false admission of lying is merely her desperate attempt to evade moral responsibility for believing in Terminiators... its incoherent.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>The transgression of racism, etc. Is sincerely believing something about the world, something we ascribe almost no moral  responsibility in any other facet of life.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Could it be negligence? </p>
      <p>Could bigotry be a thing you have a positive duty to not be an idiot about and get right? And that genuinely believing racist beliefs is a problem because it shows you failed in your charge to be intellectually correct in these matters.</p>
      <p>Lets assume a person is legally sane, and in most respects is like any-other person you meet in day to day life... they just so happen to believe a lot of new age non-sense. They’re anti-psychology, anti-chemical, anti-vaccine, pro-crystal, pro-<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goop_(company">Goop</a>) ect. And they raise their kids as such and they even advocate for their beliefs by posting on Facebook ect.</p>
      <p>Even if there are adverse outcomes or people do get hurt or even die as part of these “lifestyle” decisions we generally don’t describe these people or their non profiting enablers as moral abominations. The actual companies yes, they have a duty of care, but  the individual new agers... even if basic judgement, scientific literacy, and common sense would have allowed them to avoid the hazardous beliefs and protect others, we generally don’t ascribe a positive moral duty to be intellectually competent outside  a very select and defined crop of  professional or hazardous settings.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>How far we go in not ascribing such a duty get quite dramatic. None of the Jonestown survivors, all adults who led their families and others to their deaths in the claws of Jim Jones based on, rather suspect, religious and political beliefs were ever held responsible for some hypothetical negligence of judgement and mental hygiene.</p>
      <p>Indeed if you believe in a religion this gets rather dramatic. We modern liberal freedom-of-religion types generally believe that you have no moral duty whatsoever to actually hold the correct religious beliefs, even if your religion is evangelical!</p>
      <p>You might be actively leading people by the thousands into eternal damnation, a fate far worse than death, by practising the wrong religion....and yet you have no duty whatsoever to get your religion right before you start converting others or inducting your children into that faith.</p>
      <p>As I recall a moral philosopher once putting it: if you actually believe in your religion and damnation for failures of faith, then killing heretics is a very difficult conclusion not to come to. They are an existential memetic hazard to everyone they come into contact with. If only they were the carriers of a highly contagious, 100% lethal virus that might be acceptable, the dying may be saved. But to allow someone to walk around and converse with innocents when they’ll inevitably try to lead them into hell fire (it is the nature of ideas to be shared)... how could you let that happen!?</p>
      <p>And yet, in the 21st century, we enjoy freedom of conscious and are under no obligation to even try to get our religion right before we go out and convert. </p>
      <p>So We are under no obligation  to try and figure out whether evangelizing our ideas might lead people to eternal damnation, but whether Melanin is correlated with job success, Genital Shape with <em>Samich</em> making, or a certain minor faith with passing stealth checks: You really need to get that right!</p>
      <p>This is bizarre. And at odds with almost every other way we think of intentionality and moral culpability.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>