<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2020-02-03T06:31:58Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fgevg7f/</link>
  <title>How Wartime Hearts Turn Black</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So <a href="/r/army">r/army</a> is having a book discussion thing. Our current pick is <em>Black Hearts: One Platoon’s Descent into Madness in Iraq’s Triangle of Death</em> by Jim Frederick.</p>
      <p>As you can perhaps glean from the title, this is a harsh read. It is also, regrettably, nonfiction.</p>
      <p>I was gonna do a book review of it here, but I’ve been paralyzed from it. Content isn’t flowing. So I’m doing a top level post instead. Less content required, less pressure.</p>
      <p>Basically, the core of the book is this. In March 2006, after six months of the most insane stresses conceivable, four soldiers ditched their post and broke into an Iraqi home. They gangraped a fourteen year old girl and killed both her and her family in a quadruple homicide.</p>
      <p>Most of the meat of <em>Black Hearts</em> explores those “insane stresses”- </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>The rapid operational tempo that left them not only without rest days, but without enough time to sleep between missions/patrols/guard shifts. The months of living on the very edge of human endurance sapped the unit’s discipline and morale.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The shockingly poor leadership all the way up the chain. If you’ve ever heard the phrase “shit rolls downhill”, this is the kind of work environment it’s made for. The Lieutenant Colonel was a psycho boss who would screamed down and denigrate his subordinates over ever tiny little thing, so all the captains were constantly on edge and second guessing themselves. The Sergeant Major’s idea of leadership when they lost two guys in a single IeD attack is to come on down to the patrol base and chew people out for coming back from patrol without having shaved. Nobody involved was able to stand up and tell their superiors that the given mission was not possible- the Battalion was given the Triangle of Death to control all by itself. (For context, their replacements in the 10th Mountain Division were given the exact same mission and devoted twice as much manpower to it from day one). That basic equation- too much space, too many missions, not enough men- ran straight down to the squad and team level and was directly responsible for stress #1. It got to where three guys would hold down a traffic control point in the middle of a hostile city all by themselves for more than a day, just because there was literally nobody available to come out to relieve them.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Very much related to number two, the danger was extraordinarily high. The Triangle of Death just south of Baghdad was an al-Qaeda stronghold, as well as a fault line between Shia and Sunni. The men of the Black Hearts Battalion were under attack literally (actually literally) every single day of their deployment- mortars, IEDs, and small arms. And very much related to the poor leadership, none of their bases or TCPs had proper defenses. They had nowhere safe to rest their heads for the whole deployment. Over the course of the 11 month deployment, including the replacements, the line platoons suffered a casualty rate of about 1 in 3 men killed or grievously wounded. The danger was not merely hanging over them like the Sword of Damocles, it quite often dropped down and killed their friends.</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>Every day was an exhausting, terrifying, pointless, hateful experience without end, and at no point was there any sense that a single soul outside of their small little cared whether they lived or died.</p>
      <p>The end result, the <em>inevitable</em> end result, is that the platoon stopped identifying with anybody other than themselves. They didn’t even mesh with their own company anymore. They stopped caring about any outside standard, stopped caring about any outside morality or authority. They didn’t even identify with their own company anymore- their in group had shrunk down to twenty three guys, and even then their first loyalty was to their squadmates. It should go without saying that their view of Iraqis had gone from “inscrutable foreigners” straight to “loathsome fucking cockroaches” as their casualties mounted and the locals went blank faced when they asked them who planted that bomb that killed their buddies. The dehumanization of Iraqis was a constant.</p>
      <p>Now, if you’re like me, you want to know what the point of this is- it certainly doesn’t excuse the inexcusable rape-murder. Considering none of the other guys in the same boat as the fateful platoon that “descended into madness” went out and rape-murdered, it barely even explains it.</p>
      <p>Frederick invests a great deal of time and energy crafting a more or less deterministic chain to explain more fully why those four guys went off beyond the pale.</p>
      <p>His conclusion, summed up as best I can, is that 1st platoon Bravo Company (from whence the murder-rapists sprang) suffered the same debilitating evaporation of discipline and morale that everyone else in the Battalion suffered- the causes of which being listed above- but <em>unlike</em> their fellows, they got worse and worse over time, instead of rising up above their circumstances. Oddly and endearingly, Frederick proposes a spiritual explanation. The other companies felt the same tug of dehumanizing hatred towards the Iraqis, but their lower leadership, the squad leaders, the team leaders, the platoon sergeants, kept exhorting their guys to see things from the other guy’s point of view. To not take it personally if an Iraqi doesn’t speak up after a shooting. While the other platoons and companies were trying to make an effort to keep their guys from hating so blindly, 1st platoon Bravo Company’s lower NCOs were egging them on, encouraging fresh abuses and aggressive tactics. The ill-fated platoon even had an informal hierarchy dictating who had the right to beat up drivers at checkpoints and prisoners- the longer you’d been in the platoon the more latitude you got to break jaws. The new guys hadn’t “suffered enough” to earn the privilege to abuse Iraqis.</p>
      <p>In such an environment, something like the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmudiyah_rape_and_killings">Mahmudiyah Massacre</a> seems almost inevitable. If not this, then something else would have happened.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>