<post>
  <author>SlightlyLessHairyApe</author>
  <date>2020-02-01T11:33:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eujcbl/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_27/fg66yd4/</link>
  <title>Anti-Anti-Work</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Status: I'm trying to direct serious rage at the author into a productive discussion, success is not assured</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>First came the Golden Age, in which the land was bounteous, the forests were rich with game, and men were decent, happy, and favoured by the gods. [... ] Land became barren, crops wilted, stock died of disease; men were poor, men were bitter, son betrayed father, neighbour killed neighbour, chaos and treachery ruled.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>At the heart of every broken philosophy is a broken mythology. And nothing is more broken than the mythology that there was some idyllic pre-technological past, free from all the ills that today we blame on society. Society starts by reflecting those basic truths that <a href="/r/natureisbrutal">r/natureisbrutal</a> and, in varying degrees of success, has managed to solve or curtail them. Crops and livestock are a solved problem, murder is 1/100<sup>th</sup> what it was in centuries past. World poverty is far from solved but moving in the right direction.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The key variable between the time when men were happy and the time when they were not, according to Hesiod, is work. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Gee, you think the problem with crops being barren or the livestock dying or poverty or crime are caused by <em>working</em>? Agriculture, prosperity and justice are very much things that require people to work at them -- farmers, ranchers, judges. It's like someone blamed medicine for diseases and said "if we didn't have hospitals, we wouldn't have all these damned cancer patients!". I cannot emphasize how utterly idiotic this premise is. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Few of us are talented enough to make a living from the exercise of our passion. So, driven by economic necessity, we fall into “jobs.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>We don't <em>fall in</em> to them, those jobs start as something that needs to get done because of the laws of the physical fucking universe. Trash cannot magic itself from your bin into a landfill, someone has to dump it in a truck and drive the truck to the dump. I'm sure being a waste management engineer (to borrow the euphemism) is no one's <em>passion</em>, but that's hardly the point. The universe doesn't care, it just lets the damn trash sit there until someone moves it. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Most of these jobs are superfluous and invented—I’m sure of it!—to keep the talentless population employed.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Meanwhile in reality, there's record low unemployment in the US, and every company is trying to figure out ways to get fewer people to do more stuff. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>But it is also probably true that little girls don’t grow up wanting to become “vice-president for real-time card payments.” Or “senior manager for content licensing.” Or anything with “talent development” or “HR” in the title. Don’t get me wrong, these jobs have their uses</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The sneering! For someone who is a <em>journalist</em> and <em>author</em>, you'd think she'd have at least minimal appreciation for people that work in content licensing. Let alone as a person that uses a credit card she'd marvel that you can swipe a piece of fucking plastic anywhere in the world and a magic system will transfer the correct amount of value to the correct place within seconds and with a failure rate well below 1 in a million. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>. But how many of us are stoical enough to be motivated by the vague image of a nameless, faceless customer we will never meet, and about whom, let’s be honest, we don’t really care, when we push open the door of our open-plan at nine in the morning and brace ourselves for 10 hours of drudgery?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Oh no, your poor open-floor-plan office and drudgery! Never mind the waste management engineer that empties your trash bin or the folks that keep the sewers running so you can take a shit and never even have to <em>think</em> about where it goes. Do you think that sewage plant operator needs to conjure up your face in order to take satisfaction in his job? Do you think he needs to <em>care</em> about the people whose shit his plant processes?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>It included a quote which perfectly articulates what I anticipate will be the main objection to this article: “The most important thing is not to produce spiritual values,” writes Musil, “but food, clothing, security, order.” Indeed, why do I concern myself with a subject so esoteric? A matter so niche? Spirit, passion… Who cares, when there are real problems in the world, such as war, hunger, poverty, and disease? People doing hard manual labour to scrape by? Try talking to them about Hesiod. And isn’t denigrating work both ridiculous and futile? We need work to ensure our physical survival. Without work, we will die. I agree unequivocally: these matters take priority. But they are also written about extensively, and by commentators who are far better qualified than I am. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Well, after all this enmity, it's nice to see that she at least recognizes this much. And I do appreciate the concession that "these matters take priority". But of course</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>What I worry about is unrealised spirituality. This is my niche and the hill on which I will die. The dichotomy between what we originally want to be and what, due to the limitations of talent, circumstance, luck and, most of all, economics, we end up being, is as real as it is tragic. It is the curse of the Iron Age.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I worry about it too. But you know, pre-Iron-Age humans had basically one of it. They could not be <em>anything</em> except whatever backwards tribe they were born into, or perhaps dead in childbirth or of curable disease or killed in a petty squabble. Surely none of them could be <em>journalists compiling a collection of their short stories</em>.</p>
      <p>The fact that humans have finite means is not a curse of the Iron Age, it's the very thing it was designed to alleviate. It's produced, for the first time in history, the ability for anyone to achieve anything of what they want to be.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>A Gallup poll found that 85 percent of people hate their jobs. Business schools would say that this is due to poor strategy, poor leadership, or poor innovation. Nothing that cannot be fixed with an MBA degree. The real explanation is much simpler, however: 85 percent of people hate their jobs because, given the choice, they would never do them in the first place. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Well, sure. And if I could chose a universe in which trash didn't have to be moved in the first place, that would be pretty swell. And a pony. </p>
      <p>Less snarkily: the world is the way it is. The job is an inherent property of those facts and not of the people that execute them. Complaining about the job is comparing about the physical laws of the universe. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>At best, it is the choice of an animal looking for food and shelter, not of a human agent created in God’s image. He was right. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Nailed it!</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>As we leave childhood and the need to earn a living becomes increasingly urgent, our dreams start getting trimmed and trampled and squashed, until there comes a day when we no longer remember them. We begin by seeking the sublime. We end up resigned to the ordinary.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>We leave childhood and its perverse mythology and adapt ourselves to reality, inconvenient facts and all.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>