<post>
  <author>anechoicmedia</author>
  <date>2020-08-24T10:19:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ib82ju/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_17_2020/g2of52i/</link>
  <title>The Problem of Inflation Analyses</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Health care is a mess since it's not hedonically adjusted. A change from $1000 death to $10,000 cure is treated as 10x inflation, which is grossly wrong.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This sort of encapsulates the entire problem as I see it; I'll expand a little on each part.</p>
      <p>The strawman economist says that adding new options to the world is an unalloyed good. Either you don't buy, and your utility is the same, or you exercise new options that give you more marginal utility for the same dollars.</p>
      <p>The immediate wrinkle here is that choice doesn't exist, because the way healthcare works in most countries is that the state defines a baseline basket of healthcare products which you are obligated to buy through some form of financial scheme, be it taxes, insurance, employer pools, etc. So if HHS, or your employer health plan, decides to put Lucemyra* (~ $2,000/mo) on the Drug List as a covered alternative to clonidine ($5/mo), if you don't agree that it's 400 times better, you life just got slightly worse.</p>
      <p>The libertarian prescription is to abolish mandatory coverage, and let individuals choose to continue to live with the living standards of the 1960s. But like abolishing wage minimums, this looks to be off the table everywhere. Every country, as it develops, seems to have a ratcheting consensus of what the standard of living is supposed to be, and enforces it on all its members, one way or another.</p>
      <p>And in practice, even in a market, the world is not served to you à la carte. Healthcare services are bundled, and often bargained for collectively, via employer or union. Exercising a preference on any particular part of that basket of goods now requires a new job, or buying individually (which costs a substantial premium, defeating the point.) Since one can not simultaneously optimize along hundreds of dimensions of preferences in their job search, compromising with the consensus healthcare plan is unavoidable.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>I have more examples, but they're not any different, and all involve some of the following aspects:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>you don't actually have a choice; it is literally illegal not to buy

<ul><li>automakers invent air bags, gov't mandates air bags</li><li>DuPont invents fire resistant home insulation; gov't adds to building code</li><li>illegal not to pay into retirement, medicare, etc</li></ul></li>
        <li>choice is impossible since markets and infrastructure already decided for you

<ul><li>walking to work not possible since decades of people preceding you put the jobs and houses an hour's drive apart</li><li>unemployable without a smartphone</li><li>stores carry products whose turnover justifies the shelf space, not the cheapest things from fifty years ago just so you personally can exercise individual choice in buying them</li></ul></li>
        <li>the mere existence of the choice makes your life worse

<ul><li>new cancer cure replaces the certainty of death according to God's plan with another thing you have to buy for your family to be a worthy provider</li><li>potential to extend life another six months at great expense is actually a horrifying choice nobody is equipped to make, not a wonderful innovation</li></ul></li>
      </ul>
      <p>I think of almost everything this way now, and it gives me much more belief in the harm of inequality as such.</p>
      <hr />
      <h3>Education</h3>
      <p>Ticks a lot of these same boxes. K-12 schooling has become roughly three times more expensive since the 1970s, it's illegal not to pay for it, and nobody thinks it's gotten three times better over that period of time. For men in particular, your opportunity as a high school degree holder is arguably worse in absolute terms.</p>
      <p>A graph of increasing college attainment can be a sign of things getting worse, depending on what it is you think colleges are selling. As a mental exercise, substitute for the Y axis something like "taxi medallion ownership" and ponder whether that's an indicator of wealth or dysfunction. The marginal purchaser of a degree certainly benefits, but if you think of degrees as a positional status good, or something like an occupational license, then their general prevalence is not a sign of life getting easier for people.</p>
      <p>An example I've used before: Today, four years of in-state public law school costs about $106k. What would that have cost my grandfather, a lawyer, fifty or sixty years ago?</p>
      <p>The answer is that it doesn't matter, because in his day, the law didn't require my grandfather to attend law school to become licensed. He just studied on his own, passed the bar, and opened a successful business that continues to employ people today.</p>
      <p>So from my family, the rate of inflation for "becoming a lawyer" is <em>infinity percent</em>. Had he been required to get a degree (as the law does today), my grandfather's incrementing by one the national ownership of college degrees would have been a sign of relative deprivation, not wealth.</p>
      <hr />
      <h3>Housing</h3>
      <p>This is another one where the metrics I once thought told an unambiguous story have an alternative interpretation. Mainly, the housing of yesteryear is illegal to build anywhere, for both code and zoning reasons. As your local YIMBY will probably tell you, big houses are a tool of economic exclusion, and just about every city has some mechanism whereby building lots of small houses and apartments is de facto illegal, to keep out low-class people.</p>
      <p>The thing that matters to your economic security is the minimum ante for buying a home, <em>any home</em>, in a safe area near employment**. So even if 1,500 sq. ft. would have been fine, you buy the 2,000 sq. ft. house that the market actually has to offer you where the jobs are. Average house size goes up - just as average years of education goes up -- and it's not because housing is so much more affordable these days.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>* Borrowing an example from a recent SSC post</p>
      <p>** You can add "... and near people who speak my language" to that if you think part of maintaining your living standards is being able to talk to your neighbors, which increases the cost if you live here in Texas.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>