<post>
  <author>Denswend</author>
  <date>2020-08-20T07:04:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ib82ju/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_17_2020/g26vcql/</link>
  <title>Covid Deaths and Dignity of Life</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>No. I do feel that because of age and generational distance, as well as you know, familial distance. Furthermore, I hold two perspectives that might sound positively monstrous, even for this place. So I'd like to explain them. Please bear in mind that what shaped these perspectives are my experiences, both lived and expected, and I am not a resident of USA or Western Europe.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Due to a certain Yugoslav socialist mentality, it was common enough for certain people to go in pension in mid 50s. Due to a certain Yugoslav nationalist mentality, a sort of a war erupted, a society-permeating and all-encompassing war that left huge scars on our population. And certain pension fonds erupted, gone without trace. This results in boomers who worked for 20-30ish years to enjoy generous pensions for 20-30 years. I know a lot of people like that, This results in generation x military veterans going into pensions in mid 40s, pensions being quite sizeable. I know a lot of said veterans, one of them being my father who laughed because he said his pension is higher than my paycheck in a deficient medical position. Go figure. </p>
      <p>Ministry of Social Security is an absolute staggering beast, with their input being the three times as large as Ministry of Health. How is it funded? Through taxes, yes, but mainly through thing called <strong>intergenerational solidarity</strong>. It is mandatory. It might be an inner libertarian in me, but whenever I hear of non-optional solidarity, I translate that as theft. This means that every working citizen (non-pensioner) gives 15% of his brutto (before taxes) paycheck, which translates to 20% of netto (after taxes) paycheck. Since percentages are numbers are unpalatable to a lot of people, for emphasis I will translate that as a <em>fucking fifth</em>.</p>
      <p>Over the course of my working life, which will depending on my proclivity for suicidal thought, I will give a fifth of my earnings, my life, to my parents (who I have one of), and my grandparents (who I do not have). As well as everybody else in that group, because it modern welfare state, we're all family and biology doesn't matter that much. Furthermore, due to sheer demographic differences as well as differences in political participation, pensioners and elderly have an effective stranglehold on political power. To reiterate, I am in a position where a <em>fucking fifth</em> of my work is siphoned off to people who retired in mid 50s (my own father went into retirement at the age of 40), while I will not retire until my 70s (or even at all), while that same cohort who my work is siphoned off to the people holding considerably more political power than me. Do you understand as to why <em>children</em>, like me, would be miffed a bit? </p>
      <p>Now, <em>children</em> like me, have to sacrifice their own economical livelihood to protect the lives of people who already take a sizeable portion of their economical livelihood. Not me specifically, I profit from the plagues. But my brother, who works in service industry, now finds himself hard pressed for money and payments to the bank do not stop. So much for intergenerational solidarity. Thing is, any policy regarding COVID, from "do nothing" to "lockdown everything" will have a certain impact on people. For every one percentage of unemployment that goes up, 40 000 people die. Brad Pitt said it, it must be true. So you're just picking which groups to kill.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>My second perspective is that medicine has, for the vast majority of its life, been a malignant pseudo-science, that has survived only because of arrogance of medical staff and the resulting confidence that this same arrogance instills in the hoi polloi. Just read up on what happened to my man Semmelweis, who insisted that doctors and nurses wash their hands (like certain Jewish enclaves were doing in middle ages and updwards). Bullied into suicide. But fine, that was a hundred years ago. Now situation changed, and the medicine moved from bias prone self experience into evidence based, science oriented. They've even discovered <a href="https://care.diabetesjournals.org/content/17/2/152.abstract">integrals!</a> But my view is that medicine and medicine adjacent fields are still evil. The paradigm that permeates the field is one of aggressive life extension in numerical value, while the quality of said life decays quickly with every new medical intervention that seeks to put on a few years more. Very rare are medical problems which we <em>cure</em>, and more often are those we <em>treat</em>. And of those we <em>treat</em>, a significant portion of those are those that come in advanced age, helped by stress of unhealthy life, where body's machinery simply loses its potence, and there is nothing you can do to restore it to a previous working state. For that matter, I consider myself a semi-necromancer, a member of parasitic caste that lengthens <em>dying</em>, not life.</p>
      <p>Now, I do not believe in <em>sanctity</em> of human life. That's just how my dice rolls. I believe instead, in <em>dignity</em> of life, and inherent beauty of life fully lived. And what the elderly, especially excessively elderly who are at risk of COVID, and those in nursing homes (which I have more experience than I want) have, is not a dignified life. Barely mobile, barely <em>coherent</em>, incapable of defecating or showering by themselves, loaded up with various medications (and remember, theirs is a serious condition - serious conditions are treated with serious medication, and serious medication have serious side-effects), utterly helpless and dependent on other people, and in rare moments of clarity utterly aware of their own situation. Just now, I paused writing what is (I hope) a coherent post, walked to the bathroom, shat, then showered, and waltzed back here - the notion that any of these actions be impaired or slowed by anything other than my own desires is something I find utterly terrifying. </p>
      <p>And I do find the notion that I don't feel the same or even similar to my grandparents a bit baffling. I wasn't a test tube baby and I really do not lack empathy. It would be a lot easier if I did. I loved my granpa and grandma. I absolutely <em>hated</em> seeing my grandfather, a quick and agile man (many times my physical superior in his hay day), turn into an obese, barely mobile person who on a good day pops 10 pills and vegetates in front of mind-numbing television, and on a bad day is barely coherent enough to yell at his wife or his son. He died in a hospital, loaded up with a salvo of antibiotics, heavily sedated, with one moment of clarity, just enough for him to notice that he is stuck with catheters and IVs and pleading his family to not look at him like this, after a pulmonary infection by antibiotic resistant bacteria found commonly in urinary tract. Truth be, I was glad that he stopped <em>suffering</em>. </p>
      <p>So no, I do not mean to say that "it's not a big deal when nasty old people die lol". It is a big deal. I mean to say that we will deal. I dealt when my grandparents died. My father dealt when my grandparents died. Because we all intuitively transcribe a hierarchy of values for life, and understand death. We imbue our family structure with <em>telos</em>, apply reciprocity to that telos and come to the notion of of filial piety. Without <em>telos</em>, no filial piety. Purpose of one generation is to protect and provide for the next generation - to that extent one generation <em>borrows</em> from the previous to hand to the next. (From my first perspective you can see that our esteemed elders failed hard at that, but that is irrelevant to this) Ask an arbitrary amount of people what is more tragic - a father burying a son, or son burying a father. Furthermore, I do agree with the sentiment of filial piety. I simply do not agree with methods of it. A dignified life should be accompanied with a dignified death, not slow and irreversible degradation until one's life turns into a cruel mockery of the very principles of living. I <em>hope</em> that I will have enough mental strength to avoid that. </p>
      <p>So from my perspective, lockdown policies which as implemented at the cost of everyone, are simply another form of cruel semi-necromancy that utterly dominates medical field. You inconvenience everyone to prolong the torture of people you should hold in high esteem. To me, that is simply evil.</p>
      <hr />
    </div>
  </body>
</post>