<post>
  <author>Denswend</author>
  <date>2020-08-26T10:30:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ifiyso/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_24_2020/g2wb71g/</link>
  <title>Defining Religion</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Back a while ago Scott wrote a post on "is everything religion". And I do remember being relatively unimpressed with that post, as it contains no rigorous (the type of rigor Scott can ocassionally put up in his effortposts) analysis.
If we were to ask a question of a particular X being religious or at least adjacent enough to religious behaviours that, if you were to squint, it passes as a religion, we'd have to first coherently define a religion.
This definition must be in a manner that includes everything that is definitely a religion, excludes everything that is definitely not a religion, and rigorous enough so that the edge cases can be coherently and reasonably placed in either category without no apparent inconsistency.
Luckily enough, there was also a guy who gave such a definition. He is maybe more famous for his <em>anomie</em>, establishing sociology and studying society back when positivism was all the rage. So I'm going to circle through different definitions of religion, and why exactly Durkheim rejects them. I will provide a very brief outline, and for more discussions you can read Elementary Forms of Religious Life (first chapter).</p>
      <p>First definition ties religion with the concept of <em>supernatural</em>, and this is relatively lazy, but passes a quick smell test. Durkheim says no, because this concept of supernatural must first include natural - for a fact (a phenomenon, etc) to be supernatural we must first have a concrete category of natural order. 
This concept of a natural order is relatively new phenomenon and applied retroactively. Furthemore, religious forces were used to explain <em>consistent</em> and normal phenomena.
Second definition ties religion with the concept of a "<em>spiritual being</em> (quick parkour around the concept of God). First problem is Buddishm. Buddha is hardly a spiritual being, because his divine role is hardly compatible with other divinities - Buddha is dead, in nirvana, and cannot influence human existence anymore. Furthemore, he states that Brahmanism (which may be Hinduism) is just a step behind open atheism - many deities have in time became a form of unique principle, facless and abstract.
Furthermore, there are even some deistic religions (Judaism is his first example) that contain certain beliefs and practices that stand orthogonal to the concept of spiritual being. Bible says that a woman must be isolated during a certain time in the month - what does Yahweh have to do with that?</p>
      <p>He says that religion must not be considered an undivisible entity, and we therefore must examine parts that constitute a religion (hence elementary forms). Religious phenomena can be classified as <em>beliefs (thoughts) * and *practices (movement)</em>. Important to this phenomena is the distinction between <em>sacred</em> and the <em>profane</em>. Sacred being dogma, a hierarchical order of things and beliefs that a profane man cannot touch without sanction. He then adds that the necessary thing for a religion is that it must posses ability to form a collective based on its practices and beliefs.
The full extent of the definition is then :</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>A system of beliefs and practices that make distinction between sacred (that which cannot be questioned profanely without sanction) and profane, and that said system unites its practitioners into one single moral community</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Now this is a powerful definition because it includes the obvious (Islam, Christianity) and the less-obvious but definitely (Buddhism, Shinto) religions. Now since people are fuzzy categories, societies are fuzzier still, people's understanding of society (which we call sociology) is maybe the fuzziest, and there is a problem of overfitting this definition.
For that matter, I must add that Durkheim was very far from the nu-atheist-enlightened-blabla, he considered religion an important catalyst of an orderly society. Furthemore he was a sociologist who was fully into sociology. Where you put "God", put "Society" instead, and one of an insight that is attributed to him (maybe he was explicit somewhere, maybe this is just implicit extension of that) is that in weakening of explicit religion, an <em>ideology</em> will be a suitable substitution (maybe just an evolution of religion).
In absence of religious outlet, politics will do. "Rituals that are worshipped during mass ceremonies of bolshevism, fascism, communism and even post-communist nationalism lead not just to collective "zeal" but mass histeria, its practitioners bow to less spontaneous, but more zealous and simpler form of symbolized community - with punishment for the outgroup being crueler still, a solidarity brought forth not by sacrifice of totemic animal, but of mass human sacrifice."
Indeed, pictures of Nuremberg Rally and similar gatherings do evoke a certain feeling of religious awe, regardless of it leading to awesome or awful consequences. And much like Durkheim, I do not believe an ideology to be a bad thing, but uniquely necessary thing for society to function.</p>
      <p>My own opinion is that Durkheim wasted a lot of time studying totemist system in Australia. Much more interesting would be to define the <em>itch</em> that religion scratches. From definition of that <em>itch</em>, we can see what also can scratch that said itch. Maybe ideology is not a religion, but it is my most humble belief that certain ideologies scratch that religious itch, and in doing so they substitute religion and all the implications of it. 
So far I thought of three (3) different itches that religion scratches, and how ideology scratches them also.</p>
      <p>First itch would be the need to <strong>unambiguously differentiate the groups to the in-group, out-group, and the far-group</strong>. To this end, I'll simply link <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2016/04/04/the-ideology-is-not-the-movement/">Scott's "The Ideology is not the Movement"</a>.
Second itch would be the need to <strong>provide legitimacy for existing, or yet-to-exist power structures</strong>. Fun fact, first estate in medieval Europe was the priest caste (the aristocrates were second). India does not have the explicit numering, but similar still is the Brahmin caste. Consider the difference in crowning of Charlemagne and the crowning of Napoleon. 
Third itch is maybe the most subtle, but one itch that religion and ideology both scratch is that they provide a <strong>working theory on how one relates his existence to existence of other members of a group, and how they relate their existence of other members of that same group and vice versa</strong>. When I say the working theory, I do not mean that it provides sufficient mechanistic explanations of natural world.
Science does that, and it is only marginally related to the itch in question. It's been often said that technological progress marches regardless of social progress (certain ideologies can slow or hasten technological progress), or similarly that one can effectively disentangle social progress form technological progress because the causal connection of say "LGBT RIGHTS" and "antibiotics" is rather unclear.
Less important is the movement of atoms in the water compared to the questions of what is virtue, what is a virtuous life, how can I pursue it, what stops me from pursuing it, and what should I do to the things that prevent me from pursuing it. While the legitimacy of power itch is of great importance to the ruling class, this is useful to potentially every member of said ideology/religion and it maps onto "searching for meaning in this brutal world" memeplex.</p>
      <p>I position that ideologies and religion, in order to be fully realized need to have that three important characteristics. Only when an ideology is fully realized, can it move to capture positions of power, and the said capture is something that depends of societal and cultural context, inherent ability of executors of that capture, as well as the potential for that religion/ideology to enhance/diminish abilities of its members.
The salience of ideology/religion, directly relates to how close it is to centres of power and how do the existing centres of power relate to that ideology/religion.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>