<post>
  <author>EfficiencyPlenty</author>
  <date>2020-08-25T20:57:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ifiyso/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_24_2020/g2ubobl/</link>
  <title>The Inside View from a Jail Cell</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Last year I found myself in a very unexpected position, which was inside of a jail cell. Considering the discussions regarding criminal justice this year, I wanted to share my experience and what I learned from it. This did not take place in America.</p>
      <p>I was first detained at the end of my driveway on my way to work where about a dozen plainclothes officers stepped up and presented me with a search warrant for my home. They turned the place upside down and looked positively gleeful when they found a small sheet of LSD slipped between the pages of a book. The officers collected the contraband and all of my phones and computers into the back of their vehicle before finally serving a warrant for my arrest: a letter containing MDMA had arrived from the Netherlands, and it was addressed to me. I was handcuffed, and we all got in their van and drove back to the police station where I would live for the next six weeks until I could get bailed out.</p>
      <p>I would come to know a few other inmates, but naturally I learned the most about my cell mate, M. Whispering, (communicating was forbidden except during our 20 minute exercise period) we would pass time talking about our lives. M was much older than I was, perhaps in his 50s or 60s, and I will be the first to say that he had lived a far harder life than I ever will. No stranger to a cell, M had been sentenced to prison multiple times before being arrested yet again. He had already been in jail for 5 months awaiting trial when I arrived, and he was still there when I left, unable to post bail. Outside of prison, he worked menial jobs for low pay and was unhappily married until his divorce. For fun, M liked cars, meth, and burglary which would land him back in prison. M's face matched his lifestyle: bald, jowly, and with many missing teeth. I feel compelled to point out that despite all this, he already had another girlfriend. M was very proud of her, and he exchanged letters with her often and quite proudly showed off her photo. So yeah, if you're stressing about finding a girlfriend, don't. Furthermore, M was incredibly popular with the inmates and guards. He was invaluable for showing me the ropes when I first arrived, and we regularly shared reading material even though it was against the rules. We also happily traded stories about drugs. He told me all about meth, and I described my psychedelic experiences to him. The guards would regularly stop by to chat with M for fun, and when the morning shift came in they would always tell him about the baseball game from the previous day.</p>
      <p>I eventually got to go home, but not before M got his sentence: 6 years in prison for burglary and methamphetamine possession. An inmate in the cell next to us got just 1 year for vandalism, and he was so distraught he tried to put a ballpoint pen through his neck to kill himself. M was mostly upset because we all had to give up our pens after that. For my part, I got 2 years of prison time, but the sentence was suspended on appeal.</p>
      <p>I can't deny that the experience left me in a dark place mentally and pushed me off the cliff of "moderate liberal" and dangerously toward the abyss of anarcho-capitalism. Being arrested, locked in a cage, and then grovelling before a judge not to put me back in a cage has left me very skeptical of state coercion in principle. But I still agree that we need laws and punishment, so what of it then?</p>
      <p>I would be in favor of replacing short prison sentences partially or totally with corporal punishment, like caning in Singapore for example. Ideally penitentiaries would be places of penance and rehabilitation, but to my knowledge no country except maybe Norway actually executes that idea. If the only objective then is to make convicts suffer as punishment, why drag it out in the longest, most expensive way possible? My theory is that most people in developed, wealthy countries would not have the stomach for it. People could not bear to watch a man yell and cry as he is whipped for vandalism, so we put him somewhere we can't see for a while and secretly hope the other convicts do what we don't have the guts to. Wouldn’t corporal punishment be more merciful to the convict too? I would have gladly traded my 2 year sentence for a whipping or caning session if it meant I could go home to my loved ones and carry on with my life at the end of the day, albeit much bloodier. Maybe I wouldn’t have lost my job! There are however people so dangerously antisocial that they need to be isolated from society, and for them prisons will always have their place.</p>
      <p>Please have some mercy on the people behind bars in your country. None of them, not even the Norwegians, are having a good time. Yes, they probably did something bad, but they also probably don't deserve to be raped, assaulted, or killed. One of them could even be a fellow motte-poster.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>