<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-08-19T17:17:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ib82ju/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_17_2020/g24dwc5/</link>
  <title>Don't Underestimate the Selflessness Pill</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I’m not even sure that a selflessness pill would do what they say it would.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Oh but it will. Look at what they're actually proposing: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Moral enhancement is the use of substances to make you more moral. The psychoactive substances act on your ability to reason about what the right thing to do is, or your ability to be empathetic or altruistic or cooperative.</p>
        <p>For example, <strong>oxytocin</strong>, the chemical that, <em>among other things</em>, can induce labor or increase the bond between mother and child, may cause a person to be more empathetic and <a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1189047">altruistic</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0001128">more giving and generous</a>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ijnp/pyx047">The same goes for <strong>psilocybin</strong></a>, the active component of “magic mushrooms.” These substances have been shown to <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40732-015-0139-y">lower aggressive behavior in those with antisocial personality disorder</a> and to improve the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psyneuen.2017.07.483">ability of sociopaths to recognize emotion in others</a>. These substances interact directly with the psychological underpinnings of moral behavior ...</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>That's a nice way to put it, but more cynically, oxytocin just increases <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0306453015002073">conformity in response to social pressure</a>. It also, as one of those links helpfully shows, promotes "tend and defend" behaviour, which is to say, increases anxiety about harms [to ingroup]. Or how about it? <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/114/2/268">Oxytocin levels surge in troops of chimpanzees preparing for conflict with rival groups</a>. You really can cherrypick the studies which frame it one way or another, but in the end it's not a "morality" drug whatsoever, and the very idea is preposterous. (It's telling how in the very next paragraph he offhandedly says that drugs "that make you more rational could also help", even though his argument for social discancing is ostensibly rational and boils down to the tragedy of the commons.)   </p>
      <p>As for the second-line of therapy for free-thinking, he proposes a psychedelic drug. Let me just say that I have no bias against psychedelics. Still. There's a semi-crazy but very erudite guy running <a href="/r/Psychedelics_Society">/r/Psychedelics_Society</a>. He made a stink about Scott's review of that Friston/Carart-Harris' paper which "explained"
its effects: <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/09/10/ssc-journal-club-relaxed-beliefs-under-psychedelics-and-the-anarchic-brain/">Relaxed Beliefs Under Psychedelics And The Anarchic Brain</a>. I've been meaning to write about it, but didn't find the energy. The thing is: I think that guy's kinda right, and Friston's paradigm is creepy in exactly the same way as the above duplicitious framing of oxytocin. On what grounds do we expect that "relaxing beliefs" and falling into "global minimum" has anything to do with accurate modelling of physical reality rather than something else? That it causes us to find a more accurate world-view, rather than one primed by social conditioning, system 1 thinking, general quantity of signals and presented opinions? This entire line of opposition to "biased" top-down thinking smells like open borders, like Twitter mob democracy, and it seems like people who do a lot of drugs become very very <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2016/04/28/why-were-early-psychedelicists-so-weird/">weird</a> and <a href="http://www.mckennite.com/articles/feminism">extra far left</a>, not perfectly unbiased. It's a trope among Western psychonautics proponents that "bad thoughts" can be cured and <a href="https://twitter.com/hilaryagro/status/1229219747969064960?s=20">replaced with socialism</a> by a good dose of drugs. They seriously put hopes on that approach to "redeeming" society. Sometimes, however, <a href="https://www.psymposia.com/magazine/lucy-in-the-sky-with-nazis-psychedelics-and-the-right-wing/">totally opposite things happen</a>; and gwern famously did not change his worldview at all. My own experience tells me that people update not towards some specific politics or beliefs, but rather towards taking <em>very seriously</em> what has accumulated in their mental space, by their own or someone else's efforts. If it's a certain kind of media message... Imagine hearing 24/7 that <strong>black bodies are literally being slaughtered by cops every day</strong> and that <strong>not wearing mask is murder</strong> but dismissing it as rhetorics or out of general conservatism. Your skeptical system-2 is "biased" against it, it prevents updates. Now we relax beliefs, and in the "anarchic brain" quantity overwhelms quality. You gasp: "how could I go about my life while complicit in this!" and repent. What a glorious revolution of the mind, in the interests of those who control the narrative!  </p>
      <p>Scott writes: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Speaking of Carhart-Harris’ overenthusiasm for psychedelics running a little ahead of the evidence, the paper ends with a weird section comparing the hierarchial structure of the brain to the hierarchical structure of society, and speculating that just as psychedelics cause an “anarchic brain” where the highest-level brain structures fail to “govern” lower-level activity, so they may cause society to dissolve or something [...] Sure, whatever.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>No, not "whatever". If <strong>I</strong> were under influence now, I'd scream "don't you fucking notice what they're trying to do? It's not a damn joke! And anarchism is not even a real belief system, it's precisely an engineered bludgeon to destroy societies!"</p>
      <p>Don't underestimate these people. Oxytocin+psilocybin is one hell of a combination to propose just like that, "off the top of my head". They don't care about ethics as colloquially understood, and may come across as goofy tryhards at times, but they are smart and know what they're doing.<br />
Russian revolutionaries also weren't as intellectually rigorous as they were made out to be, yet it was proven to be enough.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>