<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-08-23T15:54:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/iexnnx/smallscale_question_sunday_for_the_week_of_august/g2lfst6/</link>
  <title>Why Do You Date?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>This is normal to a certain degree, but as is to be expected in a dating relationship, they want to see me more and more; and I keep jealously guarding my alone time.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Here is a simple question for you: why do you date at all?</p>
      <p>You have described it as "fun," you describe certain kinds of interpersonal attention as "enjoyable," but if you are dating <em>because</em> it is fun and enjoyable, there is a good chance that what you mostly enjoy is the novelty of a new person.  Analytically, this cannot last, not ever.  Nothing is new forever.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I keep jealously guarding my alone time.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>"Love" is a slippery concept, many different things to many different people, but historically a central feature of love has been self-sacrifice.  When you are willing to watch a movie you doubt you will enjoy, because someone you care about wants to <em>watch it with you</em>, to share the experience, that is a small sort of love.  When you think of someone else's comfort before you think of your own, when you do the work of tolerating someone else's flaws and they do the same for you--love is fundamentally interpersonal.  There are lots of selfish reasons to <em>get into</em> a relationship.  But there are fewer selfish reasons to <em>stay</em> in a relationship.  Long-term familial bonds, as between husband and wife or parent and child, are about committing a portion of oneself to the well-being of someone else.  Ideally it is a reciprocal commitment!</p>
      <p>And often it is a commitment grounded in a larger project.  Historically this has most often been something like "have children and raise them."  In the 20th century, Western civilization decided to spend a lot of time talking about "alternative" family arrangements, we developed a vast lexicon of descriptors for household makeup, so as not to needlessly distress the childless, the single-parents, the same-sex parents, and so forth.  But it is still true around the world that most children are raised by a mother and a father.  Perhaps with the help of others also!  But the separation of long-term romance and child-raising (broadly facilitated by the advent of reliable birth control) has turned "dating," for many people, into a purely hedonic pursuit: am I having fun?  If yes, go again!  If no, find a different amusement.</p>
      <p>There is nothing fundamentally objectionable about this, I think, if you look inside yourself and decide that a string of (comparatively) short-term romantic relationships is all you want in terms of "family" life.  But if you want something else, I submit, you will need to be willing to undertake the <em>work</em> of getting what you would prefer to have--willing to make the sacrifices that get you somewhere else.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"That girl is swell, she's pretty and intelligent and we have a good time together; however I really feel like what I want to do right now is finish Alasdair Gray's <em>Lanark</em>."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Something of an aside, but speaking as someone in a relationship older than most redditors: after you have committed yourself to a person and a mutual project (be that raising children or simply building a life together), it is common to find that what you want to do is finish Alasdair Gray's <em>Lanark</em> while sitting in the same room where your love is knitting, or playing <em>Doom</em>, or making dinner.  It is not so much a matter of whether you have a good time together, though you may often do that--it is more a question of whether time is better spent together, even when you are not engaged in the same activity.</p>
      <p>Perhaps that is not the life you are looking for.  But you seem to be looking for <em>something</em>, so I thought I might at least point out the possibility that you are getting in your own way by thinking too much about your enjoyment of dating itself, rather than the ostensible <em>purpose</em> of dating--which is still, in most human cultures, a chance to get to know someone sufficiently to decide whether you want to keep them around even after the novelty wears off, whether you want to entwine your lives into the project of one life being lived together by two (or more!) people.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>