<post>
  <author>procrastinationrs</author>
  <date>2020-08-23T04:08:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ib82ju/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_17_2020/g2jvz6g/</link>
  <title>Pseudo-Irony</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>All these seem to share a quality that should be referred to as "fauxrony" but isn't. (That term isn't widely used but seems to refer to failed efforts at irony.) Let's call it "pseudo-irony". </p>
      <p>Irony is a dominant form of expression in US and UK culture (and many others). Genuine (or maybe <em>prototypical</em>) irony involves stating a falsehood that, when understood, points at a related truth. It also (often) provides "ironic distance" -- the speaker or writer is understood as not approving of the unspoken truth picked out by the falsehood and therefore not responsible for it.</p>
      <p>Irony sometimes creates a hall-of-mirrors effect that makes it difficult to discuss and pin down. I think it's at least arguable that the term "ironic" has come to refer to things said with the relevant subtle changes in tone and emphasis, regardless of the ultimate accuracy of the statement. This sort of makes sense because specific forms of "irony" can die in the sense of "dead metaphor". So once it's common enough in the culture one can use dead irony <em>ironically</em>, and now, due to the double layering, one is literally expressing a truth, although a "dead truth". </p>
      <p>Pseudo-irony is different, but parasitic on the difficult-to-pin-down aspect of irony. It consists of using means of expressing irony (those subtle changes in tone and emphasis) to express a) a truth b) that one has some responsibility for. The ultimate benefit of this form of expression is that it still provides some "distance" by convention, sort of like an unspoken "what ya gonna do?" but even less likely to prompt an objection. I can't tell if this applies to the last meme -- I don't know enough about the context -- but it seems to be what's going on with the other two. </p>
      <p>("This but unironically" can be said either ironically or pseudo-ironically, to refer to something originally said either ironically, pseudo-ironically, or straightforwardly, so it doesn't really cut at a joint.)</p>
      <p>The most forum-salient form of pseudo-irony I can think of is that once before he reversed a permanent ban on ssc.com Scott Alexander alluded to the likeliness of his doing so because of that user's popularity on the forum, and the many expressed objections to the ban. This was expressed in the style of irony but was almost certainly why he eventually did it. The pseudo-irony functioned to forestall the natural questions the action would otherwise raise about the overall project, with all its earnest sanctimony about truth-seeking and neutrality. (Sorry, I don't have a link and don't think discussing the specific specifics would be productive.)</p>
      <p>(Edit: added missing word "forestall".)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>