<post>
  <author>UAnchovy</author>
  <date>2020-08-19T10:05:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ib82ju/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_17_2020/g234m5p/</link>
  <title>To What Extent Are Shared Values Needed?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I suppose I should also add that 'the Bible' here can be shorthand for an awful lot of religious language, liturgy, and so on. I can remember when I was young being shocked to discover that my neighbour wasn't able to recite the Lord's Prayer from memory. He didn't even know <em>how it went -</em> he didn't recognise it when I prompted him. I knew that his family wasn't that religious, but even so, I expected the Lord's Prayer to be a universal touchstone.</p>
      <p>Anyway...</p>
      <p>I don't see any deliberate attempt to create a replacement. There is no attempt to create a 'decolonised canon' or a 'global canon'. </p>
      <p>I wonder if this is the influence of postmodernism? (In the technical sense, not in the oh-no-cultural-Marxists-sense.) That is, one of the hallmarks of postmodernist/poststructuralist thought is a suspicion of grand narratives, of any totalising account of what it means to be human. As such any book or collection of books that purports to offer a stable insight into what it means to be human is suspect - and in need of deconstruction.</p>
      <p>There is no attempt to create an alternative canon, because the objection is not to the works in the canon, but to the very idea of a canon. Trying to unify society around a shared canon is <em>inherently</em> totalising, inherently an act of aggression. A canon can only existed in a shared culture, which is to say a sort of <em>mono</em>culture that by definition must assert itself <em>over</em> cultural diversity.</p>
      <p>So I don't think the decolonisers, so to speak, have any substitute. A substitute would just be trading one imperialism for another. I suspect the decolonised endgame is a kaleidoscope of canons, an infinite array of diverse cultures and sacred texts, constantly encountering one another: the eternal joy of novelty.</p>
      <p>The question I would raise in response is whether such a vision is compatible with a robust concept of civil society. I suspect the decolonising/multicultural approach has actually not interrogated itself ruthlessly enough (isn't deconstruction itself an ideology or grand narrative? isn't multiculturalism itself a cultural ideal?), and what it actually has in practice is an assumed set of universal values, with superficial cultural differences sitting on top. There's a failure to reckon with how deep the cultural diversity goes in practice. </p>
      <p>(This is also, incidentally, a question I have about Scott's Archipelago: the many diverse communities are lovely, but he envisions the Archipelago as intensely patriotic. Everyone supposedly has the values of their chosen island, but then also a set of meta-values that constitute loyalty to the whole Archipelago. But where do those meta-values come from? How can they possibly be sustained?)</p>
      <p>Thus the question for me, then, is to what extent are shared cultural/spiritual/moral values necessary for people to live together, and if they are, to what extent are those values dependent on shared narratives (art, literature, philosophy, etc.) to survive?</p>
      <p>I'm not suggesting that we need to make everyone go to Sunday school by force and start memorising Shakespeare in primary school, but it still seems like we need some shared sense of identity, some common cultural ocean in which to swim together. Where's the best balance point between common identity and individual liberty?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>