<post>
  <author>BurdensomeCount</author>
  <date>2020-07-29T03:22:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/fzl2vbb/</link>
  <title>Why Have Women's Sports?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The recent posts about transgender women in sports has got me thinking: Why should we have women's sports at all rather than just one big open competition where everyone can compete? This also has the nice benefit of getting rid of the transgender sports question completely since everyone is free to compete without regard to gender.</p>
      <p>The arguments I hear for women's sports is that women are naturally weaker/slower than men on average and this is due to their genetics. Combined with the fast tail decay of a Gaussian distribution this means that if we held only open contests there would probably never be a women who makes it to the top levels of her sport. I agree with the reasoning thus far and agree that if we did this female athletes would by and large disappear except for maybe a few niche sports like gymnastics where other factors are more important.</p>
      <p>However just like how you don't choose your gender but it influences how good you are at sports there are many many other similar factors too. For example South Asians and black people are far less likely to have the V shape torso necessary for becoming a world class swimmer. Hence why pretty much all the swimming records are held by white people and Olympic finals are almost exclusively populated by them. So just like how being born a women means you won't really be able to compete with white men in swimming, being born Indian relegates you to pretty much the same fate.</p>
      <p>In fact India as a country does abysmally at the Olympics (2 medals total in 2016,one silver and one bronze) for a country with almost 1.4 billion people. Furthermore it is pretty clearly established that the genetics of Indian people means they do not have the genetic capacity to do be physically hyper fit in the same way whites can (this is so extreme that for Indians the recommended healthy BMI is &lt;= 22.9 instead of 25, since extra weight they put on is far more likely to become fat than muscle than for white people).</p>
      <p>However you never hear of a special Indians only category at the Olympics and anyone who suggested it would be considered as out of their mind. The typical argument would be that elite sports is not meant to be fair but they showcase the best of the best. But in that case why have women's sports, why should all the myraid of other unfairness's in sports (race, height, body build, speed at which you can eliminate lactic acid etc) be dismissed with a simple "Life ain't fair" while women get their own competitions for the same reasons that if you were to apply to race would get you laughed at and summarily dismissed?</p>
      <p>To me this sounds like female privilege and a vestige of a long gone era where people had other reasons for segregating by gender (e.g. modesty etc.) that no longer apply. As society moves away from a binary male female split I think it would be best if we did away with the idea of women's sports, especially at the elite level. Sure, this doesn't mean they can't play them at lower levels and if there was a valid reason (such as being tackled by a bigger man being dangerous in a contact sport) they could even have leagues that forbade anyone (male or female) with more than a certain amount of body mass. In general stratifying leagues by ability rather than gender would make a more equitable experience for everyone, and also put an end to the current dilemma trans people face.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>