<post>
  <author>Capital_Room</author>
  <date>2020-07-31T21:55:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/fzx4wbe/</link>
  <title>We Cannot "Solve" Poor Condition of Back Row Americans By Bringing All to the Front Row</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm reminded here of some bits from Chris Arnade's <em>Dignity</em>, which I recently read (my mom insisted), and which also intersect with some other discussions here, particularly DeBoer on education.</p>
      <p>Arnade makes the distinction between "Front Row" (of the classroom) and "Back Row" America (basically the same division Murray points to in <em>Coming Apart</em>) — those smart, credentialed strivers who do well in school and in bureaucratized environments, and fit much of that Smithsonian "white culture" versus those who don't. And that Back Row America suffers not just from material poverty, but increasingly from a lack of <em>dignity</em> — the dominant Front Row America sees their values as worthless, scorns their refusal to leave their communities and assimilate, and mock them for clinging to religion and tradition (their primary remaining source of meaning and dignity) — and with associated dysfunctions (drugs, unstable and dysfunctional relationships, etc.) often a product of the resulting anomie, pain, and despair.</p>
      <p>Arnade points out in his chapter on religion, when discussing churches as sources of aid, that the secular providers of aid are built and staffed by Front Row Americans, resulting in rules-laden systems that Back Row Americans struggle to navigate "like mice in a maze." He points out, in the chapter on why people aren't so enthusiastic to abandon dying Back Row towns and communities, that not only does successfully relocating require more resources and skills than many Front Row Americans think, and require separating from family and community, but that it requires learning to navigate an entirely different culture, that of Front Row America. And that it's <em>understandable</em> that not everyone, Black or White, <em>wants</em> to abandon their way of life in favor of assimilating to a foreign culture.</p>
      <p>But most relevant was in the chapter on racism:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The system isn’t just legally rigged against them; it is rigged against their entire worldview. It is rigged against people who find meaning from place and from faith. It is a system that says you cannot reject anyone based on the color of their skin, but you can and should reject those without the proper credentials, and minorities rarely start with the proper credentials.</p>
        <p>It is a system that offers only an extraordinarily narrow path, requiring one to be uprooted from family and home, and then buy into the front row worldview, It is a system especially hard on minorities who suffer from the least access to credentials.</p>
        <p>The front row when it views the problems faced by minorities doesn't bend, redefine, or adjust their definition of success. They rarely reevaluate their own values, their own worldview, their own priorities. They rarely look inward at the status quo they have constructed and its narrow and rigid definition of success. They rarely ask if maybe their narrow definition of success, narrow definition of value, is itself exclusionary.</p>
        <p>Instead they tell minorities, like they tell the entire back row, that they need to readjust their values, readjust their worldview, and try to join the front row. They do this by offering a ew of them help via an accelerated pathway to the credentials they have.</p>
        <p>Like anyone from the back row, many minorities don't necessarily want to buy into the front row world. They don't want to leave their family and change where they live, who they are, what they believe, what they like, how they act, what they care for, what they value.</p>
        <p>In the black community the term "acting white" captures some of this, but it is larger than just how you behave; it is changing what you believe. It requires not just "acting front row" but becoming front row. Given the absurdly narrow path available, given the overwhelming amount stacked against them, that is something most can't do. It is also something many don't care to do anyway—and for good reason.</p>
        <p>The direct solution we offer for minorities is affirmative action, an accelerated boost to the front row for a lucky few, an although justifiable in the short term, it is a Band-Aid for system needing surgery. For one thing, it still presumes that the main problem is a lack of education or credentialed achievement, impaling that people who value less measurable forms of meaning get what’s coming to them. For another, affirmative action inflames racial tensions as it drives another wedge between the white and black members of the back row.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In short, the traditional education-centric approaches from many on the left, much like "bootstraps" narratives from many on the right, ultimately try to "solve" the problem of the poor condition of Back Row Americans by <em>attempting to turn them into Front Row Americans</em>, with the unquestioned assumption that the latter is clearly the better way to live.</p>
      <p>But, as DeBoer notes, that's a doomed project, because not everyone is <em>able</em> to be properly educated into the Front Row. Add in Arnade's point about those additional who are not <em>willing</em> to abandon their values and assimilate. So, how do we provide not just monetary hand-outs, but <em>respect</em> and <em>dignity</em> to Back Row America? That is, assuming one is not willing to just "bite the bullet," declare Front Row culture objectively superior to the alternatives and that those in the Back Row unable or unwilling to join it deserve whatever they get.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>