<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-08-03T00:09:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/g05oka7/</link>
  <title>The User Viewpoint Focus Series</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Posting this deliberately late on a Sunday because it's an inchoate idea and I just want to sound it out. In short, I think there are a bunch of interestingly different political and cultural perspectives on display here, but so often they're only on display in the context of reaction - e.g., leftist posters reacting to trad cons, liberals reacting to NRx posters, etc..</p>
      <p>Additionally, I think a lot of the content triggers here are themselves kind of reactive - I only get to find out about the interesting ideas and perspectives held by the people here in the context of news stories. But I'd be really interested to get a more complete sense of the worldview of posters, especially our regulars. What are <a href="/u/Darwin2500">u/Darwin2500</a>'s core values? What does <a href="/u/Ilforte">u/Ilforte</a> think is the future of Western civilization? What does <a href="/u/TracingWoodgrains">u/TracingWoodgrains</a> think are the deepest faultlines of the modern culture war? Which stock options does <a href="/u/naraburns">u/naraburns</a> recommend? What does <a href="/u/ZorbaTHut">u/ZorbaTHut</a> think about the future of entertainment? What is <a href="/u/Lykurg480">u/Lykurg480</a>'s prognosis for the relationship between the humanities and the sciences?</p>
      <p>A final factor in all of this is that I actually really like forums in which there are clear recognisable personalities; it reminds me of the good old days of 90s/early 00s web forums. I know we're a big community in which people come and go, but anything that adds a bit more humanity to viewpoints is good, in my book.</p>
      <p>So here's my tentative suggestion: how do people feel about the idea of "user viewpoint focus" posts once a week or so? Sort of like a mini-interview that regulars would eventually be asked to do? Obviously OPSEC might be a concern insofar as we'd be asking people to pin their colours to a mast, but the hope would be to aim for big philosophical perspectives rather than more toxoplasmic specifics. In my head, the ideal way this would work is that we'd have something like 3-5 standardised questions like the above that everyone would get asked and which would help clarify the genuine contours of disagreement among the different strains of thought in the subreddit. However, for fun and variation, it'd also be cool to let each invited poster choose a couple of questions of their own.</p>
      <p>Of course there's the issue of who we'd ask to do this. First, it should probably be on a volunteer or nomination basis to begin with, maybe with a lottery element. Second, at the risk of sounding elitist, I think we'd obviously aim to solicit opinions in the first instance from people with lots of QCs. At the very least, they're more likely than average to provide interesting and well-written answers. And third, we'd look for viewpoint diversity.</p>
      <p>I don't know - as I say, an inchoate idea for now, with lots of details to be ironed out. But fuck, I'd love to get some more 'complete' perspectives from you all. Consider this an initial probe - corrections very welcome!</p>
      <p>
        <strong>EDIT:</strong> as for practicalities, it occurs to me that the simplest way to proceed at the outset (and with minimal mod involvement/workload) may be for me to inaugurate a simple "chain interview" system where I just decide the first person to interview with some starting questions, they in turn decide someone to interview, etc.. But would welcome feedback and <em>particularly</em> suggestions for questions before I start!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>