<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-07-29T22:57:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/fzo66v6/</link>
  <title>Defying the Data on Trans Athletes</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Oof. One of the things I hate most is to <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/vrHRcEDMjZcx5Yfru/i-defy-the-data">defy the data</a> due to its implausibility in light of my priors. How pleasant would it have been to blithely trust "yay-science", and to dance hand in hand with all right-thinking folks, to enjoy the march of Progress! But it is necessary to be paranoid in a world of scientific activism, I'm afraid; and while she might even be correct with regards to some specific fields, there probably are competitions where you just can't get away from male advantage in basic skeletal frame. We could go over the methodology, but I'd leave this to better-learned folks and use the sniff test.  </p>
      <p>First things first: in her <a href="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/1e6a/bd2c1e03ba88e9ac8da94ea1d69ff3f4878a.pdf">2015 paper</a>, N=8. It's endurance running - one of the sports where, as she correctly notes, body/bone mass is a disadvantage:  <em>It should be noted that these results are only valid for distance running. Transgender women are  taller  and  larger,  on  average,  than  46,XX  women (Gooren  and  Bunck,  2004,  425-429),  and  these differences probably would result in performance advantages in events in which height and strength  are  obvious  precursors  to  success</em>. (<strong>thank you Joanna Harper</strong>). <del>On top of that, <em>most  of  the  runners  in  the  study  were  more  than  30  years  old</em> - so we're hardly talking about peak competitors who might "dominate" the publicly visible sports scene.</del></p>
      <p>Here's the juicy part: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Many  sports  followed  the  lead  of  the  IOC,  and  in  subsequent  years  there  have  been  transgender women competing in sports such as golf (Mianne Bagger and Lana Lawless), cycling (Natalie  Van  Gogh,  Michelle  Dumaresq,  and  Kristin  Worley),  martial  arts  (Nong  Toom,  and  Fallon  Fox),  and  basketball  (Gabrielle  Ludwig).  None  of  these  women  has  been  particularly  successful at the highest levels of sport after gender reassignment, and one could argue that this lack  of  success  over  ten  years  would  be  a  strong  indication  of  the  fairness  of  permitting  transgender women to compete against cisgender women.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>No idea about most of those people, but there are more interesting names now: off the top of my head, the weightlifter <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Laurel_Hubbard">Laurel Hubbard</a> (New Zealand junior record, then 14! years of obscurity, then transition and, after 5 more years, Oceania Gold and World Silver medals) and the infamous cyclist <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Veronica_Ivy">Veronica Ivy/Rachel McKinnon</a> (world records). The name that jumped out at me, however, was Fallon Fox. Yeah, <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Fallon_Fox">that Fallon Fox</a>. In 2013, </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Joe Rogan opposed Fallon Fox receiving licensing, saying, "First of all, she's not really a she. She's a transgender, post-op person. The operation doesn't shave down your bone density. It doesn't change. You look at a man's hands and you look at a woman's hands and they're built different. They're just thicker, they're stronger, your wrists are thicker, your elbows are thicker, your joints are thicker. Just <strong>the mechanical function of punching, a man can do it much harder than a woman can</strong>, period."<a href="http://bleacherreport.com/articles/1573044-ufc-joe-rogan-to-transgender-mma-fighter-fallon-fox-youre-a-man">8</a>* </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Well, he received a lot of flak for this utterly unscientific and crude opinion (you probably remember the Bernie endorsement brouhaha). I guess he should have asked Jamie to pull up some scientific consensus to educate himself, instead of transphobic propaganda! Anyway, come 2014, Fox retired with 5-1 record, since: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>During Fox's fight against Tamikka Brents, Brents <strong>suffered a concussion, an orbital bone fracture, and seven staples to the head in the 1st round.</strong> After her loss, Brents took to social media to convey her thoughts on the experience of fighting Fox: "I've fought a lot of women and have never felt the strength that I felt in a fight as I did that night. I can't answer whether it's because she was born a man or not because I'm not a doctor. I can only say, I've never felt so overpowered ever in my life and I am an abnormally strong female in my own right," she stated. <strong>"Her grip was different, I could usually move around in the clinch against other females but couldn't move at all in Fox's clinch...</strong>"<a href="http://www.cagepotato.com/after-being-tkod-by-fallon-fox-tamikka-brents-says-transgender-fighters-in-mma-just-isnt-fair/">18</a></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Sorry, I can't not quote the very next paragraph because nothing is ever a coincidence: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Eric <strong>Vilain</strong>, the director of the Institute For Society And Genetics at UCLA, worked with the Association of Boxing Commissions when they wrote their policy on transgender athletes. He stated in Time magazine that "Male to female transsexuals have significantly less muscle strength and bone density, and higher fat mass, than males" ... When asked if Fox could, nonetheless, be stronger than her competitors, Vilain replied that it was possible, but noted that "sports is made up of competitors who, by definition, have advantages for all kinds of genetics reasons" [and cackled].</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Says Fallon Fox:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Remember when commentators said Jackie Robinson had an unfair advantage because black people had "larger heel bones" than the white men he was competing with? Are we repeating history yet again with <strong>bogus bone claims</strong>? Can we couple these bogus claims with Rogan's horrible language that was aimed at me from the video I put out last week? I'm a transgender woman. I deserve equal treatment and respect to other types of women. I </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>So, in the end, have we noticed the skulls yet?  </p>
      <p>Chances are, you don't have to go all the way to skulls. <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/782557v1.full.pdf">In 2019</a>, there's been a paper comparing MtF and FtM transgendered persons who do not compete in sports, concluding that <em>Baseline muscle volume correlated highly with strength (R&gt;0.75), yet the relative change in muscle volume and strength correlated only moderately (R=0.65 in TW and R=0.32 in TM). The absolute levels of muscle volume and knee extension strength after the intervention still favored the TW.  ...Despite the robust changes in lower-limb muscle mass and strength in TM, the TW still had an absolute advantage following 12months of gender-affirming hormone treatment.</em></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <em>Ivy argued that there was no evidence that being born male gave an advantage in the race [...]</em>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>0HPLovecraft, on the other hand, <a href="https://twitter.com/0x49fa98/status/1281386724212572168?s=20">argued</a> that <em>Knowledge constrains action; Foucauldian power operates by means of knowledge; the sovereign sets the null hypothesis. Cathedral power justifies itself thus: "there is no evidence that my truth isn't true".</em></p>
      <p>On the other <em>other</em> hand, <a href="https://cyclingmagazine.ca/sections/news/canadian-becomes-first-transgender-women-to-win-a-female-world-title-on-the-track/">you don't need evidence either.</a></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“We cannot have a woman legally recognized as a trans woman in society, and not be recognized that way in sports,” McKinnon explained. “Focusing on performance advantage is largely irrelevant because this is a rights issue. We shouldn’t be worried about trans people taking over the Olympics. We should be worried about their fairness and human rights instead.” McKinnon continued by explaining that it’s not possible to measure the unfair advantage transgender women have so that should be irrelevant to the conversation on whether they are allowed to compete.<br />
“This is bigger than sports and it’s about human rights,” McKinnon said in USA Today. “By catering to cisgender people’s views, that furthers transgender people’s oppression. <strong>When it comes to extending rights to a minority population, why would we ask the majority?</strong> I bet a lot of white people were pissed off when we desegregated sports racially and allowed black people. But they had to deal with it.”</p>
      </blockquote>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>