<post>
  <author>Njordsier</author>
  <date>2020-07-31T14:59:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/fzvbdoa/</link>
  <title>What To Expect With a Democratic Trifecta</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Remember that with a Republican trifecta, the two major legislative projects<sup>1</sup> of the 2017-2018 term were 1) repeal Obamacare, and 2) tax cuts. Both were conducted under budget reconciliation rules which prevented the filibuster, and even then one failed to pass, and the one that did pass did so narrowly after a lot of compromise and concessions.</p>
      <p>The most powerful senators are the ones in the majority party who can credibly threaten to buck their party to extract concessions. For example, Lisa Murkowski got a bunch of pork for Alaska while threatening to vote against the tax cut bill.</p>
      <p>If Democrats take the Senate, it will be by flipping red and purple states with candidates who promise to put the interests of their constituents over the party, like they did in the House in 2018, and these freshmen will not be setting out to aggravate the moderates who put them there. Even if the filibuster is gone, expect any legislation that actually gets passed to be very watered down from what the overpromising fringes of the party whip up the base over.</p>
      <p>An example: under a Democratic trifecta, I expect a bill that forms a committee to study reparations to pass (unless puritans on the fringe vote against it because it "doesn't go far enough"), but I expect an actual reparations implementation to stall out even without the filibuster. I expect a "universal background checks" bill to pass, but don't expect a mandatory buyback or blanket ban on all guns.</p>
      <p>And if a hypothetical Democratic trifecta is too reckless with passing partisan legislation, expect the conservative backlash to end the trifecta quickly and take back the House.</p>
      <p>The kind of legislation you can expect a Democratic trifecta to pass will be very different from what the House currently passes under the expectation that Mitch McConnell won't even hold a vote on it. The Republican Congress voted to repeal Obamacare dozens of times under Obama, but as soon as they got a President who <em>wouldn't</em> veto it, they couldn't get it done, even under filibuster-free budget reconciliation rules. Even when Mitch McConnell trolled the Democrats by holding a vote on the House-passed Green New Deal resolution, Democratic senators abstained in protest. Once it's common knowledge that legislation passed in one house will actually be voted on by the other, and that legislation that passes both houses will go to the President's desk, the dynamics change drastically.</p>
      <p>I'd personally like to see the filibuster stay, but require actually standing up and holding the floor indefinitely to perform. Make it a personally costly move rather than the default. If something's worth subverting the Senate majority over, it would be good politics to be seen making a Leslie Knope-style grandstand.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Not only DC and Puerto Rico, but you can also split existing states - so if, as this plan suggests, the Democrats wanted to split up California, or New York, or Maine, they could - as long as those states' overwhelmingly democratic legislatures voted in favor. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'm highly confident that even if DC becomes a state, we won't be breaking up California or New York to pack the Senate. State legislatures won't be enthusiastic about limiting their own power (by making their own jurisdictions smaller) just to own the conservatives. And Puerto Rico would need to consent to becoming a state, which they don't seem unified on, and even if they did, they wouldn't necessarily send reliably Democratic senators. (Their non-voting representative in the House is a Republican!)</p>
      <ol>
        <li>I guess you could also throw in the Supreme Court and lower court confirmations, which are also exempt from the filibuster.</li>
      </ol>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>