<post>
  <author>NotSoIncandenza</author>
  <date>2020-08-01T01:09:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/fzxuqym/</link>
  <title>Potential For War Over Race and IQ</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I have been thinking a lot about the three-pronged meltdown of the last few months (Covid/Floyd/Economy) and, in turn, the rolling wave of crisis and revolt it's provoked throughout the media. And in turn, I read this review today, of a book I am looking forward to:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/31/books/review-caste-isabel-wilkerson-origins-of-our-discontents.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/31/books/review-caste-isabel-wilkerson-origins-of-our-discontents.html</a>
      </p>
      <p>I was struck by how hyperbolic and effusive it was, given the book's controversial claim, at least was published in the NYT Mag (that America treats Black people as a caste akin to....Jews in Nazi Germany), and it occurred to me:</p>
      <p>Does anyone else feel like the ground is being seeded for an all-encompassing war over Race and IQ over the next few years? That this may in fact become a defining issue of the next few years?</p>
      <p>Let me make clear my priors. I used to think, like most *right-thinking* people, that the purpose of journalism is to tell the public the truth and thus,  we need free speech to engage in a collective act of reasoning and the scientific method and we must allow for diverse viewpoints so that we can all learn from each other, etc.</p>
      <p>And I don't think that's wrong, per se (I think most journalists think they are trying to do this!).  But that's maybe not the best way of looking at it. I think that's a better description of the scientific process, which is slow, collective, peer-reviewed, etc. I think in journalism, at least in American journalism, there are these major fundamental questions which dominate the news cycle and its discontents, and most writers want to "play in that sandbox" while the question is "hot".</p>
      <p>And while over time, we maybe reach some collective and agreed upon knowledge about the realities of certain questions (Iraq: Bad idea! Gay marriage: Good idea! Climate change: real!), while the questions are "hot", there is an extraordinary amount of pressure to line up with all your colleagues who agree with you, on one side of the ball or the other and essentially scrum, rugby-style. Particularly given how closely the two parties now align with the two "sides" of American journalism--and the growing interest journalists have in advancing political agendas as opposed to.....writing stuff?--it feels like journalists are more interested in "being on the right side" of defining fights of the day, not necessarily "telling the truth".</p>
      <p>Ordinarily, I thought the issue of race and IQ was far beyond the pale for most people, and honestly, not all that interesting. (The science will say whatever it does, whenever it does.) But there is now a growing brigade of credentialed and respected journalists and academics who are staking their territory on "The NYT has gone too far; they won't tell the truth about things". Many of these people have wagered their incomes on such a claim, literally: subscribe to my newsletter because the NYT won't publish me!</p>
      <p>More importantly, there is an ever-strengthening wing, in numbers, reach, and temperature, of "woke" reformers, and many Black Americans, particularly those in high-profile professional occupations, feel suddenly energized and entitled to reform and reign over the commanding heights of their professions. (It was tweeted today the NYT union demanded 24% of employees be Black by 2025, in keeping with NYC demographics. To give one example.) These sectors are hugely competitive, mostly because they are full of highly motivated, highly successful, hardworking and ambitious people, who are mostly White--almost all of whom advertise merely that they are very liberal and down for the cause.  Whether or not anyone wants to admit it, there is an enormous demand to simply make this stuff go away--whether that demand is latent, whispered or even shouted in private emails :p. A counter-narrative, the many of these differences and discrepancies are simply caused by biology itself, suddenly seems very enticing, has enough evidence, and is a perfect opponent for the woke mores of the moment. What was previously relegated to "tiny advances in knowledges of the genome" becomes center court at Wimbledon: debates about fairness, truth, equality and the very nature of the country.</p>
      <p>Also, I just don't see Trump winning a second term and the Republican party is going to want to move on and forward. So on a basic level, the media is gonna need some new things to fight about.</p>
      <p>Usually, attempts to dive into the dregs of race and IQ can be answered with a shrug and a "really, why should we publish this? Now, with ___ going on?". But there is a growing cadre of motivated journalists with their own platforms, who have given up their establishment cred. There is no one to censor or not publish them because now they publish themselves and publicize each other. Their organizing ethos is "nothing sacred, and always telling the truth, unlike the woke left media"--and this topic is the Kahuna. (It's so easy to see how overstepping the science will happen, simply because of the temptation this topic brings, in terms of attention and controversy.) The establishment media can try to denounce them, but that will involve drawing further attention to the issue, which only publicizes it and encourages people to line up on both sides, etc. (See above.) And the relevance of these issues, with a Black President or, worse President Trump, is easy to brush off, but with a President Biden overstepping with some diversity-based initiative in the midst of woke mania is another thing entirely. (I can just hear some clever journalist saying, "If all we're going to do is talk about group differences, why can't we talk about group differences?") Further, given the Harper's letter, and the response to it, I can see some academics publicly putting themselves on the "wrong" side of the debate, if only because there has been such a clear line drawn between the wokeness of certain parts of the left and their traditional, liberal values.</p>
      <p>Finally,  I really worry that the organizing principles of the modern liberal ethos are going to get swallowed by this debate in a way that is difficult to understand. If you truly believe that all people are created equally and that race is a distraction and a hinderance to moral behavior, you can just treat everyone as individuals and ignore whatever group differences may or may not exist. But if you have gotten away from race-blindness, have placed all your intellectual cards on "loving science", are exhausted and threatened by the woke agenda, and  most importantly, believe intelligence is the cardinal virtue (and regularly snub your nose at Trump voters and the like, by saying simply, "they're dumb"), I think the dark side of the argument may have some real impact. Although it will never be spoken aloud, I think the number of powerful and exhausted white liberals who may read this stuff and have it drive their thinking is....not small.</p>
      <p>Thoughts?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>