<post>
  <author>ridrip</author>
  <date>2020-07-30T20:59:55Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/fzs9u8d/</link>
  <title>Why People Insist On Talking About Genetics and Group Differences</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Murray is saying he's agnostic about a range of possibilities (which often doesn't include the possibility that there's a genetic advantage to people of African ancestry), but I'm saying there's just really no good science about this. I think where the more major disagreement is - what, then, is the risk-to-benefit ratio of spending time pontificating about that possibility in the absence of any real scientific data? There's one set of values - "We should be able to talk openly and honestly about anything, and this is one possibility though we don't have good data, but let's speculate - and it's our ability to talk about any possibility in the world that's prioritized" and there's another different value that people weight - "What are the harms done by that speculation?" Even if it doesn't necessarily feed into, is it at least consistent with some really ugly racist views about the inferiority in black people? So I think some people push back on this - "Well, why should we talk about something on which we are scientifically agnostic that just so happens to reinforce a really ugly stereotype?"</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think this is where the holes in her thinking are. Which I suppose is why its the main point of disagreement between her and Harris. The issue here is that she is assuming speculation only works in one direction as far as harms go. Speculation is going to happen regardless. The differences in outcomes for different groups are too obvious and well documented for any society interested in equality not to speculate.</p>
      <p>When you taboo speculation in one category you drive all of that speculation into another. It's true that if group genetics aren't the cause of the gaps in achievement between groups that pushing this idea could harm underachieving groups. However, the opposite is also true. If group differences are the cause, then speculating it's all about environment and trying to balance outcomes based on those factors could be actively harming people. </p>
      <p>We've spent 50+ years chasing after every conceivable environmental difference that could be causing the differences in outcome, the largest state in our country is on the verge of openly removing language about equality and equal treatment under the law from its books so it can overtly, de jure discriminate against specific groups to try and balance these outcomes. If the genetic theory turns out to be true people like Harden have done serious harms to people in society.</p>
      <p>I think another issue people are missing and also the source of all the "If Murray and Harris don't want genetics to be the explanation for group differences why do they talk about them so much." Is that Murray and Harris here aren't saying don't speculate about environmental factors. Harden is saying "we don't know what the source of differences in outcomes are, but don't speculate about genetics as that causes harms." Murray and Harris are more like, "we don't know the source of different group outcomes, speculating about both should be allowed."</p>
      <p>Reality is Harris and Murray here are choosing the option that minimizes harms. By allowing speculation in either direction you allow for criticism in both directions. When you have a choice to make and you don't know which option is correct and both options could cause harms you want to be careful and critical of both choices. Disallowing speculation in one direction eliminates a good deal of criticism of one option which makes people less hesitant to push that option and accelerates any harms it causes.</p>
      <p>Murray and Harris aren't pushing for genetics as an explanation for group outcomes because they personally prefer that explanation. They're pushing for it because they believe that allowing speculation in both directions allows us to be skeptical in either direction and not make hasty, poorly informed policy decisions that cause major harm to ethnic groups. If we lived in a mirror society where all speculation about environmental causes for group outcomes was disallowed I feel confident saying they'd be talking mostly about environmental causes rather than genetic ones.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>