<post>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2020-08-01T17:16:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hym5xb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_27_2020/g002e24/</link>
  <title>Do Journalists Believe What They Write?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The OP is right, journalists believe they're searching for the truth. They believe what they're writing is true.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You are just asserting this without evidence and in direct contradiction to my overall experience. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gzh35ADgc64">I disagree</a>.</p>
      <p>The most obvious counterpoint I would note is that it is very much not the case that journalists simply aren't aware of the falsity of their narratives. Readers tell them so,  pointing out their misdirection every day, in comments, in full-length responses on Medium or Quillette, on Twitter, etc. I personally have interacted with several prominent journalists and aligned academics, they've responded to me or otherwise acknowledged the response, and then have continued to either peddle the same falsities or stand silent while their co-workers have. Even the more reasonable writers, like Conor Friedersdorf, can't be relied upon to push back on his outlet's noxious and utterly pervasive false racial narratives yet clutches his pearls when Trump highlights a single instance of black on white violence:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <a href="https://twitter.com/conor64/status/1275258318055849985">Trump is seizing on and amplifying random, anomolous instances of interracial violence, needlessly inflaming racial tensions at a moment of polarization and social upheaval. This is abhorrent and irresponsible. His subordinates and children know this and should say so.</a>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>When it is pointed out to staid Connor that this is <strong><em>exactly</em></strong> his parent outlet's bread and butter, he clumsily refuses all culpability. Small wonder that The Atlantic completely removed its comment section so they could avoid pushback from members of their readership not interested in playing stupid along with their staffers</p>
      <p>For another example, <em>Vox</em>'s Matt Yglesias increasingly acknowledges Steve Sailer's commentary to his commentary, but refuses to actually incorporate those facts into his paradigm. And even he was recently <a href="https://nypost.com/2020/07/10/vox-shows-its-opposition-to-justice-and-open-debate/">castrated</a> after his boss - <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JournoList">JournoList</a> and <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/national/archive/2010/07/meet-the-new-journolist-smaller-than-the-old-journolist/60159/">Cabalist</a> progenitor  (recall, these are explicitly secret channels for journos to cooperatively craft narratives) Ezra Klein - muzzled him with a commitment to not say 'contentious' (read: narrative challenging) things on Twitter anymore</p>
      <p>Moreover, your theory of mind also requires that journalists be astoundingly stupid in the exact same ways universally across the board as well as being impervious to new information. Your frame posits that <em>every</em> mainstream journalist - from the <em>Times</em> to the <em>Post</em> to <em>The</em><em>Guardian</em> and everywhere in between - as well as all of their editors simultaneously make 'an honest mistake' where they think the appropriate comparison point for deaths by police is base population rates and yet <em>none</em> of them take this fallacy to its inexorable conclusion that police are woefully misandrist given that men are &gt;22x more likely to be killed by police than women? They're <em>all</em> exactly the precise level of stupid to get this wrong in the <em>exact</em> same way but without actually following the logic through or acknowledging it when interlocutors do so? Beggars belief</p>
      <p>And then there's just the nakedly tendentious handling of similar circumstances to account for. I'm not going to spend my Saturday compiling obvious and laughable journalistic hypocrisies for you, but stuff like <a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EW8Rg-uVAAAYIli?format=jpg&amp;name=4096x4096">Michelle Goldberg</a>'s treatment of the Kavanaugh accusations vs Biden accusations is illustrative. That's not an off the cuff reaction that happened to be inconsistent, these are professional, full-length editorials that she sits down to churn out for the premier paper in the nation and its just straight up partisan hackery. And Goldberg singed the Harper's letter! She's one of the comparatively <em>less</em> mindkilled ones!</p>
      <p>Throw in treatment of Cuomo vs DeSantis for another example, where the governor in the <em>more</em> populous state is given constant flak despite having ~20% of the deaths of the guy who is all but fellated for having the worst crisis management in the country</p>
      <p>Finally, and I'm frankly surprised I have to bring this up, but just look at how they act. The entire corporate press spontaneously decided to capitalize 'Black' but keep 'white' lowercase this year. You <em>seriously</em> think that was the result of some sober etymological analysis that, in an effort to be balanced, fair, and truthful, just happened to come to such a batshit conclusion? Honestly, if you do not recognize that as plain-as-day social signaling and statement of allegiance, I view you as quite the rube</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>400 words is not enough to get to the bottom of complex economic, political or social issues. But it's just not because people are sitting around conjuring up new ways to trick the population [...] The journos you're taking issue with [are]  they're just trying to convey the facts (as best as they understand them) to you</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't think it's possible for me to disagree any more strongly. The problem with what passes for journalistic articles these days is <em>not</em> length. You can have tweets with more veracity and insight than entire thinkpieces, and, if anything, brevity would serve to sweep away the bullshit framing and insufferable social signaling that pads out their pablum. The problem is <em>content</em>, not <em>form</em>, and really the content-makers at its core. I would be interested if you have anything to support your perspective beyond 'no really, they mean well they're just irredeemably stupid in endlessly ideologically convenient ways'</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>