<post>
  <author>asdfasdflkjlkjlkj</author>
  <date>2020-05-06T18:14:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpoqeue/</link>
  <title>A Thorough Review of the Arbery Shooting</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I want to make a top-level post about the Ahmaud Arbery shooting which includes links a summary of and links to the actual relevant information in this case, including</p>
      <ol>
        <li>the <em>actual</em> police report on which nearly all speculation is being based</li>
        <li>the followup investigation</li>
      </ol>
      <p>I want to do this because I think evidence is important. I also think that too often, these sorts of hot-button topics become avatars for larger, more abstractly contentious issues (e.g. "the woke rush to judgment," "America is a racist country"), with the result that they from fall hopelessly into abstract speculation which is more or less removed from the actual facts of the particular case.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>WHAT HAPPENED</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Here is a <a href="https://int.nyt.com/data/documenthelper/6915-arbery-shooting/b52fa09cdc974b970b79/optimized/full.pdf">link</a> to the police report.</p>
      <p>Here are some relevant sections:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Upon my arrival I... I began speaking with Gregory McMichael who was a witness to the incident. McMichael stated there have been several Break-ins in the neighborhood and further the suspect was caught on surveillance video. <strong>McMichael stated he was in his front yard and saw the suspect from the break-ins "hauling ass" down Satilla Drive toward Burford Drive. McMichael stated he then ran inside his house and called to Travis (McMichael) and said "Travis the guy is running down the street lets go". McMichael stated he went to his bedroom and grabbed his .357 Magnum and Travis grabbed his shotgun because they "didn't know if the male was armed or not". McMichael stated "the other night" they saw the same male and he stuck his hand down his pants which lead them to believe the male was armed.</strong></p>
        <p>McMichael stated he and Travis got in the truck and drove down Satilla Drive toward Burford Drive. <strong>McMichael stated when they arrived at the intersection of Satilla Drive and Holmes Drive, they saw the unidentified male running down Burford drive. McMichael then stated Travis drive down Burford and attempted to cut off the male. McMichael stated the unidentified male turned around and began running back the direction from which he came and "Roddy"  [</strong>"Roddy" is not listed by name as a witness but a letter from the Waycross County DA leads me to believe he is witness "Bryan, William R.", who joined the chase in his own truck] <strong>attempted to block him which was unsuccessful. McMichael stated he then jumped into the bed of the truck and he and Travis continued to Holmes in an attempt to intercept him.</strong></p>
        <p>
          <strong>McMichael stated they saw the unidentified male and shouted "stop stop, we want to talk to you". Michael stated they pulled up beside the male and shouted stop again at which time Travis exited the truck with the shotgun. McMichael stated the unidentified male began to violently attack Travis and the two men then started fighting over the shotgun at which point Travis fired a shot and then a second later there was a second shot.</strong> Michael stated the male fell face down on the pavement with his hand under his body. McMichael stated he rolled the man over to see if the male had a weapon.  </p>
        <p>I observed blood on McMichael's hands from rollingthe unidentified male over.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>So the story is, the McMichaels (Greg and Travis) see Arbery "hauling ass," suspect he's responsible for several burgleries in the area, and go out to catch him. It's not stated directly in the report, but they must have enlisted the help of "Roddy," who pursues in a separate truck.</p>
      <p>So now there's two trucks going after Arbery. The McMichaels' truck overtakes him and cuts him off. He runs the other way, but then Roddy's truck attempts to trap him. Arbery escapes and continues running.</p>
      <p>McMichaels comes back the other way and pulls up alongside Arbery, shouting for him to stop. Travis McMichaels is driving, whereas Greg is in the flatbed. They drive in front of him and stop the truck, and Travis gets out of the driver's seat toting his shotgun. At this point, Arbery runs around the truck towards Travis and begins struggling with him, eventually for the gun. He is shot and dies.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fIve50vSeLQ">Here is the video</a> of the incident, shot by Roddy himself.</p>
      <p>These are the two most important pieces of information we have to go on for the killing itself.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>THE STATE'S RESPONSE</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Greg McMichael has a connection to the DA's office: he worked there as an investigator from '82-'89. Because of this, his former boss, Jackie Johnson, recuses herself from the case. A month later, the top Waycross County prosecutor, Roger Barnhill, is reassigned to the case, but he recuses himself as well at the behest of Ahmaud's mother, who does not like that <em>his</em> son worked in the same office as Jackie Johnson and, formerly, Greg McMichael. </p>
      <p>In a <a href="https://int.nyt.com/data/documenthelper/6916-george-barnhill-letter-to-glyn/b52fa09cdc974b970b79/optimized/full.pdf">letter</a>, Barnhill denies that there is any kinship between him and the McMichaels, but asks that the Georgia Attorney General Office find him another DA who can determine whether there is sufficient evidence to bring a case against McMichaels before a Grand Jury. In the same letter, he explains why it is his professional opinion, shared with "Senior Trial Attorneys," that there are no grounds for arrest. His reasoning is that the McMichaels and Roddy "were following, in 'hot pursuit' a burglary suspect, with solid first hand probable cause, in their neighborhood, and asking/ telling him to stop. It appears their intent was to stop and hold this criminal suspect until law enforcement arrived. Under Georgia Law this is perfectly legal."</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <em>OCGA17-4-60 "A private person may arrest an offender if the offense is committed in his presence or within his immediate knowledge. If the offense is a felony and the offender is escaping or attempting to escape, a private person may arrest him upon reasonable and probable grounds of suspicion"</em>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>He further notes that they were legally entitled to carry their guns in the open, before getting to the fight itself. At first, he describes what we've all seen in the video: Arbery runs along the right side of the truck, then makes a 90-degree turn around its front and ends up in a struggle with Travis McMichael, who eventually shoots him three times. He notes that it is not actually obvious who pulled the trigger. But then he gets into the issue of who is culpable for the fight. I want to quote his evaluation directly, because I find it pretty enlightening:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Given the fact that Arbery initiated the fight, at the point Arbery grabbed the shotgun, under Georgia Law, McMichael was allowed to use deadly force to protect himself... Arbery's mental health records &amp; prior convictions help explain his apparent aggressive nature and his possible thought pattern to attack an armed man.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>(The prior convictions he's referring to are 2013 charge after he took a gun to a high-school basketball game, a shoplifting charge, and a 2018 probation violation. I haven't tracked down the mental health stuff.)</p>
      <p>This is, of course, the crux of the controversy: was Arbery aggressing them or were they aggressing Arbery? If two trucks chased Arbery down and cut him off while he was out for a jog, then it's a pretty big stretch for the occupants of those trucks to claim they were "aggressed" when he finally took action to defend himself, and it is extremely dubious that the DA immediately takes their side on the issue. If, on the other hand, the McMichaels had just caught arbery "red-handed" after committing a burglary, then suddenly, his attack on them looks far less like self-defense and far more like "trying to get away with it."</p>
      <p>The New York Times <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/26/us/ahmed-arbery-shooting-georgia.html">writes</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In a separate document, Mr. Barnhill stated that video exists of Mr. Arbery “burglarizing a home immediately preceding the chase and confrontation.” In the letter to the police, he cites a separate video of the shooting filmed by a third pursuer.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This claim has been repeated all over the news. Every piece I've seen quotes this paragraph from the Times. I cannot find any record of this separate document, and every other source I've seen says that Arbery was, in fact, just out for a jog. I am very confused about what to make of this element of the case, and I do not understand why no one is demanding that police release the video of Arbery burglarizing houses immediately prior to his shooting. The immediacy is extremely important: the Times cites a former US attorney in Georgia, who writes “The law does not allow a group of people to form an armed posse and chase down an unarmed person who they believe might have possibly been the perpetrator of a past crime."</p>
      <p>In the linked letter, Barnhill quotes the state's Use of Force in Defense and No Duty To Retreat Laws (OCGA 16-3-21 and OCGA 16-3-23.1) and recommends, "it is our conclusion there is insufficient probable cause to issue arrest warrants at this time."</p>
      <p>The case is now being handled by Tom Durden, a DA from another county. He faced pressure from activists to prosecute, and as of today, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/05/05/us/ahmaud-arbery-killing-georgia.html">it looks like the matter is headed for a grand jury</a>.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>