<post>
  <author>CriticalDuty</author>
  <date>2020-05-08T01:44:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpu0ua0/</link>
  <title>Fictional Psychopathy as Wish Fulfillment</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think a lot of fictional portrayals of psychopaths wind up being wish fulfillment by writers, or fan service, in that they reflect a desire to do antisocial things that are forbidden by moral considerations, or they reflect an inner fantasy of wealth and power that the viewer imagines he might possess if only he were sufficiently ruthless (as in the case of characters like Lex Luthor).</p>
      <p>It impugns the perversity of the audience, in other words. A good example is the series <em>Hannibal</em>. Hannibal Lecter is introduced in the series as a cruel and sadistic man with no regard for the pain of others; in the very first episode, he murders a teenage girl, removes her lungs while she's still alive and then eats them, all for no reason but to play a game with the FBI. But <em>Hannibal</em> also had a disproportionately young female fanbase that liked Mads Mikkelsen and Hugh Dancy, and so the writers molded characters to fit the tastes and sensibilities of their audience. Future episodes revolved around how elegant and refined Hannibal's murders were, how brilliant his mind and how tortured his lonely soul, and built fantasies about how he only "punished" people who probably had it coming (one particularly egregious example has Hannibal killing a politician who voted to authorize development within a habitat for endangered birds). It was all a way of giving the audience permission to like this character because he has some "redeeming" features. And aspects of psychopathy that the audience would find distinctly unappealing were scrubbed out completely; Francis Dolarhyde's habit of raping the corpses of his female victims was a detail from the book that never made it to the show, because the writers were aware of who their audience consisted of. These people are portrayed as charming because the audience wants them to be charming.</p>
      <p>Patrick Bateman isn't really meant to be seen as charming, and definitely not as rational. Bateman is severely mentally ill and has violent hallucinations, which differentiates him from characters like Lecter - in fact all of Bateman's crimes are implied to be hallucinations. The only reason he gets away with his proclivities is that the people in his professional and social circles are completely self-absorbed; his colleagues are coked-out, roided-out narcissists and his fiancée is a bimbo airhead. Anyone who really gets close to him catches on pretty quickly that he's insane, like the prostitutes he brings back to his place to rape and kill. The point of Bateman isn't really Bateman; it's Ellis characterizing the yuppie scene of the 80's and 90's as so utterly degenerate that someone as obviously deranged as Patrick Bateman could just blend in unnoticed.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>