<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-05-08T18:46:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpwhmpy/</link>
  <title>Varied Thoughts on Conspiracy Theories</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>But most people aren’t capable of, nor would they be interested in, total skepticism</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'm not actually so sure of this. Growing up in the rural UK, a certain kind of quiet epistemic humility was pretty common among a lot of my neighbours. "Oh I don't keep up with politics," or "The world's a complicated place, I'll stick to my vegetable patch, thanks." I actually worry that the modern media ecosystem and increased partisan fracturing has made this kind of position harder to adopt, especially among younger people. People - even people who aren't Extremely Online - are subject to pressures to cultivate their 'political brand' and show solidarity with friends of one stripe or another. So I don't think skepticism and uncertainty are the reserve of the intellectual elite, nor should they be.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>you make it sound like the primary reason he knows so much about global warming is to pwn people who believe in it</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>My dad is certainly intellectually pugilistic by temperament, but in this case I think he's more sinned against than sinning. Specifically, I think what happened is that he was quietly voicing doubts or uncertainties a decade or so ago and kept getting pounced on. So he responded by arming himself with a deep knowledge of the field, so he wouldn't keep getting beaten up, and now (if you'll forgive the cliche) the hunted has become the hunter. So while I think his motives are mixed, I think he's responding in a way that many reasonable people would.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Aren’t the central examples of conspiracy theories that come to mind all along these lines? It’s hard for me to think of something commonly called a “conspiracy theory” that doesn’t do either one of these.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think you may be right, but only on a technicality. Specifically, I think the notion of "conspiracy theory" is conceptually downstream of "conspiracy <em>theorist</em>", and this latter is a normatively laden concept. Philosopher Jacob Stegenga's book <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/medical-nihilism-9780198747048?cc=gb&amp;lang=en&amp;"><em>Medical Nihilism</em></a>, for example, basically argues that a huge swathe of modern medicine is no better than placebo. But I don't think we'd intuitively count him as a conspiracy theorist because his views are fairly well defended (though massively controversial) and he's an academic at a top institution. That's a long winded way of saying that from a purely epistemic point of view, the category of "conspiracy theories" is probably too value-laden to be of much use. Perhaps I should have framed the above discussion, then, in terms of how we should be more prima facie open to tolerating and even welcoming discussion 'fringe ideas', while allowing that we might have good reasons in individual cases to doubt the epistemic motives of the person you're arguing with and terminate particular interactions.</p>
      <p>However, I also think that some things that get labelled as conspiracy theories often lack clear political motives. My next door neighbour growing up was always insistent that the moon landings were faked. And while he was a curmudgeonly contrarian, I can't see that this was a result of some particular animus he had towards particular political parties or structures. He just thought there was no way humans could have gotten past the Van Allen belt.</p>
      <p>On a broader note: I'm pretty doubtful of the idea that we can sort beliefs neatly into the "innocuous" and "motivated" categories. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/g0ck7p/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_13_2020/fnmzy2w/?context=3&amp;sort=best">As I was arguing a couple of weeks ago</a>, I think <em>everyone's</em> beliefs are systematically influenced by non-rational factors to a high degree, notably social ones, and it's the exception rather than the rule that we can identify the specific mechanisms and factors involved. And while there are cases where it's just immediately apparent that someone's views about a descriptive matter follow from a particular ideological commitment or social identification, the difference between that and the 'good cases' is really a matter of transparency and (perhaps) degree. While I don't think it follows that we should take <em>everyone</em> at face value and assume they're sincerely interested in truth (sometimes a troll really is just a troll), I'm very wary of too-quickly assigning sharp boundaries between good- and bad-faith actors. In fact, it's something I even worry about on occasion in the context of this subreddit.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>