<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-05-05T21:38:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpll6ey/</link>
  <title>In Praise of Casual Sex</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>At the risk of sounding very off-message - I think this is totally unsurprising, and may even be rational in the grand scheme of things. To be blunt about it, I think most straight men <em>want</em> to have experienced lots of sexual variety; they <em>admire</em> those men who can achieve this; and they <em>envy</em> others if they haven't achieved it themselves.</p>
      <p>On the wanting side: most (if not all) men have a pretty deep and phylogenetically ancient drive for sexual validation through having lots of partners (see e.g., <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coolidge_effect">the Coolidge effect</a>). Of course, that doesn't mean that it's necessarily in most men's interest to indulge this drive, nor does it follow from the fact that most straight men <em>want</em> lots of sex with varied partners that they take inordinate amounts of <em>pleasure</em> from the act. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2756052/">But 'wanting' are 'liking' are two quite distinct phenomena</a>, and this can be seen in everything from mindless eating to binge watching TV shows and gaming (on the negative side) to drives for status or achievement (on the positive side). For my part, I don't think we should only want those things that bring us pleasure; instead, we should aim to find ways to acknowledge and (where reasonable) healthily satisfy our deep urges rather than fence them off under the label of 'irrational drives'.</p>
      <p>On the admiration side: in addition to its being a deep biological urge, I think it's undeniably a pretty impressive achievement for most straight men to be sexually successful. Good looks may help, but it usually requires charisma, social skills, and a certain mental toughness for a straight guy to have lots of sexual partners. Of course, there are lots of ecological variables that might make it easier or harder, but if a straight man has a history of having lots of sex with attractive women it usually bespeaks some impressive talents. These are frequently transferable to most other areas of life, from empathy to social networking. Of course, many roads lead to Rome, and it may be that a sexually successful man is simple an extreme risk-taking sociopath; but typically those people don't arouse admiration in the same way.</p>
      <p>On the envy side: even if casual sex per se isn't always what it's cracked up to be, the experience of meeting a stranger at a bar and a few hours later seeing her naked in your bed and having her melt in your arms as she comes while she reveals deep personal things about herself that she hasn't told even some of her close friends... well that's just an incredibly intimate, thrilling, and rewarding experience for most straight men, even if your orgasm per se is mediocre. I spent a lot of my 20s on SSRIs that meant it was all but impossible for me to come, but I still loved the experience of being naked and intimate with a hot stranger. Indeed, some of the best memories and peak experiences of my whole life come from this period (and I usually remember the foreplay a lot more than the sex). There's also a kind of permanent confidence boost and psychological relief that a lot of straight men experience from having been able to prove to themselves that they can be charming, suave, and attractive enough to have a lot of sexual partners.</p>
      <p>Now, I'm sure there are plenty of men who don't relate to the above, but as a general rule, I think most straight guys would agree, even if it's a slightly uncomfortable thing to admit; far easier to say "oh that's my lizard brain talking!", and excuse oneself from the hard work (akin to saying "oh, I'm not a gym bro, I don't really care about being in shape"). And if I was, say, giving advice to a young guy about to move to a big city and he asked me if it was irrational for him to put a fairly high priority on having a lot of sex, I'd tell him absolutely not, and he should fill his boots (while being a compassionate lover and a decent human being, of course).</p>
      <p>I wouldn't <em>necessarily</em> give that advice to you, though. For one, you say you don't enjoy the casual sex, but if you also really don't enjoy the other things that come packaged with it (the intimacy, the nakedness, the thrill, the surge of positive self-image, etc.) then it may well be that your drive is a bit more on the irrational side, and you might look at the kinds of therapy options others have discussed. You might also feel that you've exhausted the kinds of personal development gains I mention above that are associated with having a lot of dating experience, in which case you may have hit diminishing returns a while back while still feeling in the thrall of an alien desire. Again, in that case, some kind of therapy might be a good option. But I also wouldn't want other straight men reading this - especially younger ones - to think there's anything pathological about wanting to have lots of sexual experiences, even if they find the actual orgasms or sex mediocre, nor would I want them to rationalise away a perfect legitimate and potentially empowering desire on the grounds that it might be daunting, ego-bruising, or exhausting.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>