<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-05-06T01:42:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpmb7l6/</link>
  <title>Eurozone: Battle for Aid</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Disclaimer:</strong> I am not an economist, nor am I a citizen of the Eurozone. I consequently welcome correction on anything that follows.</p>
      <p>As some of you may be aware there has been a battle being waged in the Eurozone concerning how to best help the countries most affected by the coronavirus pandemic. Italy, Portugal, and Spain were hard hit by the initial wave of the virus putting pressure on their already struggling economies, while Greece has suffered from the collapse in tourism.</p>
      <p>The European Central Bank has responded with <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/20200430-ecb-european-central-bank-bond-buyback-pandemic-emergency-purchase-programme-christine-lagarde-covid-19-coronavirus">the "Pandemic Emergency Purchase Program" (PEPP)</a>, which involves the ECB buying government bonds from countries that are worst affected, thereby reducing the cost of their borrowing needs. As I understand it, this fiscal stimulus is effectively a form of 'quantitative easing' aka the ECB creating money, but it does not amount to a direct transfer between countries because the ECB retains the bonds as assets. Insofar as this has any negative effect on countries like Germany, the Netherlands, Austria, and Finland (the so-called 'Frugal Four') it is only via relatively minor expected effects on inflation and the depreciation of the Euro as a currency.</p>
      <p>This policy may help countries like Italy in the short-term but it does of course increase their indebtedness in the long-term. Hence one proposed alternative - supported, as I understand it, by everyone except the Frugal Four - is the so-called "<a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/coronabonds-could-bail-europe-out-tie-it-together/2020/04/10/e07b3d5c-7afd-11ea-a311-adb1344719a9_story.html">Coronabonds</a>" program, which would see the ECB sell bonds on the international market and transfer the funds back to the member states in accordance with their needs. This would be a direct fiscal stimulus while the bonds would remain on the balance sheet of the ECB, to be paid for collectively by the Eurozone as a whole using contributions from individual economies (although I don't see why the ECB couldn't just pay for them itself via printing money; any insights appreciated).</p>
      <p>The refusal of the Frugal Four to countenance these measures <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/apr/01/coronavirus-could-be-final-straw-for-eu-european-experts-warn">has generated considerable anger in countries like Italy</a> and could threaten the integrity of the Eurozone in the longer term. One poll from March found that 88% of Italians "felt Europe was failing to support Italy" and 67% viewed "EU membership as a disadvantage" (<a href="https://www.ecfr.eu/article/commentary_whatever_it_takes_italy_and_covid_19_crisis">source</a>).</p>
      <p>The latest development in this saga is that <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2020/05/05/german-top-court-says-ecbs-qe-partially-violates-law.html">a German court has now challenged even the ECB's existing PEPP program</a> - already seen by many as a weak response to a serious crisis - and has given the ECB three months to address its concerns, failing which the Bundesbank could withdraw from the PEPP program (note: I have no idea what this would mean for the PEPP program). In any case, this is likely to stoke anger in Southern Europe even further.</p>
      <p>As I noted above, I am not an economist, but I wrote the above fairly carefully so I believe it's mostly correct. I am now going to relax my standards a lot and speak off the cuff. Specifically, I will give a very short dialogue to give a slightly simplified summary of what my German and Italian friends 'Gunther' and 'Paolo' have said to me about this crisis, thereby giving a sense of the two opposing positions.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Gunther:</strong>
        <em>Portugal, Italy, Greece, and Spain - you so called "PIGS" - failed to get your fiscal house in order when the times were good. You have luxurious social policies, undisciplined government finances, and an unwillingness to embrace painful reform. While we Germans are committed to the Eurozone it would simply be a moral hazard for German taxpayers to bail you out now.</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Paolo:</strong>
        <em>Gee, thanks for the 'PIGS' quip. But you Germans</em>
        <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judensau">
          <em>like to compare people you look down</em>
        </a>
        <em>upon to pigs, don't you? Second, you may criticise us for not living up to your economic example in your cherry picked areas but in some ways we're more responsible than you; get back to us in 2031 when Germany will match Italy's statutory retirement age of 67. Besides, you're no angels yourself - you've</em>
        <a href="https://factcheckeu.info/en/article/la-germania-ha-violato-il-patto-di-stabilit%C3%A0-18-volte-come-dice-juncker">
          <em>violated the European Growth and Stability Pact eighteen times</em>
        </a>
        <em>!</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Gunther:</strong>
        <em>Ahem. Well, you've done it twenty-eight times, I believe... nobody's perfect. But the fact is that Italy is saddled with mountains of debt and has a sclerotic economy. Painful reforms are necessary - we did it ourselves</em>
        <a href="https://www.worldbank.org/en/news/opinion/2013/12/16/lessons-from-germany">
          <em>back in 2003</em>
        </a>
        <em>. Or would you like to keep living off the sweat of German workers forever? I never knew an Italian who turned down a free lunch, and if we give you Coronabonds then we'll be paying for your aperitivi in perpetuity.</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Paolo:</strong>
        <em>At least we have some aperitivi worth eating. Look, we'd like to get our economy back on track, but the fact is that our membership of the Eurozone has mainly benefited Germany exporters at our expense. If we'd had control of our own currency, we'd have been able to compete with you on price in the international market. Meanwhile, by removing differences in the strengths of our currencies, the Euro has also made it easier for you to sell your cars competitively in Italy. Whereas what have we gotten out of it except a bunch of dodgy loans from German banks?</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Gunter:</strong>
        <em>Oh, I'm so sorry for giving you cheap credit. If you'd actually spent it on infrastructure and investment rather than living la dolce vita maybe you wouldn't be in this mess now. You're lucky the ECB is still bailing out you out...</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Paolo:</strong>
        <em>If we still had control of our monetary policy, we wouldn't need bailing out! We could engage in quantitative easing of our own to pay the bills, let our currency depreciate, and start undercutting you again on exports! Good luck selling BMWs and Mercedes in Italy when currency differentials mean you can get a nice Alfa Romeo for half the price.</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Gunter:</strong>
        <em>Oh, aren't we terrible, giving you better access to nice things. I can't possibly imagine why anyone would rather drive a BMW than a Fiat Punto. But fine, if you want to leave, the door's over there.</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Paolo:</strong>
        <em>I knew all this talk of European solidarity was mere hot air. You lot could solve the Eurozone's problems with minimal cost to German citizens. Whatever happened to our great dream? Alexander Hamilton federalized America's debt and look at how that helped unify the young United States. But not you. Not so much "e pluribus unum" as "e pluribus uno" - from all to one, specifically Germany. Out for yourself, just like you were in 193-</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Gunter:</strong>
        <em>Don't even go there. Besides, it's not like you can talk! We learned fascism from you!</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Paolo:</strong>
        <em>Vaffanculo!</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Gunter:</strong>
        <em>Du Fickfehler!</em>
      </p>
      <p>Ahem. I hope that doesn't violate the sub's rules on unnecessary antagonism but it accurately captures the tone of some recent conversations I've come across. However, I really have no idea who's in the 'right' here, or if the claims above are accurate, or if there are any clear answers here. I would love to hear what others think, especially Europeans and economists!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>