<post>
  <author>GavinSkulldrinker</author>
  <date>2020-05-06T17:48:12Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpon550/</link>
  <title>Analyzing Narratives on the Arbery Shooting</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>To steelman the top comment as much as I feel willing to;</p>
      <p>My priors are that whenever there's a shooting of a black man, there's immediately a contingent of people who will declare it unjust regardless of any facts, because really it's just an excuse to bring up their talking points about police brutality and racism.  This is accompanied by a willful blindness to the fact that sometimes black people commit crimes. </p>
      <p>A blindness so willful that I can't imagine anyone who actually LIVES in major city truly believes it; as a sincere attitude, I can only imagine it coming from a small-town college kid or teenager who's turbo-progressive and is just itching to get away from their ignorant, racist, gay-hating, monogamous cis patriarchy-upholding family.  In which case, they're in for a nasty shock when they get their car stolen, and it turns out it wasn't a neo-nazi that did it, but a bored black teenager who drove it around with his friends for a weekend, then ditched it when it ran out of fuel.  (Which, I remind myself, was because he didn't have any money to buy more gas, not because he didn't know cars can be re-fueled).</p>
      <p>This phenomenon is colloquially known among internet racists as "Dey dindu nuffin, dey good boys."</p>
      <p>Actual riots happened in Milwaukee (I'm from Wisconsin, and live in Milwaukee as of 2018, so the whole thing was pretty close-to-home for me.) This happened when a black police officer shot a black citizen who was brandishing a gun.  The funny thing is that they were in the same high school (where they disliked each other, so that removes some of the poetry).  There's a lot you can take away from that; is it an example of the different paths people can take in life, something-something-bootstraps?  Or is it a tragic tale about someone from an impoverished community making something of himself only to be seen as an oppressor by his former neighbors?  Did the cop see himself as protecting his old community, or did he see his career as an escape from people he despised?  From what I can tell, the cop might have also been kinda a dick.  Is it a tragedy about how black people are still stuck doing unpleasant working-class jobs that whites don't want to do?  Jobs like shooting other black people.</p>
      <p>Instead it's "cops is racist, burn everything except for the weave stores, we need our weave."</p>
      <p>So in this incident, the narrative was "a black dude was innocently jogging through a neighborhood, on his way to do pillar-of-his-community-stuff, when a pickup full of rednecks rolled up, called him "Boy" for good measure, and killed him in cold blood.  And it was definitely racism, because he was jogging while wearing a polo shirt with an engineering textbook in his backpack.</p>
      <p>The gun in high school thing runs counter to that narrative.  Therefore it seems like a salient point to bring up.  I actually think it doesn't and isn't, but it IS if you think you're trying to disprove someone's " dindu nuffin" assertation.</p>
      <p>Now, the funny thing is that by this point, I don't need to actually hear someone put forth the dindu nuffin narrative, because I already have a simulation of that person in my head to do it for me.</p>
      <p>And the even funnier thing is that you can tell the same story about people picking apart unjust shootings to explain how they're not unjust at all.</p>
      <p>Sorry, I'm on mobile and this was kinda rambly.</p>
      <p>Maybe my point is that it helps to remember that other people are bouncing off of different surfaces than you, which informs their current trajectories?</p>
      <p>I actually in no way think that the dead guy in this situation behaved poorly.  Between the ACTUAL threat of a gang of good-ole-boys high on tryhard vigilantism who've found a hooligan to scare off, AND the overblown fear in his own head of the Trump white supremacy finally coming for him, yes, dude was undoubtedly afraid for his life and had no confidence that compliance or innocence would protect him.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>