<post>
  <author>Iconochasm</author>
  <date>2020-05-06T13:26:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpnsgtm/</link>
  <title>Leading Intelligent Horses Via Careful Masonry</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>So, how does one convince an otherwise intelligent and reasonable person they are wrong?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You can lead a horse to water, but you can't make him think.  Functionally speaking, you can't, at least how you've phrased this.  I once used a metaphor that we don't just have "two movies", but "two (or a few million) cinematic universes".  Our beliefs and ideas about anything that matters are far from independent; they are a complex wall built brick-by-brick of interconnected and interdependent object-level beliefs about reality, half-remembered statistics, inherent predispositions, vague conclusions bridging a half-dozen belief-nodes like rebar, and the entire beautiful mess is mortared together with higher level, partially abstracted <em>remembrances of prior conclusions</em> (which are remarkably resistant to damage). </p>
      <p>What this means is that even if you get an unusually honest and open person to sit down, and really hammer away at a topic like evolution, or capitalism, it's like swinging a hammer at a solid brick wall.  You look at the sledge hammer, look at the brick you're hitting and think "This hammer is going to pulverize this brick!"  But there's an entire wall there that will support the brick labeled "Specific Fact About Evolution" or "Particular Claim About The Dangers Of Vaccines", that diffuses out the kinetic energy of each hit, vastly increasing the effort required to shatter that one brick.  And say you shatter that brick.  Muscles burning, flushed with victory, you've finally reduced that brick to <em>dust</em>, by relentless hammering blows of FACTS AND LOGIC.  </p>
      <p>The rest of the wall is still there.</p>
      <p>The brain is a master mason.</p>
      <p>Enduring the loss of a brick is trivial.  Replacing it, the work of a few minutes.</p>
      <p>Actually changing someone's mind on a major, top-level topic is akin to reorienting the entire wall 90 degrees.  You're never going to do it on your own with a sledge hammer while the mason fights you, you <em>need</em> the active assistance of the mason to get anywhere.  If I can completely torture this metaphor, what you need to do is show the mason a new foundation.  You have to do this without directly threatening the existing wall, because masons are suspicious and defensive-minded creatures.  And then you have to show the mason that the new foundation is so much superior to the old one, that it's worth <em>theory-crafting</em> a new wall, you know, just as a fun exercise, without committing to anything, certainly not committing to the enormous work of building a new wall.  Sometimes, with a young mason, this will suffice.  The promise of the new wall will outstrip the old one, which is not so established and settled.  It might be perfectly designed for elaborate mosaics like "I am smarter than my family", or "I am part of a movement".  The sunk cost will seem less daunting.  And the mason, young and energetic, will leap to build the new wall, perhaps purchasing a fedora, or talking a lot about Ayn Rand.  Older walls are harder; they are settled and battle-hardened, their mason's much more invested.  For those it's a slow process of rebuilding/moving the wall, brick by brick, hesitant and slow to commitment.  </p>
      <p>Dropping the metaphor, this would represent convincing someone that a small portion of a belief structure is incorrect, without threatening the whole.  "Maybe God guided evolution", or "Here's one particular area where government regulation might help" or "Here's one small area where government should deregulate".  That's <em>one brick</em> layed on a new foundation.  Once you get a few, maybe the mason will start to build it higher, as the senses and top-level cognitive processes naturally generate additional bricks, some of them will be good fits for the new wall.  To be a mason is to build walls, but a brick that doesn't fit anywhere can only be discarded.  Every day a million ideologues encounter a stat or fact that doesn't mesh with their worldview, and they promptly delete it from consideration ("Probably lying somewhere, it's not even worth looking into.")  You can't change someone else's mind, but you <em>can</em> show them a new way to put those ill-fitting bricks.  </p>
      <p>To give an example, on Discord, one of my friends has been continually shitting on New Jersey's Governor Murphy.  Not in a broad ideological way, but specific attacks on Murphy in particular that definitely <em>do not</em> code as red tribe, or attacks on Democrats in general.  Doing this, he's getting engagement and soft agreement from most of our friends, including the more ideological leftwing ones.  I would not be surprised if, come the next gubernatorial election, a "Fuck Murphy In Particular" argument might convince most of our friends to vote 3rd party, or stay home, or maybe even for a Republican challenger.  Because he's not attacking their existing walls, he's showing them how to lay a 90 degree turn, paved in bricks like "Where the fuck is our legalized weed?" and "So golfing is essential to life, but picnics are illegal?"</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>