<post>
  <author>onyomi</author>
  <date>2020-05-06T05:52:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpmxis7/</link>
  <title>Let a Thousand Amish Sects Bloom</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>What do MSNBC, Fox News, low birth rates, the obesity epidemic, Covid-19, women in the workforce, and "late capitalism" have in common? Over-optimization.</p>
      <p>I'm very pro-free market, but have been thinking for a while about a steelman criticism of "capitalism" as academics and some people colloquially use it (though the way some people use it colloquially it just seems to mean "greed," but I think we can do better than that). And while I agree that <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpi6izs?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x">use of the term</a> "late capitalism" tends to be a flag for leftist ideologues I nonetheless wonder if the term might be useful for helping to explain the trend of falling birth rates in developed countries that thread was about, as well as maybe much else (note that I'm not sure how much my use of the term "late capitalism" here is in keeping with current academic usage; it's possible I'm reinventing the wheel, but all I can say is I haven't seen it put this way myself).</p>
      <p>What's good about capitalism? It gives the people what they want. It sees a demand and it supplies. I'm not going to claim here that people (only) want dumb things or that enlightened experts can know better than them what they really "need," only that that's what makes it work. Wherever there's a want unmet, even one people didn't know they had, capitalism <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2016/07/25/how-the-west-was-won/">seeks and destroys</a>. Destroying want is a pretty good thing.</p>
      <p>But what happens when this process runs untrammeled within an individualistic/atomized society? Basically it takes out all the "<a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/yLLkWMDbC9ZNKbjDG/slack">slack</a>" in the system through "optimization." Can you increase profits by outsourcing your tech support to call centers in India? Do it. If you don't the other guy will. And when people look at the price of the computer are they going to pick your more expensive model because you didn't outsource? No. They'll pick the cheap one and later realize the tech support sucks. But hey, everyone's doing it so all the tech support is going to suck anyway. What you still provide tech support by phone? You've got to automate that shit...</p>
      <p>But it's not just outsourcing our tech support (you're not racist against Indians, are you?), we outsourced our child care, creating the "two income trap" (you're not sexist, are you?). Outsourcing, capitalism tells us, is good. It's more efficient. Division of labor. Each person does what he or she is best at and if society has more use for the labor of intelligent women in the workplace than at home who are we to argue?</p>
      <p>But there's more slack! Your wife is still cooking everything from scratch at home? But there's cheap delivery made to an exacting standard and hyperpalatable available! You're still playing cards with your neighbors? But there's TV and Netflix and... You're still reading the newspaper? But you can get hyper-concentrated outrage and fear fed into your living room 24-7 and on your commute! I can't possibly afford to have a child now... I still haven't paid off my student loans (which I used to take the slack out of my youth, delaying adulthood as long as humanly possible), plus my wife really cares about her career...</p>
      <p>With Covid we've heard a lot about "bringing home the supply chain" and really it's a similar issue: in the short run capitalism says if you can get it cheaper made abroad then why wouldn't you? If you don't your competitors will. Think your customers care about that little "Made in America" sticker? Well guess what I can finish the very last stage of production in America and slap one of those on there too...</p>
      <p>What can be done (and why isn't Elizabeth Warren advocating for women to leave the workforce and a halt to immigration?)? Obviously it's complicated, but my best guess for an antidote to the ills of individual freedom taken to the extreme (hence "late" capitalism) is more macro-freedom to organize societies some of which may be more restrictive of their members' individual freedom. Let a thousand Amish sects, not all of which are religious or reject technology, bloom. Decentralize, allow ethnostates, etc.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>