<post>
  <author>professorgerm</author>
  <date>2020-05-06T20:15:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpp55jb/</link>
  <title>Distinguishing Lip Service from Sincere Practice in Religion</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>How much of their behavior follows from their professed religion? </p>
      <p>A likely poor but convenient example: Joe Biden says he's Catholic. At some point in his life he attended Mass regularly, and perhaps still does. However, his political stances are opposed to the doctrine of the church, perhaps most notably on abortion. Unlike the million flavors of Protestant, there's much less wiggle room for Catholics, and likewise Biden has been refused Communion at times for his stance on abortion. His political stances are <em>fundamentally opposed</em> to the Official Views of his religion. Biden at one time claimed his personal beliefs shouldn't interfere with others. Ignoring major complications of such a view, the superior compromise would be <em>abstaining from votes he can't support</em>, not voting against his personal beliefs. If he thinks its wrong, how can he in good conscience and good faith think that it's good for others?</p>
      <p>It's hard for me to view Biden as anything more than lip service. </p>
      <p>If you'd like to point out Republicans doing equivalent things, go right ahead, and there's a good chance I'll agree, but I think "Catholic actively supporting abortion" is a pretty strong example in my book. To be frank, I think it's quite hard for an <em>honest</em> religious person of <em>any stripe</em> to enter politics, especially in such a diverse country. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>If "large portions" of the left oppose mainstream traditional religion, then why has every single democratic president (and every serious candidate, as far as i'm aware) been religious?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'd also focus on the <em>mainstream</em><strong><em>traditional</em></strong> aspect, rather than just going with Jiro's "lip service" complaint (valid though it may be). Dems can be religious, but they for sure can't be <em>traditional</em>. </p>
      <p>Pro-life, or just not maximally full-throatedly pro-choice? Not gonna make it. Think that gender differences are important? Well, this one gets convoluted, but if you think <em>traditional</em> gender roles are at all valid you're not gonna make it. If you agree with Chesterton that birth control is better for corporations than for women's success and happiness, you're not gonna make it. If you're a Christian that doesn't throw out, ignore, or <em>less than maximally reject</em> everything Paul wrote in the Bible, you're not gonna make it. You'll get Mitt Romney and Mike Pence from the right, but you'll not see equally traditional/fundamentalist/etc people from the left because the left is wholly incompatible and outright hostile to even a hint of that. </p>
      <p>There's also the factor of conservative Blacks always voting Dem even though Dems are outright hostile to so many of their beliefs. If that voting block was  actually up for grabs instead of just being assumed Dem, elections would get much more interesting.</p>
      <p>That said, you do ask an interesting question, if I may rephrase: why will so few people vote for professed atheists? </p>
      <p>One part is that to win the general, you still have to appeal to religious people, but in polls even atheists aren't <em>that likely</em> to vote for an atheist, and religious people will vote for people of other religions over atheists.</p>
      <p>I think another part is that even many "de facto" (as opposed to committed, Harris/Dawkins/Hitchens style) atheists prefer the idea of a deontologist in charge, even if they're only nominally, barely, "culturally but not really" deontologist, possibly for reasons of relative predictability. I'm just spinning ideas, though, and have no real support for this.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>