<post>
  <author>Ame_Damnee</author>
  <date>2021-01-04T19:34:16Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/gi3kaff/</link>
  <title>How trans activists undermine decades of feminism through reifying gender stereotypes</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I don't feel like I get TERFs. The core of it seems to be feminist activists who are salty about having lost the Oppression Olympics to trans people</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't know if I'm a TERF or not but trying to explain it from an older-school version of feminism (I can't keep up with what Wave we're supposed to be on now - is it Third, Revised Third, or Fourth?) here's the thing: the argument commonly used to explain transness to the majority is "born in the wrong body/a woman's brain in a man's body".</p>
      <p>Now I know this is a very fraught notion and that not all trans people etc. and that really it's simply a catchy slogan to get the vast majority of ordinary people who don't know much about the entire thing to sympathise with trans rights activism, the same way that "born this way" was used for gay rights (even though that was not without its problems).  But taking it at the Lowest Common Denominator level, the notion is that "I'm a woman because I have a female brain".</p>
      <p>And that is flying in the face of decades of "there are no such things as a 'male' brain and a 'female' brain" work in feminism, precisely because the male/female brain alleged dichotomy had been used to rationalise everything from "women are dumber than men because their brains are smaller, Science proves it!" to the centuries of "women are emotional, irrational, incapable of higher abstract thought, natural caretakers and nurturers".  It is just as irritating when you have women indulging in this kind of glop - "Women are all peace-loving Earth Mothers and if only women could be in political power there would be no more wars or poverty or sickness" - because that's dividing up human traits into neat piles where every A has X and every B has Y, and then making it a corollary that no A is Y and no B is X.</p>
      <p>That had to be fought against because it was an argument for why "women can't be... whatever".    There's a very funny Harry Enfield sketch about <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LS37SNYjg8w&amp;list=RDLS37SNYjg8w">women, know your limits!</a> and while it's certainly exaggerated, the notion that "too much education is bad for a woman, it turns them masculine and unnatural" certainly was in the air.  EDIT: I'm quite happy that there may indeed be structural differences between male and female brains, but I think any work on "this sector lights up in men looking at pictures of trains and this other sector lights up in women looking at pictures of babies so this means men like things and women like people" is still on the level of "feeling your bumps in phrenology".</p>
      <p>And then along come trans rights activism and trans women saying "I knew I was really a woman because I liked pink and playing with dolls and dresses" and the definition of femininity they utilise is one where it's makeup and hairstyles and cute sundresses and being a girly girl.</p>
      <p>Which is very fucking damn irritating when you're a cis woman who has never been a girly girl, was never interested in being a girly girl, had to work out for herself a lot of shit around 'am I a real girl if I'm not a girly girl who likes girly girl stuff?' and has some what are now masculine-coded interests, but also integrated for herself "well hell yes I am a real woman even if I don't have stereotypical 'female' interests".</p>
      <p>It's the stereotyping that is annoying.  And it's like drag, which is a very exaggerated performative version of femininity and which in some instances does give off overtones of not liking women very much, but which is a performance art of its own and can be judged that way: nobody really expects women to be the grotesque caricatures of drag.  But for transness, in some instances, the caricature, the stereotype, <strong>is</strong> meant sincerely as a vision of "this is what a woman is/how a woman should be".  Or at least, it looks like it is meant sincerely.  Again, I realise that there is a ton of history behind this, including medical access to transition/hormones where psychological evaluations emphasised "are you living like the gender you say you are?  are you wearing makeup and behaving in an ultra-feminine manner?"</p>
      <p>But yeah, from this side of the fence it looks like all the work of thirty years pushing back against "what are little boys/little girls made of?" has been reverted, by a bunch of men in dresses who want to play at being Wendy Darling.  When something like saying "people who menstruate? people who get pregnant? you mean women?" can get you fired from your job when up to quite recently this was merely common sense, so it sounds like the modern version of <a href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Chinese_Stories/Calling_a_deer_a_horse">see deer say horse</a>.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>