<post>
  <author>bamboo-coffee</author>
  <date>2021-01-05T06:10:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kqko1d/new_york_magazine_investigation_concludes_that/gi5lcua/</link>
  <title>Reasons why suspicion of China, in connection with COVID-19, seems warranted</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Let's say there is an apartment building that gets roaches. The landlord (PRC) of the building lives on the top floor. He happens to have a lizard and he breeds cockroaches (level 4 research center) for their food. He isn't the only one to do this in the building, but the only one on his floor (only l4 facility in china). One day, a room mate sees a cockroach outside the landlords room (case zero). Then, his room mates start seeing cockroaches in their rooms (spread in wuhan). Then the tenants on the same floor (spread through China). Finally, the entire building starts to have an influx of roaches.</p>
      <p>When approached by the tenants throughout the building about the source, the landlord refuses to let in an expert exterminator unless it's his friend (WHO) who is hired by the owner of the building (the UN) who is also a friend. The prechosen exterminator says there are roaches, but they came from somewhere else. He also says no one else can look in the room, and the fact that people suspect the landlord of causing a massive infestation is an insane conspiracy theory. The landlord threatens any of his room mates (the chinese people) if they speak out about who they think started the infestation. An adjacent apartment (taiwan), successfully keeps out nearly all roaches, but is banned from community meetings discussing the issue by the landlord, the exterminator and the owner of the building. </p>
      <p>In the end, no one can gather proof that the origin was the roach farm because the room mates cannot speak freely, and no one has seen the room except the landlord and the exterminator.</p>
      <p>Now trusting the landlord and his friends is not necessarily wrong. In fact, we don't know for sure if it was his farm that started it. There is evidence that he and his friends have provided to prove otherwise. But, we also know that he has a reason to lie and we have a big burden of proof that is impossible to obtain with his secrecy and collusion. </p>
      <p>It is for this reason that discussion should be allowed and even encouraged. When it is shamed, censored and banned, you create a shroud that may cover actual innocence but it can cover a lot more. It is not indecent to want answers. You are right that an investigation would not be trusted by some (myself included), but that is not further proof of innocence, nor is it proof of guilt. It is a side effect of geopolitical assymetrical influence and that something is rotten in the state of denmark. You argue that questioning the official story is insane, I think it is insane not to. I accept evidence points in the other direction, but the obvious obsfucation from China, WHO, twitter, etc, makes any final analysis derived from the aforementioned sources less than reliable at best. </p>
      <p>Countries are experimenting with deadly viruses, and somehow you are here asking for less accountability and shaming those who want more.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>