<post>
  <author>deluks917_</author>
  <date>2021-01-07T18:58:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/gigdaz5/</link>
  <title>Being a self-professed far-leftist who opposed police brutality against the Capitol rioters</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>As someone quite far on the left I have to say:</p>
      <p>I do not support police brutality against disruptive protestors. I do not support handing out prison sentences to disruptive protestors. The carceral system is incredibly harsh in the United States. We need to be consistent in our opposition to American style criminal injustice.</p>
      <p>We do not know the details of everything that went on and some of the protestors may have acted very badly. But the majority of the protestors should have been allowed to safely go home. The police were initially restrained but became much more violent at night. One woman was shot by the police and based on the <a href="https://twitter.com/dancohen3000/status/1347076676342185984">video</a> her death was a tragedy. As far as I know, fifty-two people were arrested. I hope they get off relatively easily.</p>
      <p>For the most part, the protestors were not trying to install themselves as part of a dictatorial regime. I assume the vast majority of them were normal people who thought the election was stolen. I do not think there is much evidence for this claim but people they trusted repeatedly told them it was true. It was even more delusional to think this disruption would lead to anything positive from their point of view. The protests have already led to thedonlad.win being put at risk. Further marginalization of their movement is coming. </p>
      <p>The protestors were not really an organized fascist group. But even if they were literal Nazis I would not glorify the police and carceral system. The balance of power can change and situations like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indonesian_mass_killings_of_1965%E2%80%9366">Indonessian Mass Killings</a> should make us very wary. I can also understand why the victims of police brutality might feel vindicated to see the police turn on the blue lives matter crew. The protestors were fellow humans who were sadly misled. They, like all people who arguably broken laws, deserve compassion and understanding. </p>
      <p>The USA has had the top incarceration rate in the world for over a decade. The police constantly break laws and use excessive force. I see many people calling for the protestors to be prosecuted to the full extent of the law. In America that often means destroying their lives. I hope the protestors come to their senses and are able to return to their lives. The only people who killed anyone were the police. We really need to keep our priorities straight and maintain a compassionate mindset.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>