<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2021-01-07T17:56:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/gig4sdg/</link>
  <title>Why right wing populsim should have secured buy-in from cultural and intellectual elites</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Just another quick take on last night's events. Specifically, it's helped me crystallise the realisation that the current wave of right-wing populism has suffered badly by <strong>not securing any buy-in from cultural and intellectual elites</strong>.</p>
      <p>"That's the point!" some might say; "this is about rising up against the corrupt elites! Drain the swamp!" The problem is that the elites are, well, elite. They write the sympathetic newspaper columns. They provide funding and organisation. They find powerful themes and memes that resonate beyond the core movement. They use their clout to bring in new members.</p>
      <p>And the elites aren't a homogeneous bunch. From business elites and the financial elites of Wall Street to the tech elite to the Ivy League professors and journalists, to the union bosses, TV execs, YouTubers, artists and writers, judges, lawyers, church leaders... all of these groups have only partially overlapping interests, and a successful subversive movement should aim to recruit at least some of them to their side.</p>
      <p>As an illustration of how this "elite vacuum" in modern right-wing populism hurt the movement, note how <em>dumb</em> and <em>tribal</em> most of the big ideas are. Qanon is galaxy-brained conspiracism; the election fraud narrative was horribly handled and championed by borderline deranged people like Sidney Powell. Where are the exciting big tent ideas of the modern right? "Drain the swamp" was a good first pass, but it remained inchoate and intellectually underdeveloped; besides, Trump failed to deliver on it, and nothing has taken its place.</p>
      <p>The point about this kind of narrative construction isn't so much to provide an ideology as to provide a hermeneutics and commentary on a movement that can draw in outsiders and make it less toxic. Anyone looking for an explanation of the summer riots last year had no shortage of explainers, ranging from the entry-level "too many black men are being killed by police" to the sophomore-level "systemic racism and bias" to the priestly caste narratives about white supremacism and social constructivism. This made it easy for the left to spin - or more kindly, to constructively interpret - the scenes of burning buildings and riots. No such gloss and damage control is possible in the case of present day right-wing populism precisely because no elites have been brought into the process, to spin existing animus and develop powerful motivating themes to begin with.</p>
      <p>A nice contrast here is with Brexit. While most of the British elite establishment was opposed to Brexit, you had smart, articulate, and influential political figures like Dan Hannan, Jacob Rees Mogg, and Boris Johnson making a good popular case for it and detoxifying it ("it's about <em>sovereignty</em>!"), as well as support from quite a few prominent and well-loved celebrities and public figures who made it seem less alien and scary to the UK public. My sense is that the GOP used to rely on business elites and faith leaders for this kind of intellectual labour, but as the party has shifted towards economic populism and away from tradcon conservatism, they've lost the total loyalty of these groups.</p>
      <p>I think the likes of Moldbug realised the importance of the 'long march through the institutions', but the idea of constructing a set of parallel institutions in opposition to the Cathedral was hopelessly overoptimistic. Instead, they should have focused on fostering islands of ideological opposition within the Cathedral itself. I'm sure many NRx folk would say that that was impossible, but the likes of Jordan Peterson suggest to me that that's overstating matters; there are lots of heterodox thinkers in academia and journalism who would love to speak out, but it's very hard to do so when your potential allies are so removed from consensus reality.</p>
      <p>Moreover, I think the right largely squandered the gift of Peterson - a mild-mannered, articulate, thoughtful academic pushing back against the excesses of modern progressivism, selling tens of millions of copies of his books. Now, I should clarify that I'm no huge fan of Peterson (simply because I struggled to get into his books), but he did a brilliant job of providing a sensible accessible commentary on popular anger and frustration, one that elegantly exploited ideological incoherencies in the modern progressive left. That's part of why he quickly became such a bête noire on the left - he was a <em>huge</em> threat, not least because his success provided an initial opening for other disgruntled elites to start coming out of the closet.</p>
      <p>But for various reasons that I don't fully understand, the populist American right went down the conspiracist rabbit holes rather than bringing in people like Peterson as key figures, while memes, outrage, and galaxy-brained thinking reigned. And I think the next potential Peterson is going to have a much harder time offering sympathetic commentaries and interpretations of the right in the wake of last night's events and the ugly meltdown of late-stage Trumpism.</p>
      <p>I say all this as a heterodox liberal rather than a conservative. But I'm also a value pluralist, and I think that many of the concerns of the right are legitimate, and even some of them that I don't entirely share I can at least respect.</p>
      <p>On that note, let me add a constructive suggestion, namely that I think there's still space for the reconstruction and rehabilitation of at least some of the concerns of the popular right, and its channeling into a genuine mass movement capable of securing at least some elite buy-in.</p>
      <p>A good approach, it seems to me, would be to follow the likes of Peterson and adopt a broad ideological banner of "Common Sense". Critical race theory and modern approaches to gender are intellectually pretty kooky and are not widely shared, even among the intellectual and cultural elites (there are a <em>lot</em> of pissed off liberals in academia). Forget conspiracies and cults of personality; focus instead on defining what you're <em>against</em>, while remaining pluralist about positive commitments. Castigate big tech and the oligopolies of big tech and finance. Focus on the rule of law, the importance of history, and the value of hard work and entrepreneurship. Identify key leaders and influencers within Hispanic, Black, and Asian communities who can help foster a diverse popular coalition. These are big powerful messages that will resonate far more than Pizzagate or Satan-worshipping cabals of pedophiles.</p>
      <p>I realise that many will probably think this kind of elite-controlled take on right-wing populism is <em>selling out</em> or <em>missing the point -</em> it's about destroying the cathedral, not building a new one in its place. But ideological purity is a luxury reserved for those who are already winning the big battles, and you can't win those battles without elite buy-in.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>