<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2021-01-07T18:49:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/gigc4uo/</link>
  <title>Setting a policy agenda for the future of American conservatism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think most political battles are framed around ideology, and most policy proposals are really ideological insignia. But I can certainly have a stab - here are some ideas.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <strong>Regulation and trust-busting for big tech.</strong> Almost everyone dislikes big tech. Talk about media manipulation, harm to young people (especially young women) from social media, lack of competition, selling out to China. Appeal to universal values rather than making partisan claims.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Sing the praises of small businesses and entrepreneurs.</strong> Again, everyone likes entrepreneurs, and this message goes down well in Asian and Hispanic communities. Call out unnecessary certification and credentialism and other barriers to entry in so many professions. Stoke the American Dream rhetoric and talk about how big business is making it harder for people to build their own pathways to success.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Standing up to indoctrination in schools.</strong> Don't get too embroiled in the object-level issues about racism etc.. Talk instead about how, e.g., young white children - including children of immigrants - are being made to feel generational guilt and anxiety over the colour of their skin, and that this isn't fair on young people ("Surely we've moved past the idea that the sins of the fathers shall be visited upon the sons?"). Call for greater oversight of syllabi, with a positive message that no-one should be made to feel bad about their identity.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Free speech on campus.</strong> Talk about the importance of higher education as a place for the free exploration of ideas. Call out the most egregious examples of campus suppression of speech, while singling out for praise those universities that have adopted robust freedom of speech protections.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Doing better by our boys.</strong> Talk about the lack of positive male role models (a issue that resonates especially well in African-American communities). Sing the praises of mentorship and the importance of not making boys feel bad about their male identity. Talk up the value of things like sports and clubs as providing better pathways for boys to channel competition.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Cost control in education.</strong> Talk about what a travesty it is that university tuition has skyrocketed. Say that kids should be able to pay their way through education at a public school via working a summer job. Shift the debate about costs in higher ed away from debt forgiveness to cost reduction, emphasising the insane cost disease that's seen tuition soar over the last three or four decades.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Supporting working families.</strong> Sing the praises of the family unit as the basis for society and the importance of children learning the value of hard work from their parents. Identify ways that the federal government can support working class families, whether through subsidised childcare and providing additional child benefits to families with at least one working parent.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>More help for struggling communities.</strong> Talk about the <em>regional</em> inequalities in the US, and emphasise a vision of America as a <em>geographically</em> pluralist society, rather than one whose economy is concentrated in big cities. Find ways to channel funding to rural and small town communities that have fallen behind.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>That's just spitballing, but should give you an idea. I realise that the above is fairly light on <em>concrete policies</em>, but frankly anything I could come up with on the spot isn't going to be great. What you should do in each is get a bunch of wonks at a friendly think-tank to produce some feasible policies within federal purview that may not be as dramatic as the rhetoric might suggest, but would make the US a marginally better place.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>