<post>
  <author>Kistaro</author>
  <date>2021-01-08T22:26:16Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/gilazgk/</link>
  <title>A matrix of views on the Rittenhouse and Babbitt shootings</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's easy to imagine, IMO, a very oversimplified 2x2 grid of extremely broad opinions: (was the shooting of Ashli Babbitt appropriate?) x (were the shootings by Kyle Rittenhouse appropriate?) . Let's call these factors "B" and "R", respectively, denoting the "appropriate shoot" view with capital letters and "inappropriate shoot" with lowercase letters.</p>
      <p>It sounds to me like you can empathize with people who are in category "BR" or category "br" as fully consistent. I think these reflect easy-to-understand beliefs: people can defend themselves or people they are explicitly employed to defend, with lethal force, against unknown attackers in an obviously dangerous violent situation, or this is a categorically inappropriate use of force and there must be a much more obvious threat to shoot with.</p>
      <p>"Br" and "bR" therefore reflect groups who distinguish between these scenarios. I'm in group "BR", but it's not hard or me to imagine reasons other than _pure_ partisan bias that would put someone in the "these scenarios are not equivalent enough" groups. </p>
      <p>For group "Br", the shooter of Babbitt was a law enforcement official explicitly defending a location every reasonable person would expect to be defended with outright military force: a political meeting house where a substantial portion of the nation's highest-ranking elected officials were at that moment, when the group of people attempting to gain territory and gain entry were actively hostile to that group and had been displaying arms and violent behavior. Rittenhouse, meanwhile, was in public, did not know anything in particular about the people he was shooting, was a minor, was not a law enforcement officer, was not defending _hundreds_ of high-ranking national officials, had no obligation to be where he was, and had no duty to carry a firearm.</p>
      <p>For group "bR", Rittenhouse fired on people actively in the middle of assaulting him personally. He was actively under physical attack for his latter two shots, and had good reason to believe he had been shot at by his pursuer on his first shot, and his pursuer was physically fighting for his gun. The law enforcement official who fired on Babbitt was not being pursued, had a strong positional advantage over the woman trying to squeeze through a window, had other plausible and less-lethal means of resisting further advancement into the secured area (although a good whack to the head _is_ lethal force anyway), and was not in immediate danger.</p>
      <p>So I don't think it's too hard to see reasons someone would fall into any group. "BR" and "br" reflect general beliefs about self-defense with lethal force, or with firearms, in chaotic situations. "Br" and "bR" consider the situations to be relevantly different; I can find obvious divisions in "who is shooting?" and "was the person who shot in immediate danger on the scale of seconds before possible death?" that would lead to these conclusions.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>