<post>
  <author>Niebelfader</author>
  <date>2021-01-07T01:41:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/gidhw77/</link>
  <title>Contradicting the narrative that the fall of the Berlin Wall was in any way spontaneous</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The crowd didn't have a plan when the Berlin wall came down.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'll bite that bullet: the fall of the Berlin Wall (in terms of the physical structure) <em>was</em> a LARP. It was a performative act done out of emotion that didn't affect anything in the political process; it was a symptom, not a cause, of underlying political change. If not for the institutional support, the crowd would have been shipped to the gulag the next day and the wall would have been put right back up.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Most of the east block fell without a plan or even much organizing.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The removal of the physical structure was just the parade at the end of the already mostly-completed political process of Gorbachev's "Sinatra doctrine" plan (<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinatra_Doctrine">https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinatra_Doctrine</a>). It wasn't a plan he was <em>happy</em> about - what metropole is <em>happy</em> about not having the power to impose it's will on its colonies? - but it absolutely was a <em>plan</em>, designed to minimize bloodshed during a collapse he saw as inevitable. The secessionists within the Iron Curtain satellite states (Miklós Németh, Lech Walesa, etc) absolutely had a plan and a justified true belief in the possibility of success.</p>
      <p>The perception of the dissolution of the Soviet bloc as an unplanned upwelling of organic, leaderless people power is largely Western propaganda, for whom it is useful to perceive it as a decentralised uprising rather than a series of shadowy auto-coups by power-hungry local political elites who wanted to rule their own fiefs without interference from Moscow. I remind you that Shevardnadze in Georgia and Niyazov in Turkmenistan remained in power uninterrupted through the collapse of the Warsaw Pact and well into the 2000s.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>