<post>
  <author>OracleOutlook</author>
  <date>2021-01-05T23:54:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/gi8rxge/</link>
  <title>Whether the Pope is in doctrinal error on the death penalty</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think the word 'inadmissible' puts it in the realm of a prudential matter.  He also states the death penalty, "no longer necessary from that of penal justice."  Necessary is a prudential matter.  Pope Francis is saying that Catholics cannot resort to the death penalty today.  He cannot state that the death penalty is intrinsically immoral to the degree that there are no situations where it would be allowed.  Prior Popes have magisterially declared that the death penalty is allowed.  That capital punishment can be legitimate at least in principle is a teaching that clearly meets the criteria for being an infallible and irreformable doctrine of the ordinary Magisterium of the Church.</p>
      <p>For example, Pope Innocent (ha) III stated, "We declare that the secular power can without mortal sin impose a judgment of blood provided the punishment is carried out not in hatred but with good judgment, not inconsiderately but after mature deliberation."  The consistent teaching of the Church has always been that the death penalty is allowed and not a sin to enact.  </p>
      <p>While Pope Francis' justification for asking Catholics to prudentially not support the death penalty lies in the intrinsic value and dignity of human life, other prudential matters have similar justifications.  Not only that, all his recommendations seem prudential.  "It is impossible to imagine that states today have no other means than capital punishment to protect the lives of other people from the unjust aggressor." The position he says there is no stepping back from is that the death penalty "is inadequate from a moral standpoint and no longer necessary from that of penal justice."  Inadequate and no longer necessary sounds like a prudential judgement to me.</p>
      <p>He also mentions that a life sentence is a secret death penalty, so Catholics are now required to resist life sentences as well.  From a practical matter I'm not sure how the states can "protect the lives of other people from the unjust aggressor" without imprisoning at least a few people for their entire lifespan, but hey, he's the pope.  </p>
      <p>The entire section is a bit of a mess and I can see why many theologians are tempted to just say that he's in doctrinal error.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>