<post>
  <author>stucchio</author>
  <date>2021-01-04T17:00:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kq3o1s/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_04/gi30htc/</link>
  <title>Why EM radiation from your cell phone should not be high on your list of health concerns</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>As a former physicist, I'll provide a little bit of non-medical knowledge, namely how electromagnetic radiation interacts with organic molecules. The tl;dr; of this is that based on physics alone we can conclude that the radiation from cell phones doesn't have any medically significant effect.</p>
      <p>In much the same way, you don't need an FDA supervised RCT to determine that a 1/2" styrofoam sword won't break children's bones when they whack each other with it. Basic physics is sufficient.</p>
      <p>But the key problem with our medical establishment is that <em>they don't build and use models</em>. Instead, they just use RCTs. If an RCT has a false positive that contradicts all theories, it must be true. If you know that f(1) = 2, f(2) = 4, f(4)=6 and f(4)=8, medical people find it unreasonable to speculate that f(2.01) = 4.02. Hence you get messes like this.</p>
      <p>Onward, to the physics of electromagnetic radiation:</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Ionizing Radiation</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Ionizing radiation is well understood. The way it works is very simple; if a chemical bond has energy E, then it can only be ionized by radiation with frequency w &lt; C/E (C being a known constant). The frequencies which start becoming biologically relevant are essentially UV radiation, so wear your sunscreen.</p>
      <p>And BTW - if you've ever seen the sun you've been exposed to more ionizing radiation than a cell phone emits.</p>
      <p>This is a first order approximation. The higher order terms are so small that in order to run experiments testing the theory, you need to put atoms into microwave resonating cavities (basically high powered microwave ovens). (Keywords here are "multiphoton effect".)</p>
      <p>You can determine that energy levels for this are too low very easily with the following experiment:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Put a phone near your head and make a call.</li>
        <li>If your head doesn't explode, the energy levels are too low for multiphoton effect.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>
        <strong>Thermal effects</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Radiation can heat stuff up. The warmth of your phone or other electronics sitting in your pocket heats up your body orders of magnitude more. If you're having trouble conceiving, don't wear tight pants with a hot phone.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Weird stuff</strong>
      </p>
      <p>There are other applications of EM radiation in chemistry. For the most part these consist of "lets produce a cold low density gas, then use genetic algorithms to find the exact right laser pulse to get the compound we want". </p>
      <p>Needless to say, "cold low density gas" is the overriding concern here. At human body temperatures and normal atmospheric pressure, all sorts of chemical reactions happen. The laser pulse engineered reactions are super rare. So by stopping every other chemical reaction with cold/low density, you make it physically possible to measure the weird stuff.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>