<post>
  <author>CanIHaveASong</author>
  <date>2020-11-23T21:41:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jzbis2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_23/gddga4h/</link>
  <title>Inappropriate Advances In the Video Game Industry: A Candid Discussion</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I work a very niche role in the video games industry.  I briefly tried to go mainstream, and worked with a small studio for two years.  Within that two years, I had three industry men try to get me in bed.  All three either had some kind of power over me or were higher status in the industry, and implied that sleeping with them would enhance my career.  Two of them touched me inappropriately. </p>
      <p>I get the instinct to make things like this just not matter.  "Of course men want to sleep with women!"  "What does asking hurt?"  But even when these things don't result in technically consensual sex with an uncomfortable power dynamic, they're still really damaging to the women involved.  Part of the reason I decided not to go mainstream in my industry is because it is <em>degrading</em> to be offered things in exchange for sex, and that was clearly going to be a feature of working in mainstream video games.  </p>
      <p>I looked at what Chris Avellone is purported to have done.  It's not rape.  But he has treated women in his industry in a way that is incredibly degrading.  </p>
      <p>I think this is something #metoo fails to capture.  It's not all consent and non-consent.  #metoo was an outrage not so much at the lack of consent (it all appeared to be consensual), but of the degrading nature of the relationship given the power dynamics.  </p>
      <p>I don't know what to do about Avellone.  On one hand, I really don't think what he did was right, and he should stop it.  On the other hand, his kind of behavior is rampant in the video games industry. He's kind of a product of our culture, where the only thing that matters in sex is consent, not respect.  </p>
      <p>Is it worth an ended career?  No, I don't think so, though I'm happy enough to see him shamed.  The only thing that will stop this is making approaching women in that manner socially unacceptable.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>