<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-11-21T04:30:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gd0lvi8/</link>
  <title>Outlining a Battleground: Trisomy-21 and Abortion</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Danes are quite open about abortion—astonishingly so to my American ears—but abortions for a fetal anomaly, and especially Down syndrome, are different. They still carry a stigma. “I think it’s because we as a society like to think of ourselves as inclusive,” Lou said. “We are a rich society, and we think it’s important that different types of people should be here.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Less than half a year ago, MSU Grad Union President Kevin Bird sabotaged the career of Steven Hsu over his work towards medically justifiable embryo selection (<a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2017/11/01/105176/eugenics-20-were-at-the-dawn-of-choosing-embryos-by-health-height-and-more/">context of Hsu's project</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/GradEmpUnion/status/1270829003130261504">Bird's action</a>), and I got <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/gysmxy/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_08_2020/ftq4gto/">temp-banned here</a> and eventually perma-banned over at <a href="/r/slatestarcodex">/r/slatestarcodex</a> for foaming at the mouth when expressing my hatred of him. Nevertheless, it seems I failed to learn my lesson and to stop being surprised by these kinds of arguments even when they're voiced by multiple independent posters on <a href="/r/TheMotte">/r/TheMotte</a>. Kevin literally advocates for abortion <em>but only non-selective abortion</em><a href="https://twitter.com/itsbirdemic/status/1187145207202111488">because</a>: «Deafness isn’t a disease or a thing that needs to be removed from the population... There's simply no reason to decide deafness is an undesirable condition that ought not be allowed to exist in the world. That's an identical position and way of thinking to eugenics... <strong>The core problem isn't that eugenics forcibly removes people, it's the imposition of a hierarchy of human value</strong>.» <a href="https://twitter.com/itsbirdemic/status/1187404925635985409">And</a>: «I'm not pro-life but deciding to have an abortion because you don't want any child is very different than having an abortion because you don't want a particular kind of child. <strong>The decision made wrt the embryo has implications for how we view human life and human value at large</strong>.» This is also the logic that we see here, in bioethicists' arguments, and in the Danish debate. </p>
      <p>Rant incoming.</p>
      <p>In my view, this is blue-and-orange morality, to the extent that even trying to match it to some familiar representations feels like a waste of time. Intelligence is good. Health is good. Beauty is good. Strength is good. All functional capabilities are good. This is an essentially pagan view of "good", the kind of virtue that Greeks sought in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arete"><em>arete</em></a>; its abandonment has been pathological and regressive in a pure evolutionary sense. The desirability of arete is not meaningfully challenged by detractors, and basically everything they bring forth can be trivially twisted to damage their own views. But even if it were not so, why on Earth should anyone care about weird decadent aliens who ponder the subjectivity of goodness and the value of preserving the abstract, unfeeling category "people with disabilities" while children are born into the world of sound without hearing, into the world of thought without even middling mental prowess? And the idea that individuals with Down's are happier and thus their lives are worth living (maybe even extra worth living!) is a crippling blow to utilitarianism. Hook your kids to heroin IV drips if you want, but in my mind's eye there is a clear, self-evidently just path towards human flourishing, and it does not include mass murder of sentients nor the degradation of human beings into powerless, infertile, dimly self-aware half-pets. "It's problematic to label certain genetic makeup as inferior"? You bet your ass trisomy 21 is inferior to normal genotype! This is not even prejudice; I have the arguable honor of having been friends with a trisomy 21 person, in early childhood. I enjoyed playing with him; it was painful to leave him behind when talking became important. The nature of mental disability is <em>limit</em>. Being inherently limited, limited by your very design, is a horrible way to lack freedom, one that can be compared only to the cruelest forms of external oppression. How does the petty debate about needless crimes of Nazi Germany (not even the large-scale things, just some auxiliary policy, that had failed to attract much notice until 60s or 70s) weigh anything in comparison to this?<br />
It's little wonder that women, wishing the best to their children, find the strength to overcome the brainwashing, even as they feel bad about it later. But who should feel bad in their place is all those academic eggheads who misled them. Imagine actually tabooing the notions of "superiority" and "inferiority" so as to ensure that, even though the lion's share of our value functions are dependent on the traits we possess or see in people our fate is intertwined with, no one's life can be deemed rather more worth living and thus everyone gets to «enjoy» Harrison Bergeron brand of equality forever! </p>
      <p>This is an implicit conflict between two very different systems of thought, incompatible intuitions, corresponding to very dissimilar modes of maintaining a civilization. One, long reduced to an stubborn undercurrent, is on its way out; it's grounded in instinct, natural history, causality, matter and sciences («natural philosophy»), which grew out of fascination with the objective reality given to us in perception. The other, ascendant, works by appealing to casuistry, formal moral codes, categories and abstract rules for manipulating those with the purpose of generating normative statements and evoking emotional responses; it is affiliated with humanities, moral philosophy and law. On the casual level, the first one amounts to folk heuristics and biases, and the second to conformism and shunning of dissidents. </p>
      <p>It is probably impossible to bridge the gap with mere words. I only wish that people in the first camp realized who they are and what's at stake.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>