<post>
  <author>Krytan</author>
  <date>2020-11-19T18:09:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gcuos54/</link>
  <title>The Tragedy of the Online Commons</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This (and the discussion of the weaponization of Amazon reviews below) ties in neatly with what I experienced in the PS5 release, to reinforce a thought I have had, that the online space is being ruthlessly weaponized so that only the most efficient and aggressive actors can really utilize it (such as the  high frequency trading algorithms replacing and displacing humans.) - and that there aren't really any incentives working against this. Specifically : obeying the rules is broadly and minorly beneficial to everyone, but defecting from the rules is super duper beneficial to those who engage in it, and neutral to many other people. </p>
      <p>First, the Amazon review situation, briefly : even with 'reviews only by verified purchasers' companies can pay people to buy products from competitors, leave a bad review, and buy products from them, and leave a good review. This is lucrative for the companies, because reviews are just that important.  These reviewers would be very difficult for bots to catch. </p>
      <p>Then consider yelp : many restaurants basically feel like Yelp is the mafia, coming in and saying if they don't get their cut, they will make sure the restaurants reviews are bad or don't show up etc. And of course, entitled patrons routinely claim that if their meal isn't comped, they are going to leave a bad review on Yelp, etc. Some restaurants wish they could just opt out of the online review space, but that's not possible. </p>
      <p>Now, consider the online ordering of in demand tech items. Such as the RTX 3080. It's almost impossible for a 'normal' person to buy them. When they go up for sale online, they are instantly bought out by sophisticated bots (who can easily bypass things like captcha), and then they are resold on the secondary market (to bitcoin miners, etc). </p>
      <p>Same thing happened with the PS5. Tons of bots lying in wait to automatically monitor sites for availability, then jump on and instantly order them. Every retailer that tried to sell some things online (target, walmart, best buy, etc) had massive issues, where if you added the item to your cart the instant it was available, by the time you battled through the errors and got to the confirm payment screen, they were already totally out of stock. (We are talking a couple seconds here). There would be people who had been ready online waiting with saved payment information and shipping information and who got beat out by the bots every single time (8-10 times). </p>
      <p>Then you hop over to ebay and see hundreds of listings of the PS5 for double MSRP, etc. Overall the PS5 release was a fiasco. Most places did NOT do in person pre-ordering, but online only, because of COVID, and their online infrastructure was simply not set up to handle the sudden surge of bots and people trying to grab the items. Target's system more or less entirely broke (payments could not be processed) so they had to sell most of their stock in person. </p>
      <p>And you know what? That worked really well. I went to the store about an hour before it opened, and there was already a line of people there. It turned out I was too late, too many people in front of me, but what happened is, as soon as there were more people inline than they had units for, they came out, gave out tickets, one to each person, for each unit they had, and then told them to come back when the store opened. They did, they walked in, they presented their ticket, they forked over some cash, they got their PS5, they walked out. Simple. Reliable. Easy peasy. Stores need to do way more in person only purchases for things like this, I think. That was literally the only part of the release process that wasn't shrouded in frustration or enormous technical glitches. I didn't even come close to getting a PS5 from the in person orders but the whole process wasn't frustrating at all. It was clear and transparent.   </p>
      <p>You might think people being unable to buy a new video card or PS5 really doesn't matter in the grand scheme of things, but reading the forums, it feels very much like another aspect in the culture war : normal people being routinely and systematically shafted by richer people (the bots cost thousands to purchase) who are willing to violate civilized norms in order to reap a huge profit, while the corporations and government stand by and do nothing, and why should they? They get their cut anyway. The seething repressed anger on display was pretty impressive. It *feels* vaguely dystopian. People felt literally powerless in the face of inhuman algorithms, and hopeless that anyone would do anything about it. </p>
      <p>Behind me in line was  older black blue collar worker on his phone talking to his wife in the line at Target. He was telling her he hadn't been able to get a single one online and was now standing in line at Target at 6 am in the freezing cold trying to get one in person, but it didn't look likely. He said he thought they probably wouldn't be able to get one for their son on Christmas and then he mentioned that there were people selling them on ebay for 1,000 (instead of the 500 retail) and maybe they should 'bite the bullet' and get that, and apparently his wife pointed out they couldn't afford that because then there was a lot of back and forth about what things they could cut and sacrifices they could make so this random scalper could get an extra $500 in his pocket so their son could get a PS5 for Christmas. </p>
      <p>I really, really think people need to do more to prevent this kind of behavior. Whether it's sneakers or concert tickets or graphics cards of game consoles - why on earth should we let scalpers buy everything and drive up the prices? (There were multiple scalpers on twitter showing off their literal hundreds big stashes of PS5's - easy 80k profit, more than a years wages - and for what?) They aren't providing any useful service here, at all. It's purely parasitical.  There are various things stores could do to try to prevent people from buying too many (such as shipping only one to an address, doing in person only pre-orders/release day events, etc). But why are they motivated to do this? The units get sold either way, and trying to prevent fraudulent scalpers is a non zero cost. It's true that if you do in person only release events, you get another person physically into your store (who may buy other products or make return visits), which is a positive thing, but I'm not sure it's enough of a positive thing to matter. </p>
      <p>Sites like ebay could very easily say "All right, for the first 90 days, you aren't allowed to sell something for more than MSRP". It would be much harder for mr scalper to unload 200 PS5's if he couldn't just dump them all on ebay. But why would ebay do this? They get their cut from PS5's sold on ebay, and the higher the price rises, the bigger their profits. </p>
      <p>The government could mandate they do this, but again, how does that benefit the government? The higher prices and increased number of transactions means more tax revenue for them. The manufacturers don't care one way or the other, because the units are sold and eventually end up in someones hands. Maybe they even secretly like the idea of people paying 1,000 for a PS5 and consequently being much more invested in it than if they'd paid 500? </p>
      <p>It seems like all the primary major actors who could make positive changes, would have to do so in the knowledge they are trading personal financial benefit for the vague promises of societal improvement. That doesn't seem to be a trend we are following right now, to say the least. </p>
      <p>I kind of preferred the internet to when it was more wild territory, more informal. I'm not a huge fan of the current route where it's just one more piece of the hyper-competitive, maximum efficiency corporatism puzzle.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>