<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-11-19T02:34:12Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gcsf7f8/</link>
  <title>Dreams of Less Civilization and More Crime</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Hard disagree.</p>
      <p>I’d much prefer increased crime + less civilization, if it got rid of the state and “civilizations” stranglehold on individual liberty and prosperity.</p>
      <p>The welfare state is extortion racket whereby the the state grabs your resources as “protection” money pays it to those threatening you to continue enabling their threatening, and then prevents you from defending yourself since after all “this is a civilized society! the state has a monopoly on the use of force”.</p>
      <p>The welfare state and the cops don’t prevent random violence against people and its property, they’re the cause of it. If the police were actually abolished in Minneapolis or Portland the rioting would stop instantly because shop owners and private citizens would finally be free to shoot those threatening their lives and livelihoods.</p>
      <p>It is impossible to have months on end of looting and “lawlessness” without a whole lot of cops maintaining that status quo.</p>
      <p>.
Contrary to what you suggest we have observed what the truly desperate poor do when they don’t have state subsidized leisure, shelter, and food... they do what our vastly poorer great grand parents did and vastly poorer south asians are doing now... They work 16 hour days to secure that food, shelter, and leisure (and they get to the leisured state rather quickly and creatively  if they can help it).</p>
      <p>The phenomenon of riots that can last weeks or even months with seemingly no political organizing or profit being made is a phenomenon of welfare states and the financial security that comes from government largess... you cannot find a city in the world were the poor were able to riot for weeks let alone  months on end... the closest you get is colour revolutions by the upper middle class like Maidan or Tahrir square...</p>
      <p>It only in wealthy western countries where the poor seem mysteriously able to loot and riot for multiple fiscal quarters.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>