<post>
  <author>OracleOutlook</author>
  <date>2020-11-20T00:09:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gcw167l/</link>
  <title>QAnon History and its Pizzagate Roots</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Here's my take on it, though I only saw the beginning of Q. I don't know what it has turned into now.</p>
      <p>QAnnon cannot be separated from Pizzagate, though it has grown past Pizzagate.  The Podesta leaks showed that there was something secretive and possibly malicious going on with the Hilary campaign and Democratic politicians in particular.  For example, one of the emails showed that Podesta and his associates wanted to create a <a href="https://www.catholicnewsagency.com/news/is-there-a-deeper-network-behind-the-catholic-spring-56682">"Catholic Spring,"</a> hearkening back to the Arab Spring, and had created the organizations Catholics United and Catholics in Alliance for the Common Good in order to change Catholic teaching on matters of sexuality.  Several practicing Catholics took offense at the idea of an American politician trying to co-opt their religion for someone's political movement.  Usually politics and religion work the other way around.  </p>
      <p>In addition to the usual political scheming (see above), there appeared to be a code written into a few emails.  This code referenced pizza and food items a lot.  The most egregious example is, <a href="https://64.media.tumblr.com/bd464ffa0c84f07303a033944a8fed35/tumblr_inline_og35hfvLbs1t5zudu_540.png">"The realtor found a handkerchief.  (I think it has a map that seems pizza-related.  Is it yorus?"</a>  The misspelling of yours makes people assume that it's not an autocomplete accident.  It's clearly some kind of code.  You can see in the forwarded email that the realtor described it as a "square cloth handkerchief (white w/ black)" so the pizza/map aspects of it are inferred by the person emailing Podesta.  The realtor was not in on the code, but the assistant was.  </p>
      <p>This is just one of at least half a dozen examples of pizza appearing in emails that pizza made no sense in.  Now cheese pizza is a well known (in 4Chan circles) code for child porn, so it makes sense that 4Chan people drew that connection first.  Someone else was able to make a connection to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Handkerchief_code">handkerchief codes</a>, though I'm not quite sure what a checkered handkerchief is supposed to represent here.  </p>
      <p>People also investigated Podesta's associates and people referenced in the emails and discovered that they had <a href="https://64.media.tumblr.com/90fb7431328dc482998e99c9bcd0a8af/tumblr_inline_ogaxyyGWW81t5zudu_540.png">weird</a><a href="https://64.media.tumblr.com/8904b4e040cc0cabb3495f7843c9ce38/tumblr_inline_ogb080reu41svtbld_540.jpg">artwork</a><a href="https://64.media.tumblr.com/d1bb1991fbe28462d8638c5454757da8/tumblr_inline_ogaxvkGpQ91t5zudu_540.png">and</a><a href="https://64.media.tumblr.com/4a266f4330d5b5e309cb889da238b8e3/tumblr_inline_ogay1eLl7h1t5zudu_540.png">Instagram</a><a href="https://64.media.tumblr.com/6b57cf36beeb5bd13b86cdbe5377c288/tumblr_inline_ogaxwcu5as1t5zudu_540.png">accounts</a>.  Not necessarily a capital crime, but the 'researchers' already had the assumption that they had discovered a child porn network.  The weirdness of their targets did not help.  <a href="https://candyemoji.wordpress.com/2016/11/06/libertarianprincess-libertarianprincess/">This</a> has a good compilation of the "evidence" that people were able to dig up, if you are curious to see what kinds of connections people were making.  </p>
      <p>While this was going on, discussion of Pizzagate started being censored in most venues.  4Chan was one of the last places to talk about it without fear of censorship.  People were feeling angry and helpless.  A lot of people felt like they had enough evidence to believe in Pizzagate, but that there was nothing they could do to stop it or effect it. The thing about child sex abuse is it has a way of making nothing else mattering.  If thousands of toddlers are actually being tortured, then any action you can do to stop it, whatever the personal cost to you, is worth it.  Hence the one guy shooting up Comet Pizza.  Some people were able to resolve this tension by continuing to dig into people's personal lives, with the belief that one day they would have enough evidence to get on mainstream media or convince enough people.  Other people were unable to resolve this tension on their own.  </p>
      <p>Enter Donald Trump.  He won the US election shortly after all this went on.  He defeated Hilary Clinton, making him the natural champion for those who opposed her and her operatives.  But all that means nothing if Trump is not aware of the child sex ring problem.  In order for Trump to be the Pizzagate champion and therefore absolve people of their personal responsibility to help these kids, they needed a sign.  </p>
      <p>There were a few Proto-Q sources who claimed to be government officials (still back in November 2016.)  One that sticks out was someone claiming to be an FBI agent.  They basically said that the FBI in upstate New York were more conservative, knew about the child sex rings, and supported Donald Trump.  He said that FBI in D.C. were on the side of the rich/powerful child molesters and this imbalance kept the FBI from doing their jobs and rooting out corruption.  With the election of Donald Trump, he and his coworkers believed that the FBI would finally have the opportunity to arrest the ring leaders and save the children.  </p>
      <p>What's interesting is that this source did not claim to have any personal contact with the Trump campaign (as far as I can remember).  All the same, this guy made a number of Q like predictions, like X person would be arrested by the end of 2017 etc, etc.  He said that big things were in the works.  This conspiracy kind of brewed with different anons coming forward with more information.  However, after Trump became President, people noticed that things were not obviously changing.  No one was arrested, there were no giant revelations, nothing.  Instead, the powers that be, media conglomerates, corporations, judges, etc all seemed to be getting the upper hand on Trump.  Their champion was barely treading water.  </p>
      <p>People who still believed in Pizzagate still had the tension of nothing happening to fix the problem.  Some anonymous person (Not Q) made a claim that Hilary Clinton would be arrested on a specific date on 2017.  Q then responded to back up the claim.  This was the first public sighting of Q.  </p>
      <p>Now Q and the other anonymous were obviously wrong.  HRC was not arrested, nothing happened.  But Q was able to spin it as the attempts were thwarted by powerful actors in the deep state.  To understand how this could be effective, you might need to read up on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inoculation_theory">Inoculation Theory of persuasion</a>.  If someone is primed ahead of time to believe that there will be a future persuasion attempt, they are more likely to resist it and become further entrenched in their own views.  If a persuader is able to explain away a problem before it becomes apparent, the problem is easier to accept.   Q and other 4Chan members laid the groundwork for powerful people in governmental agencies to stop Q's predictions.  Therefore, when the predictions did not happen people already had a framework for understanding how this could be the case and Q could still remain true.  <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/iwu6qq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_21/g6c391i/?context=3">I am reminded of this conversation from earlier.</a></p>
      <p>Now the most obvious solution to Q is that Q is a somewhat unscrupulous Trump supporter who saw a large potential voting block and decided to seize it. He made Trump the solution to their unmet need.   But Q is somewhat difficult to disprove to someone who already believes in Q.  For one thing, there is the circular logic aspect where even if Q is real, Trump's enemies are powerful and have already been running the whole world for decades now, so it is expected that Trump will face setbacks.  For another, people have a psychological need to believe that someone is working to solve the worlds problems.  To accept that Q is a liar is to accept that they spent the last few years as spectators to a shitshow instead of doing something about their convictions.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>