<post>
  <author>professorgerm</author>
  <date>2020-11-18T17:56:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gcqnuns/</link>
  <title>Why Fraud Fits the Surrounding Narrative of Democrats but not Republicans</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>if it was such an effective tool, why is its use limited so neatly to one side?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Superweapons generally are, or they stop working. See also: accusations of racism or sexism; one side gets them to stick and the other doesn't. One side managed to redefine racism and weaponize their new definition, with seemingly no <em>effective</em> reaction from the other side! Is that because conservatives/Republicans are just more principled and won't play those definition games, or because they <em>can't</em>? </p>
      <p>Edit: I'm sure you can find a similar example from the right (perhaps THE TROOPS! post 9/11 or any other wartime), but I can't think of any case where both sides use the <em>exact same</em> weapon like this.</p>
      <p>Is there a "socio-political superweapon" that both sides deploy, but its effectiveness doesn't wear out?</p>
      <p>That said, I've theorized before but can no longer find the past comments: it's largely a matter of the natural tendencies of the parties and their opinions on voting.</p>
      <p>Democrats have <em>long</em> been the "maximize vote <em>total</em>" party, get everyone even remotely possible to vote, with opposition to voter ID laws, MTV or Facebook "get out the vote," they have more volunteers to do <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g700tbk/">ballot harvesting</a>. To my knowledge and I'm open to correction, historic instances of <em>significant</em> dead voters have been Democratic strongholds like Chicago's machine and "Blue Dog" West Virginia (so, pre-90s).</p>
      <p>Republicans, on the other hand, are the "maximize vote <em>legitimacy</em>" (to put it charitably) party, with voter ID laws, voter roll purges, restrictions on polling hours and locations (this would be the part where they get fishier to me).</p>
      <p>Even if actual fraud isn't naturally more in the Democratic wheelhouse, it's a more natural fit for the <em>surrounding narrative</em>. I think the parties are roughly equally unprincipled, but because of their surrounding narratives "fraud stories" fit Dems better regardless of facts, and Reps use other tactics like questionable court cases.</p>
      <p>I think the sheer volume of Democratic volunteers contributes to this as well, and that it's often (around here, anyways) that they rely on their "passionately intense" radicals to do groundwork with a more "ends justify the means" attitude, and that contributes to their "left in the primary, center in the general" approach. Whether or not Democratic activists <em>commit</em> more fraud, it "fits" the popular imagination that anyone calling themselves an activist is more likely to push the boundaries of acceptability that way, and it's at least the <em>perception</em> that the Democrats have more die-hard activists in that manner.</p>
      <p>This is a little wonkier but density may play a factor too: with the "Dems in cities" narrative, and I wouldn't be surprised if it's easier to get ballots for your neighbors in an apartment building (shared mailbox areas?) than, say, a redder suburb.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>