<post>
  <author>Steve132</author>
  <date>2020-11-23T05:54:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jz8lq5/failed_priesthood_and_a_retrospective_on_ip/gdb1z8s/</link>
  <title>The Overwhelming Cultural Victory of Copyright Reform Movement</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This argument completely ignores the incredible and insane cultural victories that the copyright reform movement won which led to disinterest.</p>
      <p>Point 1), piracy is way down because the strong IP tyrants saw the way the wind was blowing and made concessions and reforms on the market rather than lose the whole damn pie.   In particular, nobody pirates PC games anymore.  Nobody.  Because steam exists.  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>We think there is a fundamental misconception about piracy. Piracy is almost always a service problem and not a pricing problem," he said. "If a pirate offers a product anywhere in the world, 24 x 7, purchasable from the convenience of your personal computer, and the legal provider says the product is region-locked, will come to your country 3 months after the US release, and can only be purchased at a brick and mortar store, then the pirate's service is more valuable."
The proof is in the proverbial pudding. "Prior to entering the Russian market, we were told that Russia was a waste of time because everyone would pirate our products. Russia is now about to become [Steam's] largest market in Europe," Newell said.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>--Gabe Newell in 2011</p>
      <p>Intellectual property holders realized that if they didn't compromise with the pirates and instead continued to fight 16 year old kids commiting piracy with prison sentences and draconian fines that they'd still have piracy but they'd lose the court of public opinion and soon after that they'd lose the REAL courts.  So rather than let it get to that point they, you know, changed their tactics and compromised and gave the pirates huge concessions.</p>
      <p>Steam launched in 2003, itunes launched in 2003, Gabe said that quote in 2011, steam hit 75% marketshare in 2013, the same year iTunes became the number 1 music provider in the world.   The Kindle store launched in 2007 with 80k titles and by 2014 had 2.7 million titles.   Netflix pivoted to video on demand in 2007 and you know the rest of that story.  YouTube launched in 2005. Spotify launched in 2006.</p>
      <p>Are you really, honestly telling me that the copyright reform movement whipping into a fever pitch peaking at the start of the 00s in 2003-2004 is completely unrelated and has nothing at all to do with the introduction of legal cheap streaming services for games, music, movies, and books in the mid 00s?  You expect me to believe that the total dominance of those platforms today and the decrease in lawsuits for 16 year olds is completely uncorrelated with the decline of interest in the copyright reform movement? </p>
      <p>It's the analogy of big pharma realizing that if they keep paying congress to fight the drug war they will eventually lose the drug war and then lose their regulatory capture, so they switch their corporate lobbying to focus on decriminalization so they can launch their cushy Colorado dispensaries and CBT treatments.</p>
      <p>If you told a time traveling anti-copyright culture warrior that as of 2020, there are essentially no lawsuits, no prison terms for 15 year olds and essentially all content in games, music, TV, movies, and books are  available <em>legally</em> for $10/mo to everyone in the world on all their devices with a searchable user interface that grandmas can use and is safer than torrenting, they'd be giddy with the intoxication of their impending near total victory over the RIAA.</p>
      <p>The only thing they didn't get was the total abolition of copyright law on the books, but only extremist zealots wanted that and they were never going to get a constitutional amendment passed for that anyway.  America going legally vegan was more likely than that.   They majority of the movement would describe the resulting compromise that is the status quo as a huge win.</p>
      <p>2)  regarding the things they never built.   That is absolutely hilarious.  Because if you told the most zealous open source advocate in 2001 that by 2020 nearly everyone on the planet would carry a Linux or FreeBSD in their pocket, and that 97% of servers would run a totally free software OS and people suggesting windows would he laughed at.   Or that the desktop browser wars were over and IE was so totally destroyed that its successor made by Microsoft was almost entirely open sourcr AND that its only two major competitors were totally open source.  That Microsoft had integrated Linux into Windows AND become the world's largest host of free software.  That nobody respectable installed freeware anymore unless it was open-source and that major computer science journals began rejecting results that weren't released on github.  That companies worth working for as a coder no longer looked at your resume but wanted proof that you had a long history of contributing to open source products.</p>
      <p>Again, theyd be giddy with glee at the impending total victory over M$ they were about to recieve on literally all of their current fighting fronts.</p>
      <p>Its pretty damn ironic to claim that Lawrence lessig had no cultural impact whatsoever, on a forum designated as a cult of personality for a writer who <strong>chose to release his works under a permissive commercial use allowed creative commons license</strong>.   How can you say that free culture warriors didn't win when people are freely selling Scott's collective works with his blessing?   </p>
      <p>How can you just shrug at the fact that Flickr and SoundCloud and Google and Archive.org and Wikipedia all allow you to search for works by creative commons license and you can find literally hundreds if millions of works?   </p>
      <p>I remember in 2003, people made fun of a new open source encyclopedia that anyone could edit.  It would never be used by serious people for serious research is what People said.  People said it would die quickly if it was released under creative commons because someone could steal it and resell it. .....And now Britannica is fucking dead.</p>
      <p>2009 gave us an <strong>open source reserve bank</strong> and <strong>open source money</strong> for gods sake, and by 2014 we have open source stock markets and in 2020 people are legitimately discussing in semi serious tones whether or not the open source money is a fundamental threat to <strong>state sovereignty</strong>.</p>
      <p>
        <em>The copyright reform movement didn't die.  It won so completely and resoundingly from 2000-2020 that it retired.   It forced its enemies to adopt its norms, and it's institutions and creations are so ubiquitous and massive that you don't even notice that they form the building blocks for  your entire cultural universe and way of life.    You think the movement died because its not around you. But the reason its not around you is it shifted the Overton window so radically and built so much that you can't imagine your reality any other way so you don't notice it.  With very few winnable battles left unwon, it claimed victory and went home to retire in peace.</em>
      </p>
      <p>If you want to meet the movement's grandchildren who are still fighting, look up all the people bitching about YouTube copyright strike system and trying to engineer functional alternatives.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>