<post>
  <author>WokeandRedpilled</author>
  <date>2020-11-19T05:57:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gcsyjs7/</link>
  <title>An Effortpost on Child Support</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So uh. I got into a debate with someone on <a href="/r/news">r/news</a>, and ended up making a massive effort post on child support. It's like a 4 part series, so I figure I'd post it here since people might find it interesting.  It's a bit too long to reasonably rewrite, so just imagine someone very irritated replying between the first and second post.</p>
      <p>The original post is here: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/news/comments/jwdsoq/the_victims_in_a_weekend_shooting_at_a_central_el/gcsjcsl/?context=3">https://www.reddit.com/r/news/comments/jwdsoq/the_victims_in_a_weekend_shooting_at_a_central_el/gcsjcsl/?context=3</a></p>
      <p>Part 1:</p>
      <p>Basically, Child support's underlying purpose is the 'equalize the experience of the children at each parent's household, in order to prevent future conflicts of custody'. The example I was given by a <em>family court judge</em> (who currently is in practice) is, say that a father has an xbox, and a playstation, and a brand new computer for the kids to play with. Meanwhile, the mother only has an xbox. The worry is that the kids will like the father's home more, and therefore will want to stay with him more, which will cause custody problems later. Thus, the father should have to pay the mother enough money so that she can buy a playstation and a brand new computer, so that the kids won't decide favorites based on money.</p>
      <p>Note that this 'equalizing' isn't done along any other axis; if a parent has the ability to spend more time with the kid, good on him. If the parent lives in a nicer/funner neighborhood, good on her. Doesn't matter if down the line it causes favorites, the court doesn't fix that. It only 'fixes' child support.</p>
      <p>In practice, child support is formulaic, and broadly calculated (in the vast majority of states, a small minority gets more involved) through either purely through a percentage of the richer parent's income, or through a comparison of the richer and poorer parent's income (with a percentage being calculated based on the difference).</p>
      <p>This means that in some states, it doesn't matter if the mother is significantly above the poverty line: the father (and it's the father in 95% of the time) still will have to pay the mother, to afford the kid a life of luxury, not only when they're living at his home, but also when they're living at their mother's.</p>
      <p>Note that there is no obligation for the mother to actually spend the money on the kid: if the mother decides to use it on a cruise for herself, well, its not the court's job to step in and look over her shoulder, more power to her.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, this means that, if you make more than the other parent, even if you have 50/50 custody, or indeed, even if you have primary custody, you will still have to pay child support (and in the vast majority of cases, in practice the father <em>will</em>).</p>
      <p>Now, in order to make sure that you pay, the amount of child support you owe is calculated with either your actual income, or your imputed income. Your imputed income is based on a bunch of factors, including your previous job history, and your education and skills. So for example, if you work a hard, stressful, or even physically draining job like mining or deep sea fishing, and after getting divorced you want to take it easier and get a degree and transfer to something that isn't chipping away at your life, the court will not recognize that decision as valid, and continue to charge you child support according to your imputed income, which is the income you had before your change. Only when you face an involuntary change in employment, like getting fired or having an accident at work, can you end. Hell, for a bit, there was a real question whether <em>retiring at 65 would reduce child support</em> (fortunately, it does).</p>
      <p>Note that there is no similarly strict obligation for the other parent: if the other parent is a stay at home parent, and the court decides this is 'in the best interest of the child', which they often do for mothers, then the mom can refuse to ever get a job for the entirety of the child's lifetime, and your child support will reflect that refusal by forcing you to give her more money (in a majority of jurisdictions).</p>
      <p>As a side note, child support doesn't terminate based on 'voluntary reductions' in income. However, going to prison is considered a voluntary reduction in income. Thus, when you're in prison, your child support counter continues to go up, and you'll leave prison in massive debt. With very few prospects to get a job. And you can be thrown back in prison, accrue fines and penalties, and be publically shamed if you fall behind in child support. Good fucking luck bud.</p>
      <p>Finally, it doesn't matter if you were raped, you'll still have to pay child support. YES, if you as a guy were raped, and the woman gets a child, YOU HAVE TO PAY HER MONEY, WHICH SHE CAN USE UNSUPERVISED, FOR AT LEAST 18 YEARS (at least because in some states it goes to 21, and some states includes requirements for college expenses). There is a <em>strong line of precedent</em> that if you were raped when you were 13 as a guy, you'll still find yourself being forced to pay child support for your pedophile rapist. Because 'the child is the only truely innocent party'.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>