<post>
  <author>bsbbtnh</author>
  <date>2020-05-09T09:58:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpzhf8i/</link>
  <title>What Good Would Come if Arbery's Killers Were In the Right?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I just ask myself, even if the guys who killed Arbery were in the right, what good has come from it? Let's say it was a legal citizens arrest, a legal self-defense, and Arbery was a bad guy, guilty of everything he's been accused of. What good, overall, has come from this incident?</p>
      <p>Arbery has lost his life. His family and friends have lost him. The men who chased him down have lost their freedom, potentially permanently, and their friends and family suffer that loss. And the community loses them all. Few people are a net negative on their community. So these are all losses for the general community.</p>
      <p>If Arbery was a serial burglar, then we've saved a few grand of items. Maybe saved tens (or hundreds) in jailing and court costs. But now we are going to spend more, as a society, in litigating the death of Arbery. Not just on prosecution costs, and potentially jailing the shooters, but a greater cost to society.</p>
      <p>Is the community safer? Probably not. There is likely a division forming in the community. Racial tensions creeping up around the country. A deep stain the community and the nation won't get out for decades to come.</p>
      <p>The harm to individual gun rights, to practical uses of citizens arrest, to self-defense, have all been endangered. </p>
      <p>Building a strong community shouldn't revolve around locking up undesirables, or running them out of town (or killing them). It should be aimed at making those individuals better. </p>
      <p>The potential outcomes if these individuals had hopped in their vehicles, greeted Arbery as a neighbor and member of their community, and offered hope, help or opportunity, would have likely been positive for everyone involved. </p>
      <p>Or to just call the police. </p>
      <p>I understand there's value in having communities police themselves to a certain degree. But there's much more benefit if the community rehabilitates, the police focus on enforcement, and the courts on justice. More and more we see the bonds of community weakening. This is happening on nearly every level, from the family, extended family, to friends and acquaintances, to the community at large. The threads holding us all together are splitting.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>