<post>
  <author>c_o_r_b_a</author>
  <date>2020-05-11T04:06:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fq8mwpy/</link>
  <title>The Most Gender-Imbalanced Game</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>To add an anecdote, as a life-long social-competitive gamer (at least up until a certain age; haven't touched any games in many years), the super niche MMO games I played that catered most to our market had the most imbalanced gender ratio of anything I've ever seen.</p>
      <p>The most archetypal of the bunch was very ruthless and cutthroat, and modeled similarly to EVE, except with more of a focus on individual combat. Shittalking and trolling in-game and on the forums was also a huge component, and in many cases a bigger component than playing the game itself. Depending on who you asked, the game had the most "toxic" or the most fun community of any MMO.</p>
      <p>Activities generally centered around trying to annihilate one's tribal enemies, on the object and meta level: kill them and take their equipment; kill all of them and take their territories; do it so effectively and so often that they all quit the game permanently; continue mocking them relentlessly on forums after they all quit. (This in large part led to the game's undoing, because eventually there was no one left to quit besides the single clan that came out on top, and so they got bored and all quit, too.)</p>
      <p>It was, in my opinion, a very real-feeling war and geopolitics simulator, in part because those features emerged organically, like they did in EVE. Espionage, propaganda, subterfuge, diplomacy, economic warfare, ruses de guerre... There were no formal simulation or role-playing aspects to the game. Humans just did what humans in such a setting will naturally end up doing once they form competing groups.</p>
      <p>During the game's post-release peak, there were about 5 - 10,000 active players, and female players were so rare that all of them were pretty much publicly known. I'm sure there were many more women who just didn't disclose their gender or played only the less social aspects of the game, but a year after the game's release, of the active players who were part of the game world's geopolitics in any way, I think there were maybe 10 - 20 women that I can remember. No missing zeroes there. Of well-known players, I think there were about 5 women and hundreds of men.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>