<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-05-10T04:15:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fq4tz97/</link>
  <title>Gaming Motivations, Gender, and Snobbery</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Quick bit of fairly light Sunday discussion with a minor CW angle, specifically on videogaming. I was chatting to an academic colleague a few months ago who's been involved in an interdisciplinary project looking at people's videogaming motivations and habits, and after a lot of surveys and number crunching he and his fellow researchers found three fairly distinct 'clusters' of motivations for gamers, as follows.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <strong>Competition motives:</strong> gaming motivated by a desire to display skill as measured by one's individual or team performance relative to other human players.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Mastery gaming:</strong> gaming motivated by individual improvement or progress within a game.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Escapist gaming:</strong> gaming motivated by a desire to lose oneself in a world or a story.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Note that while some gamers displayed all these motivations to a high degree, the large majority of the gamers in the sample were dominated by one motive or another.</p>
      <p>I would link to his research but in addition to some standard OPSEC considerations, (a) I don't think most of it is published yet, (b) I haven't actually looked at his data in detail (most of the above is drawn from a long conversation at a bar), and (c) I kind of want to go off on some tangents of my own here that he probably wouldn't endorse.</p>
      <p>Before doing that, though, I'd want to suggest - purely from the armchair - that we can break down these categories a little further.</p>
      <p>Thinking about my competitive gaming friends, for example, it seems to me they fall into two subcategories, namely those who are mostly motivated by <em>individual excellence</em> and those who are primarily <em>social-competitive gamers</em> who only really enjoy competition in the context of clans or other online groups.</p>
      <p>In the mastery category, it seems to me like there's an intuitive distinction between the kind of <em>progress mastery</em> that comes from largely playing a game for a long time and unlocking lots of stuff or getting lots of XP (the <em>Animal Crossing</em> style of progression, also exhibited in some forgiving sandbox games) and the kind of <em>expertise mastery</em> that comes from actually honing one's skill and ability to manipulate the game's systems (think <em>Dark Souls</em>).</p>
      <p>Finally, in the escapist category, it seems like there's a big distinction between the kind of <em>roleplaying escapism</em> that involves getting lost in rich game worlds (think of big RPGs) and the kind of <em>cathartic escapism</em> that's a matter of running around blowing off steam and blowing stuff up (think of the way a lot of people seem to play the new <em>Doom</em> games, for example, or a lot of what people doing when playing GTA).</p>
      <p>With those categories on the table, let me throw out two quick more provocative angles on this question.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>First</strong>, I think that maybe these categories could be useful for understanding gender and gaming. My anecdotal experience suggests that competition motives are vastly more common among male rather than female gamers. In fact, whereas I could probably name a couple of dozen male friends who at some time or another have been putting in 15+ hours a week in competitive online gaming, I don't have a single female friend who does this.</p>
      <p>Surprisingly, something similar is true in my experience of the escapism category. Just going off stereotypes and the excellent representation of women in, e.g., literary circles, you might think that female gamers would be disproportionately represented among the players of big lore-heavy narrative games, but this doesn't match my experience at all. If anything, at a purely heuristic level, I'd say the more elaborate and lore-heavy the RPG, the more likely it is to have a male-skewed player base. However, the (again anecdotal) gender differences I've seen in this kind of motivation are less stark than in the competition domain, and in particular I know quite a few women who've played and enjoyed 5-6 hour short narrative games (e.g., <em>Firewatch, What Remains of Edith Finch, Gone Home,</em> etc.).</p>
      <p>However, I know a <em>shit ton</em> of women who seem to display mastery motivations for gaming, frequently in phone-based games. Specifically, I've noticed a lot of more casual female gamers seem to be very drawn to what I was calling progress-based mastery, where they steadily unlock features or gain XP or improve some virtual avatar or object (think of e.g. <em>Homescapes</em> or <em>Matchington Manor</em>). That's not to deny that a lot of these women get very good at the games in question. However, when I think of friends who fall clearly into the 'expertise mastery' category, they're all male, and do silly stuff like ultra hard difficulty iron man no-reload challenges for fun, just to prove their skill, and I don't know any women gamer who exhibit that kind of obsessive desire for improving expertise.</p>
      <p>In any case, while I find this schema quite useful for thinking about gender differences in gaming, I don't want to use it to make any grand claims about male or female nature, and even if the above observations are true I want to remain neutral about how much is due to marketing, socialisation, etc.. However, I am really curious to hear what other people think, especially any female gamers here.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Second,</strong> and more briefly, this schema has really helped me get clear on some of my own snobbery about gaming. Specifically, I'm almost entirely what I called a 'roleplaying escapist' gamer - I love big complex RPGs where you can spent a couple of hours just reading codex entries and dense dialogues. I'm a huge fan of all the classic old school CRPGs (<em>Baldur's Gate</em> etc.) and their modern spinoffs (<em>Pillars of Eternity</em>, <em>Tyranny</em>) and my favourite game of all time is <em>Planescape Torment</em>, though <em>Disco Elysium</em> really gave it a run for its money thanks to some spectacular writing and world building.</p>
      <p>The times I've spent playing these games have in some cases been among the peak aesthetic experiences in my life, and every bit as engaging and rewarding as reading great novels or seeing good films. So I get pretty defensive when I see people <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ffprqc/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_09_2020/fkiawfy/?context=3&amp;sort=best">suggesting that videogames in general are a waste of time, as in the one of the March CW threads</a>.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, I've long suspected that <em>certain kinds</em> of gaming are a waste of time. I could never get my head around why people would spend thousands of hours becoming <em>really really</em> good at a specific RTS or shooter when with that same time they could have read a bunch of great novels or watched some great movies or just <em>played dozens of rich narrative games</em>. It's not like they're even developing a useful skill!</p>
      <p>I have a bit more sympathy for mastery gaming, having, e.g., spent plowed 1000+ hours into Kerbal Space Program myself over the years. But when I hear about people doing <em>extremes</em> of expertise gaming, e.g., the aforementioned ultra-hardcore iron man modes or ridiculous self-imposed challenges it again feels to me like a colossal waste of time, equivalent to rewatching the same movie fifty or a hundred times.</p>
      <p>But when - with the above schema in mind - I think about gaming not as a single hobby but rather as a set of loosely related activities that different people do for very different reasons, this kind of snobbery almost starts to feel like a category mistake on my part. Other people are just approaching gaming with completely different goals and motivations from me, to the extent that you might even question whether there's really a helpful unified psychological category of 'people who like videogames.' It's like two people who like cooking, except one is obsessed with optimising nutrition and the other is optimising flavour - while they might converge on some of the same recipes on occasion, there's going to be no real common ground for them to argue about whose general preferences are superior. Which is kind of a relief, I guess?</p>
      <p>Now, this doesn't totally do away with my snobbery; I <em>do</em> think in general there are clearer and more concrete long-term payoffs for spending thousands of hours playing a bunch of rich narrative games than investing the same time playing the same shooter over and over again for years or coming up with ever more contrived challenges to test your skill. But I also feel a bit less muddled about the situation and perhaps more inclined to think of things in terms of blameless disagreement and different motives rather than irrational preferences or lack of good taste. Again, I'd be really interested to hear what others think about this.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>