<post>
  <author>Eihabu</author>
  <date>2020-05-11T11:50:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fq9gtzl/</link>
  <title>Inconsistencies in the Trayvon Martin Case</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I spent most of my adult life as a leftie, and I'd say I still lean more liberal than not, despite the level of frustrations I have. I dug into this case when it was still fresh in Florida, not expecting it to make national news. At the time I had hundreds of RSS feeds running and I was just reading stuff and posting about what I was finding constantly. The first experience that really disaffected me from the left was sharing my findings (correlating various timestamps with geographic spots in Twin Lakes basically proves Zimmerman's version of events correct - the altercation happened between where he ended the phone call and his truck, when the place Trayvon was supposedly running to was in a perpendicular direction) and being shocked at the violent reaction from so many people I thought of as good friends.</p>
      <p>This guy reading these texts and trying to imitate the ebonics is cringy as fuck and makes the documentary come off 100 times less credible. But looking back at it in retrospect, I can't see how the "do you think Trayvon was steady shagging a girl a year older and 100 pounds heavier than him" argument alone isn't immediately persuasive to basically everyone. All the leading and dragging the witness that we already knew about from back then is just icing on the cake. It's kind of ironic that the "pro-Trayvon" camp wants everyone to believe he was dating someone who was braindead and obese, when it's obvious to me just on face value alone that it's far more likely his girlfriend was someone younger and more attractive. I'm actually kicking myself because I know how easy it would have been to do what this guy did and fill in these kinds of details myself. Signing up for the RemindMeBot too...</p>
      <p>For those that don't have the patience to sit through 60+ minutes for the documentary, Gilbert also goes through traffic records and finds printed signatures from Brittany Diamond Eugene (it's not her nickname but her actual legal name) that are absolute spot-on matches for the signature on the letter that was presented in the trial. Crump originally presented the girlfriend to the media as someone who was 16, and then when Rachel Jeantel was presented and 18 years old they claimed that she initially lied about her age because she wanted more privacy. But Brittany Diamond Eugene was in fact 16 years old at the time.</p>
      <p>After that he gets an unredacted version of the investigative report on obtaining the witness and gets her address. <strong><em>It is in fact the address of the Brittany Diamond Eugene he found</em></strong>. The report claims they came to that address only to be redirected to the second address, where they found Rachel Jeantel. There's literally no way to argue this is wrong, unless Gilbert is doing fraudulent work to the point that he outright faked the unredacted version of the document he shows on the doc.</p>
      <p>Again, the case here is stronger than even /u/<a href="https://www.reddit.com/user/locustrendevous/">locustrendevous</a> is making it sound. The level of coincidence you need to explain this away is not "someone that looked damn similar was sending him pictures," but "what are the chances someone <em>literally named Diamond Eugene was at the very first address federal investigators went to</em> and has a signature that looks exactly like the one on the letter, and someone <em>in her social circle</em> has her legal middle and last name as a nickname and has a signature that looks <em>exactly</em> like hers when signing it."</p>
      <p>After all of that, he even meets her in person to buy some fashion dresses from her... and gets her to sign Christmas cards to people with fake names similar to words in the letter that was used in the trial (one is "Blessing Turner," to get her to sign the word "blessing"). <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bart_Baggett">Bart Baggett</a> is the handwriting expert he consults about it, and as you see summarized on the Wikipedia page he's pretty nonpartisan and well respected in the mainstream. "He is a court qualified forensic handwriting expert in the field of forensic document examination and has testified in over 85 US courtrooms at the local and federal level." He ends up saying he's confident there's no way Rachel Jeantel did it, but he thinks it's more likely Francine Serve wrote the cursive body of it than Diamond (though either is possible in his opinion).</p>
      <p>If you aren't aware or have forgotten the basic details of the case, you should remember at this point that when this letter was given to Rachel Jeantel to read in court, <em>she wasn't even able to read it off of the paper because - as she openly stated when asked to read it - she can't read cursive.</em> The "explanation" for this after the fact was that she had a friend write it, but I've never even heard of somebody writing someone a letter by having someone else write it and then signing it at the end. Sybrina Fulton said she considered this letter "personal" and she clearly hesitated for a long time giving it to investigators... but it's nothing but a point-by-point testimony to the Crump version of events, there's nothing most people would call "personal" in it at all. So the letter being "personal" probably isn't why she held it back for so long. </p>
      <p>Wrapping it up, he collects trash from Rachel Jeantel's house and sends it to Speckin Forensic Laboratories in Michigan along with envelopes that Diamond Eugene licked shut when he met her in person (which was recorded). They came back with a greater than 99% probability that Rachel Jeantel and Diamond Eugene are half-sisters through the Haitian mother living at that address, Marie Eugene. Then he says this explains why Diamond's second phone number was in the name of Daniel Eugene.... who by public knowledge is Rachel Jeantel's brother.</p>
      <p>The blatant weirdness and awkwardness dealing with basic questions during Rachel Jeantel's testimony all makes a hell of a lot more sense after this. (ex.1)  Rachel: "I'm feeling real guilty." Investigator: "Why?" Rachel: "Cuz I ain't know about it. I ain't know about it." (None of them seem to know what the hell she's talking about and they never press her on it) (ex.2) <strong>Investigator: "And you said, my name is Diamond Eugene?" Rachel: "Don't say my name. Don't say my fake name. Don't say my age. Don't say my fake age."</strong></p>
      <p>It was more than obvious to me 8 whole years ago that this sounds like a tampered witness trying to talk "off the record" to the person tampering them... this just fills in the missing pieces to paint a full picture.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>