<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-05-09T19:17:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fq2117x/</link>
  <title>In Praise of Cryonics and Immortalism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There's <em>so much</em> said on the topic of cryonics that I am disinclined to add my meagre share. Still, there is insufficient opposition to the ideas you have presented. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Prioritizing the lives of the now-alive over people who could be alive in the future is the opposite of what how we traditionally build moral societies </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Currently existing Western society already has a value system, one enforced by asymmetric financial and reputational risks which prevent any bold moves for all but the most powerful and unscrupulous actors. While the short story you link to is dystopian, even a slightly more morally consistent world would find us similarly disgusting. Looking at incentives, we (meaning "Americacentric civilization" here) do not optimize for hypothetical future people's happiness, nor for presently living ones' fulfillment, nor for any sort of responsible median position: we optimize for not getting sued and ruined, even if that would kill everybody (see also: Scott's lamentations about <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/08/16/an-iron-curtain-has-descended-upon-psychopharmacology/">risks of prescribing patients Russian meds which work</a>). To put it simply, there is virtually no cryonics because of red tape and gossipping fools having extreme leverage, not because of any principled opposition like the kind you are trying to portray.<br />
There is also very little money in meaningful life extension, but a gargantuan industry dedicated to stretching the last 5-6 years of pre-mortal cognitive decline into 25-30, at the cost – be it in dollars or QALY or man-hours or watt-hours or picodegrees of average global temperature – to everyone. (People also seem unconcerned about this enough to choose a visibly demented person to contend for leadership in the world's most powerful country, but that's another matter). Yet you are concerned about resources that could possibly be wasted on cryonics. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“Cryonics as default” moves us closer to the “death is the worst possible policy outcome” camp, which narrows the ambitions of civilization as a whole.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>We have zero ambitions "as a civilization"; maybe a few vague political ones, like "equity" or "ending maleness" or something. Space exploration at this point is driven by, like, one unstable enterpreneur dude, widely mocked as shitlord who was "born into wealth" and therefore unworthy of any respect. (No, SpaceX having a few thousand employees willing to move to Texas is not evidence of a civilization-scale ambition). Human cognitive enhancement is, eh, also seemingly pushed by that same dude? Human genetic enhancement is taboo because Nazis (for some reason), unlike euthanasia. Nanoassemblers are "meh", despite <a href="http://www.molecularassembler.com/Papers/MinToolset.pdf">strong evidence for their feasibility</a>. Fusion, synthbio, you name it – everything has stalled, interesting only to weird outliers, except for AI (actually narrow ML, primarily incentivized by ad bubble which is at the verge of a collapse). Serious people tend to pooh-pooh this pessimism, thinking that this is like the middle of 20th century and surely in some time we will figure it all out. Serious people are wrong, but the more important aspect is that they could only be right for accidental economic reasons. There is no coordinated ambition. The very emotional connotations of such ambitions are taboo now. We still have individual ambitions; inasmuch as humans live miserable and inconsequential lives, those are proportionally puny – and shrinking. Afford a family, afford a house, afford a dog, afford a gaming PC, afford Nintendo Switch. Is that what we'd preserve by avoiding cryonics? </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The saying goes, “science advances one funeral at a time”.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The usual "clever" objection to immortalism as a threat to novelty strikes me as concern trolling. It's also (since we're citing Big Yud) a variation of an archetypal <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/2MD3NMLBPCqPfnfre/cached-thoughts">cached thought</a>. «Death. Complete the pattern: “Death gives meaning to life.”» Science progresses, “one funeral at the time.”  Did anyone <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/11/09/ars-longa-vita-brevis/">except Scott</a> seriously think this through? Aside from the catchy quote, is there evidence in support of mortality helping the progress of science or whatever? Maybe it's actually <em>dementia</em> and <em>institutional sclerosis</em> which prevent it? How many 30 year old geniuses were blocking new paradigm-shattering research? How much possible progress is lost on torturously re-learning the same foundational stuff every generation, given that we still have fresh-faced undergrads singing paeans to Marxism, roughly 150 years after it should have become embarrassing, and our dominant system of economic production, consumption, and associated socio-economic phenomena is apparently <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Post-Fordism">"Post-Fordism"</a>? Etc.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>EDIT.</strong> The combative tone of this text, and its original conclusion especially, caused some discontent here. <a href="http://www.nonresistance.org/docs_htm/Tolstoy/Answer_to_the_Synod.html">Alas:</a> «Whether these beliefs of mine offend, pain, or tempt anyone, or interfere with anything or anyone, or displease anyone – I can change them as little as I can change my body.» What I can try to change, however, is their expression, to optimize for light rather than heat.<br />
So, to reiterate: I believe that there is, morally speaking, <em>not enough</em> opposition for cryonics skepticism such as that presented by OP, because people have a tendency to find justice in status quo. In the general case of (effectively) insurmountable circumstances, this is known as <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Just-world_hypothesis">just-world fallacy</a>. In the specific context of defending our current relationship with mortality (derisively called "deathism" by some), this attitude is, I feel, adequately examined in Nick Bostrom's <a href="https://nickbostrom.com/fable/dragon.html">Fable of the Dragon-Tyrant</a>. I cannot weasel out of admitting that yes, this is about "false consciousness" (or rather, false consciousness is the same class of mistake); but so what? It doesn't detract from sincerity or intelligence of "deathists"; just like <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/George_Fitzhugh#/Cannibals_All!">George Fitzhugh</a> with his slavery apologism, they raise some interesting points re: benefits of dying. It's just that I think their points are nullified by other considerations; when you overcome the mental resistance and allow that status quo (aging-related death itself, all infrastructure we've built around it and putative problems this system solves) might be not just injust but <em>nightmarishly bad</em> and amenable to systemic change, those considerations become self-evident pretty quickly; making deathism – including opposition to cryonics – not a proper, thorough philosophical position.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>