<post>
  <author>Lykurg480</author>
  <date>2020-05-08T23:57:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fpxgl4g/</link>
  <title>Neurath's Boat, Mathematics, and Social Trust in Knowledge</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I can understand why you found your dad inspiring in that regard, but I dont think hes very representative of "scepticism", so to speak. For one, you can achieve 90% of the effect he has by just learning a few premade talking points (this goes for other topics as well). I trust your judgement that thats not what happened here, but its quite common, and propably a large part of why the authorities have no patience. But also...</p>
      <p>Most people cant understand math. Even when they got good grades; it continues to be basically magic to them. Yet, most of them dont doubt the discipline. I think this is mostly down to trust: trust in the society that tells them its important, trust in their uncle whos a math teacher, etc. Now, what happens to people who for some reason dont trust society, and/or whos social background has noone to bear witness? You might be aware that scholars in critical post-deconstruction argue that mathematics is a white supremacist construct to manufacture justifications for political boo. And AFAICT, they havent done anything wrong arriving at that conclusion. Most people, if theyre honest, find that they really do believe in mathematics purely for social reasons. Quite a few of them dont seem to have considered that other people might understand, but even if they did, how could they distinguish it from claims of divine revelation? (To anyone who wants to make a clever argument here: keep in mind that they have to be able to understand it. I mean, go for it anyway, Id love to read it, but it propably wont help.) And yeah, lots of social claims depend on math. If it were bullshit, quite many would have been deprived for now reason. It has something tragic to it, because some of them, especially the ones who first had the idea, were propably unusually diligent in questioning "common knowledge", and it has made it worse for them. And I know that even if I catch one of those, who really did think this through and isnt just repeating something, who genuinely wants to to know and is ready to update, theres nothing I can say that makes a difference. Its a little bit of the horror of calvinist predestination in real life.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I think that it's really hard to know who to trust and to what degree, and figuring out who to believe and trust on various object-level issues is almost as hard as determining suitable beliefs about those object-level issues in the first place.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is propably true for the way youre asking the question. Starting with no trust in anyone, an bestowing it only on an inductive basis from agreement with things you found independently, the leverage from authority is indeed small. But that isnt realistic. A baby inherently trusts its mother, and as the child grows it will extend this to those she extends it to. Eventually it will come to form trusting relationships unassisted with the knowledge it gained, and might even come to distrust its parents. And if its mildly autistic and reads the right sort of blogs, it might even start to award its trust on a purely inductive basis - but even then, the knowledge gained beforehand is not thrown out just for failing to meet this standard (if anyone actually literally does this, please tell me. Ill do my best to get them a Darwin Award in the newly created information hazard category). When you demand trust from scratch, of course there is no answer. Someone below brought up <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neurath%27s_boat">Neuraths boat</a> - its just as true of trust as of belief.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>