<post>
  <author>nomenym</author>
  <date>2020-05-10T15:00:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gd5irz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_04_2020/fq62220/</link>
  <title>Painting a Picture of the Arbery Shooting</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This small town of Brunswick sounds an awful lot like towns that I’m now familiar with in the south. If so, then it’s probably highly segregated by race. The proportion of blacks in the county may be high, but there are likely subdivisions and sleepy residential roads where you practically never see a black man unless he’s delivering something.</p>
      <p>Most people are lower class, with 25 percent of the population living under the official poverty line and a median household income of about $22,000. My guess is that blacks make up a much smaller percentage of the middle class and a much higher percentage below the property line. It’s likely Arbery was from one of these lower class, maybe underclass, black communities where perhaps a majority live under the poverty line. These are likely the hotspots for violent crime and petty thefts.</p>
      <p>In my experience, jogging is really not an activity that is at all common in these communities, particularly among young black men, and especially when they’re no longer in school. Moreover, people pretty much stick to their own territories. It would be strange to see a 25 year old black guy going to a jog, and even stranger to see them go for a jog in a relatively inaccessible, and probably all white, subdivision.</p>
      <p>Chances are the McMichaels hardly ever see much foot traffic on their road, and they probably know everyone they normally see. It’s just how these places are—if you see a stranger, then it’s something that you take notice of. If Arbery regularly went jogging through this neighborhood, as was suggested by his mother, it is highly unlikely this was not known by the residents. They would see him, and wonder who this outsider is, and why he came to their subdivision to go for a jog. After seeing him jog by two or three times, they would accept it as normal.</p>
      <p>By law, Arbery may have had every right to be on this public road, but the unwritten social norms of the local culture likely meant that seeing a young black guy running down this road was probably very unexpected. I hate to say it, but I know some subdivisions near me where if I saw someone like Arbery running down the road, I was be very suspicious that they were up to no good. By the standards of the local culture, the idea that he would have just driven out there just for a jog would be pretty fantastical. The fact that he’s black must undeniably come into such a judgement just because how racially segregated these small towns can be.</p>
      <p>Arbery wasn’t a teenager (he was 25) and would have known all this. He would have known his very presence on that road would have raised eyebrows. He would have known that most of the local residents have guns, and the local culture is very much pro “shoot trespassers, ask questions later”. Arbery would likely have shared these attitudes and expectations. The idea that he would, by himself, just wandered into a partially completed home “just to explore” in a community like this is straining credulity.</p>
      <p>The McMichaels seem like southern stereotypes. In their mind, they were just trying to protect themselves, their family, and their community from a predatory menace. Culturally, they value bravery and independence, and tend to not look to authorities for permission or instruction. In this respect, they are probably much more like their victim than most people commenting here—who are, dare I say, more domesticated.</p>
      <p>The McMichaels are probably racist in the general sense that they see black people as the outgroup, and that feeling is almost certainly mutual. I doubt they hate black people as such, but they’re nonetheless quite happy to remain segregated from them. They’re almost certainly prejudiced against young black men. However, crucially, I don’t think Arbery would still be alive today if he was white. If he had instead been a white guy with a skin head, tattoos, and a wife beater, he’d probably still be dead. </p>
      <p>My opinion is that Arbery was very likely the burglar, and was up to no good the day he was killed. He was not out jogging but was likely trying to flee the area after realising he had been spotted. I suspect McMichaels was right, as a matter of fact, to assume Arbery was the burglar. However, McMichaels may not have had sufficient basis, as a matter of law, for conducting a citizens arrest, and he went about it rather poorly. I don’t think he intended to kill Arbery, but his actions escalated the confrontation more than was necessary. The McMichaels’ overzealous pursuit reaulted in Arbery’s death, and for that they deserve some blame.</p>
      <p>All that said, this moralistic Monday morning quarterbacking is rather nauseating. In the heat of the moment, making these kind of judgement calls is not exactly easy. Do you let a thief get away or do you risk chasing down an innocent man? How much direct knowledge do you have to have of a crime to perform a citizens arrest? (We’ve been discussing it here for days and people still disagree.) Is that man “hauling ass” really the guy from the surveillance footage? And you have a few minutes to make these decisions in what probably feels like a few seconds. Do you say “stop, this is a citizens arrest” or do you say “hey, stop, we just want to talk”? Adrenaline is pumping, you have seconds to act, and what your choice of words might be the difference between 6 months and 10 years in prison. What do you say?</p>
      <p>People who are quick to explain-away Arbery’s seemingly suicidal charge at his armed pursuers will point out that he feared for his life. In the heat of the moment, with only seconds to think, irrational acts are not unusual. However, this courtesy is not extended the McMichaels, who believed they were pursuing a likely armed burglar. Indeed, even though Arbery was not armed, McMichaels would have been right to fear his life—Arbery very nearly wrestled the shotgun from him, and then McMichaels would probably be the one dead in the road. (I note that this would make the story leas likely to be national news.)</p>
      <p>It would be interesting if Arbery was the burglar but McMichaels gets convicted because he didn’t technically have “immediate knowledge” of a crime. This would mean that the McMichaels did not chase down an innocent jogger, but rather caught a thief who attacked when cornered. This would see McMichaels convicted but without satisfying the politically salient narrative that made this story blow up in the first place. How many people would still celebrate McMichaels’s conviction as a victory against racism?</p>
      <p>From what I can tell, everyone is fault here. Arbery probably was the burglar they were looking for and, while death was certainly not a fitting punishment for the crime, I’m not going to lose sleep over it. Meanwhile, the McMichaels were likely stupid and overzealous wannabe heroes who miscalculated badly and man is dead because of it. I appreciate they mostly had noble intentions, and I can sympathise because we all make bad judgement calls sometimes. However, my prejudice against stupid southern white hicks tells me they probably relished the chance to give chase and point their guns at someone. Besides, they’re atrociously ugly and we haven’t had our Twitter-sponsored two minutes hate in a while. It’s nice to have something to take our minds off the wuflu pandemic, isn’t it?</p>
      <p>Kind of rambled. Sorry.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>