<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-04-06T12:54:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fvsrae/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_06_2020/fml3kb2/</link>
  <title>The Three Ages Model: Do Hard Times Create Good Men?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm sure we've all heard the "three ages of men" <a href="https://preview.redd.it/v5f0nwje5kz11.jpg?width=640&amp;crop=smart&amp;auto=webp&amp;s=1be2e1e33e7ee1b11b7b6386affe355df7c8cb69">quote/meme</a> at this point -  "hard times create strong men, strong men create good times, good times create weak men and weak men create hard times." The quote in its modern form is attributed to author G. Michael Hopf, but it's essentially the same idea as that captured by the widely-quoted quip of Voltaire that "History is only the pattern of silken slippers descending the stairs to the thunder of hobnailed boots climbing upward from below" (note: after half an hour of searching, I've been unable to find an original source; this is the <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/27955922?seq=1">earliest</a> I can find, so any tips welcome). It's also similar in spirit to the model of wealth that holds that "the first generation makes it, the second generation spends it, and the third generation blows it.” And 14th century Arab historian Ibn Khaldun wrote <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibn_Khaldun#Kit%C4%81b_al-%CA%BBIbar">a whole work</a> on the topic. As wikipedia summarises -</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Perhaps the most frequently cited observation drawn from Ibn Khaldūn's work is the notion that when a society becomes a great civilization (and, presumably, the dominant culture in its region), its high point is followed by a period of decay. This means that the next cohesive group that conquers the diminished civilization is, by comparison, a group of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbarians">barbarians</a>. Once the barbarians solidify their control over the conquered society, however, they become attracted to its more refined aspects, such as literacy and arts, and either assimilate into or appropriate such cultural practices. Then, eventually, the former barbarians will be conquered by a new set of barbarians, who will repeat the process.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I believe similar ideas crop up in the Mongol and Chinese cultures, in which the vulgarity and savagery of the barbarian is seen ultimately as a source of strength and the delicacy and sophistication of the civilized peoples as the seed of their undoing.</p>
      <p>I've had similar reflections myself a lot lately, particularly in regard to the West and China. The  documentary <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Factory">American Factory</a> paints a picture of American workers as lazy, entitled, and mentally and physically sluggish in comparison to their Chinese counterparts, and a common take on this was that it was due to the lives of relative ease and comfort enjoyed by the Americans in comparison to the Chinese who had recent memories of famine and hardship. And interestingly, one of the main responses I encountered from both Western and Asian family and friends in response to the Chinese-worshipping that came in the wake of the documentary was that the newest Chinese generation is just as much a bunch of spoilt, overweight, ADHD-riddled brats as their Western peers, again conforming to the three ages model. Meanwhile the flailing response of most Western countries to coronavirus - managing to be both complacent and panicky at the same time - in comparison to East Asia makes me more sympathetic to the idea that we are indeed heading down the stairs in fluffy pink slippers.</p>
      <p>And yet for all its intuitive appeal and wealth of historical exemplars, the three ages model seems riddled with conceptual confusions and dubious assumptions. There's a clear spotlight fallacy here, for example: the most dramatic civilizational collapses are dramatic precisely because they concern a civilization that was incredibly rich and successful. To say that wealth and success somehow <strong>cause</strong> civilizational collapse seems like saying that - since the biggest stock market losses were experienced by millionaires - we should avoid becoming millionaires lest we lose large amounts of money. How many poor, weak, and historically illegible civilizations have collapsed without leaving a historical record? How many tribes of the savage steppe peoples so beloved by Ibn Khaldun vanished without a trace due to infighting, famine, or plague?</p>
      <p>There are also significant uncertainties surrounding the relationship between the quality of elites and civilizational strength. The moment when a civilization collapses is likely to be a moment when its leaders are at their least efficient, but is that because the elites 'blew it up', or because a declining state produces less impressive elites, or perhaps because when the state is teetering for structural reasons, the genuinely smart and talented elites can see the writing on the wall and don't bother fighting for a first-class cabin on a sinking ship?</p>
      <p>Moreover, the three ages model seems to conform a bit too closely to the cries of '<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/O_tempora_o_mores!">o tempora o mores</a>' that come with each passing generation, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Clouds">have done since time immemorial</a>. "In my day, we used to have to carry ten bushels of wheat to the ziggurat each morning with none of these fancy carts you decadent youths use." It's just too much of cliche to take seriously. And besides, the Romans of 200 BC or the Athenians of 500 BC certainly enjoyed more decadent lifestyles than their grandparents, yet they vastly outperformed them in terms of military and civilizational achievements.</p>
      <p>And yet despite all this, I do find there to be something intuitive in the idea that the souls of nations and civilizations can be in rude or ill health, and that there is some strong relationship between the toughness of a state's citizens on the one hand and its cultural and moral flourishing on the other (a topic frequently covered by Dan Carlin). But I'd be very interested to hear if anyone can shed any genuine light on whether this model holds up, or how we could test it in a way that would make it genuinely informative rather than a mere historical just-so story. For example, have any quantatively-minded historians like Peter Turchin attempted to operationalise and model it? Any thoughts welcome!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>