<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-04-04T14:15:12Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/frkulx/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_30_2020/fmeocwz/</link>
  <title>Trust In Media: Some Perspectives</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Trust in media has been dropping both within the Western world and beyond for at least two decades now (e.g., <a href="https://www.journalism.co.uk/news/reuters-digital-news-report-finds-that-trust-in-the-media-continues-to-fall/s2/a740147/">[1]</a>, <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/267047/americans-trust-mass-media-edges-down.aspx">[2]</a>, <a href="https://www.ceu.edu/article/2019-06-21/trust-media-declining-worldwide-according-2019-digital-news-report">[3]</a>), and my sense is that Trump, Brexit, and now Coronavirus have all applied acute pressure on a chronically strained relationship between the media and the public. For example, I'm no fan of Trump (and would probably have voted for Hillary had I been eligible), but at least half the news stories I see that are critical of him are misleading at best and sometimes downright false, to the point where I have lost all faith in the ability of the big papers to cover these issues. One might also reasonably think that structural issues (the rise of social media and the click-economy) have changed the economic dynamics of journalism in a way that contributes to a long-term decline in public trust.</p>
      <p>These aren't new worries of course, and lots of ink has been spilled on the issue, but I'm finding them increasingly concerning. My intuition is that the fourth estate plays a critical role in the long-term health of democracy, and the collapse of trust in media institutions (especially the big ones) contributes to partisanship, division, and misinformation.</p>
      <p>Those of you who were following the conservative blogosphere back in the late 2000s might recall the  <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/28/books/28conserv.html">'epistemic closure'</a> debate that briefly became trendy. In short, the worry was that conservatives had fenced themselves off in their intellectual walled gardens and were now being intellectually eviscerated in the wake of the changing face of media and an increasingly 'flat' informational environment. In retrospect, these worries about how the end of epistemic closure would damage conservatism look quaint and optimistic. Epistemic closure hasn't ended - it's increased, and technology has contributed to the problem, as targeting algorithms get better at showing us stuff we're liable to agree with and the new digitally-enabled 'Great Sorting' means we're increasingly unlikely to <a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2017/10/05/politics/friends-political-party/index.html">have friends from opposing political parties</a>.</p>
      <p>So, I fear that trust in the media is collapsing and this will have dire consequences for democracy, intellectual integrity, and social cohesion. But enough with the bemoaning of the problem. What's to be done about it? Here are four quick hot takes. I'd be interested to hear which if any of them people here are sympathetic to.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(1) The Cynic: There's no problem.</strong> This is just the intellectual equivalent to handwringing about the 'youth of today' and the corrupting influence of the latest technology. The press is shit, yes, but it has always been shit. Complaints about tabloids and the yellow press are as old as these institutions themselves. And frankly, a lot of the present angst about declining trust is coming from the old grey ladies of established media who are shocked that they no longer control the Overton Window. Sucks to be them, but not bad news for the rest of us.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Response:</strong> maybe, but trust in the media really *is* declining now, isn't it? Same with rising partisan sentiment. These can't be dismissed as "nothing new under the sun".</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(2) The Wonk: There is a problem, and it's directly solvable.</strong> Media, technology, and politics operate in dynamic equilibrium, so it's hardly surprising that the massive changes in information technology over the last three decades have led to big changes in the media market and society. This creates new challenges, but ones we'll be able to solve. Remember the 90s when spam emails were a huge problem for end users? Now we have smart efficient behind-the-scenes solutions to them. There's good reason to think that we can do the same in the domain of media with things like fact-checking algorithms. We might also just need better science-based regulation. For example, as we getting a better understanding of the epistemic and social effects of the targeting and recommendations algorithms employed by social and media networks, we might be able to identify certain pernicious trends and legislate against them.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Response:</strong> any attempt to develop objective fact-checking frameworks is going to be mired in philosophical and political issues that are millennia old. As a modern example, look at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Babylon_Bee#Snopes.com_controversy">the mess</a> that Snopes has gotten itself into. Moreover, it's not clear how much targeting algorithms are to blame for the current mess; despite <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2018/03/youtube-extremism-and-the-long-tail/555350/">the kerfuffle over YouTube's algorithms radicalising people</a>, for example, <a href="https://archive.is/Q27nH">the latest academic take</a> on the issue is that their role has been overstated, and the surge in right-wing online content is more due to under-served political communities flocking to voices that represent them.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(3) The Tory: There is a problem, but it'll sort itself out.</strong> Maybe there won't be an easy political or technological fix for the problem of declining trust in the media, but we're still in the turbulent adolescence of these new social-technological systems like social media and YouTube. What we're essentially seeing right now is a form of technological culture shock, <a href="https://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/online-exhibits/exhibits/show/reformation/role-of-printing">like Europe after the development of movable type</a>. As people gain more experience with these systems and a greater proportion of the audience grow up as 'digital natives' we can expect the dynamics of public debate and trust to develop and become more resilient. It may take a while, but we'll get there in the end.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Response:</strong> it may seem like a safe bet to say "we'll adapt", but there's no guarantee that the process will take place in any kind of reasonable timeframe. Two hundred years after Guttenberg, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thirty_Years%27_War#Casualties_and_disease">somewhere in the region of a fifth of the population of Germany died in a bloody sectarian war</a> ushered in by a Reformation hypercharged by spreading literacy. More fundamentally one might worry that technology - rather than causing a peculiar shock - is merely exposing fracture-lines in our society that have already existed for decades. Note, for example, that fifteen years before Guttenberg, <a href="https://www.peoplesworld.org/article/today-in-history-jan-hus-burned-at-the-stake-600-years-ago/">Jan Hus</a> was burned at the stake for his popular criticisms of the Catholic Church. Perhaps what we're seeing now is not so much a technological culture shock as the collapse of the middle-brow propaganda machines that suppressed and silenced prior voices of dissent. If so, then we shouldn't expect the problem to disappear just because we get more familiar with the tech.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(4) The neoreactionary: The problem is unsolvable.</strong> Liberal democracy was always going to collapse under its internal contradictions, especially as multiculturalism and the cult of the individual replaced more cohesive community-, faith-, and nation-based values systems. When you combine a bunch of people with radically incompatible values and no shared sense of identity with a pluralistic and anarchic media environment, of course you're going to get accelerated breakdown of common structures. The old media were a flimsy scaffold holding the Cathedral together, and now they're collapsing, the Cathedral itself isn't far behind. Maybe some illiterate Frank will build anew from the ruins of empire, but it's not a project we can yet begin to make sense of. The only certainty we have for now is decline and collapse.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Response:</strong> The Cathedral has stronger foundations than many think. Europe survived Communism, Fascism, and the end of the colonial era with its core political structures broadly intact, and Western civilization has had a great knack for reinventing itself for at least 1200 years. Moreover, the insane pace of global development and technological change makes old certainties of decline and stagnation far less plausible. Few people predicted the civilisation-shaping influence of the smartphone and almost no-one predicted the rise of social media. Technologies like AI, gene-editing, and virtual reality are all in their infancy and have the potential to shape the future of our society and our species far more dramatically than Facebook or Google. For now it might seem like things are falling apart, but who knows what kind of revelations may be at hand?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>