<post>
  <author>Faceh</author>
  <date>2020-04-08T17:15:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fvsrae/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_06_2020/fmt38sn/</link>
  <title>In Support of Taleb: The Weaknesses of IQ as a Metric</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>It's hard to square Taleb citations with Taleb's well known position that people do not differ in intelligence and that IQ is a myth. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't want to hash that debate out again, but I think I have come to understand his point about IQ, and very close to agreeing with it. I do NOT think his point is that 'people do not differ in intillegence,' but HE would use a different definition for intelligence than "scores high on IQ tests." One based around survival and success under real world conditions, which are the only ones that matter. Long term it doesn't matter how high your IQ is if you get snuffed from the gene pool.</p>
      <p>His main point: IQ is not actually a solid predictor of success/outcomes on most metrics <em>once you get above 100.</em></p>
      <p>He concedes that at 85 and below, yes, IQ correlates <em>strongly</em> with outcomes. But also <em>you don't need an IQ test to tell when somebody is mentally disabled</em> and unable to function normally. So if the IQ test isn't telling you anything <em>additional</em> about those people, then its not actually useful for that purpose. So take away the high correlation with outcomes for low IQ persons, and suddenly the correlation of IQ to outcome gets looser.</p>
      <p>For instance: if I were to tell you <em>only</em> the IQ number of a randomly selected person, would you be able to tell me their likely income? total wealth? What job they hold? </p>
      <p>Keep in mind that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mensa_International">Mensa has 134,000 members</a> and most of them aren't very well known for anything.</p>
      <p>Take <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Langan#Early_life_and_career">Christopher Langan</a>, who scores <em>extremely</em> high on IQ tests. The guy has <strong>ZERO</strong> meaningful, impactful achievements to his name and by his own admission has a low income, worked many hard manual labor jobs during his life, and fosters some fairly bizarre ideas that are simply not supported by evidence yet he espouses absolute confidence in them.</p>
      <p>If IQ has such a high correlate to success, you'd expect this guy would be pulling down six figures at least, or would be well known and respected in a particular field, or otherwise would have made some great impact on the world.</p>
      <p>Now lets say I tell you that a particular person is a multi-billionaire, or the CEO of a Fortune 500 company. Hell, lets just say that its Jeff Bezos. Can you guess what his IQ is? Would you say it is higher or lower than Elon Musk, given how Amazon is worth 10x more than Tesla? Pick a random billionaire CEO and would you be able to confidently state that their IQ is above 130?</p>
      <p>And, finally, do we know how many high IQ individuals end up broke, destitute, possibly even homeless or end up with a debilitating mental disease? <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted_Kaczynski">Ted Kaczynski</a> was a math prodigy. Still ended up living in a shack on his own volition. These folks don't make headlines and might not even be included in data because we don't notice them unless they start putting bombs in the mail.</p>
      <p>I think the implication here is that there are other mental features that help ensure actual, real world success that aren't captured by IQ tests. Likely stuff like discipline, willingness to take risks BUT ALSO to avoid self-destructive behaviors, and <em>not</em> being mentally unstable.</p>
      <p>Which is all just to say that you'll have people with 150+ IQs who do nothing with it but sit around in socks with sandals playing chess all day, and some who end up winning Nobels and founding billion-dollar startups... <strong>but you couldn't tell which was which just be looking at their score.</strong></p>
      <p>Whatever IQ is measuring, it seems at best a necessary but not <em>sufficient</em> factor for certain kinds of achievement, and thus is not a measure that should be used in isolation.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>What I'm not so sure on is if this holds when analyzing populations. Given one population with IQ average of 105, and another with IQ average 115, I think I would have to bet that the one with the higher average IQ will tend to achieve more overall success.</p>
      <p>This point Taleb hasn't seemed to address directly.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>