<post>
  <author>Mexatt</author>
  <date>2020-04-10T07:44:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fvsrae/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_06_2020/fmz36vr/</link>
  <title>The Exam System Across Chinese Dynasties</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I remember watching something that said that the Chinese system of formal examinations goes back really far. These were exams for government officials.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Kind of yes, kind of no. The system as we understand it today dates back fairly recently: the Ming dynasty is when you could say it attained today's stereotype of all encompassing, society-determining influence. It existed everywhere in Song China, too, but the <em>culture</em> to sustain it hadn't quite fully matured yet: It was still easy enough for influential and wealthy provincial gentry to simply buy entry into the central government when they didn't feel like competing in the exams. And the exam process itself wasn't strictly fair and meritocratic in as meaningful a manner as it would come to embody in the Ming.</p>
      <p>There was also a great discontinuity in the Yuan and the earliest years of the Ming (the founder of the Ming dynasty did <em>not</em> like the Confucian gentry and re-introduced the examination system with great hesitancy), where the examination system lapsed entirely for roughly a century. The Mongols preferred to staff their government with foreigners who would be dependent on and loyal to them, not to the local populace and its cultural history.</p>
      <p>Even moreso than the Song, the Tang dynasty was <em>dominated</em> by a great aristocracy. To the extent that the examination system existed, it was a formality that served to either credential the scions of an aristocracy of wealth and military prowess or provide the occasional bright young provincial administrator to serve underneath that aristocracy.</p>
      <p>The Sui substantially invented the examination system. It didn't really exist before them. While studying the classics in the Han dynasty and parts of the intermediate dynasties in the North was certainly a thing, there was no serious, formal apparatus for doing so. There were certainly no regular, formal examinations for students to aspire to as a road to high bureaucratic postings. Confucianism was the sometimes-ideological-underpinning-of-the-state (although never as seriously as it would become from the Song onward, and never without some discomfort and occasional hostility between the Emperor and the Confucians), but it was no where near what it would become. Under the Han, older means of declaring dynastic legitimacy still held a stronger sway over the populace.</p>
      <p>The Qin, of course, had no time at all for Confucianism, let alone an examination system.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>