<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-04-02T16:13:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/frkulx/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_30_2020/fm870u4/</link>
  <title>Explaining the CCP's Disinterest Towards Facts</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This may be one of the weirdest nitpicks I've ever seen someone try to spin in favor of the tyrants who rule China.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Let's take the "Tiananmen square massacre". How many people died on that square in 1989 ?</p>
        <p>0</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The Tiananmen Square Massacre refers to the <strong>thousands</strong> of <em>casualties</em> sustained by protesters trying to block the military from advancing into Tiananmen Square.  (Remember, "casualty" doesn't mean death, but the number who actually died remains a mystery, with estimates ranging from hundreds to thousands; the number wounded was definitely in the thousands.)</p>
      <p>Your response appears to be... "but no one died in the actual square?"  Okay--so what?   You don't like the name?  The "Battle of Gettysburg" was not fought entirely within the boundary of the town, should we re-name it, too?</p>
      <p>"Pedantic" does not even begin to capture the level of reality denial you seem to be engaging in here. Western media has some pretty serious problems, but one big one is how much the media is <em>already</em> happy to carry water for the CCP.</p>
      <p>So far as I can tell, the CCP does not care about facts; at best, the CCP cares about harmony.  One of the most readily-observed cultural divides I notice in dealing with my Chinese students is that they don't seem to <em>understand</em> the importance Westerners attach to "truth."  It is easy to get the impression that such students are liars, cheaters, etc. but I think such loaded words obscure a much more complicated problem: that my Chinese students are culturally disposed to do <em>whatever</em> they think will result in the most harmonious relationship with others and with their community.  It took me a long time to grasp that the rampant cheating I deal with from Chinese (nationals, but not Westernized ethnics) students was their response to feeling ashamed at not being able to give me the answers (they figured) I wanted.  They saw me as an authority figure telling them to perform some task, and when they realized the only way to succeed at the level I was telling them to succeed at was to cheat, <em>they did that</em>.  Weirdly, by communicating lowered <em>expectations</em>, I have gotten much better quality (and honestly-produced) work from my Chinese students.  Whereas my Western students tend to need to be told to shoot for the moon, or they will give me bare-minimum effort every time.</p>
      <p>So my attempt to charitably interpret the <em>utter bullshit</em> that is constantly streaming from mouthpieces of the CCP is that the Western impulse to see them as sneaky liars is mistaken; rather, the CCP communicates untruths just when those untruths seem best-situated to promote social, cultural, etc. harmony.  They are not even very good communists, often; "CCP" might more accurately stand for "Chinese Confucian Party."  Because my experience with Chinese nationals and the Chinese government both is that they are much more reliable than Westerners at pursuing group cohesion and harmony <em>a la</em> Confucius--but they simply do not share the West's obsession with forming fully veridical propositions when communicating with others.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>