<post>
  <author>Rumpole_of_The_Motte</author>
  <date>2020-04-08T00:48:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fvsrae/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_06_2020/fmqtusl/</link>
  <title>Hawaii as Melting Pot, and the Perks of Casual Racism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Okay, white male born, raised and living on Oahu here. Public school graduate, center-right, I do vote republican here when the candidates aren't straight up loons. I've toyed with the idea of a big effort post about how weird it is to watch the US culture war from Hawaii. Having experienced the racism you are talking about all my life, the overwhelming take away is that racism is not the big deal everyone says it is.</p>
      <p>You've made some really great observations, but I think being a visitor during a time when all visitors are supposed to be under a 14 day quarantine and many people would like to halt all flights into the islands is going to color some experiences. The Governor has been on TV asking people not to come here. I'm sure you are getting a lot of coded warnings from people with genuine concern.</p>
      <p>Car break-ins are more about opportunity than racism. Its really easy to spot a rental car and they are really low risk targets. Even if you are caught, the victims rarely press charges. They don't care if you are from Michigan or Japan, in fact, Japanese tourists are preferred as easier marks. The government is corrupt, but I don't think that is a racial thing so much as an old boys network type problem. Part of the issue with public schools is that the private schools are so well established that all of your intelligent, conscientious kids end up there. They fall on racial lines, but are not necessarily caused by them.</p>
      <p>In a lot of ways, Hawaii was one of the most successful examples of the melting pot model of multiculturalism. </p>
      <p>The Kingdom of Hawaii culturally was pretty pro integration early on, with plenty of intermarriage with immigrant groups. If you meet someone who is part Hawaiian, ask them if they are also part Chinese. Its almost a given. White plantation managers took advantage of ethnic pride among various Asian groups early on. Japanese are asking for a raise? Go hire some Chinese labor instead. Eventually they wised up and formed integrated labor unions. That was the start of the Democrat party in Hawaii. </p>
      <p>Racism is used to enforce the conformity needed to made the whole thing function. We have ethnic slurs for everyone. Japanese who move here from the mainland are called katonks by the Japanese born here. I would argue <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kS2YLvGGtwY">its a good thing</a> or at least a useful thing. It punishes adherence to previous cultural norms and enforces the new culture. You know you have made it in Hawaii when you can make an ethnic joke about every person in the room and have them all laughing along. You may never feel as free in your life as you do in those moments. </p>
      <p>That impulse towards integration is why people from the mainland insisting on doing things the way they did back in California or wherever are resisted. They might be more efficient, but they are culturally destabilizing. Within a melting pot, you have to integrate first, then you can change things. Hawaii runs on metis like few places.</p>
      <p>Three factors are really stressing that system right now. The influx of wealthy mainlanders who refuse integration and have the resources to impose their will on others is one. On the other end of the spectrum are Micronesians who immigrate temporarily thanks to the compact of free association without needed to attempt integration. They are a drain on social services and generally not well liked by other pacific islanders. Finally, the general belief that America has failed as a melting pot is threatening to undermine successful integration here in Hawaii. As grievance politics begins to colonize our culture too many groups are learning how profitable it is to defect. The playbook for the TMT telescope project protest was taken straight from pipeline protests on the mainland. These new developments threaten the old détente and have increased distrust of newcomers.</p>
      <p>Sorry, this is an incomplete thought, but I need to get back to work. ama though.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>