<post>
  <author>SayingAndUnsaying</author>
  <date>2020-04-07T18:59:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fvsrae/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_06_2020/fmpreen/</link>
  <title>Hawaiian Travels and Fear of a Rainbow Planet</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Mauna Kea Microcosm</strong>
      </p>
      <p>At the beginning of this thing I mentioned that I’d played in the snow on the big island. Got some great pictures, too! Turns out that Mauna Kea, one of Hawaii’s two major peaks, is really, really tall, clocking in at about 4200 meters. I’m fighting the urge to write at length about the very interesting journey to the summit, but I will mention that when it snows up there the locals bring boogie boards and go tobogganing. </p>
      <p>Anyhow, given the low population density on the island, its location in the middle of the Pacific, and the elevation of the peak (almost always well above the clouds), Mauna Kea is an ideal location for telescopes and other astronomy-related endeavors. Several major installations have been built up at the top… which is naturally an unbearable violation of a Hawaiian sacred site.</p>
      <p>The organizers of the latest installation, known as the Thirty Meter Telescope (TMT), saw the tension caused by previous facilities and resolved to not make the same mistakes. They reached out to Hawaiian community leaders, made any number of concessions, pledged funds to community improvement projects, and set aside money for STEM preparation and scholarships for natives.</p>
      <p>...None of which mattered. Ten years later, the site is still regularly blockaded by the occupy-style tent villages for which the Hawaiians have developed such a penchant. Workers at the existing telescopes have been prevented from accessing them for weeks at a time. (The relevant entities are still on the hook for those projects and scholarships, though, and have paid out over $7 million since 2014.) As recently as September of last year, Governor Ige was receiving death threats due to his public endorsement of proceeding with construction. Many of the protestors seem to be tied into the Hawaiian sovereignty movement, which I won’t mention again because it’s exactly as feckless and sad as you’d expect.</p>
      <p>The tents are festooned with banners and signs decrying ‘oppression’, ‘erasure’, and ‘colonialism’. As far as I can tell, these villages are populated by an entire class of professional native victims, who have no jobs, nothing else to do, and live on the road, moving from contested site to contested site. As harsh as that probably sounds, I’m actually trying to reserve judgment. It’s not <a href="https://twitter.com/wrathofgnon/status/691089920534794240"><em>my</em> chosen method</a> for saving my dying culture, but upon reflection this course of action probably has the highest expected return for their communities. After all, guilt-wracked haole have proven over and over again that they’ll pay out even when the natives don’t hold up their end of the deal.</p>
      <p>It’s been interesting to observe how the Hawaiians are learning to play the game. I recently re-watched Disney’s <em>Moana</em> and was curious as to how accurate certain facets of it were. I’d read that Disney had done the same thing as the TMT people and created some sort of cultural sensitivity council to interface with Pacific Islanders and ensure that no toes would be stepped on. Well, it turns out Polynesian history is pretty cool, but the point is that in the process of researching it I ran into any number of disgruntled culture warriors with bones to pick -- as well as their polar opposites:</p>
      <p>“It’s fantastic that they depicted Maui as overweight. That’s an important part of our cultural heritage and we should be proud of it.” <strong>/</strong> “Portraying Pacific Islanders as obese is a disgusting racist stereotype. It’s only because of the introduction of the Western diet under colonialism that our people are so afflicted by obesity.”</p>
      <p>“I was glad to see how the villagers lived in harmony with nature and particularly how they made use of so many parts of the coconut palm. It’s impossible to overstate how important the coconut is to our culture.” <strong>/</strong> “Making such a big deal about coconuts, and having a group of bad guys who wear coconut shells, is unacceptable. ‘Coconut’ is a racial slur. Pretty much our version of the n-word.”</p>
      <p>And so on. Though one unexpected opinion came from someone who was upset that Moana’s people weren’t portrayed as more warlike. “Polynesian history is essentially the people from one island wiping out the people on the next island, over and over again. Take that away and it’s not us any more.”</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Whites, Red and Blue</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I met a smug Peter Gabriel-type at Kalama Beach who was wearing a shirt which read, </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Borders? I have never seen one. But I have heard that they exist in the minds of some people.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>We looked out at the sea together, and it got me to thinking. Hawaii is the planet’s single most geographically-isolated populated landmass. The whole immigration controversy must seem impossibly abstract and far-away to the residents here. Even so, the irony of this guy wearing such a shirt <em>on the beach</em> was just too much for me.</p>
      <p>Hawaii has been solidly blue for decades. In 2008 it voted 72% democrat to 27% republican, with similar numbers in 2012 -- but, of course, Obama was a local boy. (Restaurants here are replete with grainy, printed-out photos of him with the owners. A local hiking trail was paved and made into a tourist attraction after he visited it.) 2016 is probably a better indicator of the enduring realities here, and went 62-30 in favor of Clinton -- the highest percentage for the democrats of any state (though not DC).</p>
      <p>I take it as given that most non-whites are going to vote Democrat, but was curious as to how whites vote in the only state in which they are a minority. Turns out that among white residents there’s a fairly even split. (Given this, only about half of the votes for Trump could have come from whites. My speculation is that the rest came disproportionately from the Filipinos, who are after all responsible for the roadside anti-abortion installations.) </p>
      <p>But this doesn’t tell the whole story. Turns out that whites divide pretty well into two camps: permanent residents, who vote Democrat, and temporary residents made up almost entirely of the state’s large armed forces presence, who vote Republican. </p>
      <p>(Interesting but not especially impactful is the lesser-known island of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niihau">Niihau</a>, purchased by a private family from one of the Kamehamehas, who pocketed ten grand for the place. All but one of Niihau’s voters voted for GW in 2004, and in 2016 60% of Niihau voted for Trump. I have been told this is because the owners of the island simply eject anyone whose politics they don’t like. I find this dynamic endlessly fascinating.)</p>
      <p>Most of the insight I’ve gained into Hawaii’s racial tensions have come from online fora for locals, but the rest has come from military people, who, being red tribers, are a lot less reticent to tell it how it is in person. I’ve been doing a lot of gentle probing among the remaining, leftist whites, trying to figure out how they view the situation given that they’re under the constant if low-level threat of racially-motivated theft and assault and are too afraid to send their children to school. No direct answers so far, but then, I’ve been asking anything but directly. </p>
      <p>The main impression I’ve come away with is that they’re intent on seeing themselves as ‘cool’ haole -- insiders, accepted by the natives, etc., even when they clearly are not, and never will be. Desperate to be validated by native approval. Somehow the phrase ‘temporarily embarrassed millionaires’ keeps coming to mind, though I’m at a loss as to how to connect it. They wink and smile at the native crime, as though, ha, kids will be kids. They carefully craft plausible reasons for their children not to go to public school that have nothing at all to do with the truth.</p>
      <p>(The asians, meanwhile, continue to go peacefully about their business, quietly prosperous, not above all this so much as blessedly out of view over to one side. For now?)</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Conclusion: Fear of a Rainbow Planet</strong>
      </p>
      <p>What becomes of a society with a permanent racial underclass? A society whose founding myth is one (disproportionately successful) ethnic group evilly oppressing everyone else? Where this sentiment has become so mainstream, so constantly repeated, that even that ethnic group has internalized it? (When that ethnic group is, or becomes, a minority?)</p>
      <p>The situation here has me concerned. Open racial hostility is ubiquitous -- and almost wholly directed at whites. Institutions are corrupt and ineffectual, often pressing hard on the scales to award contracts and positions to ‘minority’ firms and applicants who are anything but the most meritorious. Resentful discrimination and harassment are prevalent in government, education, and the workplace. I think the only reason the whole thing hasn’t gone down in flames is because it’s buoyed by the massive tourism industry, but that won’t work for most of the mainland, which is where I find my thoughts turning.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>