<post>
  <author>sbrogzni</author>
  <date>2020-04-08T16:59:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fvsrae/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_06_2020/fmt13mo/</link>
  <title>On the Loss of Faith In Experts</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think there is three main factors in the loss of faith in experts in general :</p>
      <p>1- Experts not respecting hume's law.</p>
      <p>Hume's law basically says that one person expertise on what "is" is not a basis to justify his expertise on what "ought to be". Couple of examples can come to mind :</p>
      <p>A liberal economist have an expertise on how to maximise GDP growth of a country, but his belief that GDP growth maximisation should be the goal of society is a political question, debatable by society at large.</p>
      <p>A general is the expert on how to invade a country, but the question of whether or not we should invade the country is a political question that can be debated by most people.</p>
      <p>A civil engineer is the expert on how to build a bridge, but deciding whether or not we should build a bridge is a political question.</p>
      <p>A lawyer is the expert on the application of the law as it is, but his opinion on what the law ought to be is debatable.</p>
      <p>Very often, experts act like their political opinion on what course of actions must be taken to solve a problem relative to their field of expertise should be the final answer.  this is not true, their main role should be laying out the possible options in a neutral manner and their consequences, and then add their opinion if they want but they should make it clear that it's their opinion and not a fact.</p>
      <p>2- fear of groupthink among experts.</p>
      <p>Groupthink is also common among experts. Very often it is justified by evidence : the overwhelming majority biologist believe in evolution, same for astrophysicists believing in the big bang, or a somewhat less overwhelming majority climate scientist believing in man-made climate change. But sometimes, the observable groupthink is not justified by evidence : The large majority of economist are in favor of globalization of markets, is there a large amount of evidence that it's the best course of action for a country ? A majority of social science believe that inequality of outcomes is a proof of discrimination, I don't see strong evidence to back this belief.</p>
      <p>As a community, experts of a given field are just as suceptible to groupthink as any other group. When non experts observe such groupthink within a field of science, it is necessary to make a judgement call on whether or not it is justified.</p>
      <p>Unfortunately, this requirement to make a judgement call on a case by case basis is often used by populists (left and right leaning) to deny good science. The worse example of that in my mind is climate change denial. Flat-earthers would fit in as well (in a more comical and harmless manner)</p>
      <p>3- fear of lack of independence from experts</p>
      <p>Again, here we need to make a judgement call to decide if experts are independant enough in their assessment.</p>
      <p>It is very legitimate to doubt the opinions of economists and political scientists that work in think tanks. For exemple, any canadian that hear about a study from the fraser institute  (economic right wing think tank) can guess the conclusion only by reading the title... often it's the same for the rarer left wing think tanks. There's also cases of food scientists getting paid by agro-business to show that sugar is good for the heart.</p>
      <p>But just like #2, the legitimate concern for independance can be abused by denialists to shove away good science.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <strong>Second, what are the appropriate rational epistemic responses to declining trust in experts?</strong>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't think there are shortcuts that can be used to quickly make the difference between good science, good science tainted by political bias, and bad science. You have to answer these questions on a case by case basis and make a judgement call :</p>
      <p>1- Does this makes sense ?</p>
      <p>2- Is there undisclosed/pre-supposed hypothesis in the expert statement ? If yes do they make sense ?</p>
      <p>3- Who is this expert working for ? What is the interest of the expert's employer ?</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <strong>First, is there indeed a growing antipathy towards expertise on the left, and if so, what should we make of it?</strong>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't know if it's growing or not, but being a left winger myself I can certainly say that antipathy against experts has always been there on the left, expect maybe it's not as loud as it is on the right and not against the same experts. Most of the left takes anything that comes out of economists with a big grain of salt, with good reason in my opinion since the majority of them limit their thinking along the lines of neo-liberalism. some of the left also deny good science, for example denial of the human health safety of GMO crops. There is also the irrational fear of nuclear energy that's popular in left wing circles. Plenty of economic left wingers have the same justifiable doubts as the right about identity social studies.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>