<post>
  <author>UAnchovy</author>
  <date>2020-04-05T05:31:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/frkulx/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_30_2020/fmh2j8j/</link>
  <title>Explaining Catholic Integralist Goals</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Right. Vermeule's an integralist, and floating around in the same school as people like Sohrab Ahmari. Catholicism is integral to the project: if you follow conservative Protestant culture-warring in a similar area, you'll notice they take a very different approach.</p>
      <p>Meador's 2017 <a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/benedict-option-political-theology/">article on liberal and post-liberal political theologies</a> is helpful here, I think.</p>
      <p>It seems to me that a core difference here is the different roles of Catholicism and Protestantism in American history. Conservative Christians like to argue America was founded as a Christian nation, but that claim should be qualified: America was founded as a <em>Protestant</em> nation, not in explicitly confessional terms, but as a sort of background cultural assumption. The American constitution resembles some sort of presbyterian ecclesial polity far more than it does anything Catholic - self-governing local communities bound together by the interpretation of a shared sacred text, mediating their disagreements through representatives appointed to a shared synod; and these disagreements are assumed to be resolvable because of the universality of reason and the perspicuity of the sacred texts in question.</p>
      <p>Evangelical Protestants can thus be more at ease with an American political order that reflects their own assumptions about community, governance, and law. (It is surely no coincidence that David French, Ahmari's most famous sparring partner, is an evangelical Protestant.) This is not the case for Catholics, to the extent that even figures as mainstream as Ross Douthat <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/12/08/opinion/sunday/wasps-meritocracy-ross-douthat.html">joke about</a> 'a multiracial, multilingual Catholic aristocracy ruling from Quebec to Chile'.</p>
      <p>So, theory:</p>
      <p>While Vermeule doesn't come out and say it, what he's running up against here is the Protestant character of the United States constitution, in both its written and unwritten forms.</p>
      <p>(Disclaimer: Protestantism is, of course, a very broad category, and the Protestantism I'm talking about here is very different to, say, the history of Lutheranism in Germany. I am talking about a kind of Protestant settlement that I think existed at the time of the American Revolution.)</p>
      <p>Again, Vermeule doesn't quite come out and say it, but his 'common-good constitutionalism' is pretty obviously in tension with the US constitution, but because he's in America and trying to appeal to American conservatives, he can't just say "the constitution is a problem, we need a better one". He has to make a case for reinterpreting the constitution in line with his particular sectional goals. Naturally it's pilloried by the two people in the top-level comment here. It's a goal that will not appeal to anyone outside the general sphere of Catholic integralism: you might get your Ahmaris or your Patrick Deneens on board, but you will not get many American conservatives beyond that.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>