<post>
  <author>zzzyxas</author>
  <date>2020-04-01T23:58:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fscavf/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_4/fm63iyr/</link>
  <title>Combining Strengths of Podcasts and Journalism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Because this would be more readily addressable if Dr. Griffin had linked to a source, I'll take this as an opportunity to discuss the podcast format—which, after eight of these, I'm starting to have very strong opinions on.</p>
      <p>The pro of a podcast format is that humans can speak more quickly than they can write.
Insofar as bleeding-edge expert time is valuable, especially in this sort of crisis time (in this TWiV, Dr. Griffin gave his interview on a break in a hospital parking lot), this allows them to present at a level of depth you can't really find anywhere else.
A good host—Julia Galef or Joe Rogan are excellent for their various audiences—can poke such an expert when they're talking past a lay listener or to address common objections.</p>
      <p>Podcasts also have some downsides:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>You cannot hyperlink aural content (yet)</li>
        <li>If the discussion misses some point, that point gets missed, whereas if you miss something in writing, you'll normally catch it in revision.</li>
        <li>You cannot C-f audio (yet)</li>
        <li>Text reads faster than audio listens, to the point that you're losing a huge amount of your audience to the time investment</li>
        <li>If a podcast listener misses something going on in the discussion, it's much harder to go back and re-listen than it is to go back and reread text. These notes usually take 2–4 hours to create from ~1 hour of podcast, but I started doing it because I found myself halfway through the Ralph Baric interview and realized I hadn't actually learned anything.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>So: podcasts bad, traditional journalism is people with no particular background in a subject trying to write authoritatively on it, which never ends well.
Literal Ph.D. virologists have a lot to learn from their Ph.D. coronavirologist colleagues; a journalism major stands no chance.
But science communication is important!
What do?</p>
      <p>The first, and probably best, answer is to find failed journalism majors.
For instance, I have a friend who did a journalism major because she liked writing for her high school newspaper, but double majored in something that was remunerative because she also liked to eat.
She's currently in a reasonably well-paying career and does some amount of freelance journalism on the side in an area where she can speak fluently with people who are best-in-the-world.
I don't know of anyone else who does this, but journalism as a side hustle for people who are professionals in another field who also happen to be good at writing and enjoy journalism seems like a niche that could get filled, especially if <a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/blog/2020/03/24/try-our-latest-test-pilot-firefox-for-a-better-web-offering-privacy-and-faster-access-to-great-content/">Firefox Better Web</a> takes off and makes it remotely profitable to do something like that.</p>
      <p>Second is the podcast note-taker.
The idea is what I do with these TWiV notes, except good.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Expert sits down and talks about whatever, for however long they like</li>
        <li>The podcast-writer, who (unlike me) has ~an undergrad understanding of the field (e.g. biology major for coronavirus researcher) occasionally interjects for the expert to clarify something or address common misconceptions or whatever. Unlike current journalists, they certainly don't ask questions, because they, not being a Ph.D. in the field, don't have the background to ask the right questions.</li>
        <li>The podcast-writer ghostwrites the expert's presentation into some sort of publicly-consumable article. This bit here is the time- and skill-intensive part, with all the typing and searching up hyperlinks and making judgement calls about completeness/correctness/conciseness tradeoffs. This is the main area that justifies the existence of the podcast-writer.</li>
        <li>Once the podcast-writer has written the article, the expert goes back over it and makes fixes. To my understanding, this step is entirely missing from any version of modern journalism, which is a real bummer, since this means that I either have to rely on a journalism major correctly understanding a deeply technical area or give up on reading popular articles entirely. (I choose the latter.)</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Of course, this probably won't fix journalism, because the communists are going to go read Jacobin or whatever and libertarians are going to go read Reason or whatever and conservative are going to go read Breitbart or whatever and the market for articles that might update your beliefs—which is necessary if they're going to contain valuable information—is about three dozen rationalists.
But a man can dream.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>