<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-01-20T01:07:19Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gjw8bav/</link>
  <title>Kevin Williamson's "Father Fuhrer" and poor white Americans</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>_</p>
      <h3>
        <strong>Kevin and the White American</strong>
      </h3>
      <p>Two pieces of writing defined, for me, the lead up to the 2016 election. It would be simply false to say that even a substantial minority of those who voted for Donald Trump (or anyone else) read them, but they captured - nevertheless - a debate on the intellectual right (including this forum's earlier incarnation) about many of the people who voted for him. </p>
      <p>The first was the oft-quoted <a href="https://claremontreviewofbooks.com/digital/the-flight-93-election/">'Flight 93 Election'</a>' by Michael Anton. </p>
      <p>The second was <a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/magazine/2016/03/28/father-f-hrer/">'Father Fuhrer'</a> by Kevin Williamson.</p>
      <p>'The Flight 93 Election' was above all the exhortation of one elite conservative to another about themselves - Anton addressing the people of [right wing] "think-tanks, magazines, conferences, fellowships, and such" - that they ought to vote for radical change, whatever the consequence: "Let’s be very blunt here: if you genuinely think things can go on with no fundamental change needed, then you have implicitly admitted that conservatism is wrong. Wrong philosophically, wrong on human nature, wrong on the nature of politics, and wrong in its policy prescriptions." His preaching was to the upper-middle class conservative, the patrician conservative, maybe, who could be persuaded to throw his own wood on the bonfire out of a fear that everything he believed in was headed toward oblivion any other way. Anton is less concerned with the white american poor; he may have affection for them but they are not his focus - he is interested in his own people, in what remains of the conservative 'professional managerial class', and in his argument that now ought to be their last stand, even if they must throw in their lot with a grifter and a charlatan.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Williamson's piece was directed at a similar audience (one imagines few midwestern rust-belt factory workers and west virginia opioid addicts read the National Review, although perhaps that's snobbery), but in a different direction. Williamson dislikes Donald Trump, but he <em>despises</em> those who like Donald Trump. Not, admittedly, the wealthy retirees of Boca Raton, or the farmers of California's central valley, or affluent Idaho libertarians or renegade Wall Street asset managers. They have their reasons, diverse as they are, and Williams' writing generally sees them as legitimate, if sometimes in conflict with his own views. Williamson's target is a vast class of poor suburban and rural whites who live at the bottom of America's class hierarchy, the veneration of whom he hates and the lifestyle of which he finds repulsive. </p>
      <p>Williamson has a book released last year called '<em>Big White Ghetto: Dead Broke, Stone-Cold Stupid, and High on Rage in the Dank Woolly Wilds of the "Real America"</em>. Its thesis can largely be summed up in his 2016 article, though, (slightly abridged by me) here: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>[elite conservative support for Trump] is immoral because it perpetuates a lie: that the white working class that finds itself attracted to Trump has been victimized by outside forces. It hasn’t. If you spend time in hardscrabble, white upstate New York, or eastern Kentucky, or my own native West Texas, and you take an honest look at the welfare dependency, the drug and alcohol addiction, the family anarchy — which is to say, the whelping of human children with all the respect and wisdom of a stray dog — you will come to an awful realization. It wasn’t Beijing. It wasn’t even Washington, as bad as Washington can be. It wasn’t immigrants from Mexico, excessive and problematic as our current immigration levels are. It wasn’t any of that.</p>
        <p>Nothing happened to them. There wasn’t some awful disaster. There wasn’t a war or a famine or a plague or a foreign occupation. Even the economic changes of the past few decades do very little to explain the dysfunction and negligence — and the incomprehensible malice — of poor white America. So the gypsum business in Garbutt ain’t what it used to be. There is more to life in the 21st century than wallboard and cheap sentimentality about how the Man closed the factories down.</p>
        <p>The truth about these dysfunctional, downscale communities is that they deserve to die. Economically, they are negative assets. Morally, they are indefensible. Forget all your cheap theatrical Bruce Springsteen crap. Forget your sanctimony about struggling Rust Belt factory towns and your conspiracy theories about the wily Orientals stealing our jobs. Forget your goddamned gypsum, and, if he has a problem with that, forget Ed Burke, too. The white American underclass is in thrall to a vicious, selfish culture whose main products are misery and used heroin needles. Donald Trump’s speeches make them feel good. So does OxyContin. What they need isn’t analgesics, literal or political. They need real opportunity, which means that they need real change, which means that they need U-Haul.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>At the time, Williamson's words caused quite the stir - not just on the right, but on the left also. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/30/opinion/campaign-stops/who-are-the-angriest-republicans.html">The New York Times noted</a>, perhaps correctly, that "these blue-collar white Republicans, a mainstay of the conservative coalition for decades, are now vilified by their former right-wing allies as a “non-Christian” force “in thrall to a vicious, selfish culture,” corrupted by the same “sense of entitlement” that Democratic minorities were formerly accused of". <a href="https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2016/03/national-review-says-pro-trump-working-class-whites-are-lazy-and-selfish.html">Slate magazine added that</a> "it was perhaps inevitable that conservative partisans would lash back at the working-class white voters who support Trump,  but even so, the contempt with which a new National Review piece attacks poor white Middle American families is remarkable." </p>
      <p>It wasn't that Williamson was a conservative attacking Trump - that was common - it was that he wasn't attacking him primarily for alleged racism or stupidity or just being a hack in the same way that the neoconservative right often did (Williamson pays the occasional morsel of respect to this view, but it is not at the center of his argument). Williamson was attacking Trump because he perceived his supporters to be <em>scum</em>, white trash no less deserving of contempt than the disregard conservative americans were often believed to show poor minorities in the inner cities. </p>
      <hr />
      <p>Frame Williamson's point slightly differently, though, and it's an interesting argument. What Wiliamson argues is essentially that <strong><em>horrific though the American liberal elite may have been, morally, ethically, ideologically, whatever</em></strong> - Godless heathens though they are - <strong><em>they are not responsible for the condition of America's white poor.</em></strong></p>
      <p>Affirmative action at Harvard and Yale does not, God bless their hearts, trouble these people or their children. Google and Goldman Sachs dismissing good whites and asian top-20 college grads in their hunt for black and latinx women programmers and investment bankers does not affect the life chances of the trailer park single mother with three kids by three different men and a fourth on the way. Whether the police in Portland, Oregon or New York, New York are indeed defunded by a brave <em>Boricua</em> city councilmember isn't relevant to public safety in West Virginia. Whether Joe Bloggs gets replaced as a System Administrator at Disney in Anaheim by Aditya Balakrishnan on an H1B isn't either, nor is Drag Queen Story Hour in a Silver Lake public library. Nor is wealthy whites in Westchester being forced to build more 'diverse' public housing. Nor is Princeton requiring 'diversity statements' from incoming faculty members. </p>
      <p>Williamson's argument isn't that these things are good - quite to the contrary, he regularly rails against practically all of them, and even mentions several in his piece. It's that these things affect middle class and upper middle class whites - the kids of lawyers and bankers and engineers who are actually applying to Ivy League colleges and medical shools and internships in FAANG software development. They apply to people who see half their monthly salary go to funding overpaid teachers in shitty inner-city schools, who see the 'gifted and talented' programs in Boston or New York high schools get cut to support 'school integration'. They apply to people like us, here on this board and in the circles Williamson inhabits. Small town plumbing businesses in rural white America don't require diversity statements. </p>
      <p>Williamson's argument is that poor whites have fucked themselves, and that only they can un-fuck themselves, and that there is no president, regardless of his policies or his power, who can do it for them. In other words, that Trump could never succeed because he promised to improve the lives of people who could only ever be helped by themselves.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>