<post>
  <author>4bpp</author>
  <date>2021-01-20T13:27:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gjxwy4f/</link>
  <title>The importance of avoiding cross-cultural typical-minding on gender issues</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I felt a little sorry for her, reading that interview. Is she truly content to be referred to, however jokingly, as a "future trophy wife" by someone who tells her directly and somewhat dismissively that she has "medium talent" despite considering her worthy of an interview? Does the shitposting make it all worthwhile, for her?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Without being able to articulate quite cleanly <em>why</em>, I feel that it's really interesting that you point this out as something to feel sorry for her over. The warning that it's not going to be clean or articulate out of the way, I'm going to make a subpar attempt at conveying why.</p>
      <p>My own mental model of her, as a fellow (if lapsed) Eastern European, says that it probably did not cost her anything at all to make these assertions; she really just found them structurally humorous, factually true, and perhaps a good device to subtly convey a core point of the interview. You seem to instead imagine that she is going to have a moment staring at the inky blackness of her ceiling at night where she will wonder if it was all worth it to debase herself like that, and if it wouldn't be better if she gave up her toxic community and chose to associate with people who truly value her after all.</p>
      <p>The cynic, they say, knows the price of everything and the value of nothing. Eastern Europeans are among the planet's foremost cynics with respect to human interaction, and of course, the "they" in the preceding sentence are non-cynics, that is, it's an outgroup description. To the believing cynic, value is a delusion that distracts you from seeing the price. The sentence you quoted is nothing but a flex about how good she is at seeing her own price; you might tell her to <em>value</em> herself more, but to this she might retort something like "you anglos are always so hyperaware of your own 'value', but have this pathological inability to soberly look at your price". Indeed, in the "Western slutty/Eastern slutty" section, she talks about more or less exactly this, which makes me think that the "self-debasement" you quoted was a calculated illustration.</p>
      <p>Living in the anglosphere, one might be forgiven to think that a sense of self-worth, especially one that is self-evidently proven lacking by describing oneself as a "future trophy wife", is a basic and universal human need, but I think that if there is any human universal there at all, the Anglo-American notion is at most a semantic shotgun round that accidentally hits a corner of it, and mostly socially constructed otherwise. After all, plenty of cultures, including the interviewee's (mine?) and others I have interacted with (CN, JP), make do without it. (You could speculate that the latter two have some similar notions, but neither of them would self-evidently suggest that a description as a "future trophy wife" of "medium talent" is something to cry into one's pillow over.) Conversely, when I first came to the US and was put in a teaching position, at first it was really quite a big culture shock for me and took significant adjustment to internalise that I must absolutely <em>not</em> tell my students, directly or in a roundabout way, that they have medium talent or are otherwise not destined for greatness, and that my social success and likeability will indeed correlate highly with how naturally and convincingly I can tell those for whom this is the case that it is not so.</p>
      <p>In short, I don't think you should assume that this was an unpleasant experience for the interviewee just because it would have been one for you. It might be equivalent to the somewhat Tolkienian* mistake of seeing Japanese people eat sushi and thinking, "They have to eat <em>raw fish</em>? How can they live like that?".</p>
      <p>* I can only imagine that the point of that scene where Gollum threw a fit over the hobbits cooking the fish they caught would have been lost in some translations.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>