<post>
  <author>cantbeproductive</author>
  <date>2021-01-20T03:40:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gjwp8ya/</link>
  <title>The difference between rural white conservatism, and rural white nihilism</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Small town plumbing businesses in rural white America don't require diversity statements. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I can speak as someone whose cousin passed away from a drug overdose a few months ago, whose family worked in a plumbing business in rural White America.</p>
      <p>
        <em>It's the culture, stupid.</em> It's not the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/It%27s_the_economy,_stupid"><em>economy,</em></a> stupid, to speak memetically.</p>
      <p>My relatives on one side come from blue collar White American stock. One married in and has stories of their grandmother shooting squirrels to cook into stew. My grandparents pray the rosary every morning, grandpa owned a family business. All my cousins are well-adjusted and spiritually healthy. Some have cozy DC jobs, some are teachers, some are in finance, some are continuing the family business.</p>
      <p>I thought a lot about why one of my cousins drifted into drugs, and I also have experience with other friends who drifted into drugs. Without revealing too much deep or personal information, what separated the ones who got into hard drugs from the ones who got into 9-to-5's and haircuts was the culture that they attached to. This applies both to my cousins and to the people I know. </p>
      <p>The "well-adjusted" (again to speak broadly) did not attach to hip hop culture, or to the general non-religious nihilism that is in vogue in some corners of the internet. The ones that got into drugs are the ones that imbibed that culture nightly. They believe America sucks for so and so reasons, that the West sucks for x and y reasons, that there's no real spiritual point in living, and their main form of entertainment and cultural connection is very nihilistic and hedonistic music. </p>
      <p>At some point, deciding to try hard drugs is a choice. And I think that choice is often made because they believe that the culture around hard drugs is attractive. And I think it's often made because they do not see any real purpose in being sober, a long-term thinker, dealing with the pangs of life. And they've been bombarded online with this kind of music, via music videos.</p>
      <p>I was watching the Duck Dynasty podcast the other day. One of the more recent episodes. The host, an archetype of blue collar White America, says he never drinks. Not even a sip. He had a higher-up in Yeti (the company) on the pod. This guy got into hard drugs in his youth. Absolutely hit rock bottom. Nothing helped for him but finding religion. This is what the podcast was about: hitting rock bottom in drugs, finding religion (a personal relationship with Jesus), coming out clean and far better.</p>
      <p>There's a connection you can draw here, between the emphasis on personal relationship in evangelicalism, barren blue collar culture, and the psychology of belonging. Humans really need close relationships, and these "saved" evangelicals are developing the closest relationship of their life with God. </p>
      <p>To go back to my point, this barren nihilistic culture is liberal. It ain't conservative. When liberals drive through poor towns and wonder why there's nothing to do, it's because they're not at church. Trump, at least to some degree, was against this nihilistic culture. "We are a great nation under God, we are a great people, a strong people, you've got good genes," etc. What would Obama say? That if you had a son and married a Mestiza, he might look like George Zimmerman?</p>
      <p>I think "Trumpism" was something positive for many conservatives to grab on to, really. It was positive conservatism. It was a good identity. I don't think it'll go away any time soon, Trump will be a legend for decades. This kind of impact on culture is much more real than bullshit like GDP. The poor Chinese who work 12 hour days have the same kind of strong, positive culture, although there's is much more artificial. What Trump says about America you can tell he means, what Obama says about America you can tell he hired a very good Harvard speech writer to work on to get the phrasing just right.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>