<post>
  <author>CriticalDuty</author>
  <date>2021-01-19T20:26:33Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gjv9jbu/</link>
  <title>The formless void is as American as apple pie</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>multiculturalism is as American as apple pie</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.thenation.com/article/archive/what-trump-and-carson-get-wrong-islam-is-as-american-as-apple-pie/">Islam</a> is as American as apple pie. <a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/opinion/are-nazis-as-american-as-apple-pie/article36020995/">Nazism</a> is as American as apple pie. <a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/158921/socialism-american-pence-biden-sanders-2020-election">Socialism</a> is as American as apple pie. <a href="https://www.counterpunch.org/2020/06/12/riots-are-as-american-as-apple-pie/">Riots</a> are as American as apple pie. <a href="https://theintercept.com/2020/09/17/forced-sterilization-ice-us-history/">Eugenics</a> is as American as apple pie. <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/sep/21/culture-american-apple-pie-week-in-patriarchy">Rape</a> is as American as apple pie. <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/why-apple-pie-linked-america-180963157/">Apple pie</a> itself is of disputed provenance. </p>
      <p>Pompeo is clearly in the wrong here, but not because multiculturalism is some quintessentially American tradition - it's because we have long since left behind the time when anyone could articulate a cohesive and understandable American identity and the characteristic elements associated with it. You can say clearly what is and isn't Japanese food. You can say what isn't a Japanese religion, or what isn't a Japanese tradition, or what isn't a Japanese language. You cannot say any of these things about America without ten thousand indignant howls about how you're gatekeeping Americanness. The very concept of an American identity is merely the fulcrum in a political tug-of-war where different tribes of Americans screech about how they're the real Americans and everyone else is betraying the true spirit of the country. A nation without a coherent identity is merely a bank to be looted and divvied up for racial spoils. Who assimilates into a formless void?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>