<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2021-01-18T15:11:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gjq4le2/</link>
  <title>Revising conflict/mistake theory into a more granular matrix</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Against mistake/conflict theory</strong>
      </p>
      <p>
        <em>tl;dr - we should replace mistake/conflict theory with a more nuanced framework that distinguishes between the perceived content of a dispute and how we think it should be approached.</em>
      </p>
      <p>I have a good friend called Jeff who is <em>very</em> anti-Tory. He posts memes on Facebook almost daily making fun of Tories and Brexiteers, usually pretty crude ones. Recently I was chatting to him on the phone and he said he'd had a revelation: that the only reason someone could have for voting Tory was because they were racist, simple as that.</p>
      <p>My response to Jeff was to suggest that I thought he wasn't doing a very good job of thinking about the 'Tory mindset'. Rather than being racist, maybe they just had different priorities - more concerned about upholding tradition, perhaps, or preserving spiritual meaning in a secular world, or more worried about the fragility of our social and economic systems. And even if Jeff didn't share these values himself, he might try to recognise them as legitimate albeit alien concerns.</p>
      <p>Jeff seemed genuinely surprised at this idea, and I don't blame him. This is something that I think has fallen out of lot of contemporary political discourse - the idea that we can endorse a kind of <em>democratic pluralism</em> about values, recognising that people approach the world from different angles and identify different sources of meaning and importance. We don't need to share these values personally in order to respect that others care about them. And thanks to the liberal democratic tradition, we have a great way of resolving and balancing these competing interests without the need for bloodshed or malice. </p>
      <p>This conversation also made something else clear to me, something I'd been trying to put my finger on a for a while: <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/24/conflict-vs-mistake/">the conflict/mistake dichotomy popularised on SSC</a> and widely discussed here is not just incorrect but also misleading. In short, I think the main mistake it makes is to confuse <strong><em>sources</em></strong> of disagreement with people's preferred <strong><em>means of resolving</em></strong> them. Mistake theory suggests that the sources of our disagreement lie in empirical disputes; conflict theory suggests that the best way to resolve our disputes is through adversarial means. But as suggested by my conversation with Jeff, you can locate the source of disagreement in <em>values</em> rather than empirical facts while still think that <em>co-operative</em> means are the best way to resolve the disagreement.</p>
      <p>With this in mind, I'd like to suggest an alternate framework for categorising ways of approaching disputes, which we could neatly summarise via a 2x3 matrix. The two columns track the methods of resolution, namely <em>adversarial</em> vs <em>co-operative</em>, while the rows track the sources of disagreement: facts, values, and interests. I'll quickly go through the six permutations. Note that these are descriptors of how people <em>approach</em> or <em>conceptualise</em> disputes, not the disputes themselves, and people can be <em>wrong</em> about whether a dispute is really about facts or value.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Type 1 disagreement: Co-operative/Facts ("Scientific disagreement")</strong>
      </p>
      <p>First we have a disagreement that someone takes to be factual in nature but to which they adopt a co-operative means of resolution. This is the ideal of a lot of scientific dispute, even if real-world science doesn't always live up to the marketing. It's also, I think, how a lot of early internet atheists approached religion: "These poor religious folk are misinformed! Let's help them by giving them the information they may be lacking." Some people also approached the Brexit and Scottish independence debates like this - as a matter to be resolved amicably by pie charts and spreadsheets.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Type 2 disagreement: Adversarial/Facts ("Epistemic paternalism")</strong>
      </p>
      <p>This picks out the case where someone disagrees about facts but has given up trying to convince their opponents through honest methods. Maybe your opponents are too dogmatic or too stupid to get the point, or maybe they're so immersed in 'fake news' and malicious marketing to be persuaded through normal means. So you have to resort to skullduggery or manipulation. You might attempt to socially shame or ridicule your opponents into changing their minds, or knowingly distort the evidence in the name of ultimate truth: that awkward study gets suppressed ("it's a bad study anyway"), the simple narrative gets boosted ("it's right in principle even if the methods are flawed"), the enemy propagandists get silenced ("they're malicious actors anyway"). Some later internet atheism as well as Dawkins fall into this pattern, and I see a lot of this from the likes of Vox.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Type 3 disagreement: Cooperative/Values ("Liberal pluralism")</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Here we have a situation where someone takes there to be irreconcilable value differences, but is concerned to get along all the same and find a mutually satisfactory solution. I think we're very familiar with this in daily life: one employee in a company cares a great deal about animal rights and wants to change company policy to reflect this; others disagree, but value the employee's perspective and are happy to try to work out a way that their values get represented. This kind of pluralism has unfortunately fallen out of a lot of our discourse around politics, but at its best, it's the secret sauce that makes liberal democracy work. As one exceptionally admirable friend of mine put it, "I don't identify as Tory myself, but I'm glad that some people do, because it means that some sources of value that I might otherwise have missed get adequate representation."  </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Type 4 disagreement: Adversarial/Values ("Moral Struggle")</strong>
      </p>
      <p>This category is meant to capture those disagreements that are taken to involve <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/07/18/fundamental-value-differences-are-not-that-fundamental/">fundamental value disputes</a>, and where a party has decided that adversarial methods are required. This is elegantly captured by <a href="https://thingofthings.wordpress.com/2018/06/25/conservatives-as-moral-mutants/">one of Ozy's most famous/notorious posts</a>: "my read of the psychological evidence is that, from my value system, about half the country is evil and it is in my self-interest to shame the expression of their values, indoctrinate their children, and work for a future where their values are no longer represented on this Earth." I also see this attitude <em>a lot</em> in the animal rights activism world. A lot of vegans and activists basically see 'carnists' as having faulty moral compasses that can't realistically be corrected, hence justifying the use of a wide range of tactics to secure the rights and well-being of animals.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Type 5 disagreement: Co-operative/Interests ("Amicable interest arbitration")</strong>
      </p>
      <p>In theory, the fact/value distinction should be exhaustive, but when we move from the messy realm of pure philosophy to talking about politics, I think it's helpful to add a third category, namely <em>interests</em>. This is meant to pick out cases where people can at least nominally agree about the facts of the matter and share values, but nonetheless have a disagreement. Crude case: we're deciding who gets the last slice of pizza. I want it, you want it. Neither of thinks we <em>deserve</em> it more, but that's not going to get in the way of us trying to get it.</p>
      <p>But there's still room for two different strategies here. The first one is the case where a person recognises there to be opposing interests at stake, but doesn't want to be adversarial, perhaps because they like the other party, are averse to conflict, or just has an ingrained sense of fair play. I think a lot of everyday debates about things like fair distribution of household chores fall into this category, as well as some political debates about things like tax. When I hear Democrats talk about relatively benign Republicans, for example, they often talk about the case of those who just would prefer not to pay more tax. In general, someone adopting this approach to a situation is looking for a <em>fair compromise</em>.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Type 6 disagreement: Adversarial/Interests ("Self-interested struggle")</strong>
      </p>
      <p>The final case I have in mind is one where someone takes their interests to be generally opposed to another party and thinks that the best way forward is to adopt adversarial methods. It doesn't mean they can never cooperate - there might be prisoner's dilemmas situations where the best short-term equilibrium is reluctant co-operation. But the person adopting this mindset will be looking for a good opportunity to screw the other party over. While I'm not an expert on Marxism, I think a lot of discussions of class struggle certainly paint things this way: the interests of different classes are diametrically opposed, and long-term cooperation is impossible, thus making revolution inevitable. This is also broadly the model of disagreement captured by the Hobbesian mindset, as well as my own model for how psychopaths move through the world.</p>
      <p>So much for the framework; but what's it all in aid of? Well, I think it can be helpful to categorise disputes, partly because most of us get into arguments with an 'autopilot' mindset and don't think about methodology anything like enough. If we stop and ask "is what we're arguing about a matter of fact, values, and interests?" and "what are the pros and cons of cooperative vs adversarial strategies here?", we might make some progress. I might ask my friend Jeff (or maybe Ozy), "hey, why are you approaching this from a Type 4 perspective? Why not a Type 3 perspective?"</p>
      <p>Additionally, from the perspective of modelling disputes, I think this is vastly better than the mistake/conflict dichotomy. Just because you're arguing about a matter of fact doesn't mean the other person is being cooperative, and just because you're arguing about a matter of value, it doesn't mean you need to come to blows.</p>
      <p>Feedback, as always, is welcome.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>