<post>
  <author>GeriatricZergling</author>
  <date>2021-01-18T15:39:37Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gjq7paf/</link>
  <title>The hubris of geoengineering and the law of unintended consequences</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Why not geoengineering? It’s cheap, potentially powerful and can be untalented by a lone actor without necessitating a global coordination effort.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Because of the disastrous potential side effects.</p>
      <p>For instance, the top level comment mentions dumping SO2 into the air.  This is such a terrible idea that, if I ever find the first person to seriously propose it, I will personally punch them in the throat.  That's how stupid of an idea it is.</p>
      <p>The problem is that SO2 does not stay in the air - it settles down, and when it does, it boosts sulfate levels and, more important, drops pH of soil and water.  Many organisms, especially the invisible ones which make up the VAST majority of all functioning ecosystems, are very sensitive to pH.  Some might be killed outright.  Others might actually benefit, but in doing so, overwhelm other parts of the system.</p>
      <p>I think a lot of posters here (and on the related SSC subreddit) fail to grasp the core issues here, so I'll lay them out:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>The sheer scope and complexity of the global ecosystem is so far beyond any system humanity has ever analyzed as to make all of physics look like kindergarten.  EVERYTHING is nonlinear, and EVERYTHING depends upon dozens or hundreds of other interactions, and ALL of those depend upon hundreds or thousands of empirical values and variables, the vast majority of which we have no idea about.  Hell, just look at what small differences in temperature, rainfall, etc. can do, not just with global warming but with past/prehistoric events.</li>
        <li>Correspondingly, our knowledge of this system is still in its infancy.  This isn't to disparage ecologists, they have an insanely tough job.  But experiments are extremely difficult and long, require statistics that make RCTs look like child's play, and are often limited in scope, despite the vastness of these systems in both time, space, and diversity.  As our understanding has grown, we've been forced to reckon with the nonlinear, dynamic, and literally chaotic (as in chaos theory) nature of these systems even in small, contained, scales.  By definition, long-term prediction is impossible<sup>a</sup> from such systems - physics can't manage it with a double-pendulum, now imagine something just as nonlinear but as complex as an ecosystem.</li>
        <li>We are utterly dependent upon it.  Every breath you take, every bite you eat, every drop of water you drink.  Our food is just special mutants in prepared soils, still utterly dependent upon the environment (hydroponics are just separating the bits - they still have to get the water, nutrients, etc. from somewhere).  Even astronauts are tied to it - CO2 scrubbers and urine recycling just lets them space out the supply shipments from Earth.  Biosphere was a total failure, and any closed system that persists long time is a) very small and dominated by such small organisms and b) largely consists of "bottling nature" without genuinely understanding it (e.g. sealed terrariums that run for years).</li>
        <li>There is a very, very long history of both unintentional and intentional alterations of the environment going terribly wrong.  Invasive species are the simplest and most charismatic example, but more subtle and complex ones abound.  Put up levees to prevent flooding, no more fertile soil from flooding, plus the coastal wetlands aren't replenished by new sediment and start receding, leading to fewer fish fry nurseries and and collapse of key fish stocks.  Repeat ad infinitum.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>So, to sum up: We as a species are utterly and completely dependent upon a vast, global system which is incredibly complex, poorly understood, prone to highly nonlinear responses, and impossible to effectively predict with any level of precision. <strong>The idea that we can "simply" dump a load of chemicals into the atmosphere and not expect weird, insane, possibly disastrous, results through extraordinarily complex causal chains is basically the purest example of the definition of "hubris" I can imagine.</strong></p>
      <p>____</p>
      <p>
        <sup>a</sup>-This does seem incompatible with predictions from climate change, but step back and look at those predictions.  Most boil down to "this happened before X million years ago and this is what happened" or "here's how this affects species/group X, and it will have effects rippling out from them", with a subtext of "maybe fucking with the planet's life support system when we don't understand it is a bad idea."</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>