<post>
  <author>grendel-khan</author>
  <date>2021-01-20T05:06:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gjwxrlt/</link>
  <title>San Francisco politics, I think!</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This week in San Francisco, <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/projects/2020/sf-city-hall-corruption-who-is-nuru/">"S.F. City Hall scandal: Mohammed Nuru and the other key players in expanding corruption case"</a>. This is a description of the first year of an ongoing scandal. (Tangential to, but still part of, an ongoing <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/neoliberal/comments/8a9o5i/on_the_nimby_subject/dwx6oef/">series about housing</a>, mostly in California.)</p>
      <p>San Francisco has <a href="https://twitter.com/hanlonbt/status/1347294899327037440">a legendarily complex planning approval process</a>; it was notably abused in <a href="https://medium.com/yimbyneoliberal/the-great-falafel-debacle-27231edce59e">the falafel debacle</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/_fruchtose/status/1271280300228632576">the ice cream imbroglio</a>. The Department of Building Inspection (separate from the Planning process!) provides <a href="https://sfdbi.org/ftp/uploadedfiles/dbi/Key_Information/19GettingCityPermitWeb1006.pdf">a 58-page "Getting a City Permit" reader</a>, which opens with "Obtaining a City Permit can undoubtedly be one of the most confusing processes you may ever experience..."</p>
      <p>Into all of this, enter Mohammed Nuru, self-described "<a href="https://twitter.com/mrcleansf">MrCleanSF</a>" and director of San Francisco's Public Works Department. On January 27, 2020, Nuru and Nick Bovis, a restaurant owner, were arrested by the FBI for a 2018 attempt to bribe a San Francisco Airport Commissioner with $5,000 in exchange for preference in a lease for airport concession space. <a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-ndca/press-release/file/1240101/download">The FBI complaint is here</a>; from it I learned the term ["honest services fraud"], denoting that Nuru and Bovis deprived the public of the benefits of their honest service by their selfishness.</p>
      <p>Nuru is also <a href="https://sfist.com/2020/02/14/mayor-breed-admits-relationship-with-nuru-as-well-as-gifts-from-him/">the mayor's ex</a> (from before she was in office), and she had received over five thousand dollars in free car repairs from him, as a gift. (The Mayor's salary is over three hundred thousand dollars a year.) The complaint named Nuru's "GIRLFRIEND 1", who <a href="https://sfist.com/2020/02/21/girlfriend-1-identified-in-mohammed-nuru-scandal-and-its-not-london-breed/">was later identified as Sandra Zuniga</a>, head of both the Office of Neighborhood Services and the "Fix-It-Team" in the Mayor's office.</p>
      <p>In a separate case, on May 12, the FBI <a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-ndca/pr/san-francisco-based-building-contractor-and-former-building-commission-member-charged">arrested Rodrigo Santos, the former President of the city's Building Inspection Commission</a> for nearly half a million dollars in bank fraud. You can see <a href="https://www.kqed.org/news/11817788/former-sf-building-inspection-commissioner-arrested-and-charged-with-bank-fraud">checks that he altered</a>, originally made out to "DBI" (Department of Building Inspection"), altered to read "RoDBIgo Santos". (<a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/462042494/Rodrigo-Santos-Affidavit">Criminal complaint here</a>.) As of last September, Santos was <a href="https://missionlocal.org/2020/09/rodrigo-santos-dbi/">still doing murky deals</a> while out on bail; because the process is so Byzantine, the <em>real</em> system involves working around the official one.</p>
      <p>Back to the main story. On May 14, <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Nick-Bovis-pleads-guilty-to-fraud-charges-15268652.php">Nick Bovis pled guilty</a> to honest services and wire fraud, and agreed to cooperate with the FBI. On June 8, <a href="https://www.sfexaminer.com/news/nuru-scandal-widens-as-three-more-charged-in-sf-city-hall-corruption-probe/">Sandra Zuniga was charged</a> with money laundering for taking checks from contractors and using them on gifts for Nuru; two city contractors, <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/6939685-BalmreHernandez-1.html">Balmore Hernandez</a> and <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/6939637-FlorenceKongcomplaint.html">Florence Kong</a>, were also charged, for bribery and for lying to the FBI, respectively. And on June 24, <a href="https://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/news/2020/06/24/fbi-doj-walter-wong-public-works-permits-plea-deal.html">Walter Wing Lok Wong agreed to plead guilty</a> with allegations of bribery and money laundering involving Nuru and others, dating back to 2004. Wong is a "permit expediter", a real job that actually exists in San Francisco.</p>
      <p>Continuing: on September 17, <a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-ndca/pr/new-charges-plea-deals-san-francisco-city-hall-corruption-investigation">Alan Varela and Bill Gilmartin, leads of an engineering firm, were charged with bribery</a> (<a href="https://www.courthousenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/varela-gilmartin-complaint.pdf">criminal complaint</a>); they bribed Nuru with, among other things, a $40,000 tractor. This investigation stemmed from Balmore Hernandez's agreement to assist in the investigation, as he was the primary go-between for Varela and Gilmartin to bribe Nuru.</p>
      <p>On October 9, <a href="https://www.sfexaminer.com/news/contractors-charged-in-nuru-corruption-scandal-plead-guilty/">Hernandez and Kong entered plea deals</a>, the details of which are not public. On November 18, <a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-ndca/pr/san-francisco-trash-company-executive-charged-bribing-company-s-chief-san-francisco">Paul Fredrick Giusti, an executive for Recology, was charged by the IRS</a> (<a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-ndca/press-release/file/1338416/download">criminal complaint</a>); he's accused of bribing Nuru with over a million dollars, part of which was laundered through "holiday donations" to Lefty O'Doul's Foundation for Kids, which was run by Nick Bovis, who used the money to pay for holiday parties for the Department of Public Works. On November 30, <a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-ndca/pr/general-manager-san-francisco-public-utilities-commission-charged-honest-services-wire">Harlan Kelly, the General Manager of the San Francisco Public Utilities Commission, was charged with accepting bribes</a> (<a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-ndca/press-release/file/1341026/download">criminal complaint</a>) from Wong, as well as delivering confidential bid documents as part of a scheme to steer a multi-million dollar contract for LED streetlights to Wong. Kelly is being <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Was-cocaine-found-in-ex-SFPUC-chief-s-S-F-15785350.php">subjected to drug testing</a> after a search of his home turned up cocaine residue, which his attorned explained as "some residue found in the house from a party, but it had nothing to do with Harlan".</p>
      <p>Several peripheral characters are involved: <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/local-politics/article/SF-corruption-investigation-yields-14-new-15090454.php">Zhang Li, a billionaire hotel developer</a>, was subpoenaed, and was likely the anonymous developer listed in the original complaint who bribed Nuru with a two thousand dollar bottle of wine, among other things. On March 10, <a href="https://apnews.com/article/bad8f34db540d9e8584addfab263433f">Building Inspections Director Tom Hui was fired</a> for receiving free dinners from applicants, and for approaching Wong to intervene and place his son and son's girlfriend in city jobs. And on January 21, 2021, <a href="https://www.courthousenews.com/san-francisco-city-administrator-resigns-amid-corruption-probe/">Naomi Kelly, the City Administrator</a> and Harlan Kelly's wife, announced that she would step down. She's the highest-ranking appointed official in the city.</p>
      <p>In light of this ongoing cavalcade of indictments (it's unlikely that we've seen the last; Harlan Kelly will be arraigned on February 2, and Wong is still cooperating with the FBI), supervisor Matt Haney <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20201009204125/https://twitter.com/gov_sf/status/1314667224989220864">proposed more Commissions to "provide oversight"</a>. Former Mayor Willie Brown, who mentored Nuru, both Kellys, and Breed, and appointed Santos, has been <a href="https://www.kqed.org/news/11849988/nuru-scandal-former-mayor-willie-brown-reflects-on-long-time-allies-charged-by-fbi">paying for Nuru's defense</a>, and defended the allegations by saying that "It's not like someone built a bridge and used inferior products to build the bridge, and therefore risked the lives of lots of people." (There is <a href="https://twitter.com/uhshanti/status/1336052414961516545">literally a bridge <em>named after Brown</em> that has safety problems due to inferior materials</a>.)</p>
      <p>The bottom line of all this, <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/heatherknight/article/The-S-F-building-department-is-a-mess-Its-ties-15796068.php">as the <em>San Francisco Chronicle</em> notes</a>, is that the official system is so sclerotic that it drives the real work into backroom deals. It's why <a href="https://twitter.com/dividebyzerovc/status/1338904438023487489">San Franciscans demand cash from their neighbors</a> to refrain from filing discretionary reviews. This was <a href="https://twitter.com/_fruchtose/status/1350991365312802822">a known problem in 2004</a>--what became of Rudy Nothenberg?--and while the city controller's office has <a href="https://sfcontroller.org/sites/default/files/Documents/Auditing/Public%20Integrity%20Review%20-%20Non-City%20Organizations%2009.24.20.pdf">proposed auditing requirements</a> which seem to miss the point entirely, the Mayor proposed <a href="https://twitter.com/Sharkyl/status/1273031920994209793">radical changes</a> to reduce permit timelines to thirty days and remove requirements for neighborhood noticing and conditional use authorizations, which <a href="https://sfplanning.org/save-our-small-businesses-initiative">passed last year as Prop H</a>. Note that it doesn't apply to much of the city, but it's something.</p>
      <p>This has nothing to do with housing, but it sort of <em>does</em>. The attempts to generate an inclusive process and neighborhood impact have the effect of creating more and more veto points, which generates an ecosystem of bribes and expediters and special cases to navigate them. The players are different, and the bribe system for housing ("community amenities") is legal, but the outcome is the same.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>