<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2021-01-18T20:08:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzpov6/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_18/gjr4e2l/</link>
  <title>Creative industries are insanely cutthroat because supply far, far outstrips demand</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Is board game design one of those insanely cut throat creative industries like YA fiction where people just weaponize these things to kill the competition and gain market share?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think your analogy is good, though it goes beyond merely "cut throat creative."  What's weird about genre fiction (I would say that SFF, romance, and YA all fall into this category for sure, and maybe there are others) that seems to also be weird about board games is that a huge percentage of the fanbase also have fairly concrete aspirations to participate in the industry.  The other place where I see similar weirdness is in the indie video game scene (but probably not the AAA scene).</p>
      <p>In these industries, it's not just about killing the competition and gaining market share, it's about recognizing that the barrier to entry is so low that success is often <em>purely</em> a matter of notoriety--or status.  I suspect anyone with an IQ over 115 and a serious interest in writing genre fiction, or designing a board game or video game, has a decent shot at coming up with a passable product on their first try.  It might be somewhat derivative or lack the finesse that an industry veteran would demonstrate, but how many <em>Dragonlance</em> or <em>Ravenloft</em> novels does that describe?  How many million-dollar Kickstarter boardgames does that cover?  How many indie video games can be described that way?  I don't know what percentage of NFL fans think "maybe I should get into the NFL?" but I suspect it is dramatically smaller than the percentage of teenage readers who think "maybe I should be an author?"</p>
      <p>The seething envy that often manifests when rookies hit a home run (or even a double) on their first shot is pretty extreme in all these spaces.  Scratch an angry fan and underneath you'll often find a failed (so far!) aspirant.  Add to this social media that gets subsumed into the culture wars, and you have a recipe for "elite overproduction syndrome."  And since it is often possible for mob leaders to cash in on witch hunts, witch hunts are incentivized...</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>