<post>
  <author>withmymindsheruns</author>
  <date>2021-01-18T00:23:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kzbrqx/the_bailey_podcast_e022_just_say_no_to_sobriety/gjo1v27/</link>
  <title>Whether joy is primarily a function of novelty, and how that relates to psychedelics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think that 'amazement and giggling' is a function of being so profoundly ejected from your normal operating state that your mind experiences the world as pure novelty. Joy is a function of that state. That's why properly cared for kids are so joyful. Proper care means that they haven't experienced the world as a threatening place to be recoiled from, and so they experience it as an unfolding tapestry of new experience which has all their senses switched onto full as they try to make sense of it.</p>
      <p>Psychedelics (i think) basically push you back into that state where you are once again faced with a world where you haven't started to ignore almost everything.</p>
      <p>As the great saint Jordan Peterson says (kind of): the state of paying attention to everything as if it is a source of potential meaning, and then extracting that meaning is profoundly enervating, it's the quintessential font of a vital life and bulwark against existential despair. But our lives tend to become routinized and most of the elements of our world gets categorised into 'not relevant' when they don't intrude into the rut of our daily existence. To remedy this we might start to add things to pay attention to- movies, reddit posts, politics, tv blah blah blah. These things can actually stimulate that state of actively engaged attention that we crave, or they can just give you a kind of faked version of it where random, meaningless shocks of stimulation are delivered, and most probably give you some mix of the two.</p>
      <p>I think the division between those two aspects is how well they facilitate the mind in the process of making sense of it's surroundings and explaining them more satisfactorily to itself. I think that's what the intense pleasure is in reading something that shows you 'this thing that you thought worked like this, well look at this bit here, now can you see it actually works like that!' That feeling of the pieces dropping into place, seeing through the veil, reaching the next level that you didn't even realise existed etc. It's the opposite of the grey sludge of too much routine where the attention just becomes lost in an inner, meandering, directionless fug that never arrives anywhere and never notices much of what is around it.</p>
      <p>I think that is where the pleasure and amazement of psychedelics come from. Psychedelics eject you from the 'normal' state into this state of pure novelty where your brain wakes up and goes from paying attention to 10% of sensory input to 70%, and that in itself is enervating and blissful.</p>
      <p>That doesn't mean that I think psychedelics are inherently positive though.</p>
      <p>My position is that the benefit of psychedelics are that second order effect (outlined above), and that the psychedelics themselves may still actually be harmful. </p>
      <p>Overall, one may outweigh the other and result in a net positive but there are other paths to that second order effect that don't involve taking the drug.</p>
      <p>It's very much possible for the attention to surface from the grey fog into the sunlight of pure experience through meditation, obviating the need of a chemical to warp the sensory input so severely that the attention is forcibly ejected from it's 'normal' ruts.</p>
      <p>Meditation also tends to be a gentler, more gradual ascent out of the fog that is self regulated by the mind's own adaptation to it, rather than being kicked naked and screaming out into the light.</p>
      <p>The 'light' the mind is thrown out into in the psychedelic experience is not 'normal' reality. Some people might assert that what you are actually seeing is some kind of underlying, more true form that the drug has granted you access to but I don't accept that. I think that you are mainly just fucked up on drugs. The feeling of profound insight isn't from seeing things more truly, it's from being awakened from a slow descent into a less and less aware state over the course of a lifetime, which is what it actually feels like as well. It's not that you go 'oh look at this new thing', it's more like 'oh, I forgot this was here the whole time'. And some of that perserveres after the psychedelic trip and might explain the longer term benefits. But nonetheless it's still kind of like getting absolutely shitfaced and going to see the sistine chapel. </p>
      <p>I have taken psychedelics and enjoyed the experience and found it somewhat life altering for the better (I think..?) but I will probably never take them again, having spent the 20 years in the interim seriously practicing meditation. To make a shitty metaphor: It seems to me something like the difference between bungy jumping and learning to fly.</p>
      <p>Also my experience with meeting people generally is that those who've taken psychedelics a lot are markedly less well adapted to life, but that might just be a function of them being a fringe thing to do and fringy people doing them.</p>
      <p>Also another way I've learned to enter that state is through drawing and painting at a reasonably skilled level. I'm sure people do it when they play music too. I don't think it's possible to get to the rarefied level of awareness achievable through straight meditation that way, but it seemed to get me a good way along the path.</p>
      <p>There are other reasons why I think that the psychedelics themselves are quite damaging but I'd have to get into a big explanation of yogic structure of consciousness that I think would be too esoteric for most of you to swallow so I'm not going to bother. It would give the conceptual framework to explain my main objection to use of psychedelics, based in my own experiences. But I don't really know what to do about that without it just ending up a really long winded argument from authority.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>