<post>
  <author>Dysautognome</author>
  <date>2021-05-21T04:58:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ne8ggb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_17_2021/gywsukf/</link>
  <title>"College was pretty strict about having to take leftist concepts for granted and it certainly exuded an exclusively leftist cultural pressure."</title>
  <category>
    <li>coteries</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It was never as acute as my experience in highschool, but college was pretty strict about having to take leftist concepts for granted and it certainly exuded an exclusively leftist cultural pressure. For example, Late Victorian Holocaust was required reading for the whole school. The professor once had us take a day off discussing it so we could all go around and tell her why we thought Robin Thicke's Blurred Lines was so problematic.</p>
      <p>And in comparison to our expectation to deconstruct Nietzche and his racist attitudes towards black people, we were explicitly told not to critique but merely describe Marx's thoughts in Das Kapital. I remember lightly pushing back on some of de Buevoir's claims in discussion, and the professor responded by making me answer the "female surgeon" paradox in front of everyone, I guess in an attempt to embarrass me (I got it correct without hesitating and he was surprised, so I'm not sure what he expected).  Even in my STEM courses we would receive topical asides denouncing congressional Republicans. I had a STEM professor crack a joke that they were glad a recent hurricane tore through Florida because the state votes Republican. We had 2 introductory genetics lectures dedicated to how genetic differences between human populations are impossible, and half a genetics lecture dedicated to how genetics says nothing about transgenderism.</p>
      <p>This is to say nothing of the administrators' behavior. Posters on racial injustice, recruiting for La Raza, and rape culture were put up by administrative departments for gender and 'multi-cultural centers' all around the campus. We actually did end up having a day each year where all classes were cancelled so we could attend various lectures on white privilege and activism. My campus also unanimously voted to append any <em>accusations</em> of sexual misconduct to student's transcripts so that they couldn't transfer if they were in the process of being railed by a kangaroo court.</p>
      <p>So again, maybe you're lucky, but the claim this doesn't happen is impossible to square with my experience at all. I genuinely believe that the people who are telling me otherwise are discounting evidence or just blatantly lying for partisan reasons. I've experienced it from so many educators in so many environments and it complies incredibly well with all of the behavior I see reported on elsewhere.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>