<post>
  <author>Appropriate-Report</author>
  <date>2020-05-01T15:36:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/fp67dmm/</link>
  <title>Knock-On Effects of Normalized College Cheating</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Rutgers is ranked number 62, which makes is a good school, one where your child would need 1400 (the 75th percentile) to get in. </p>
      <p>There has been a sea change in the last 40 years, from a society where not cheating was an important part of the culture, to a society where people cheat casually.  In the 80s and 90s, not cheating was a major cultural touchstone.  People felt being a trustworthy person was more important than qualifications, and many movies and stories touched on this.  </p>
      <p>In those days, colleges had honor codes, which essentially said, "we won't check your cheating, but you are on your honor not to."  The notion of honor means that it holds doubly when people are not checking.  This was taken completely seriously and worked.  People would routinely take their exams out of the exam room and finish it in the quad where it was sunnier.  People, because society made it important, chose not to cheat.</p>
      <p>What happened?  Basically, Asian students arrived, with a completely different culture.  In their culture, and I am told this by consultants that we spent a lot of money on, cheating is not seen as wrong.  I may be a trustee of a well-known college (but not top 10), and we had a problem with cheating.  After applying a few million, a report was delivered telling us that the faculty was too white, and stuck in a western mindset and that they needed to be more culturally aware of the tradition of cheating in Asian society.  </p>
      <p>What bothers most is not the cheating, but the knock-on effects.   Huge numbers of children who do not cheat, because they come from families that are culturally western, do not get into these colleges.  In general, the non-cheating cohort slips 25 or 50 college places, ending up in much worse colleges.   In a well nigh baffling case, a local exclusive private high school had a cheating scandal.  A large number of Indian and Chinese students had a long term cheating ring.  Some teachers wanted to fail them or give them bad grades, but they were told by the administration that if they did this then they would ruin the children's lives as they would not get into top colleges.  The teachers caved.  The students got into top colleges, but no-one cared about the kids who did not cheat and thus did not get in.</p>
      <p>The worst part of this is the effect it has on STEM.  STEM classes are rigorous, and as kids get better grades, the classes get harder.  If students cheat, and thus get all the questions on the homework correct, the professor makes the next class harder.  As a result, the cheaters find it more necessary to cheat, and the students who don't cheat are driven out of STEM by well nigh impossible intro classes.  Professors often will say that the classes are well within what people can do, not realizing that they don't know the abilities of the students, and are judging the ability of Chegg.</p>
      <p>This drives women out of STEM in colleges below about 25 on USNews and all non-Asian kids in colleges above this.  I spoke to the department admission officer at Berkeley recently, and he told me that CS undergraduate at Berkeley was not appropriate for honest kids, as cheating was now essential.</p>
      <p>In some of the above, I have used Asian in a sloppy way.  There are Asian cultures that do not cheat, and there are many American Born Chinese students that do not cheat.  However, you will not find them in any good colleges, as colleges care about grades, and the grades of the cheaters are higher - that's why they cheat.</p>
      <p>It is too late to do anything about this.  At the Board level in colleges, the issue has been raised by faculty, but the changes that it would need to break the pattern are not acceptable in the current climate.  Any change would hurt Asian enrollment, which is seen as unacceptable, especially given International students pay full fees.  Any change would help white boys which makes the policy changes even more unacceptable.   </p>
      <p>I would be interested if anyone else has anecdotal evidence of the same discussion happening at their college.  I know people cannot speak openly about this, as it is a little radioactive, but this silence means that any possible solution cannot be shared.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>