<post>
  <author>Interversity</author>
  <date>2020-05-02T21:33:35Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/fpat7vn/</link>
  <title>Comparing Responses to Kavanaugh and Biden Scandals</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This post is mostly for my own purposes as I wanted to have a simple, side by side comparison of what was said and asked for by politicians and other major public figures during the Kavanaugh and Biden scandals.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"Enough is enough," she continued. "One credible sexual assault claim should have been too many to get a lifetime appointment to the Supreme Court and make decisions that will affect millions of women’s lives for generations."</p>
        <p>"Two is an embarrassment," she added. "It’s time for a new nominee." </p>
      </blockquote>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/senate/408031-gillibrand-calls-for-kavanaugh-nomination-to-be-withdrawn">Kirsten Gillibrand September 2018</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"So when we say believe women, it's for this explicit intention of making sure there's space for all women to come forward to speak their truth, to be heard. And in this allegation, that is what Tara Reade has done," Gillibrand said. "She has come forward, she has spoken, and they have done an investigation in several outlets. Those investigations, Vice President Biden has called for himself. Vice President Biden has vehemently denied these allegations and I support Vice President Biden."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/04/29/politics/kirsten-gillibrand-joe-biden-support/index.html">Kirsten Gillibrand April 2020</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Furthermore, if Republican senators attempt to impugn her character, they will disgrace themselves in the eyes of the American people. Public opinion, however, is unlikely to view his alleged crime with such clemency.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2018/09/17/opinions/brett-kavanaugh-nomination-gop-watershed-moment-brawley/index.html">Lucia Brawley, CNN writer September 2018</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <blockquote>
        <p>But a trip through the details in the timeline of Reade's particular narrative gave me pause and made me wonder if that was what was at play here in this election year. Take a look for yourself. There was also the odd occasion of Reade's 2018 posting to Medium -- since deleted -- in which she publicly praised Vladimir Putin, who has poured so much time, energy and money into electing Donald Trump. She wrote, in part: "To President Putin, I say keep your eyes to the beautiful future and maybe, just maybe America will come to see Russia as I do, with eyes of love." (Reade told Vox that "when she wrote the praise of Putin, she had 'watched a bunch of Noam Chomsky' and was working on a novel set in Russia.")</p>
      </blockquote>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/05/01/opinions/we-need-to-talk-about-tara-reade-brawley/index.html">Lucia Brawley, CNN writer April 2020</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Joe Biden said Christine Blasey Ford <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2020/04/30/biden-gave-christine-blasey-ford-benefit-doubt-why-not-tara-reade/">"should be given the benefit of the doubt"</a></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Today is a profoundly heart-breaking day for women, girls and families across America. Courageous women risked their safety and well-being to speak truth about this nomination.  Tens of thousands more joined them to share their own harrowing stories of sexual assault, at great personal risk.  Yet, Senate Republicans chose to send a clear message to all women: do not speak out, and if you do – do not expect to be heard, believed or respected.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.speaker.gov/newsroom/10618">Nancy Pelosi, October 2018</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“I respect your question, and I don’t need a lecture or a speech,” Pelosi responded. “I have a complete respect for the whole 'MeToo' movement,” she added. “I have four daughters and one son. And there's a lot of excitement around the idea that women will be heard and be able to be listened to...There is also due process, and the fact that Joe Biden is Joe Biden,” the Speaker later added. “There's been statements from his campaign — not his campaign but his former employees who ran his offices and the rest, that there was never any record of this, there was never any record, and that nobody ever came forward or nobody came forward to say something about it apart from the principle involved.” The comments come after Pelosi told CNN earlier Thursday that she was "satisfied with how [Biden] has responded."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/house/495502-pelosi-tells-reporter-she-doesnt-need-a-lecture-on-biden-kavanaugh-comparison">Nancy Pelosi, April 2020</a> (What wasn't satisfactory about Kavanaugh's response? He did get a little weird when being interrogated by the Senate, but that's mostly understandable)</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Mazie Hirono in effect said <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/top-democrat-cites-kavanaughs-outcome-driven-legal-philosophy-as-reason-to-deny-him-due-process">Kavanaugh didn't deserve due process due to his judicial philosophy</a>, but is silent so far regarding Reade.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"I believe her," Harris told CBS. "Listen, first of all, anybody who comes forward at this point to be prepared to testify in the United States Senate against someone who's being nominated to one of the most powerful positions in the united States government, that takes an extraordinary amount of courage."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2018/09/18/kamala-harris-kavanaugh-accuser-827907">Kamala Harris, September 2018</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Sen. Kamala Harris, D-Calif., another former 2020 candidate and rumored vice presidential contender for the Biden ticket, said in a San Francisco Chronicle podcast interview that she can "only speak to the Joe Biden I know. The Joe Biden I know is somebody who really has fought for women and empowerment of women and for women’s equality and rights," she said... Harris also said she would be "honored" to be Biden's running mate... She told the Chronicle the current case raises "a bigger structural issue, frankly, which is that women must be able to speak without fear of retaliation."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/elections/2020/04/30/biden-democrat-supporters-tara-reade-assault-allegation/3056685001/">Kamala Harris, April 2020</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Stacey Abrams <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/elections/2020/04/30/biden-democrat-supporters-tara-reade-assault-allegation/3056685001/">wasn't quite as vociferous against Kavanaugh as others, but</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>After the courageous and compelling testimony from Dr. Christine Blasey Ford yesterday, it is shameful that Kavanaugh's nomination is being rushed forward. I believe women, and I believe survivors of violence always deserve to be supported and to have their voices heard. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>And for Reade:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Abrams cited aNYT article published April 12 as proof that Reade's claim had been properly investigated and found to not be credible—a claim that Sen. Amy Klobuchar (D., Minn.), another vice presidential hopeful, also made. The NYT, however, has said its investigation made no such conclusions, pointing to potential corroborating evidence in the story, such as former colleagues who "remembered Reade suddenly changing roles" at the time Reade claimed the assault took place.</p>
        <p>"Our investigation made no conclusion either way," the paper told the Washington Free Beacon. "The Times also spoke to a friend who said Reade told her the details of the allegation at the time; another friend and Reade’s brother say she told them of a traumatic sexual incident involving Biden."</p>
        <p>Since that story broke, a former neighbor has come out to say that Reade told her in the mid-1990s about the assault. Those developments have not swayed Abrams.</p>
        <p>"The New York Times investigation does not support the accusations against the vice president," Abrams said. "I think that he will make women proud, that he will make America proud."</p>
        <p>Abrams also falsely claimed that while Reade's accusation was investigated, there was "no investigation" of Ford's accusation against Kavanaugh. An FBI investigation found no corroboration of the allegations by Ford or Deborah Ramirez against Kavanaugh.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/elections/2020/04/30/biden-democrat-supporters-tara-reade-assault-allegation/3056685001/">Amy Klobuchar</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Sen. Amy Klobuchar, D-Minn., said she still opposes Brett Kavanaugh's confirmation to the Supreme Court as recent reporting by the New York Times raises questions about the vetting process last fall.</p>
        <p>The reporting by the newspaper indicates there was a lack of a thorough FBI investigation into the sexual assault allegations against the Supreme Court justice when he was a nominee and detailed an additional allegation that was reportedly not investigated.</p>
        <p>George Stephanopoulos asked Klobuchar on "This Week" Sunday if she thinks the latest updates on the Brett Kavanaugh assault allegations are grounds for impeachment of the now-Supreme Court Justice, Klobuchar said she has opposed his confirmation since last September when she was praised for her handling of questioning of Kavanaugh before the Senate Judiciary Committee.</p>
        <p>"I strongly oppose him, based on his views on the executive power which will continue to haunt our country, as well as how he behaved, including the allegations that we are hearing more about today," Klobuchar said. "My concern here is that the process was a sham."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Regarding Reade</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Sen. Amy Klobuchar, D-Minn., a potential pick for VP and former candidate for president, told NPR Biden is a "champion of abuses of power against women."</p>
        <p>She also pointed to the Times' reporting, saying "I agree with Vice President Biden about this, that all women in these cases have the right to be heard and have their claims thoroughly reviewed. And in this case ... there was a thorough review by The New York Times. And I think that's very important to have, especially involving public figures."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Doesn't look good.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>