<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-05-01T17:46:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/fp6n3ky/</link>
  <title>IQ Tests Are the Crysis of Intelligence</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Yes. So a good test like the army or a psychologist or a school will give you can be 20min to an hour, whereas an online test or one mensa will give you can be just 5-12minutes. </p>
      <p>Beyond that there are just a ton of ways you can mess up a test uncorrelated with concern, missed an instruction, get distracted by something else... ect.</p>
      <p>Generally in persons should be way better than online and longer ones should be more reliable, but theres huge variance.</p>
      <p>That being said they’re still highly correlated with each-other and a vastly more robust phenomenon than almost anything else in psychology.</p>
      <p>To use an analogy from gaming, whether or not a PC could run <em>Crysis</em> in 2009 was a great benchmark of a PC. like gold standard. That being said a ton of great PCs might still fail to run it if they had driver issues or calibration issues that you had yet to fiddle with, or if the Game had an unrelated stability issue to do with the latest update. Likewise some mediocre PCs “could” run it, if you fiddled with them for hours to get it to work on lowest settings. And presumably a real genius might find a way to make it “run” on his old 2001 dell pc.</p>
      <p>Now none of that says PC power isn’t real or the test is meaningless. The correlation between pc power and making <em>Crysis</em> work/ getting good benchmark results would still be damn near 0.8-0.9.  it just wasn’t a perfect test sent to us from the wisdom of the Machine God (although <em>Crysis</em> was still really damn good).</p>
      <p>Likewise IQ tests are solid benchmarks but the odds you’ll get a flop result on a bad day or a crazy result on a good day is still there. Its the most robust correlation ever found in Psychology, but it’s still <em>just</em> a correlation.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Edit: of course the obvious way to correct for this is just to repeat the test a ton of time which most PC gamers did, hell some Ran the <em>Crysis</em> benchmarking tool 5 times every time they’d download a new driver, or play with their overclocking. However most IQ tests tend to lose efficacy the 10th time you take the same one, and most professionally administered ones cost a fair amount in money and professional hours.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>