<post>
  <author>mokoroo</author>
  <date>2020-05-01T17:37:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/fp6m27d/</link>
  <title>Off to the Blacksmith's Guild for your Saucepan!</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Cheating in university...</p>
      <p>That brings back some interesting memories. This isn't at all relevant to your point, but I thought it was relevant to the topic and just sort of interesting.</p>
      <p>When I was in university I spent several years in very poor health. During that time my network of friends atrophied, my social life died, and I struggled to keep on top of my studies, failing several subjects - pain to the point where you can't sleep for more than four or so hours every night is soul-destroying and makes it impossible to focus.</p>
      <p>During this time I became friends with a drug dealer. I imagine you can puzzle out why.</p>
      <p>
        <em>He</em> in turn was friends with a man with a far greater revenue stream, the university cheater's source of essays. The university absolutely failed people who got caught plagiarising, they just didn't look very hard. Unfortunately for some international students if you copy urls and such at the start of your essay, or various textual watermarks, or TurnItIn just flags your whole essay... you will get caught. Basic competence is required.</p>
      <p>This man was a spectacular human being, by which I mean he was a spectacle. He knew <em>everyone</em>. He knew a gang of Aboriginal robbers. He knew a gang of white supremacist sailors who smuggled cigarettes (of all things - but taxation on cigarettes in Australia is <em>very</em> high). He had on one occasion mediated  a conflict between these two violent groups. He was (and proved this to my satisfaction) on a first-name basis with two people in moderately high political positions in Australia. His family were rich, but he ran away from home to make something of himself and ended up dropping out of university, selling essays, smoking cigarettes, and discussing French literature in-between sleeping with every pretty girl and guy who caught his fancy. They still sent him money on a regular basis.</p>
      <p>He was one of the ugliest people I have ever met in terms of pure unfortunate looks, but his personality could only be described as irresistibly magnetic. I had to flip through Gatsby to find this, but this paragraph applies <em>perfectly</em>.</p>
      <p>"He smiled understandingly — much more than understandingly. It was one of those rare smiles with a quality of eternal reassurance in it, that you may come across four or five times in life. It faced — or seemed to face — the whole external world for an instant, and then concentrated on you with an irresistible prejudice in your favor. It understood you just so far as you wanted to be understood, believed in you as you would like to believe in yourself, and assured you that it had precisely the impression of you that, at your best, you hoped to convey."</p>
      <p>He was a trained fencer but had given it up to learn <em>la verdadera destreza</em> or early Spanish fencing because he felt it was more true to the spirit of men with swords fighting to the death. Please don't take this as an endorsement for early Spanish fencing - I went to three training sessions and found it very dull.</p>
      <p>Despite all that he was a businessman as well. He was writing pass quality essays in an hour or two, charging $300-400 for them (top-notch essays went for only a few hundred more - the demand wasn't there), and there was a massive crop of Chinese and Arab international students who would just pay the price demanded if the quality of the good was there.</p>
      <p>I don't know precisely how many he wrote, but I know he was a fulltime worker, working an average of 40 hours a week half the year (lot of holiday time in universities), though this tended more towards mainly 15-20 hour weeks and a few 100 hour weeks. He made a lot of money, and mostly spent it on bizarre things like antique furniture, historical items (lots of naval-related items, like an old sextant that I was told was worth in the thousands of dollars), and ornately carved bookcases. </p>
      <p>Anyway, the point I came to there was maybe a little in line with your thinking.</p>
      <p>Personally, rooting out cheating is like rooting out corruption - the more its normalized the harder it gets to root out, so decisive action is necessary even if it does ruin a few lives.</p>
      <p>But isn't it <em>bizarre</em>? Chinese students going to an Australian university to get a piece of paper to avoid going to a Chinese university with a bad reputation to go get a job in China (some got the degree for immigration purposes, admittedly) and just cheating their way through the entire thing? The entire thing is a transfer of wealth from some Chinese to some Australians, but why should it be the university that profits? Why should the university get to accept cheaters dollars, look the other way, and then punish people when it needs to make a face-saving gesture?</p>
      <p>Admittedly, the academy drives a lot of human progress, but most of those marginal dollars were going to administrators anyway. Why can't it be this amazing caricature of a person who let me read various first edition books on his shelves without even telling me about that fact instead?</p>
      <p>At some point, whenever we face issues in education, well, to paraphrase - a spectre is haunting tertiary education, the spectre of Bryan Caplan. So much of what we're doing is just selling signals for prices, which is fine in a generic sense, but bad if we're paying more than lip service to the notion of meritocracy.</p>
      <p>The more I read about, the more I look back on my personal experiences, the more I'm convinced the academy drastically needs restructuring. I'm not sure what shape it should take, but modern universities are like these bizarrely anachronistic creatures from the Middle Ages still walking among us. It's like going down to the supermarket for your groceries and then off to the Blacksmith's Guild for your saucepan because <em>that's where you buy saucepans</em>. I mean, you still get the saucepan and the whole thing doesn't collapse under its own weight, but it just feels peculiar.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>