<post>
  <author>mokoroo</author>
  <date>2020-05-01T08:08:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/fp58zc9/</link>
  <title>Bridging Inferential Distance To Cure HIV</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I spent a bit of time thinking about what concepts rationalists have provided that I've personally found useful and good (sorry for the pivot, this will become relevant, I swear).</p>
      <p>To me, there are three concepts I think that were coined by rationalists and are also useful to me in everyday life.</p>
      <p>The first is <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/HLqWn5LASfhhArZ7w/expecting-short-inferential-distances">inferential distance</a>. It helped me not get frustrated with people who just didn't 'get' something, and made me realise every step had to be worked out in life as in maths. </p>
      <p>The second is <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/03/repost-epistemic-learned-helplessness/">epistemic learned helplessness</a>. The sort of 'sure, you can outargue and outlogic me but I <em>recognise</em> that so I'm not going to let you change my beliefs'.</p>
      <p>The third is maybe not coined by rationalists, but it's pushed really hard - human brains are really bad at maths. Bayes' Theorem is true which is nice, but the real takeaway is that your higher-order thinking is <em>really</em> bad at maths and internalising it is close to impossible. Scope insensitivity, general inability to calculate numbers, etc, etc, etc. Human beings don't think in maths as a general rule. Brains can be specifically trained to run maths, but it's more like a program that takes up a lot of memory and processing power and you need to shut a lot of other stuff down to do it - you can't natively have maths running in the background all the time.</p>
      <p>The first is an aside I like to mention, because I'm hoping to bridge inferential distance between you and me. I may not get it right, but to my mind the concepts of inferential distance and charity are deeply entangled - the assumption of good faith rests on a foundation of 'if we just work hard enough we can figure out each other's views and represent them honestly even if we disagree, but it <em>is</em> hard work '. </p>
      <p>What I'm trying to do here is not say you're wrong or right as such, but just get you inside my head and the head of people like me on this topic.</p>
      <p>The second and third are important to your post specifically, though.</p>
      <p>I also agree - I think it's an accurate prediction. In fact, I think it's an accurate prediction for <em>me</em>, a more left rationalist type, let alone your average punter in the street.</p>
      <p>I'm fairly sure I'd be less likely to vote 'yes' on a the poll where the question was about gay sex only, even though my preferences would absolutely be for gay people to stop having sex versus everyone having to stop (I like sex).</p>
      <p>There are two answers as to why. </p>
      <p>The first is plain scope insensitivity. The old saw about the <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/2ftJ38y9SRBCBsCzy/scope-insensitivity">birds</a> fits here - people gave roughly the same amount of money to save three orders of magnitudes of bird populations. A naive reading of the poll is something like "people value all birds past the first x birds at zero!"</p>
      <p>So the 'how long would you stop 10 million people having sex if it meant the end of HIV' and 'how long would you stop 1 billion having sex if it meant the end of HIV' are likely to have similar answers.</p>
      <p>But when you ask a question like that about everyone, my mind thinks 'alright, what <em>are</em> the costs and benefits, the benefit seems pretty large, what sort of cost can I assign to it?'</p>
      <p>When you ask it about gay people my mind thinks 'why are you asking about gay people'? </p>
      <p>Like, this maps to 'would you accept killing sixty million people if it meant x benefit' - this is a real question I might think about, but 'would you accept killing six million Jews if it meant x benefit' is not.</p>
      <p>That is to say, if you're asking about the general population I assume you're asking in good faith a question and trying to elicit a useful answer. If you ask about gay people I immediately go to a sort of epistemic learned helplessness state - you exist in a state of quantum faith, either good or bad, and I can't know which. If I vote in a poll that says 'yes, stop gay people having sex' I don't know what you want to do with that poll, but I assume you might be building a <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/05/12/weak-men-are-superweapons/">superweapon</a> of some kind.</p>
      <p>So I'd see it through a different lens and vote 'no'. Even if you put both these options on the same poll, I'd be suspicious and might vote for 'stop all sex' rather than 'stop gay sex'. It's not that I genuinely believe that, but rather that I suspect you're trying to exploit or hack my genuine beliefs to either misuse my viewpoint or try and convince me of something false. </p>
      <p>But if this was a bona fide magic button I pressed in isolation from the world, of course I'd prefer only gay people refrain from sex to eliminate HIV. </p>
      <p>The problem is you're asking people to send an expensive signal (for leftists) that maps hard on to the right wing ('we don't care as much about gay people and are willing to single them out') to be able to also send their true beliefs. It shouldn't be a surprise that they're not willing to do it.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Well, unless it's aimed at limiting anti-left speech, seemingly. tl;dr the average leftist is not at all utilitarian and fairness may indeed be one of his most sacred values</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>As a postscript, I believe in free speech because I believe in part that suppression of speech advantages communists (who I'm not much of a fan of) and fascists (likewise), depending on who can get their hands on the levers of power. Building weapons favors those willing to make use of them, and suppressing speech is a hell of a weapon. I fight for the free speech of Nazis because Nazis are the absolute canary in the coal mine - if your canary dies, you might still be fine (canaries die a lot sooner than miners and for less reason), but if your canary is alive you're definitely fine. Likewise, if Nazis have free speech in modern society speech is definitely free.</p>
      <p>But free speech isn't a <em>terminal</em> value for me, it's more like democracy. If we genuinely had a perfect immortal god-king who could run society far better I'd happily change to the new immortal god-king ideology. If suppressing speech genuinely made society better off in the long run I'd happily do it, and I think most leftists think the same. It's just that 'we have our hands on levers that can shut fascists up <em>right now</em>' is compelling, and 'wait guys, if we turn this machine on it'll inevitably be used against us in the future someday' is not.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>