<post>
  <author>ProfQuirrell</author>
  <date>2020-05-01T20:09:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/fp7478m/</link>
  <title>The Unique Value of Military University</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The Fleming stuff isn't really in my wheelhouse; I'm a civilian through and through. No military background whatsoever in my family. Students (especially after basic training when they're jumpy) will salute me on accident and I have to correct them.</p>
      <p>A few details at random to give you the flavor of the place: students are in uniform throughout the class day (unless they're in athletic clothes or sports gear) and all classes begin with a "section marcher". It's their job to take attendance, note who is missing, and start the class right on time by calling the room to attention and announcing who is there and who isn't. Students who come in late have to report in to me and I can appeal to their commanders afterwards if I'm not satisfied with their explanation.</p>
      <p>Students are on a strict schedule -- classes in the morning, then military training, then an hour for office hours -- all the instructors are expected to be in their office and students can go to anyone for help. We aren't patient with students who come in without preparation -- they're expected to show up with a clear idea of what they want out of the meeting and with some work done ahead of time. They similarly have designated study time later in the evening and officers can and do get on their case if they're playing Fortnite or whatever when they have a chemistry exam the next day.</p>
      <p>The sports teams are similarly on our side -- at more traditional colleges, it's not ... uncommon for a coach / sporting staff to push back against poor grades for their star athletes, although it hasn't happened to me personally. Here, academics are understood by everyone to be important, so more often than not the coaches back us up when we have to call out someone for poor performance. The coaches will bench whoever they feel like if their academics aren't up to snuff -- it's not uncommon, here, for the coach to say "Hey, you're failing ProfQuirrell's class, you're on the bench until you get your grades up. Make sure you talk to him during office hours tomorrow, he'll help you out."</p>
      <p>We have standards for how they behave and how we behave. We're expected to be patient and respectful towards the students -- a big part of military academies is character development and our job involves character coaching and teaching / demonstrating leadership qualities. If the kids don't know <em>how</em> to be disciplined and responsible, we try to help with that as well.</p>
      <p>Similarly, there is a culture of, as teachers, demonstrating the same qualities we want the students to show -- the military instructors HAVE to pass fitness tests. The civilians don't, but if you spend an hour of your workday at the gym nobody will care, in fact, your boss will probably be there right along with you. It's fun to work out near the students -- you wouldn't believe how well the lessons I've learned from starting weightlifting this year have translated to the classroom. The athletes love it too; it's fun to have the role reversal where your chem prof is asking you for help on squat form when he was helping you out with stoichiometry earlier in the day. It's a really special way to connect with the students.</p>
      <p>It's a really special place to teach, and I think it's a good place to be a student as well. The whole place is really built around helping you succeed and giving you the tools to be successful even if you don't have them. Granted, there are significant costs for the students ... they give up a lot of personal freedom and they give up a lot of the wild lifestyle that college is known for. This is a definite cost to them and we try not to underestimate or underappreciate what they're giving up to study and work with us.</p>
      <p>This is before you even take into account that this is the military and, even as they're collecting a paycheck, they're signing their life away for the coming years, working as officers, to pay back their education. I don't think it's a choice everyone should make, but for those that do I think they have an educational experience that is far, far better than what a traditional college is able to offer.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>