<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-06-01T10:24:19Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/nowgdg/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_31_2021/h06f9v7/</link>
  <title>"There are men who enjoy women’s company, and those who don’t, but in an age in which the barriers of casual social interaction between the sexes have come down entirely, the former have a significant advantage."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>There is a lot more to be said for personality than people here give it credit for.</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Certainly, looks and status (inc. wealth, career, social class, friends and so on) remain core to our attractiveness to each other, but I started noticing a few years ago that many of the most romantically/sexually successful men I know were far from the most objectively physically attractive, or the richest, or indeed both.</p>
      <p>Rather they were men who <em>actually like women</em>, and who enjoy their company. You may choose to believe this or not, but I genuinely think this is a highly overlooked aspect of the whole thing. There are men who enjoy women’s company, and those who don’t, but in an age in which the barriers of casual social interaction between the sexes have come down entirely, the former have a significant advantage. </p>
      <hr />
      <p>I have a feeling many rationalist men who struggle with women, or intelligent very online men in general, approach getting hot - whether they take advice from PUAs or TRP or Jordan Peterson or AskMen or anywhere else really - like they approach teaching themselves to code, or studying nootropics. They go to the gym for many hours each week, have their cycles of bulking and cutting, read up on dressing well, cologne, getting a good haircut, eating right, read up about casual conversation and escalating interactions and maybe take the PUA approach of simply asking out as many women as possible - on the street, at clubs and so on. </p>
      <p>
        <strong>I don’t deny that this strategy works</strong>, for many men, some of the time, albeit with the caveat that women who respond to street pickup attempts from strangers or sleep with average guys they meet at bars and clubs tend not to be the creme de la creme, if you will, of the sex. (And I think this is where a lot of the angry screeds here painting the modern woman as some hypergamous, muscle-and-money-hungry whore who sleeps around and who would prefer to be some rich guy’s 17th side chick to settling down with a decent loving guy comes from, as if the average woman is a bottle rat at 1oak.) </p>
      <p>But the problem with it is that these guys don’t actually want to spend a lot of time with women. They’re not interested in conversation, in discussion, in hours of flirting back and forth. They see the chase as a dull roadblock, have few or no female friends (and then only in hope they might sleep with them), don’t think women are funny or smart, and would always prefer to spend time with their male friends than with women, unless the latter involves actively or imminently having sex. One gets the impression that if they were gay, they might have no casual social interaction with women at all. </p>
      <p>This isn’t about ‘misogyny’, or saying these guys can’t/don’t get laid - that really would be a rather self-serving feminist myth, and they do - lust is a powerful force. </p>
      <p>But it is about a specific kind of male - who has masculine ‘male’ hobbies, who spends much of his free time at the gym, who might well have a male-dominated job (trades, tech, whatever), who may be technically fit and handsome yet who also gets laid much less than maybe the skinny guy in a small-time band, or the vaguely flamboyant bisexual best friend, or the guy who loves fashion and spends his weekends working at a designer thrift store, or the slightly schlubby guy who works at the stables over summer on college break, or the long haired eccentric who volunteers  as a curator at a cool art gallery on weekend - <em>all</em> of whom I know and who sleep with far more physically attractive women than themselves pretty regularly. Damn, I know a lanky, NYU dropout skinny bisexual choreographer with one of the worst examples of facial hair I’ve ever seen who literally fucked his way through a group of underwear models over the course of about a year. But he always preferred hanging out with women to men, even when he was only gay.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>