<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-06-03T14:10:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/nowgdg/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_31_2021/h0fwfzq/</link>
  <title>"...meritocracy and aristocracy are indistinguishable in the same population over long periods provided extraneous confounding factors absent."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Right - meritocracy and aristocracy are indistinguishable in the same population over long periods provided extraneous confounding factors absent. </p>
      <p>For example, self-made rich people are more common in the United States than in Europe. This has some limited industrial/economic causes, but is primarily because of immigration. When a polity permits immigration of highly skilled foreigners, some people with the genetic potential for success, but who may have been stymied by geopolitical instability, famine, poor rulers, ethnic-tribal-religious discrimination and so on may be able to succeed in a more stable, more peaceful, more liberal and wealthier jurisdiction. Similarly, high IQ Europeans who moved to Argentina are much poorer than European Americans of identical potential, because various local and regional problems over the last century have limited, arguably, their success in absolute terms. Whether it is better to thrive in a poorer state or do OK in a richer one is left to personal judgment - Levantine Arabs dominate the economies of Central America, but do merely OK-to-quite-good in the United States. These are choices individuals and families make. </p>
      <p>Where a population remains mostly identical, though, and economic growth remains limited (as huge and rapid growth can and always does increase total wealth and create more positions in the elite), elites tend to remain quite stable. In Germany, for example, the children who attend the highest tier of public school - the gymnasium - are largely the children of those who attended the gymnasium themselves.  In New York, specialized schools are largely the preserve of high IQ children of immigrants, but in a world in which America ended all immigration in 1950, they would probably be 70-90% white [Jewish], still. In a world in which it had ended all immigration in 1820, they’d probably be the descendants of the same Anglo-Dutch elite who ruled two centuries ago. Germany doesn’t have many highly performing immigrant groups, so the wave of immigration since the 1960s doesn’t much affect demographics of gymnasiums except in some very high immigration urban areas like Frankfurt and Berlin. </p>
      <p>In more stable societies that do not experience high levels of immigration by groups with higher-than-median IQ, while a child of a professor might become a banker, and the child of a banker a movie director, and the child of a doctor a professor and so on, this merely rearranges the precise occupational arrangements of the elite. The composition itself isn’t really altered at all. Indeed, if one child of every doctor became a doctor, one child of every lawyer a lawyer and so on (adjusting by need), it is highly unlikely - especially when mating is again ever more assortive - that the quality or competence of those practising those vital professions would in any way decline in the United States. Coupled with some form of Chinese-style public test to mop up the 98th+ percentile of Everyone Else in the rare occasions that somebody wins the lottery of birth and dramatically outperforms their parents, and you could run an entirely competent elite caste. The smartest commoners always figure out a way to do well, anyway. Always have. As always existed, mechanisms would allow promotion and relegation between castes, on rare occasions for whole groups or locales, in specific and limited ways. </p>
      <p>Humanity will always build classes. But determining them in Darwinian struggle governed by countless “meritocratic” factors - endless lifelong competency testing, essentially, repeated Groundhog Day style in each generation - is surely inferior to allocation of place, in which life suddenly blossoms with the freedom to pursue things based on desire, beyond the rat race.  Allocation is indeed a driver toward self-actualization, toward certainty which is what makes people happy. At five, your dad tells you you’re going to be a doctor, because he’s a doctor. Done!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>