<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-06-04T00:06:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fst0wqa/</link>
  <title>Who Knows, Maybe I'm a Bigoted Sociopath</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Broadly agree with the sentiment, as I'll say in a minute, but two quick counterpoints.</p>
      <p>(1) To <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/239288-it-s-not-what-happens-to-you-but-how-you-react">butcher Epictetus</a>, it's not what happens, but how people react to it that matters. I would not really care much about the riots, except as far as I can tell half the world has gone mad and the mistreatment of black Americans by the police is now the primary concern of most of my friends, and not just the Brits and the Americans - I've seen French, Filipino, and Argentinian friends in a state of high excitement and righteous anger, and I would have expected them to have  bigger cares closer to home at this point. The scale of the public response alone means I can reasonably get concerned. Meanwhile many on the left have been energised and outraged by Trump's reaction to the situation. It seems quite likely to me at this point that the '2020 riots' will be a big deal in the history books and will have repercussions for years to come - it's America's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dreyfus_affair">Dreyfus Affair</a> (seriously, the parallels here are interesting, in particular the ability of a 'racial injustice' to divide a whole country - I'd love to read an effortpost on this if anyone has detailed knowledge). So to tell people "it's not many lives at stake compared to COPD" may make some sense when dealing with their object-level responses to police brutality, but there's a lot more going on now.</p>
      <p>(2) Most people <em>do not think of moral significance just in terms of harm</em>. The George Floyd death strikes many Americans as yet another symbolic injustice piled on a community that has suffered historically and continues to suffer many similar injustices at the macro or micro level every day. To try to contextualise this with reference to annual COPD deaths spectacularly misses the point: these harms may be unfortunate, but they're not <em>morally outrageous</em> in the same way. This is something I do think a lot of members of this community and the broader rationalsphere so often miss. Justice, equality, fairness, respect - these are <em>far</em> more powerful moral motivators for the average person than utils or QALYs.  You can try to convince people to be consequentialists if you like, but 95% of humans just don't think that way and never will. Moreover, it's not clear to me that they <em>should</em> - things like justice seem really important to me, and I'm not confident I can capture the morally salient aspects of justice purely in terms of long-term utility or other post-hoc attempts to cram them into a utilitarian framework.</p>
      <p>Now, onto where I agree: seriously, what the fuck is happening? Every company I've ever interacted with, every forum I've ever posted in, and every website I read has seemingly decided that they have to show solidarity or make a comment in relation to the death of George Floyd. Meanwhile, my social media is a sea of displays of solidarity or outrage at this death. This is the first incident in my life that has elicited an outpouring on this scale (9/11 came close, but even then my videogaming magazines or employers didn't have to 'address the issue'). And yet I feel myself more or less entirely unmoved: I regard the death of George Floyd as a predictable consequence of a poorly functioning police system that may or may not unfairly impact black Americans (it's complicated) but has long been in need of reform. Deaths like his happen several times a year, have done for decades, and are a relatively small deal in a world that has so much suffering in it. So despite everything I say in (2), I don't get why <em>this</em> particular injustice has exploded to anything like the scale it has. It doesn't have the novelty or shock value of 9/11 or the assassination of Franz Ferdinand, the romance of the loss of the Titanic, the moral clarity of the MLK assassination, the spiritual blasphemy and ominous timing of the <a href="https://bmcr.brynmawr.edu/2012/2012.12.40/">mutilation of the herms</a>, etc.. I think of myself as a pretty empathetic person, and I put a lot of effort into trying to understand others' feelings, but in this case I genuinely feel like a 'moral idiot' - I'm baffled and disturbed at the absurd scale of the public response, particularly from people and companies thousands of miles away with zero skin in the game. I'd like to think it's because I'm just kind of curmudgeonly and contrarian and less prone to hysteria than many, and that that's what this is. But who knows, maybe I'm a bigoted sociopath.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>