<post>
  <author>HelloGunnit</author>
  <date>2020-06-04T22:10:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fswpz7y/</link>
  <title>An Officer's Account of Protests and the Coming Depolicing</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>But mostly will there be White flight? And wow will we know if white flights v2.0 is happening? It just seems weird to me no one is even discussing it.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I have a strong hunch that there will be a strong move towards depolicing in the major cities.  There will, of course, be official knee-jerk policy changes (designed to quell the protests and virtue-signal to constituents) that will further discourage active policing.  Police budgets will be cut, leading to less officers, and less pay (and thus worse officers willing to stay/become police).  However, I suspect the bigger issue will be informal depolicing on the level of individual officers.   </p>
      <p>Anecdote time:  I am a police officer  (leftish-center in most of my politics) in a large, liberal, west-coast city.  I patrol one of the most woke neighborhoods in this city and, prior to this last week, I enjoyed fairly positive interactions regularly with the residents and employees of this neighborhood.  Many of the employees and regulars at the coffee shops and restaurants that I would get lunch at knew me by first name and would greet me with a (what certainly seemed to be genuine) smile.  Often after arrests or scuffles with suspects I would stop and take a few minutes to talk with onlookers about what happened, why we did what we did, etc. and a lot of the time this seemed to really make a difference in their opinions and view of what they just saw.</p>
      <p>Since the protests started I have been working non-stop in a crowd-control capacity and have not been working patrol in my district, but I regularly drive through it on the way to the protests.  When I do, I witness a constant stream of middle fingers, expletives, and anti-police graffiti and signs.  At the protests, I am constantly, for hours at a time, told by a crowd of five to ten thousand people that I am a Nazi, that I should die, that I should be jailed, that I should quit my job in shame, that I am a murderer, etc.  For hours at a time I have glass bottles (some full of urine), road flares, rocks, mortar fireworks, bricks and eggs thrown at me.</p>
      <p>Once these protests end, I will have to go back to working patrol in my district.  Will I  be met by the same smiling faces happy to have a conversation?  Will I feel safe ordering food that's not full of spit (or worse) from local eateries?  Will I have onlookers willing to talk with me about what has happened in their neighborhood?  I don't know, but I strongly doubt it.  I, and thousands of officers like me, are going to have less and less healthy interaction with their communities.  We are going to stay in our cars.  We are going to avoid any self-initiated activity, as that is now soley a source of liability.  We are going to feel less and less loyalty to a community that increasingly vilifies us.  We are going to depolice.  Hard.    This will, seemingly inevitably, lead to an increase in both violent crime and property crime.  </p>
      <p>Will this be enough to offset the draw of the large, hip, urban metropolis to the young PMCs  and cause white flight?  I don't know, but it sure won't help stop it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>