<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-06-06T23:27:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/ft7lxql/</link>
  <title>NRx Optimism Towards China is Misdirected</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm getting very repetitive, but all of this has been foretold by the NRx thought leaders <a href="http://www.xenosystems.net/nrx-with-chinese-characteristics/">six years ago.</a></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>As a guest of the Middle Kingdom, the problem looks very different. The very last thing that is wanted here, from a reactionary perspective, is a <em>reboot</em>. On the contrary, the overwhelming priority is conservative, which is to say — more precisely — the imperative that whatever modernization takes place <em>absolutely does not take the Western path</em>. Near-total stasis would be preferable to even the most deeply intelligent reform, if the latter included the slightest hint of submission to the democratic ratchet (spelling inevitable, comprehensive social destruction). Among the reasons to support the thoroughgoing extirpation of all liberal-democratic inclination from Chinese society is the consequential real liberation this would make possible, by confirming a path of Confucian Modernization free of demotic corrosion.</p>
        <p>China is to be defended, precisely because it is alien to the Cathedral. For this same reason, it can be predicted with great confidence that the Occidental memetic onslaught against Chinese Civilization will be escalated to an extreme, as it becomes clear progressive pseudo-teleology is being rejected here. If China succeeds in refusing the Cathedral, civilization will survive. There can be no more significant — or practically counter-revolutionary — cause.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>However, I do not share your or Land's optimism For China. </p>
      <p>First, the premise of high human capital is suspect. IIRC <a href="/u/Appropriate-Report">/u/Appropriate-Report</a> used to debunk the oft-repeated figure of mean Chinese IQ being 105, showing it's based on 4 small samples one having an average 120 – unlikely to be representative. Historically China suffered military humiliations from pretty much everyone it fought, including Japan, for whom we have a reason to believe the average is 104 or so. Military might is an honest indicator of society's real productivity, and especially so in cases of smaller constituency beating a much bigger one (consider also Israel's track record, Rhodesians etc.) I've seen (but can't find) recent data on immigrants to Britain, with British Chinese having the average of 98 (and that's after self-selection to emigrate!). Chinese hijinks with PISA (bribing the organizers to only include their 4 top provinces, and apparently only the elite schools within those) would also be unneeded if they had high performance across the board. Now, I won't diminish their successes with blanket accusation of lying like Dormin does, check <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/glfldb/the_wonderful_world_of_chinese_hifi/fqyuimi/?context=3">my post on Chinese gadgets</a> for example; but the idea of "very high" human capital is not persuasive. 
There are other sides to human capital, such as conscientiousness and endurance – two qualities Asian laborers have long been stereotyped as to possess (is "industriousness" a more accurate term for China?); and stereotypes tend to be true. Since everything "good" is correlated within any group, but groups have different averages for traits, Westerners looking at Chinese productivity may project their own standards and overestimate the contribution of intelligence specifically, making them accept the figure.<br />
Mainland Chinese (which is to say, ~99% of all Chinese) are also not very creative. And unlike their Korean and Japanese brethren who's unexpectedly pedestrian output in highest-level science makes researchers invent a <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.2466/04.17.CP.4.15">"curiosity quotient"</a> for Northeast Asians, they have not demonstrated even a noticeable artistic creativity. If I am to be frank, everything they produce that I've seen to this day is more or less cringe. (Except Feng Shen Ji: shounens are supposed to be this way). Three Body Problem, which is hyped up as peak of their modern sci-fi, is cringe. No, I like it for its better parts, the imagery and some unique perspective, but half of the book is just goofy and silly, and technically it's rather poorly done. I planned a review comparing TBP with works of Strugatsky brothers, Greg Egan and Le Guin to demonstrate difference in some implicit assumptions about humanity, but gave up realizing the vast gulf in quality.    </p>
      <p>There is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demographics_of_China#Fertility_and_mortality">a large problem with Chinese fertility</a>. White nationalists like to talk of "great replacement", but actually Asians have it worse than Whites (even though they don't have the dastardly Soros to poison their wells with xenoestrogens and import the wretched barbarian hordes). On the other hand they at least have the ability to freely discuss the problem; this didn't help them yet, nor did it help Lee Kuan Yew. Just like Xi can suppress people posting Winnie the Pooh memes but can't/won't suppress wet markets and wild animal poachers, he seems impotent to affect their demographics. On top of that, perverse incentives have created a 30-million-strong surplus of desperate single males, inflating the value of women; these males are a seedbed for revolutionary ideation, and chances are women would reward more "hip" political attitudes, with predictable results.  </p>
      <p>But the most important factor is that China cannot determine what is hip. It has no soft power. Its ruling system is unappealing. It does not produce anything that could compete with the hyperpalatable, hysterical Western slurry, be that in media or specifically in ideology. CCP micromanages the creation of bullshit, but has failed to industrialize it like the West did. They could afford this in a non-globalized world, and in a more traditionalist agrarian society; this is why they're trying so hard with their Firewall, and why the "liberal" West is so adamant in repudiating it and helping Chinese dissenters to dismantle it. Even people here, being generally immune to the Cathedral's preaching, are of the mind that it is illegitimate to suppress free speech; and thus would refuse China a chance to prove its model, to show its mature form. But <strong>free speech is precisely how the Cathedral spreads</strong>. Yes, after it gains foothold it becomes deeply averse to certain liberties, and the principled Western liberals are now reeling from this. But this is as surprising and paradoxical as Hit... say, Putin crippling democracy after getting the elections to proceed in his favor once.   </p>
      <p>
        <em>added</em> Importantly, Western ideology works very well on highly educated and smart people – on natural elites. I mentioned <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greg_Egan">Greg Egan</a> above, arguably he's the "hardest" Sci-Fi author of our generation and a man with good STEM publications. He's incredibly inventive. He's also a "refugees welcome" type, quite literally encouraging more 3rd world immigration into Australia, and has used his impressive brain to come up with the idea that strong AGI is impossible because all general intelligences, above some level (modern Homo Sapiens level), are strictly equal except in speed and maybe storage space, or at least "equal" like all Turing machine implementations are. That's one hell of a steelman for egalitarianism and against AI research! Could a Chinese author popular with the geeks come up with a counterpoint, or with the defense of CCP-ruled state? Would he?</p>
      <p>I could go on but the point is that Americans have "won". There are tons of young BLM supporters in Moscow and I suspect there's about as many in Beijing; American narrative is ascendant, not the Chinese state. This narrative, first enabled by the naive notion of individual freedom that appeals to intellectuals, and then enforced by illiberal fanaticism of indoctrinated masses, will destroy both the youngest and the oldest surviving civilizations on Earth. </p>
      <p>Oh, by the way, have you seen <a href="https://twitter.com/antihero_kate/status/1268371386239778816?s=20">Steve Bannon</a> lately?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>