<post>
  <author>LongjumpingHurry</author>
  <date>2020-06-03T21:46:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsskd6e/</link>
  <title>A Deep Dive Into the Question of Chauvin's Guilt</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Have you tried talking to verified law enforcement individuals in <a href="/r/ProtectAndServe">/r/ProtectAndServe</a>? I went through a few of the threads and megathreads there a few days back (not with a fine-toothed comb, or anything, but...) and didn't see any support for the idea that Chauvin was conforming to an approved protocol.</p>
      <p>FWIW, I agree with others that, assuming you're engaging in good faith, you should be wary of your own bias (although personally I think it's often still worth showing that a biased person is relying on invalid/unsound/unreasonable argument rather than ascertaining bias and calling it a day). A charitable reading is that your sense-making has been a bit deranged by the lack of honest discussion (I know I feel some of that, so maybe I'm just projecting). I think in an ideal world there would be more such discussion. But it's also worth recognizing that the absence of (let alone suppression of) such discussion can allow/support unwarranted conclusions.</p>
      <p>Some of my own attempts to reach reasonable conclusions:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>I think it's manslaughter or 3rd degree murder. I expect there's no case to be made that Chauvin was following an approved protocol, through-and-through (as in I gather it's the case that the move itself—knee-to-neck—is approved, but that it carries limitations and requirements that Chauvin failed to fulfill). (It would be a lot more contentious if they had changed course when Floyd had lost consciousness. But they did not. I personally find it plausible that they had a justified suspicion that Floyd was experiencing a drug- (and maybe stress-) induced medical event and their fear of the crowd (IMO mixed with some amount of callousness) dissuaded them from showing their lack of control over the situation by visibly reviewing their decisions/switching to rendering medical aid/etc. I expect more of police, it seems police do too, and I find it right that they were immediately fired and an investigation was begun (before protesting began?); a charge of manslaughter (for multiple officers) seems worth pressing; and it's a reasonable context in which to bring up police reform.)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>I think it's likely that Chauvin used that technique before, or saw it being used, without it posing a threat to anyone's life, making it much less likely the he thought he was killing Floyd. Many seem to not even acknowledge that it's an officially permitted move under some circumstances (including—though I do not believe this is a case of that—using it to intentionally cause unconsciousness!).</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>I think the point that Floyd and onlookers were telling the officers the Floyd couldn't breathe is <em>much</em> less relevant than it's portrayed as being as (1) it's quite plausible that the officers didn't hear/process anything the onlookers were actually saying (it all becomes noise, they're scanning for threats, not making conversation); and (2), to the extent that the officers may have heard/processed them, I expect that the predictive value of such statements is virtually nil (that is, I expect that it, or something like it, will be said in many such situations, the vast majority of which contain no life-threatening behavior. I regard it similarly to a claim that an officer told a suspect to "Stop resisting!" in the course of an arrest: it's evidence that an arrest was occurring, and not much more. My impression comes mostly from video footage, and not direct experience, so my confidence on this point is not strong.) Not to mention, Floyd had complained about trouble breathing before they restrained him, so they would have reason to believe that they weren't causing it (leaving open the question of whether they should have been more concerned about not helping and/or aggravating the problem). (See also: Floyd complained of claustrophobia in the back of the police car, despite the fact that the encounter began with him in the driver's seat of a vehicle.)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>I think it's less clear than public opinion would suggest that Chauvin played a <em>more</em> causal role than the officer applying pressure to the torso. The disproportionate attention he's getting could be explained through some combination of race, naiveté (isn't torso pressure unintuitively bad? Wasn't that part of the conclusion in the Eric Garner case?) and that AFAIK in the first video to spread Chauvin was the only one visible.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>I have not seen discussion of a factor that makes 1st degree murder <em>more</em> plausible: Chauvin and Floyd worked security at the same place for some time (months? years?) and while it's unclear whether they met each other there (Floyd worked inside the club, Chauvin outside), they may have had personal history. (I can imagine that this is because there's no story to be told there, or that it's because additional nuance proved unnecessary.)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>I share the sense many others have expressed that manslaughter is bad, that the case may be indicative of a wider problem, one deserving of a broad public response. But it troubles me that much of the reaction and conversation seems to be premised on murder rather than manslaughter. E.g., lots of people—including some speaking from places of authority or public consensus—have been calling it a "murder in cold blood," a "lynching," or an "assassination." I expect there's a mixture of people who actually/intuitively see it that way, people who are motivated/have convinced themselves to see it that way, and people who don't see it that way but go along with it.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Likewise, I think think some of the response is premised on the officers not having been fired/prosecuted in the absence of public protest (and/or rioting). That issue seems murky to me: it's clear that prosecution would not have happened <em>before</em> protests, but that's simply because it takes time, leaving us unable to clearly demonstrate whether it would've happened regardless. I'm under the impression that they would have been fired anyway (although one could argue that they would not have been immediately fired in a previous climate, one that existed before previous public action brought about the current climate). (A bit of an ironic twist on all this is that I don't think the incident itself have played out the way we saw if the crowd hadn't been there.)</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>In sum, I <em>do</em> get the impression that there's some element of "mass delusion" at play (although it's perhaps better cast as some form of sophistry or allegiance to tribe over truth or something else more charitable). But it's not all black-and-white (how long before we lose this turn of phrase? Has it already expired?). By comparison, I thought there were elements of hysteria in the reaction to coronavirus, too—that things were being done for the wrong reasons, that it was being politicized, and so on. But (to me) that wasn't evidence, as some were suggesting, that there <em>was</em> no problem, that it demanded no response, or that anything (everything) being done was wrong. (It <em>did</em> suggest, to me, that the problems were unlikely to be handled optimally—what with mismodeling the world not usually being helpful. And also that it significantly raised the probability of spiraling to worse places in the policy space as mismodeling compounds.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>