<post>
  <author>sunday02</author>
  <date>2020-06-04T11:41:37Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsuml53/</link>
  <title>The Intrinsic Superiority of Literature as Storytelling Format</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Fiction books seem subpar as a medium for story-telling compared to the flood of excellent movies, TVs, and even video games available.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>If one values originality and lack of censorship in their stories the most, literature as the story-telling format is the best currently available option, for multiple reasons.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>ease of production — required number of content creators, qualifications, human-hours, resources per story. One person on their own v.s. entire production teams, possibility to write as a "free" hobby v.s. millions of dollars of production costs.</p>
          <ul>
            <li>the higher number of authors and titles makes emergence of original stories more likely. For example when the story would've otherwise been censored or self-censored because it contained taboo elements or overtone window problems.</li>
            <li>it makes it possible and relatively easy for people with idiosyncratic and really unique beliefs to share their vision and ideas.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>censorship</p>
          <ul>
            <li>due to high production costs, film, tv show, videogame procuders can't allow themselves to invest in uncertain stories. They'll also be more prone to altering the original plot through <a href="https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/ExecutiveMeddling">executive meddling,</a><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fnvk9MNokPw">audience screenings.</a></li>
            <li>governments (USA,<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N5xfBtD6rLY">[1]</a><a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/phil-strub-controls-hollywoods-military-access-2014-3">[2]</a><a href="https://blogs.loc.gov/kluge/2015/11/war-and-superheroes-how-the-writers-war-board-used-comics-to-spread-its-message-in-wwii/">[3.1]</a><a href="http://www.psywarrior.com/PsyopComics.html">[3.2]</a><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/1122904.Operation_Hollywood">[4]</a> China<a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/parallels/2015/05/18/407619652/how-chinas-censors-influence-hollywood">[1]</a><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/09/hollywoods-great-leap-backward-free-expression/598045/">[2]</a><a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2019/10/23/abominable-china-dreamworks-propaganda-hollywood/">[3]</a><a href="https://io9.gizmodo.com/doctor-strange-gets-china-release-date-confirming-that-1787799835">[4])</a> pay closer attention to Western films and television than to books, and keep pushing until they pass through the changes they want. China and (to a somewhat lesser degree) Russia do also greatly influence their domestic literature through extensive censorship and propaganda, but even there, with all things being equal, literature ends up being influenced less than movies and shows.</li>
            <li>culture war — there are many more book titles per a culture war participant than movie or videogame titles. So the efforts of culture war agents to censor and modify disliked plot and setting elements are more concentrated on movie or game titles.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>limitations of the medium — in a text story, you can describe almost anything your imagination is able to come up with. Videogames are limited by video-game engines, lack of good NPC AIs, unrealistic reactions of characters, simplified modeled environments,  stifled technological improvements by monopoly-holders (e.g. x86 license monopoly). Motion pictures are limited in conveying characters' inner thoughts, actors' abilities to portray difficult scenes and characters, deficit of good actors (especially child actors), costs of good actors, etc.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>speed and convenience of consumption — you can easily skip sections of text you don't find interesting. Locating and skipping to the next interesting scene in a movie is much more difficult.</p>
          <ul>
            <li>you can consume more story development per unit of time in texts, compared to motion pictures, which usually have to advance at the speed of 1s/s.</li>
            <li>reading a book requires fewer available devices, space, time, sensory input channels.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>ease of personal backups, hosting — much less space required per text file. </p>
          <ul>
            <li>This also makes story hosting much cheaper, which additionally indirectly weakens censorship against the format.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>challenging the monopoly of copyright holders over the fictional universe is much easier when you're just writing a story (fanfiction, canon v.s. fanon).</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>language as a barrier — easier to translate and gain access to the vast library of non-English text-based stories than movies and shows.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>(opinion) stifling of imagination — movies and videogames replace your imagination. You're not imagining things yourself any longer, you're just looking at things that have been pre-rendered for you. Consuming too many movies and tv shows and not enough books doesn't properly train your imagination, gradually narrows the limits of what your own imagination is capable of.</p>
          <ul>
            <li>actor appearances, audiobook reader's voice — hard-define too much about a given scene, living little freedom to the audience member's own imagination.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>easier to filter out gratuitous elements and focus on the quality of story itself. </p>
          <ul>
            <li>By their nature, motions pictures over-rely on less significant elements like pretty scenes, pretty faces, pretty visual and sound effects, etc. This makes them neglect the quality of the story's plot itself. If you take two relatively analogous titles, one of which was created in text format and the other in film-format, and strip all the "prettifying" elements from both, the remainder of the text-based story will generally end up being of a superior quality to that of a movie or a videogame.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Of course I don't mean by any of this that videogames or movies shouldn't have their place to exist. But their benefits lie in other areas; and an intrinsically better quality of the underlying story, a strive towards a more realistic portrayal of reality or a more original set of ideas are not generally among those benefits.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>