<post>
  <author>wlxd</author>
  <date>2020-06-05T21:06:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/ft0i5g8/</link>
  <title>How the Protests Cured COVID</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Here's my theory as to what's happening. I think it explains pretty well the changes in the narrative.</p>
      <p>Early on, it became clear to people in the know that there's no easy way out of the epidemics. There will be no cure developed in the next few months/years, and no vaccine either. This leaves only two options left: either try to do serious lockdown/quarantine and eradicate the virus, or just mostly let the epidemics go, while taking some reasonable steps to slow it down. </p>
      <p>Now, social desirability bias kicks in: letting epidemics go means hundreds of thousands, if not millions people will die. People feel bad about this idea, but the real issue is that <em>you can't be seen promoting this approach</em>. If people perceive that you promote this, you'll be seen as <em>evil monster</em>, regardless of whether there's any better alternative. Thus, lockdown it is.</p>
      <p>Now, a few weeks into lockdown, it becomes clear to everyone paying attention that the US is not going to eradicate the virus with lockdown, there's simply no way this is happening. On the other hand, continuing lockdown if you know you'll not eradicate it means that you're only delaying the inevitable, at <em>immense</em> cost. Fortunately for people in the know, most of them are not actually the ones paying that cost, so they don't feel too pressured to bite the bullet, even if they know that ultimately this is what needs to happen -- and of course, advocating biting the bullet is still making you an <em>evil monster</em>. At this stage, the "contact tracing" becomes a popular meme: you have some concrete way out of lockdown that doesn't make you an <em>evil monster</em>. Of course, the viability of contact tracing in the US has always been wishful thinking, but at least the can is kicked down the road: you have excuse to continue lockdowns so that death numbers go down and you don't feel bad looking at the stats, and at the same time you have hope to make things right, and you have a solution that's not <em>evil</em>.</p>
      <p>A few weeks after that, it becomes completely clear that contact tracing is not going to happen. At the same time, people get sick of the lockdowns, and the restrictions are slowly getting lifted. You know that it's going to make the numbers go back up again sooner or later, and just a few weeks ago you were calling people who didn't observe proper distancing rituals <del>unclean heretics</del> grandma killers. The cognitive dissonance kicks in. You know that there's no way out, and lots of people are going to die anyway, but admitting that we all just spent 2 months with the thumbs up our asses for no good reason, and you were the one pushing for it, will make you look like a total retard. You're now looking for a way out while saving face.</p>
      <p>Suddenly, there's an exogenous event: the protests. There are people who do not follow the proper distancing rituals, <em>and they are beyond chiding for that</em>. What a stroke of luck! You're saved from looking like a total moron: if you support the right of protestors to protest, instead of being a grandma killer, you're now a fighter for righteous cause. The social desirability bias is now on your side. Sure, the grandmas will still die, but who gives a fuck, surely if we don't care about people killed in the riots, property burned, and the livelihoods destroyed, will anyone even care about some grandmas in nursing houses? Out of sight, out of mind. Things can go back to normal, the media now have new narrative to push and can finally be allowed to stop focusing on covid. Life's good again, and we can go back to blaming the outgroup for everything that's wrong.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>