<post>
  <author>you-get-an-upvote</author>
  <date>2020-06-05T23:12:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/ft0xw0g/</link>
  <title>Old Man Yells At Motte</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is very much "Old man yells at sky", but here it goes.  I'm not limiting this to "how should we criticize the left", but talking more broadly about discourse here.</p>
      <p>Less:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Elevating flashpoints.  Besides the fact that they are blatantly cherry-picked, they're completely worthless for understanding policy.  By far the most important thing they do is push an ideological narrative, which we, as an ostensibly neutral place of discussion, should be opposed to.</li>
        <li>Excessive repetition.  "I have a relative who is virtue signalling on facebook" or "A social-justice-aligned reporter just said something obviously false" is not informative for anyone who has been on this subreddit for more than a week.  The marginal effect of such posts is primarily just booing the outgroup.</li>
        <li>Claim to be writing a steelman if you don't consider your arguments to be at all convincing.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>More:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Write posts that actually teach people something new</li>
        <li>Write posts that are empirically grounded.  Statistics are good.  Heck "the LA riots of 1992 lasted 6 days" is better than "I have a gut feeling these riots will last a long time"</li>
        <li>Do the work to collect several anecdotes.  If you want to prove that the New York Times is ideologically captured but don't want to do anything rigorous, at least put in the effort to do more than copy-paste the latest outrage link.  If there was a comment about "the 4 most recent outrages from the NYT", that would be more convincing and more valuable than the 4+ posts it currently becomes.</li>
        <li>Discuss actual policies.</li>
        <li>Summarize interesting things (books, blog posts, etc) that you don't think are wrong.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>I'd ask posters to consider if the marginal post on a topic is actually going to bring any enlightenment or understanding, or if it's just a pretense to complain about a group they don't feel like they can complain about in public.  Is this a place for discussion, or is this the political analogue of "a safe space atheists to blasphemy and feel reassured that there are people that agree with them"?</p>
      <p>I scrape comments from <a href="/r/slatestarcodes">r/slatestarcodes</a> and <a href="/r/TheMotte">r/TheMotte</a> every couple days.  According to my index, 6/7 of the most recent top-level comments from 19-23 hours ago have fewer than 200 words.  The <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsxe7n3/">longer one</a> seems fine, but the rest of them are pushing it (at best).  If we let</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I read something and have 100 words to say about it.  (Maybe I'll end my post with "what are your guys' thoughts?")</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This opens the door to low-effort stuff I'm opposed to.  From the 7 comments above:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsxidm4/">complaining about a facebook post</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsxhy60/">random new story that I have 100 words of thought on</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fswu8a0/">random old story I have 100 words of thought on</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fswt327/">uncharitable interpretation that has been made here a dozen times before</a>).</li>
      </ol>
      <p>(I should confess: there have since then been a string of higher effort top-level comments)</p>
      <p>I want to see comments that require genuine leg work (and/or relying on expertise they've already developed).</p>
      <p>To get at <a href="/u/zortlax">/u/zortlax</a>'s question</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>What would you accept as evidence that the modal opinion of this sub's poster on social justice isn't a result of conflict theorizing, waging culture war, narrative manipulation, or selective reporting, but of reasonably neutral observation?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>When I see a ton of low-effort posts/comments on my Facebook feed talking about how Trump is Bad, I interpret it as culture warring.  When I see the same thing here, I also interpret it as culture warring.</p>
      <p>If you're pretty sure gun control leads to an increase in (successful) suicides and that's sufficient reason for you to support gun control, you make some posts about your argument and maybe comment when it is particularly salient.</p>
      <p>But if you make a post every week about how a hot-off-the-presses study found that America has a higher suicide rate than the UK (sorry, I'm just trying to find a good analogy here) then you're probably driven by something other than "trying to genuinely understand the issue".</p>
      <p>What would convince me that people here were genuinely interested in the truth?</p>
      <p>If they stopped feeling compelled to post the latest twitter/news outrage that confirms the consensus of the sub (that the media overreacts to Trump, that there are mainstream social justice advocates who say ridiculous things, etc.).</p>
      <p>This is also what it would take to convince me that <a href="/r/news">r/news</a> was genuinely interested in cultivating a reasonably neutral understanding.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>