<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-05-17T12:40:19Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ne8ggb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_17_2021/gyfsliq/</link>
  <title>Doesn't Really Stand for Anything Except Itself</title>
  <category>
    <li>coteries</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The conservatives have spent the last decade waging a remarkably successful march through many of Britain’s institutions, including the boards of most public bodies, the civil service, media regulator, the top of the judiciary and even the BBC itself - all of which were once dominated by the left. David Cameron systematically placed Tory allies in key positions in the BBC, to name just one example, many times over. </p>
      <p>There’s only one problem - almost none of them are actually conservative. The British Conservative Party exists, like all the most successful political movements, to further its own existence. Having successfully judged that the attitude of the BBC and other bodies had played a role in preventing the party from effectively challenging Tony Blair and also from winning a majority in 2010, they set out to ensure that those institutions would be favorable to them from then on. They were very successful - the BBC now very rarely criticizes the Tory party and is broadly favorable to Johnson, and was deeply critical of Corbyn’s Labour in the last election. </p>
      <p>But the BBC, and the public sector, are all still very woke. Why? Because many of the very same leading cosmopolitan members of the managerial class who the Conservatives appointed to those positions share the same social views as their Labour peers, they just happen to be Tories (or willing to carry water for them). This includes, by the way, the Prime Minister’s own girlfriend, a progressive environmentalist who was ex-PR director for the Conservative Party and who is now widely considered his most influential advisor. </p>
      <p>The Conservative Party doesn’t really stand for anything except, broadly, itself. After its 2005 defeat on an anti-immigration platform it didn’t speak about immigration for a decade. After the 2008 financial crash it became a ‘shrink the state’ party almost overnight. After the EU vote it became a pro-Brexit party. After Johnson’s victory in the northern rust belt it became a pro-tax and spend economic revitalization in the north party. I’m not saying any of these are good or bad things, just that the party itself is fickle. It doesn’t really have an ideology, it exists in many ways in opposition to any ideology. </p>
      <p>Of course, waging culture war for electoral reasons isn’t unique to the UK - Orban and Erdogan, to name just two democratic leaders, have played the same game for years. But their parties and leadership are in many cases filled with true believers, and that just isn’t (in my opinion) the case in Britain. Occasionally somebody like Toby Young does slip through, but they inevitably get cancelled by the mainstream (including half the Tory party) and are demoted or forced out. </p>
      <p>Even Macron, for example, is much more radically right wing on immigration and assimilation than the Tories will ever be. A few weeks ago a British teacher was forced into hiding after showing kids a cartoon of Mohammed. The most the Tory leadership could muster was a vague condemnation in bland terms, plus giving him police protection like Salman Rushdie. Even the German CDU, Merkel’s party, condemn Islamism more forcefully. </p>
      <p>The British elite, new and old, shares much of the same politics. The Conservative Party and Boris, who was once a multicultaralist, diversity is our strength Mayor of London, is no exception.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>