<post>
  <author>bsbbtnh</author>
  <date>2020-04-29T14:00:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/foyagi3/</link>
  <title>Tenancy/Zoning Laws and Unintended Market Distortions</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Tenancy laws don't exist in a vacuum, so a 1:1 comparison is useless. Most large American cities (typically run by Democrats) have really, really poor zoning &amp; property laws, which are all aimed at helping the poor, but in reality it just creates higher and higher rents.</p>
      <p>A common one is an annual cap on property reassessments. If your property's value increases 5% in a year, the cap may be only 2%. Over a few decades, there then becomes a real distortion in the taxes paid on older properties compared to new ones. </p>
      <p>If you wanted to do a significant upgrade or renovation, that cap is typically removed. If the property changes hands, it is typically reassessed at full value. So there's a disincentive to change ownership (properties are usually owned by LLCs, and the company is sold instead), or to renovate, because a large apartment building could see <em>millions</em> in additional taxes.</p>
      <p>Rent controls are another issue. In NYC, rent control laws prevent evicting tenants. You have to buy them out of their leases and help them relocate. This has led to issues where entire buildings sit nearly empty for years, as the owners wait for tenants to die, so they can renovate or rebuild. This can be very lucrative for hold-outs. One of the highest in NYC was <a href="https://nypost.com/2014/03/02/hotel-hermit-got-17m-to-make-way-for-15-central-park-west/">$17 million</a> for a 350 square foot apartment. </p>
      <p>Anti-gentrification laws, which usually target older and poorer neighborhoods, continue a cycle of poverty. It relegates those neighborhoods to no new investments, no increase in quality of life. They usually target minority neighborhoods.</p>
      <p>Older buildings typically end up rent controlled, or protected in some form (like anti-gentrification) as affordable housing. Tenants will stay decades in the same place, no matter what their circumstances. This doesn't help the poor, it helps a small sliver of the population. Rent controls and affordable housing leads to higher prices for the remaining market units. The poor that can't get a rent-controlled apartment can't compete with the middle class, though. So the 'poor' housing ends up getting eaten up by the middle class, and your lowest rung of properties are available at middle-class prices.</p>
      <p>There's also an incentive to keep renovating newer buildings, to prevent them from getting hit with rent control, anti-gentrification, densification and other laws. So you evict all your middle-class tenants, do a useless renovation, and then jack up rents. This squeezes the middle-class, once again.</p>
      <p>It also leads to a distortion in housing stock and the housing cycle. In a "normal" city, housing goes through a life cycle. New housing goes to the lower-upper or upper-middle class. When it gets a few years (decades) old, it goes to the middle-class (they get a quality of life increase with no appreciable increase in cost). A few decades later, that housing passes to the working/lower class. And near the end of its life, the poor live there. Everybody gets value out of it, everyone gets to experience a quality of life increase from getting these 'hand-me-downs'. </p>
      <p>Once that housing is falling apart (usually neighborhoods are built together, so the whole neighborhood is crumbling), you see investment start coming in (the dreaded "gentrification"). The housing is torn down and upgraded, new businesses move in, and the upper-middle class (or lower-upper class) move on in. And the cycle continues.</p>
      <p>But we've prevented the old shit from being torn down, so the poor will never see a natural increase in quality of life. Instead, we tear down middle-class housing and hand it to the lower-upper class. We're tearing down (or renovating) housing that has 75% of its life left. But when we upgrade it, we can't sell it at 100% of its life value. We have to add in the 75% of value that never got used. We destroyed that value, but it still gets factored into the price. So a home we just rebuilt with 100% of its life left is going to sell for 175% of that value. If you buy a $100,000 house and tear it down, and then build a $500 shed, you now have a $100,500 shed. This is what is happening in the largest cities across the US.</p>
      <p>These are all largely Democrat policies, which are sold as 'helping the poor', which do the complete opposite. And the worse and worse it gets, the more it seems like these are good ideas, so those policies become more and more popular. </p>
      <p>I remember AOC getting criticized for not knowing what a garbage disposal was, and her being shocked overall by the place she was living in DC (which, looking at her videos, looks like a cookie cutter middle-class condo <em>at best</em>). Why was she shocked? Because even the middle-class in NYC live in slums. They never see the 'quality of life' increase I mentioned. A condo like that would be remodeled in a decade and sold for twice the value, never truly becoming part of the housing cycle, never making it into the hands of the middle or lower-middle class. </p>
      <p>What is happening in these cities is similar to what happened with 'Cash for Clunkers'. After the 2008 financial crisis, the federal government implemented a program that would give you a voucher if you trade-in a less efficient vehicle (that is less than 25 years old.. I guess they didn't care about the gas guzzlers from the 70s and early 80s). You buy a brand new car, get a couple grand knocked off the price, and your old car gets destroyed (it had to be drivable). This was an indirect subsidy to car companies. </p>
      <p>This of course created a distortion in the life-cycle of cars. Most of the middle-class doesn't (or didn't, at that point) buy new cars. They'd buy a car that was ~5 years old. And the working class would buy a car that's ~10 years old. And the poor would buy a car that's ~15 years old. </p>
      <p>The used car stock fell. Prices shot up. Cost for replacement parts shot up. And all that fell on those with lower incomes. And that 'quality of life' increase was lost. Poor people would get nicer cars over the years, even though they were old. They were safer than previous model years, got better mileage, had nicer interiors, more features. But now that cost is artificially inflated, the supply is knocked down, and they have to cling to their older vehicles longer.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>