<post>
  <author>cvdailyupdates</author>
  <date>2020-04-26T16:05:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g5j7zm/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_7/fond2bp/</link>
  <title>The Evolution of My Personal View on Coronavirus</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The easiest way is probably to look at four data points:</p>
      <p>1) the point in time when new information becomes available</p>
      <p>2) the point in time when the person under observation becomes aware of new information</p>
      <p>3) the point in time when the socially fashionable perspective changes</p>
      <p>4) the point in time when the person under observation changes their stated position.</p>
      <p>If (4) correlates more with (3) than with (1)/(2), then it is driven by social desirability bias. If (4) correlates more with (1)/(2) than (3), it is driven by sincere updating on new information. The more (1) correlates with (2), the more the person can be presumed to actually care about the truth of their beliefs (since the larger the delta between those two, the less effort the person is putting in to make sure their beliefs are up to date)</p>
      <hr />
      <p>For two, much less complex heuristics:</p>
      <p>a) watch how zealously they advocate their current position, and compare it to the level of knowledge and understanding they demonstrate for that position. Social desirability bias =&gt; superficial understanding; sincere updating on knowledge =&gt; demonstrated deep understanding</p>
      <p>b) watch how zealously they advocate their current position, how zealously they advocated their previous position, and how frank and open they are about how and why they changed their beliefs. Zealous on both and/or lack of addressing the how/why =&gt; social desirability bias. Suitably modest, willing to acknowledge that they were previously 'wrong', willing to discuss how and why they changed their beliefs, etc, =&gt; real update on new info</p>
      <hr />
      <p>As a personal example, I would be identified as generally conservative. The conservatives, generally, are anti-lockdown and pro-"this is no big deal". (not actually true but perceived as true, which is the important part). I am now generally anti-lockdown and pro-"this is no big deal". You will notice that in the past I was very, very doomer on this subject. You might observe that my flip to the nothingburger camp correlated with the narrative of conservatives coalescing on that position, and conclude that I am just conforming to social expectations.</p>
      <p>However you would be wrong. My decision process went approximately like this:</p>
      <p>1) (Early Jan) Some random rumours and leaks out of chinese social media. =&gt; this is probably nothing</p>
      <p>2) Rumours keep happening =&gt; ....huh maybe this is something</p>
      <p>3) Wuhan locks down =&gt; hard update to "we're all going to die", on grounds that this is an unprecedented move that dramatically hurts the CCP and they wouldn't do it unless it was severe enough that they thought they had to. </p>
      <p>4) Watch data coming out, observe the following:</p>
      <p>4a) Chinese data puts the magnitude of this crisis at dramatically lower than Chinese actions suggest. China is probably lying. If it's so bad that China is lying, that's really really bad</p>
      <p>4b) This shit is so contagious, it looks like pretty much no matter what we do, everyone is catching it. That's really bad</p>
      <p>4c) 20% hospitalization rate, 5% critical rate, 2% fatality rate. 2% of 350,000,000 = 7M dead americans. This is really really bad</p>
      <p>5) Reason through the consequences of Chinese-style lockdown happening here. Conclude that that might even be worse than the disease (various post-apocalypse breakdown-of-society scenarios running through my head). </p>
      <p>6) Italy happens and looks (to me) like their entire society is going to collapse. This is bad</p>
      <p>At this point I am firmly in the "we're all going to die" camp</p>
      <p>7) Towards the end of march, observe the following:</p>
      <p>7a) Far from my predictions of collapse, Italy has had only 25k people die. Nothing particularly exciting (in an end-of-the-world sense happens there). Updating towards "this is bad, but not world-endingly bad"</p>
      <p>7b) Far from my predictions of collapse, most of the US has been on some form of lockdown for two months. The roads are still not blockaded. There are no army vans out in public. Stores still have food. Water and power and internet still work. Updating towards "huh, not so bad"</p>
      <p>7c) Data coming from multiple sources all suggesting that people in my demographic are basically immune to serious negative impacts. I personally no longer fear drowning to death on my own lungs, update towards "this is not so bad <em>for me</em> and fuck everyone else who think their lack of preparation justifies imposing on me"</p>
      <p>7d) Data coming from multiple sources all suggesting that, while retirees are in severe danger, people in my demographic are basically immune. Retirees do not have significant influence over whether society goes on or collapses. People in my demographic do (eg. the guy in charge of an electrical power plant is probably a guy in his 40s or 50s, and not a guy in his 80s. If all the people &gt;80 die, the electricity stays on, in a way that if significant numbers of people in their 40s die, it might not). Update towards "society is not going to collapse"</p>
      <p>7e) Death data from most western sources are at least two orders of magnitude lower than what I thought they would be. Update towards "this is not as big a deal as I thought"</p>
      <p>7f) Various inexplicable discontinuities (eg why is New York having such a bad time when California is not) which all point towards various forms of both "there are actual effective mitigation strategies against the impact of this disease, once we figure out what they are" and also "as my own city more closely matches the 'low impact' cities and not the 'high impact' cities, prediction of the impact on my city goes milder". </p>
      <p>7g) observation of unnecessary politicization of crisis + various political shenanigans, update towards "this can't be that bad because if it was the people in charge wouldn't be risking fucking around like that"</p>
      <p>7h) observation of unnecessary politicization of crisis + various political shenanigans, combined with data suggesting disease is milder than I thought, update towards "the anti-disease measures will be worse than the disease and are already being actively leveraged against me, so I oppose them"</p>
      <p>Because I can explain to you the evolution of my viewpoint over time, because I can account for the specific data points that changed it, because I am more than willing to acknowledge that I was wrong in the past (I am hereby acknowledging that I took this much more seriously than necessary when it started), and because absolutely nothing in my explanation referred to mainstream news or political <em>anything</em>, it is reasonable to conclude that I hold my beliefs honestly and with depth</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>