<post>
  <author>GrapeGrater</author>
  <date>2020-04-29T20:40:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/fozlwza/</link>
  <title>Non-Monetary Barriers to Web Entry</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The notion that monetary costs are the only barrier is obsolete.</p>
      <p>Google and Apple routinely remove apps off the App Store and, by extension, effectively ban developers what amounts to the entirety of the market.</p>
      <p>Network effects make it impossible to advertise or communicate if you aren't in one of the walled gardens like Reddit. But with Reddit and the other social media giants engaging in routine censorship (market denial?) that's often not possible.</p>
      <p>The issue is that Google, Facebook, Twitter and Reddit amount to a monopoly, perhaps even more of a monopoly, than the Telecoms they love to attack and in an analogous way.</p>
      <p>Building a telegraph is not particularly difficult and running cable to your friend can become expensive or be surprisingly cheap (it depends on the distance). 40 years ago, children used to build radios from kits sold in corner stores. But if you can't get anyone on your telegraph or radio system, it doesn't really matter.</p>
      <p>Reddit, Google and the other Tech monopolies enjoy pushing the "just start your own website, it's basically free" line because they fear the kinds of regulation and anti-trust they've tried to bring upon the telecoms (see Net Neutrality). They want people to think of them as publishers so they can argue they should be given a right to dictate political discussion--while they make arguments in court they're analogous to the telephone and can't be sued (this is the publisher versus platform argument). I take the stance these companies are more like platforms and should be thought of as the new telephone company and need to be handled as such. I think you're thinking they are the new New York Times.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>