<post>
  <author>greatjasoni</author>
  <date>2020-04-29T20:31:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/fozkpko/</link>
  <title>Explaining Nietzche as Beethoven/Goethe Fanboy</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think his philosophy can be read as extreme fanboying over <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=06PPhF2tX1g">Beethoven</a> and Goethe. (Really Wagner, but that complicates the narrative too much.) He has these notions of great men who transcended their suffering and wants to rebuild humanity in their image. This would obviously mean sublimating the passions towards those transcendent aims. At the same time he has this resentment aimed against anything that would shackle the human spirit. He wants a transcendence that isn't bound by anything. You ought to indulge the passions having cast off the old masters that arbitrarily told you to limit things. I think mostly he says that out of a rhetorical flair he has. I read him as sometimes overly preoccupied with his own prose, cramming sentences full of punchlines to the detriment of direct communication. </p>
      <p>He loves Beethoven because he casts off the shackles of the old musical structure to create something that reflects the depth of the human spirit. Beethoven's music is radically more emotional and dramatic than his predecessors. (Not really but this is the narrative.) But on the other hand is a half-recognition that Beethoven was only able to produce such great works because of this Christian institution. Above I linked what is usually considered his greatest work, which is a Catholic Mass. He is only able to "transcend" the old structure because the structure exists in the first place. The music of Haydn and Mozart which Beethoven "transcends" is an extremely complex aesthetic construct that took centuries of craft and theory passed down through apprentices to work out, all explicitly to support the demands of the church. Nietzsche himself is a brilliant writer and the worlds most respected critic of Christianity. But he's only able to do that because he memorized the entire Bible when he was a teenager. His issue is maybe of thinking of our civilization's construct as a dead end. He much prefers his own idealized version of Homeric Greece, where these apprentices produced great works without stifling the passions. Beethoven has the discipline to produce a volume of great work, but with enough fire and passion that it reflects the human spirit. People like Wagner take this further, Goethe does something roughly equivalent in literature (and then walks it back). But all of that discipline and transcendence is a product of the structure in the first place. Without that structure "indulging in the human spirit" just looks like <a href="https://youtu.be/e0_DgrFgUkw?t=7">this</a>.</p>
      <p>His death of God quote kind of has an awareness of all of that. It's an apocalyptic picture of helpless impotent souls who brought about their own demise. He is lamenting the death of the structure, and is warning people that without the core of God the rest is sure to collapse. Beyond Good and Evil, and Zarathustra, are a roadmap for how to embrace the human spirit without falling into that pit. I think most of it reads better as literature than it does coherent philosophy. But clearly his ideal is something beyond the Last Men, we just never find out how they get there.</p>
      <p>The crux of it all is "transcendence." How are you creating new values and transcending humanity, if your notion of transcendence is just being more passionate and emotional? It's almost like a failure of imagination grounded in reactionary anger towards the Lutheran church. It also might stem from his lack of success as an author despite knowing he was one of the smartest people in the world, and his inability to get laid. I don't want to be too uncharitable towards him, because on paper his notion of transcendence and creation of new values is supposed to go beyond this (although that's obviously impossible). But in practice he creates this great idea and then imagines it as a weapon to beat his personal demons which were fundamentally grounded in sin.</p>
      <p>He's strange because he informs my worldview more than any other author, and yet I have the most profound disagreements with him on so many levels. I think that stems from the internal contradiction you're pointing out, and his philosophy is a brilliant but ultimately unsuccessful attempt to grapple with it. Rummaging through the wreckage is hugely insightful because the modern world <em>is</em> the wreckage. Either he was just that influential, or his own psyche was an unbearably self aware microcosm for the wider culture, or both.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>