<post>
  <author>greatjasoni</author>
  <date>2020-04-27T22:33:19Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/fosa89s/</link>
  <title>Aesthetics or Consequentialism in Ideology</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm curious about the relationship between adopting an ideology on aesthetic grounds (or roughly deontological ones), and adopting an ideology because you think it leads to the best consequences. I just wrote this for a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/g4mse5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_20_2020/fos7iqz/?context=10000">reply</a> in last weeks thread but I'm sufficiently confused about the issue that I'd like to hear what people have to say.</p>
      <p>On the one hand I'm (sort-of) a conservative for aesthetic reasons. I believe what I believe independent of the consequences. On the other hand I think that for the most part conservative solutions reduce suffering more than their common alternatives. Not entirely, because that's not the terminal value. But in my mind they just happen to be closer to "rationally correct policy" as I understand it, than what the left proposes, which is from my point of view either wasteful and ineffective or openly destructive. Is it coincidence then, that I unironically agree with this ugly nonsensical statement? "Taking money from CEO's and giving it to the poor is just going to make them worse off!"</p>
      <p>Here I would distinguish between the libertarian streak and the conservative streak on the right. They both diverge into radically different directions, and maybe converge somewhere further down the line at NRX. But inside of American conservatism they're kind of a contradictory mess. Conservatism is concerned with aesthetics, but capitalism is what destroyed traditional culture and art and values in the first place (alternatively technology if you want to go full Kaczynski). American conservatism tries to have its cake and eat it too. Yet people on the right tend to much prefer capitalism to the alternatives. I think that's why deontological libertarian ideas are so popular, the notion of "liberty" as a value. It lets capitalists <em>feel</em> like they're on the side of an aesthetic. But liberty is inherently negative, it has no positive value to provide anything. "Liberty to do what?" This leads to absurd ideas like the confederacy was fighting for states rights, without mentioning what they were going to do with those rights. Conservatism has a vague answer to this in the form of "culture" or "family" without having the stones to just say "church" or something even less fashionable these days. Either way it's not compatible with liberty, at least not in the way libertarians mean the word. It's liberty to act how conservatives think you should act.</p>
      <p>A fashionable solution is to pick "responsibility" as a terminal value, which is still negative and vague as it doesn't specify "responsibility towards what", but at least it naturally encourages a sort of libertarianism, which still produces the consequences the right wants, while still giving you something to feel like suffering over.</p>
      <p>You could complicate this further by looking at consequentialist readings of conservatism. The American conservative narrative about the black community is that the left sabotaged their culture and trapped them in welfare, leaving a completely decimated community. A bad sense of morality, encouraged by the left, caused a downfall. The left wing narrative is one of systemic racism, which the right sees as just another excuse to absolve responsibility which then produces a worse outcome. Neither narrative particularly makes sense to me, but it's interesting how they see the link between values and reduction of suffering. The issue is bad outcomes, but they act like principles are still what really matters. Maybe the solution to this is just to declare "American Conservatism" to be a contradictory mess, which I would agree with as a conservative who just happens to be American. Libertarians don't conserve anything. But the notion that "right = libertarian" is hugely prevalent. You can see it just sort of assumed in the comments all over the CW thread.</p>
      <p>One solution is just to say freedom means freedom to choose the good, where the good is defined in religious terms. This would mean that a modern libertarian utopia where everyone is free to choose whatever they want without intrusion from large powers actually decreases freedom because the inevitable result is a decline into decadence and evil. But this is just the standard way of looking at the world pre-enlightenment, and that isn't really conservatism either. Even with that definition of freedom I'd never have it as the terminal value. With a worldview like that I could very easily support a christian communist anarchy for aesthetic reasons, which is probably what the 12 disciples did, and just admit that it's doomed to fail but we should try anyways. My gut tells me it's beautiful, everyone is equal in the eyes of God who is pure love, and my mind tells me it's completely idiotic and could never be practiced by humans. <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matthew+5%3A40-45&amp;version=KJV">"And if any man will sue thee at the law, and take away thy coat, let him have thy cloke also."</a> What if I need my cloke to not freeze to death? What if I just want to keep my cloke? Of course Christianity is, in one reading, about transcending humanity to create a new heaven, and maybe that new heaven would both be beautiful and reduce suffering, because it's practiced by beings a few rungs up the ladder of divine ascendancy. Ordinary people would have to be completely insane, by sane metrics, to actually follow the teachings of Jesus. This lifestyle did not reduce suffering for the early Christians. They all died horribly for spreading it and encouraged each other to do so. We still have holidays celebrating their deaths.</p>
      <p>Which gets us back to conservatism and its inherent contradictions. Maybe conservatism sets up conditions to approximate this utopian vision while making concessions to keep it from collapsing. Conservatism relies on trust norms all over small communities so that people cooperate in iterated games. When people start defecting then you need the state to step in and trample all over the libertarian streak. But by encouraging a sense of moral character, you produce a high trust society, and that then approximates a kind of anarchist religious utopia in small doses, with just enough hierarchy so that the moral fabric of society doesn't break down. A dose of morality sets up the necessary conditions to flourish and reduce suffering. People are committed to their families, love their neighbors, watch each other's kids, spontaneously give to the needy, etc. You're not quite at the beauty of a classless moneyless society, but the community does its best to approximate it given the constraints, while not going so far that it kills people for loving each other. In practice this particular notion has never worked and the thing it's trying to approximate died the second Christianity became one with the state and people started gesturing at one morality while practicing another. People only know to love one another because the institution indoctrinates them to indoctrinate each other. If at any point the meme stops spreading, or god forbid mutates, the inquisition has to step in for the sake of the needy. Christianity was always a radical rejection of earthly powers that weren't the church and is not compatible with them. Maybe conservatism means not being so committed to that particular aesthetic for the sake of reducing suffering. What do you call a radical conservative? Either way you've reduced a grand aesthetic vision to consequentialism. Or maybe just redefined the consequences to fit your aesthetic.</p>
      <p>This applies to literally every ideology as actually practiced. Communists might be explicitly committed to materialism and only push for communism because they're convinced it's an inevitable evolution that will solve everyone's problems. Uncharitably, if they really wanted to reduce suffering they'd look at the vast amount of data saying that it doesn't work and advocate things that actually do work, and since they aren't doing that, they must be committed to communism primarily on aesthetic grounds while just coincidentally thinking it would be the best at reducing suffering. Even if suffering reduction isn't your terminal value, in practice ideologies always come suspiciously close to minimizing suffering in their own framework. The only time you're not acting like a consequentialist is when you do something knowing it will produce a bad outcome, because you had some kind of higher value to do so. If you never think such a situation arises, then you're basically a consequentialist no matter what you say, and are adjusting your map of reality to always produce the desired outcome given the ideology. Maybe I believe in <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+Corinthians+13&amp;version=NKJV">love</a>, but maybe I'm not capable of it unless things are going well.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>