<post>
  <author>mokoroo</author>
  <date>2020-04-29T09:42:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g8uasn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_27_2020/foxr4f0/</link>
  <title>The Slow Process of Bringing In Working-Class Candidates</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>But if left-wing DSA/Justice Democrats are so damn worried about their lack of appeal to the working class, you'd think they could at least give this a try.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Pinging <a href="/u/AshLael">/u/AshLael</a> as I think they'll be interested in what I have to say here.</p>
      <p>I'm a member of the Australian Labor Party (ALP from here on in). At first I joined with a particular bugaboo that I wanted addressed.</p>
      <p>In the 2019 election, though, my focus finally shifted from 'what policies are we putting forward' to 'what candidates are we putting forward'. </p>
      <p>I live in Brisbane. I did a brief analysis of the candidates in Brisbane, Greater Brisbane (Brisbane and the three small satellite cities), and finally Brisbane plus the two nearby major cities (the Gold and Sunshine Coasts, respectively). The thing that stood out was this:</p>
      <p>Versus the LNP (our right-wing party), perhaps ~70% of ALP candidates were lawyers or career student politicians. Of the remaining 30%, they were all white collar jobs or culture jobs. There were zero blue collar candidates in that region. Around 40% of the LNP were the same. About 30% of the LNP were small businesspeople or people from a trades background. Another 30% were white collar - accountants, doctors, etc.</p>
      <p>Perhaps the most important thing in a political party isn't what a party is offering in terms of policy, it's who is running it. Any political party owned by the managerial class will be for the managerial class eventually. You can stick as many upper-middle class socialists as you want into that party, but ideology is weak. If you can't include the working class in your political party's decision-making structure it will eventually diverge away from working-class interests.</p>
      <p>This was shown in the election. The ALP were <em>shellacked</em> in Queensland. The Prime Minister after winning a shock victory nobody expected said "how good is Queensland!". It was one of the worst performances the ALP have had in Queensland <em>ever</em>, and while everyone was shocked, they all started in on what policies to change, how to present things differently, etc, etc.</p>
      <p>We spent a lot of party meetings just hearing people grouse about how the election was conducted. How we put forward the wrong candidates, how we put forward our policies badly, and so on and so forth. This was all <em>true</em>, but the thing that got me annoyed was we looked at the decisions we'd made, rather than the underlying mechanism we used for making those decisions. </p>
      <p>We had a party run by lawyers and policy wonks and got complicated policy that was hard to explain to the average punter.</p>
      <p>I used to be a member of the Australian Greens (regular left rather than centre-left), and while the party was always concerned about what they thought was best for the working class, they were never at all concerned about what they thought the working class <em>wanted</em>. I left the Greens because I found the hypocrisy frustrating (and the reality of being in a party with no power and having to swallow the hypocrisy even worse). The ALP is hypocritical but at least honest about it - it does want to attract working class people, and it's willing to pay the price to do so if it could just figure out <em>how</em>.</p>
      <p>In the Greens there was always a vibe of "why don't these racist sexist white males vote for us?!". In the ALP the same feeling is "why don't our natural constituency and allies, the working class, vote for us?!". There's a feeling of being betrayed, but there's enough introspection left in the membership and the party to suspect we're also the ones defecting.</p>
      <p>This brings me to the current bee in my bonnet. I'm not a major party member in the sense that the only people of any interest in my party who know me by name are my local members, and I have no real pull. But the one thing I'm slowly grinding away on is affirmative action for blue-collar candidates.</p>
      <p>There are a lot of places where I think identity politics is stupid. I don't care if we have more Aboriginal veterinarians. But politics is intrinsically different - in a representative democracy the job for a politician is to <em>be</em> representative, and that means replicating as many of the most salient characteristics of the electorate as you can. If 10% of your population is black and you have no black politicians you genuinely have a problem in a way you don't if 10% of your population is black and you have no black badminton champions.</p>
      <p>Because of this I am strongly in favor of affirmative action for politicians (I am actually in favor of using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sortition">sortition</a> over standard electoral politics but I only ever advocate in the party for policies I have some hope of seeing implemented). I'm absolutely fine with our party's stated goal of a 50/50 gender split in representatives, and having more Aboriginal candidates, more Asians as well - things that effectively ensure more accurate representation for the Australian population.</p>
      <p>Where it falls down is that modern identity politics fails to really grasp the nature of I guess class but also culture - I grew up as what you would term in America as 'poor white trash', and I had a <em>lot</em> more in common with poor Aboriginals than I did with the children of doctors and lawyers. Conversely, two of my friends are white and south-east asian respectively - sons of high-powered corporate lawyers, judges, ambassadors and property magnates. They're both born in Australia and the difference between them is literally skin deep - they move in the same circles, have the same advantages in life. More than that, they share <em>culture</em>. Hanging out with upper-middle class and upper class people as a cultural lumpenprole is difficult, and while I skate by on some natural warmth with some, trying to move up a career ladder populated by these sorts of people is <em>really hard</em>. </p>
      <p>"Just not the best cultural fit" is something I've had said to me more than once - and it's also something I feel all the time. While I can paper over it for interviews well, <em>maintaining</em> the nebulous notion of cultural fit among the middle to upper class is really, really hard. They're not bad people, don't mistake me - I much prefer the company of the middle and upper classes to the bottom of society where I grew up, but I am very different to them and it shows unless I work hard to present myself differently (I lean hard into being eccentric - "weird smart guy who cracks sometimes inappropriate but funny jokes and is a hard greenie who loves sustainability" goes over much better than "working class guy who doesn't know what's appropriate and grew up so poor that excessive frugality and self-sufficiency were birthed from constant fear of immiserating poverty").</p>
      <p>A notion of diversity that sees those two as somehow more a more diverse group than my white friend (who has a parent judging cases in one of the highest courts in the country) and me (who grew up in a leaky, broken caravan because there was no room in the house - I had to tie down a tarpaulin over the van and squirm up under it to get in the door in storms to ensure my bed didn't get saturated on cold, stormy nights) is broken.</p>
      <p>But it's easy to diversify on race and sex - you have boobs, your skin is black, you're kissing another man - you can see it all up-front. Modern affirmative action policies are in part about diversifying the <em>visible</em> - a guy in a wheelchair looks <em>great</em> on your corporate website, but you can't show someone's past experiences and class in a single snapshot. </p>
      <p>So the difficult work of convincing my branch and my member (who is one of the very many lawyers) to bring in more working class candidates continues ever-so-slowly. I'm not sure I'll get anywhere with it, but I suppose once you discount my rather long tangent what I really wanted to say is this: some of us <em>are</em> doing our best to give this a try. It's just difficult and a lot of people on the left see it as a way to discount racism and sexism and so fight against it vociferously.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>