<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-04-27T13:11:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/g5j7zm/coronavirus_quarantine_thread_week_7/foqgkrb/</link>
  <title>The Red-Blue Color Inversion in American Politics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>On the one hand I know what you are trying to say and do, on the other I am vaguely annoyed by someone calling our lefties blue when in the UK that colour refers to the Conservatives.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Fun fact: a lot of Americans thought of <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment/tv/la-et-st-electoral-map-20161102-htmlstory.html">blue as the color of our conservatives as well</a>, because traditionally, electoral mapmakers used blue to represent Republicans, and red to represent Democrats--<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_states_and_blue_states">as far back as 1888</a>.  This is apparently standard in many places, as red tends to be associated with left-wing politics for what are presumably obvious reasons.  With the advent of televised elections, some networks kept the blue-conservative, red-progressive color scheme going consistently for years, while others did not--some appear to have color-coded for incumbents, for example.</p>
      <p>For reasons that are <em>still</em> not clear, it just so happens that in the 2000 American Presidential election, where electoral maps remained the focus of the nation for months instead of hours, the news media gradually reached an equilibrium of "red states" and "blue states" that was not without precedent, but happened to be the <em>opposite</em> of what most Americans generally thought.</p>
      <p>It's one of the strangest norm inversions in history and I am amazed at its resilience.  As an effort to de-associate the color red with American progressivism, it could not have been more successful if it were deliberate (indeed, may have been <em>less</em> successful).  And since the color red continues to be more closely associated with villainry in our popular media, there is certainly no incentive for our news reporters to buck the current equilibrium.  What fascinates <em>me</em> about it is that, at least in connection with televised and printed political outcomes, the history of blue/red electoral politics and the phrase "red state"/"blue state" should be relatively easy to track down for a dedicated historical researcher.  But the Wikipedia page, at least, does not seem to point toward any really <em>authoritative</em> academic sources on how the 2000 election wound up standardizing exactly the opposite from what one might ordinarily expect.  Apparently, it just sort of <em>happened</em> that way.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>