<post>
  <author>4bpp</author>
  <date>2019-12-13T02:15:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/famgjon/</link>
  <title>The Rise of Tribalism in the Anglosphere</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Is it really so inexplicable? Most countries in the anglosphere have arguably been moving towards a more tribal and less rules-based/institutional public sphere for a long time (in the sense that people value satisfying their tribe's ideals over those of their job or role in the system, giving us situations such as the friendly press and public's acquiescence towards the Brexiteers' tenuous relationship with facts on the one hand and the obstructionism of the Rotherham authorities on the other). In this environment, more primal political considerations might become relevant. If the only thing that will guarantee outcomes favourable to you in various aspects of public life is that tribes whose interests are aligned with yours are powerful in a diffuse sense (people expect them to win, and therefore will not even challenge them) and tribes whose interests are misaligned are weak (people expect them to lose or at least have a fair chance of doing so, resulting in challenges to anything they may champion), then delivering the allied ones a victory on a symbolic and widely attended topic is advantageous even if the immediate effects of this victory are an unalloyed negative for you.</p>
      <p>I think the intuition underpinning the comments saying that "Trump's victory will embolden racists" is correct, and applies here as well: just as Trump's victory dented the perception that the "antiracist tribe" (which happened to also be the "anti-Trump tribe") will basically win any confrontation and so it's a waste of resources to even try to challenge them, the Brexit victories dent the perception that the "anti-Brexit tribe" (which also happens to be the "globalist, pro-environment, pro-Muslim tribe") is unassailable and therefore encourage more challenges to them on topics as disparate as policing of Pakistani gangs and whether the local coal mine or industrial plant should be shut down to save the environment (which are topics that the Labour-to-Tory voters here may in fact have a personal stake in).</p>
      <p>In this framework, Labour's putative mistake isn't Corbyn being a socialist, antisemitism or vacillation on Brexit: it's that they allowed (and even encouraged) the perception that anti-Brexit, pro-Muslim, pro-environment, pro-LGBT etc. is a bundle package, and this package is <em>the future</em> (<em>and if you oppose the future, you are right up there with people building perpetual-motion machines and antigravity devices</em>). The bluff that the package is as inevitable as laws of physics was called.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>