<post>
  <author>Ashlepius</author>
  <date>2019-12-11T20:24:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/fahy18l/</link>
  <title>Harmful Academics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The interesting question is: Supposing that that advocacy is indeed harmful and inappropriate, should it affect his job in some way or should he be fully protected by the principle of academic freedom?</p>
        <p>Because if he shouldn't be protected, then many people have the same sense as current social justice advocates, just with a different sense of what is harmful and inappropriate. People argue for deplatforming and publication bias against TERFs (for example) based on the harm their ideas cause to trans men and women. The argument is that such harms analogous to the bad effects of shouting "fire" in a crowded theater.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>There is always an unstated and nebulous causal network between 'harmful outcomes' and academic ideas. It reads most often as a post-hoc rationalisation for shoring up the slipping taboo, on entertaining the notion in question without caveats. I recognise it as a common critique for inconvenient findings from demographic studies or say sex differences in ability or affinity. You will strengthen stereotypes <a href="http://www.spsp.org/news-center/blog/stereotype-accuracy-response">even if they are accurate</a>!</p>
      <p>Next, where does the demonstrated harming of the population come into play? That itself needs to draw on theoretical senses of 'normalisation' and stigma that interact to construct a state of 'marginalisation' or increased incidences of harm...somewhere and in ambiguous ways. I've yet to see this kind of model articulated in full and tested.</p>
      <p>This is also why concepts in the domain <em>that seem to be descriptive</em> are given verb-forming suffixes such as marginal-ised vs marginal, normalise—the theories say the attributes would not exist if not for the society constructing their conditions in an insiduous manner. The harmful beliefs and norms serve as the material or perhaps the precursors and all of this complex interaction is taken <em>a priori</em>.</p>
      <p>Overall, I think the benefits of free inquiry outweigh any other 'externalities' in most social sciences and humanities. Respected universities already condone extreme perspectives including Antisemitism and glorification of revolutionary violence in Black studies, postcolonial and other such departments. If the institution was actually serious about reducing such beliefs on account of their potential factors in harmful acts, these areas would not have the unscrutinized status they enjoy. So I am left with uncharitably concluding they do not subscribe their own models, at least for all populations.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>