<post>
  <author>byvlos</author>
  <date>2019-12-11T18:23:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/fahlybg/</link>
  <title>Explaining the Citizen United Ruling</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I am going from memory because I don't want to have to dig up the specifics and because ChickenOverlord already did. This is the general gist of it, but may be incorrect on details:</p>
      <p>Citizens United was a nonprofit (?) corporation created for the purposes of creating and distributing a documentary that was critical of Hillary Clinton. This organization was not affiliated with, or in any way a part of, her competitors political campaigns.</p>
      <p>Citizens United tried to release their documentary during a US election year. Clinton's campaign sued them to try and force the documentary off of the airwaves, alleging that the publishing of the documentary violated some campaign finance laws or something</p>
      <p>Citizens United said, wait, wait, hold up, how can we violate campaign laws when we <em>aren't a campaign</em>. We are just a group of concerned citizens with a viewpoint, and the first amendment makes it very clear that the law cannot impede us in proclaiming our viewpoint that you, Mrs. Clinton, would be a terrible president.</p>
      <p>The courts sided with Citizens United. However, the particulars of how the court wrote their decision set a precedent that, in effect, allowed political campaigns to skirt around campaign finance laws as long as they did so via a corporation that was not affiliated with their campaign. </p>
      <p>Essentially the problem is that "affiliated with a campaign" is a hard grey area to define. If my organization publicly announces that it has as its mission the intention to (eg) get Alice Bobson elected as the president, but it also publicly declares that it will not follow orders from her (I just really really think she's the best candidate), am I part of her campaign? After all, I have, quite explicitly, stated that we are campaigning for her to win. Or am I <em>not</em> part of her campaign? After all, "her campaign" is a formal organization, and we are not a part of it. </p>
      <p>If we are part of her campaign, and then my ability to advocate for her to be elected president is restricted, then does that mean that individuals would also be restricted? Does that mean that anybody who puts up a lawn sign is a member of her campaign? After all, they are also advocating for her to be elected. </p>
      <p>So the distinction that the court decided on was some level of formal affiliation with the campaign. Essentially, if the campaign coordinates the actions of my nonprofit, then my nonprofit is part of the campaign and subject to those restrictions. But if the campaign does not coordinate the actions of my nonprofit, then I am unrestricted and can do what I like.</p>
      <p>The problem here is that there are still grey areas. Obviously if their campaign field organizer calls up my PR guy and says "hey we need a media blitz in Portland" then that is coordination. But what if their campaign field organizer just held a press conference and said "damn, we're lagging in Portland, we really need some help there" and then my totally independent nonprofit is like "well, we really want them to win so we should go run a blitz in Portland". Is <em>that</em> coordination? The law says "no"</p>
      <p>Or, to get more nefarious, what if their field organizer and my PR guy are friends and go golfing together. What if when they're golfing the field organizer just so happens to complain about Portland, and then the following week my nonprofit does a blitz in Portland. Was that coordination? For that matter, if they went golfing together, their guy could straight up give my PR guy orders. Nobody else was there, nobody would ever know. Good luck <em>proving</em> coordination</p>
      <p>In the original case, I think most people familiar with the details would think that the obviously right decision was made. A group of people came together to criticize someone in the government. That person they were criticizing tried to use the legal system to stop them. "The government should not be able to suppress views critical of itself" is one of the most strongly held values across the country. But once the case law was set, existing political campaigns used the ruling to structure a set of corporate organizations in such a way that they could skirt around the campaign finance laws. </p>
      <p>As it is, I don't think there is a good way to set case law here that simultaneously restricts political campaigns from doing this while protecting Citizens United's rights. And, for that matter, I think that Citizens United's rights (noting that I do not mean the rights of a corporation, I mean the rights of the individuals who formed that corporation) are more important than stopping these shady campaign things. In part because I think that money in elections is mostly good, and mostly ineffective, so I don't much care about restricting it. But mostly because, again, <em><strong>the actual object-level case of Citizens United was Hillary Clinton trying to use the power of government to suppress legitimate criticism of her leadership, and "using the power of government to suppress criticism of our leaders" is some legit straight up Nazi-tier shit</strong></em>.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>