<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2019-12-12T04:03:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/faj3hz9/</link>
  <title>Contextualizing South Korea's Political Situation</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Your analysis has a lot of links but is missing a lot of context- and is carrying enough loaded assumptions that you'd benefit from checking your foreign policy sources. To start with, 'Axis of Resistance' is a dead give away of bad starting point- that's a framing device for the middle east (specifically the Iran-centric nexus), not Asia. If you asked most people from the Philippines, Korea, Indonesia, or Vietnam what the Axis of Resistance was, they'd look at you funny if they even knew what it was at all. </p>
      <p>Iran frames itself as a resistance to the first world because it considers itself in opposition to the US, Israel, and in many respects Europe (who it views as following the US lead and sanctions, no matter how much the Europeans try to separate themselves from it. That's... not how Asian countries orient themselves at all, not least because they care very much about China and not much about Europe.</p>
      <p>/</p>
      <p>The  situation with South Korea makes a substantial amount of sense given  recent news. The Trump administration's push to have South Korea pay  more is wildly unpopular. Many South Koreans have started to see Japan,  not China or North Korea, as South Korea's greatest adversary, as a  result of the recent trade war (which Japan started as a result of South  Korean court rulings against its companies relating to WWII forced  labor). There is a widespread perception that anti-Korean racism and  Japanese WWII revisionism is a barrier to improved Korean-Japanese (and  Russian-Japanese, and Chinese-Japanese) relations. A better Korea-Russia  relationship also makes a <a href="http://www.unz.com/akarlin/russia-trolls-to-better-relations-with-korea/">great deal of sense for Russia</a>, which desires to see at least <em>one</em>  major Asian neighbor other than China that is at least somewhat  friendly to it. President Moon is also skeptical of taking orders from  Washington to the same extent as the prior administration (which went  down in a massive corruption scandal), and has pursued a new and widely  celebrated foreign policy focusing on improving ties with China and  North Korea.</p>
      <p>/</p>
      <p>Your framing on much of this context is highly selective and suspect. I could start with the 'many South Koreans' (how many? According to whom? For how long beyond the last three months? Why should a three month popularity swing corresponding to a trade dispute be taken seriously as a strategic judgement?), but I'll pick on your characterization of who 'started' a trade conflict. When one country's court system says it can seize (steal) another country's corporate property, despite multiple past 'settlements' and diplomatic agreements to resolve past issues the court case is supposedly based on, the other country has very strong grounds on which to argue that it did not, in fact, start it.</p>
      <p>Nor are you actually supporting the claim (either of it's validity or that it's a widespread perceptin) of Japanese racism. Who / how many hold this view? According to who? Why is this framing putting the onus on the Japanese- what about the question and complications caused by Korean racism (it exists, more with the Korean left than right), or Russian racism (it also exists), or Chinese racism (the country that currently has a policy of citing current and historical ethnic chinese presence as a basis for territorial claims on its neighbors)? Who's framing is this <em>and why are you presenting it uncritically as common knowledge?</em></p>
      <p>Your other framings fall into similar issues. Yes, Russia wants better ROK-Russian ties... but you aren't addressing the blatant self interest of 'wants money' or 'would like to get the US out,' while your characterization of relations with Japan (implicitly not even somewhat friendly) doesn't even identify the current nature or kinds of Russian-Japanese relations. (IE, the disputed territories, Russia playing with the prospect of returning some of the islands, the ebbs and flows of post-Soviet Russia-Japanese ties.) Casting Russia as surrounded by not-even-somewhat-friendly neighbors is a traditional Russian narrative, but aside from ignoring China as an irrelevant exception (which is an elephant in the room), and Mongolia (not an elephant, also not unfriendly), and North Korea (suspicious of but not hostile towards), and an accurate description of numbers (we're already at three), it isn't exactly warranted either by any standard short of a Russian-centric standard. Russia is not a major player in the Pacific- unlike Europe, Russia isn't big enough (as a threat or a decisive actor) to warrant strong emotions. Most asian country's attitude towards Russia is indifference and opportunism.</p>
      <p>As for your characterization of President Moon...</p>
      <p>Again- widely celebrated by who, according to whom? Rapproachment with North Korea certainly isn't a novel idea- Moon cut his political teeth during the first iteratin of the Sunshine Policy. It's popularity isn't exactly demnstrating itself in Moon's approval numbers either- ROK domestic politics for the last several years has been dominated by the economy, not North Korean/China plicy.</p>
      <p>And seriously- were you paying attention to the news two-three years ago? Who do you think Moon sold his foreign policy vision to in the very first months after the last US election? There are a lot of things you can say about Moon, but 'heroically defying the US President and going against the hardline Washington consensus' isn't one of them when the American President in question is Donald Trump, he who earned so much ire and domestic criticism for chilling out with Kim Jong Un and drawing down military exercises and hosting regular ROK envoy visits to coordinate postures on North Korea engagements.</p>
      <p>Moon could hardly have had a more supportive American president if he'd meddled in a US election himself. While there may well be areas the current ROK President wishes the American one would be more supportive on- military costs being one, some sanction reliefs another- suggesting Moon is some free canon who's broken the dastardly American leash is, well, one framing that there was a leash, and two misleading at best. Write us when the ROK is restarting the Kaesong Industrial Complex despite UN sanctions over American objections, and not watching North Korea prepare to tear down the ROK-built tourist site where family reunions get held, and then we'll talk of rogue POTROKs.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>/</p>
      <p>Char limit</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>