<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2019-12-13T05:42:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/famxd26/</link>
  <title>On Nazi Whisperers and Closed Memetic Surfaces</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>On Nazi Whisperers and closed memetic surfaces.</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Recent discussion of political YouTubers has made me more tolerant of this format, so in the last two days I've been watching videos by Natalie <a href="https://youtu.be/a3XjRO4-kGk?t=168">"the Nazi whisperer"</a> Wynn aka ContraPoints after getting <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/faal5an/">one final push</a>. They're... pretty damn neat, deservingly hyped even, to the point I've had trouble falling asleep once, arguing in my head, cleverly dismantling her rhetoric, anticipating higher-level counters, generally bantering, and wondering if anybody's already done exactly this. </p>
      <p>It turns out that this didn't work, and for frustrating reasons which led me to think in a slightly new way about the depth of polarization in Culture War, justifications of deplatforming and, also, causes for lack of diversity in this subreddit. That said, this is more venting than anything.   </p>
      <p>First stop – <a href="https://medium.com/@jesse.singal/my-full-interview-with-contrapoints-23a3c3a9c542">an interview</a> where Wynn explains her tactics:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>...to see her smiling and nodding at Richard Spencer I kind of went crazy on Twitter, saying, What are you doing? This is <em>unconscionable</em> to give him this kind of platform ... In general, I do think having a debate is good. But <em>when you have very disingenuous opponents and when they are rhetorically skilled, to show up to that debate is potentially to lose a debate to a Nazi, which is very bad, so it’s something I’m afraid of</em>.... What I tried to show in that video is when you are sincere and you care you’re sort of at a disadvantage against someone who is willing to say whatever. They can kind of make you a chump.<br />
In general, there are a few things I try to do to prepare for these sorts of debates. <em>One has to do with simply picking the right people to debate. The point of a debate is not to convince the person I’m talking to, it’s to convince people watching.</em> So before you even start the debate you want to think about whether the people watching it are persuadable.<br />
...my videos are intentionally designed to be difficult to make response videos to. There’s the self-abnegating thing where I’ve kind of already built in the critique of myself, so it’s not fun for them to go on top of it. What’s fun, to them, is a somewhat preachy and earnest person misspeaking slightly. Then the vultures swoop in.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Well, okay, second stop. "Debating the Alt-Right" is indeed a very illustrative video, but what was its lesson? To save you the time, here's <a href="https://twitter.com/ContraPoints/status/865979699788472321">the takeaway from the author</a>:  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Saul responds to Fritz by completely shutting down, by being baffled and bewildered and offended and shocked. He's frankly astonished... If Cockbane debated Fritz nothing productive would happen but at least she wouldn't be bullied. She'd interrupt, accuse, get real ugly. ... So if there's a "lesson" I guess it's that we have to work on not being Saul. Maybe that means walking out of rooms like that. <strong>Or maybe it means developing anti-Fritz rhetorical strategies. But I honestly don't yet know what those are. I can't say I've ever seen someone in debate with a Pepe-grinning fascist come out on top.</strong> But if it could be done it'd be worth doing.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>And third stop. ContraPoints viewers discuss <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ContraPoints/comments/arzhr6/debating_the_altright_video_what_should_saul_have/">precisely this topic of "anti-Fritz rhetorical strategies"</a> and here's the top comment: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The problem with debating fascists it twofold. First, they're not there to win an argument, they're there to spread the message to people receptive to fascist dogma. Second, fascists lie and dance around; they don't want to give the game away, so they'll never admit their core beliefs, and they'll use dog whistles to spread the message while maintaining deniability...<br />
.. Second, you'll never pin them down on the issues, but you can try to get them off their game... If they make a mistake point it out don't let it go. Derail the conversation and keep them on the defensive.<br />
Finally, interrupt and filibuster. Whenever they pause, interject. Talk as much as possible. The less they say, the less effective they are. Do everything you can to dominate the conversation without appearing upset. Lean towards them, sit or stand up straight. Appearing as if you're the one in charge may help.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Fourth stop: <a href="https://youtu.be/QuN6GfUix7c">«The Left»</a>. A radical activist "Tabby" says:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>You do realize, don’t you, that 99% of what Antifa does is not punching Nazis. Most of what we do is behind the scenes organizing, infiltrating fascist groups, doxing them, disrupting their recruitment...</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Above, I've called <a href="https://youtu.be/zPa1wikTd5c">that video</a> very illustrative. It's really the crux of my argument, because while watching it, I have finally felt, deep down, the impossibility of ever getting to these people. Except for Fritz (Freya?) literally being a winking Nazi to drive the point home, he (she?) is not a strawman of an Alt-Right person. He's not dodging anything, in part because there's nothing to dodge: instead of making arguments, Saul behaves like a jerk who expects everyone to defer to his infantile tantrum and is surprised when it doesn't happen. He's amply called out on this in /pol/ style running comments. <em>This could be easily seen as promoting extreme right views.</em> And yet, people in the comments. They watch the same thing I do. They applaud the accuracy of the vid. They...  </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>This is a timeless work of art. This is how genocidal ideology takes hold. It's a beautiful demonstration of how naive centrism gradually shifts to the right.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>These people who in my eyes accurately represent young, intelligent, Extremely Online leftists have reasoned themselves into a bubble of conflict theory. They are crafting guidelines for themselves to intrepret any sort of inconvenient-but-not-abhorrent opponent as a secret lying Nazi, reinforcing their conflict-theoretical affinity. They're starting with the presupposition that the opposing side is disinterested in truth, arguing in bad faith, and are writing tutorials on how to counter this with even worse bad faith tactics and subversion, not seeing the apparent hypocrisy because on step 1 they've already convinced themselves that it's morally necessary to do so, to prevent ethnic cleansing or something. They (at least, CP) are aware that even-handedly moderated debates do not go in their favor, but are conditioned to see this as even more proof of being too honest and earnest to win against the crafty evil right-wingers, and of even-handedness being naive by default. Everything that for an unbiased person could be reason to think "huh, maybe I'm just wrong and MY side is the real bad guys" was explicitly defined as further evidence of being in the right. </p>
      <p>As a symbol, Fritz doesn't represent a literal Nazi. He's a stand-in for "grinning Pepe fascist" who always wins a debate, a generic articulate right-winger; the cartoonish SS clothes and him basically admitting Holocaust denial (the one smart move by Saul) are nothing more than a crutch for the viewer's ideology. Had he replied "no, I do not deny Holocaust, nor do I justify it, now back to the point", how much would be left of Saul's moral high ground? The entire goal of ContraPoints project is, in my opinion, to condition people <em>to not ask such questions</em>; to saturate their cognitive capacity with clever epicycles around unquestionable tribal loyalty. And it's progressed swimmingly. </p>
      <p>And these are only a handful of mind-killing tactics. The situation reminds me very much of one passage in Greg Egan's excellent book <em>Diaspora</em>: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Yatima tried to read vis face, but Inoshiro just gazed back with a psychoblast’s innocence. "What’s happened to you? What have you done to yourself?"<br />
Inoshiro smiled beatifically and held out vis hands. A white lotus flower blossomed from the center of each palm, both emitting identical reference tags. Yatima hesitated, then followed their scent.<br />
It was an old outlook, buried in the Ashton-Laval library, copied nine centuries before from one of the ancient memetic replicators that had infested the fleshers. It imposed a hermetically sealed package of beliefs about the nature of the self, and the futility of striving… <strong>including explicit renunciations of every mode of reasoning able to illuminate the core beliefs' failings.</strong>
Analysis with a standard tool confirmed that the outlook was universally self-affirming. Once you ran it, you could not change your mind. Once you ran it, you could not be talked out of it.  </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I've come to call such belief systems "closed memetic surfaces". It's fascinating to see one emerge in real time, and a little scary.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>