<post>
  <author>JustAWellwisher</author>
  <date>2019-12-14T12:41:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/fasguz2/</link>
  <title>Spoilerific Analysis of Full Metal Alchemist</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>The bad guy is basically willing to go all out on science to learn "everything".</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <span class="md-spoiler-text">I think we can go one better than that - the homunculus in the flask is a soulless being that, through science (as well as purging from their own body seven manifestations of sin), seeks to devour and become "God".</span>
      </p>
      <p>
        <span class="md-spoiler-text">If your definition of scientism is a faith system that seeks to replace worshiping "God" with worshiping "Science" then yeah, FMA is a repudiation of scientism, but this is only one facet of the story, if we're exploring only the ultimate antagonist of the series.</span>
      </p>
      <p>
        <span class="md-spoiler-text">I think that opposition to God and opposition to a soulless being trying to become God is secondary to FMA's extremely deep dive into putting forward a conceptualization of transhumanism through its protagonist Ed.</span>
      </p>
      <p>
        <span class="md-spoiler-text">Questions about "what does it mean to be human" are at the core of a lot of the arcs, a lot of the various characters. What does it mean to have a human soul? What are the limits of the human soul? What makes us different from a "Homunculus trapped in a flask"... I think even more important than the defeat of the antagonist was the subsequent rescue of Alphonse's (the main character's brother) human body and the sacrifice that Ed made in order to do it which was to give up his "Gate of Truth", his pathway to God. Then in the epilogue he's shown to be travelling East to learn a naturalistic philosophy of this universe's science-magic, one that is not related to the idea of pursuing ultimate truth or obtaining Godhood.</span>
      </p>
      <p>
        <span class="md-spoiler-text">I also like the reversal that FMA does with "Pride" as a concept, because it would be easy to boil down the Homunculus' failures to a sin of pride. Oh he went wrong because he thought he could become a God, he committed the sin of pride! Well, no. Pride is the only homunculus to survive the manga - as a homunculus he exists as a shadow in a container and more than all the others his true self takes on the form of his father. Even though Ed destroys his container, he chooses to save Pride's true form and eventually Pride grows to become like a human after the end of the series. One of the big aspects of FMA's message is that by denying himself his sins, the homunculus became even less human and all the 'sins' have their own humanist arcs. Pride in being human and having pride in humanity seems to be one of those things that the author considers to be intrinsic to maintaining an ethos of transhumanism and to prevent it from succumbing to the failure state that is a transhumanistic lifeform that sees "mere humans" as lesser beings. This isn't outright stated so much as shown through symbolism, especially family symbolism - fathers and brothers. Pride might have became human because of the love he came to have for his adopted family, his human mother. It's a subversive take on what is usually the "fall of man".</span>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>