<post>
  <author>Rustndusty2</author>
  <date>2019-12-14T15:12:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/eabgr3/even_space_marines_need_artillery_support_why_i/fataqep/</link>
  <title>In Defense of (OG) Star Wars</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I agree with most of what you've said about 40k here, and a lot of what you've said about Star Wars. I quite like 40k (the universe at least, I don't really care for the gameplay.) However, as a Star Wars fan I think it needs a defense. </p>
      <p>Star Wars - meaning the original three movies - is not really a war story, nor is it a universe. Star Wars is a classic Hero's Journey, Coming-of-Age tale, done with a space opera backdrop. And most importantly, the Jedi as portrayed in the original series are not soldiers, not warriors. And while there's good stuff in the Expanded Universe around these core three movies, almost any other time that stuff focuses on Jedi (or even Sith) it undermines this idea. </p>
      <p>The lightsaber is an interesting choice of weapon - it's a melee weapon used in a universe dominated by ranged weapons, one of the things 40k and Star Wars has in common. But the lightsaber is probably most famous for it's defensive use - Luke's first lesson is using his father's lightsaber to ward off blaster fire. And though he has the lightsaber, he continues to use his blaster through all three movies, because it truly is a better offensive choice. Carrying only a lightsaber, as apparently was the custom, restricts the options of a Jedi. The purpose of it was for a Jedi to defend himself or others while acting as a monk/diplomat, not as an extension of his will in battle to slaughter enemies. In other movies, and other media, the Jedi unleash the Force upon their enemies, but this as Yoda explained is a technique of the dark side.</p>
      <p>Obi-Wan in his original incarnation kills only a single time - removing a man's arm just before he shoots Luke. The Tusken Raiders are dealt with through a trick, as are the Empire's forces in Mos Eisley. When on the Death Star, he avoids the Stormtroopers and attempts to achieve his goal without ever using violence. This he does for two reasons - first is the ethos of the Jedi, to act with grace and avoid conflict. The second is that at this point we're given no reason to think he <em>could</em> slaughter his way through the station. The capability we've seen displayed so far is blocking a single blaster firing from the front, nothing like the ability of Jedi in other media to effortlessly defend from a surrounding army.</p>
      <p>Luke in the last movie does not do much at all to contribute to the destruction of the Second Death Star and the fall of the Empire. He kills a few Stormtroopers on the forest moon of Endor, but then abandons the Rebel's effort to go confront his father and the Emperor. His actions at the climax of the movie are pointless to the overall war effort - Darth Vader and Palpatine both die, yes, but they would have died anyway from the Empire's arrogance. The battle is won by the Princess and the Rebel forces allying with the Ewoks on the ground, and the valiant sacrifice of the Rebel fleet in space - holding their position against incredible odds, with faith that their comrades will come through. Yes, the final blows are struck by named characters, but fairly minor ones - most casual movie watchers likely won't remember Wedge Antilles. Luke's story is entirely one of personal growth and a search for family.</p>
      <p>Finally I have to address the prequels. Lamentably they are considered canon along with the original series. though I'd say they lose the soul of the story. Yes, Jedi are soldiers and generals, tearing their way through droid armies. Yes, Yoda begins flipping around slicing people apart. But this is not the Jedi as they should be, and that's something that the movies actually do acknowledge. The order has become entangled with politics and war, and this is why they are destroyed. Furthermore, even when they are fighting they do so with an army behind and beside them, and infamously are slaughtered en-masse when attacked from behind.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>A short note about fascism, or really specifically Nazi Germany and the Empire. The Empire had excellent aesthetics, with armies of white-armored stormtroopers and fleets of imposing star destroyers. Many people have expressed an appreciation for the aesthetics of the Wehrmacht as well - the crisp uniforms, the Stuka's howl, the massive, terrifying tanks. Similarly, both had an appreciation for superweapons. But this belies the fact that both of them <em>lost</em>. The Empire's finest legion was taken apart by teddy bears with sticks and a few militia members. While the Nazis weren't so embarrassingly destroyed, their infamous discipline and engineering (leaving aside how true either of those things were) failed. For a more direct parallel, Star Destroyers fared about as well against small fighters as Battleships did against bombers, including the famous Bismarck.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>