<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2019-12-14T23:30:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/faw5hwq/</link>
  <title>Criticisms of Bernie Sanders and His Movement</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Per the recent Motte election polling, I know there are quite a few Sanders supporters around here. As such, this is as good a place as any to test my current thoughts on him. I've become increasingly convinced that I should actively speak out against him should he show signs of getting close to the nomination, and cast a protest vote if the general somehow comes down to Sanders vs. Trump. This endorsement (and weak rescindment) more or less sealed that decision. I'd like to present my case against him and see where, if anywhere, it falls. This is aimed mostly towards people who do not consider themselves socialists, as much of the below is seen as a positive by self-described socialists.</p>
      <p>Uygur seems outright awful to me. Not listed in your post is that he denied the Armenian genocide until very recently, and of course still runs a show named after perpetrators of it. As a poster points out below, this should be every bit as unacceptable as naming a show after the Hitler youth. He's said things like "the genes of women are flawed" and joked about legalizing bestiality on his show. He's continued making disparaging remarks about women long after becoming a progressive. Just as pertinently for me, his show tends to be just as partisan and divisive as any far-right space. Much of what causes me to reject Trump seems expressed in Uygur as well. Sanders endorsing him reads to me very much as the same sort of spoils-system, everyone-on-my-team-is-good approach to politics that Trump has. </p>
      <p>This is mirrored by Sanders' previous comments about every socialist group. As late as 1989, he <a href="https://www.washingtonexaminer.com/news/bernie-sanders-praised-communist-cuba-and-the-soviet-union-in-the-1980s">spoke highly of Cuba and the USSR</a>. He stood with  communists in <a href="http://nymag.com/intelligencer/2019/05/bernie-sanders-pro-sandinista-past-problem.html">Nicaragua</a> and praised <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/bernie-sanders-only-presidential-candidate-call-bolivia-presidents-ouster-coup-1472847">Evo Morales</a> as he sought an unconstitutional third term in Bolivia. All this is old news, but it indicates the same sort of hard-line "every socialist is good" approach that makes me wary with his support for Uygur. I see no evidence that he has properly wrestled with the harms caused by those aligned with his movement.</p>
      <p>His supporters, in large part, seem to be surrounding themselves with a similar sort of media bubble as they accuse Republicans of doing. Left-leaning publications like Jacobin and Common Dreams are unreservedly behind him and against all others, as are media groups like The Young Turks. On much of reddit and twitter you see the same amplification of him and rejection of all other candidates. Online, many of them tend to openly insult every other candidate, including embracing derogatory nicknames (most recently <a href="https://twitter.com/jacobflowers/status/1205108624886059008">Mayo Pete</a> and Wall Street Pete) and promoting stray rumors as fact (Did Pete cause a <a href="https://twitter.com/jeffhauser/status/1204543875651657733">Canadian bread price fixing scandal</a>?? Let's find out!). This has escalated to the point of cheering as supporters <a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/pharms4pete/status/1204968324716728320">dox hosts of fundraisers</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/jwestin2/status/1204940401410490368">break into private residences</a>. That would be less alarming if Sanders distanced himself from this sort of behavior, but he's <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2019/03/sanders-promised-civility-hired-twitter-attack-dog/585259/">hired some of the loudest attackers, like David Sirota, to key places within his campaign</a>, and has not done anything to calm or discourage his supporters from this sort of approach. </p>
      <p>Arguably more importantly, he's 78 years old and has spent hardly any time with true skin in the game, in any position. Before being elected mayor of Burlington at 40, as this string of tweets points out, <a href="https://twitter.com/m_mendozaferrer/status/1204813774953308166">he didn't do much of anything</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/m_mendozaferrer/status/1093295853907922946">never getting a steady job and running vanity campaigns even when his son had to go on welfare</a>. Per his reporting, <a href="https://imgur.com/gallery/mmS40Gq#460q6bS">his first vote was for himself</a>. Since entering Congress in 1991, <a href="https://www.govtrack.us/congress/members/bernard_sanders/400357">he's sponsored only seven bills that passed</a>, four if you remove the ones that were just naming things. He's never tested his ideas from a position of power in real-world conditions, and has as a result had the freedom to theorize without worrying much about tradeoffs, compromise, or unintended consequences. </p>
      <p>I may cover policy decisions later and why I disagree with many of his, but those are well-trodden ground. Painting in broad strokes, I tend more globalist while he tends more nationalist. I worry that if he got any real power he would use it to run the economy into the ground. I disagree with him on a wide range of social issues. There are interesting conversations to be had around those, but my point with all of this is that I don't trust him enough to even get to those policy conversations. </p>
      <p>His movement echoes much of the harm in Trumpism: creating an echo chamber that spreads across a section of alternate media, relentlessly attacking all who disagree, and staunchly supporting all who align ideologically independent of warning signs. Many of their goals are closer than Trump's to mine, including health care reform, addressing climate change, and ensuring a strong social safety net, but that doesn't excuse the creation of a toxic movement determined to tear down anyone who disagrees. I have always opposed Trump and will always do so, but he's a known quantity at this point and in getting elected has already done the bulk of his damage. While Sanders is likely to face an uncooperative Congress, he still has a chance of doing a whole new sort of harm and legitimizing the second-most troubling political movement in the US today. His age alone makes him near-unelectable for me. I find him to be, simply put, the most alarming US politician other than Trump in my lifetime.</p>
      <p>In saying all this, though, I notice I'm in a tiny minority of politically involved people. He's got something like <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/national/release-detail?ReleaseID=3651">76/15 favorability splits among Democrats</a>, and an 89/6 split among Democrats and leaners my age. He's one of the most popular politicians among my friends, online circles I travel in, and youth in general. Many people I respect have thrown their support behind him. What am I, or they, missing?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>