<post>
  <author>yellerto56</author>
  <date>2019-12-16T18:50:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fb573ne/</link>
  <title>Egalitarianism in Starship Troopers</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>On Starship Troopers and the Dream of a Racial and Gender Utopia:</p>
      <p>I've been pondering a way to make this post for awhile. People elsewhere have touched on these ideas while focusing on other aspects of the book or film, but I thought I'd write about one aspect of both that seems increasingly far in the past ever since the modern incarnation of the Culture War came into being.</p>
      <p>For those unacquainted with it, Starship Troopers is a 1959 military science fiction novel by Robert A. Heinlein. The book examines life in the military of a future interplanetary society called the Terran Federation from the perspective of a young enlistee named Juan Rico. </p>
      <p>The most well-known and/or controversial aspect of this society is its limiting "citizenship" (the right to vote and hold political office) to those who have completed a term of military (or in some cases civil) service. The book takes great pains to explain that service is open to all and completely voluntary: even the most disabled person will not be refused and will be assigned a task for which they have the capacity, and servicemen may resign from their position at any time, even right before battle (at the price of being barred from citizenship for life). Much has been written on the merits/demerits of this form of political organization elsewhere. </p>
      <p>What I want to focus on is one of the book's less discussed features. Like many utopian science fiction properties in the latter half of the 20th century (here's looking at you, Star Trek), Starship Troopers envisions a world where in the process of expanding to other planets, humanity has shed its old divisions of race, class, and nation in favor of becoming one species united. Several recruits to the military are noted to be of (1950's American) minority ethnic backgrounds, like Breckinridge (black), Shujumi (Japanese), and Rico himself (Filipino). While these characters are noted to retain some of their family history and customs (i.e. there is no form of cultural assimilation that involves completely losing touch with one's ethnic background) nowhere is it stated that they are subject to any exclusion, discrimination, or differing treatment based on their race. When Rico (the narrator) is subject to any criticism or discipline, it is always based on his actions and performance alone.</p>
      <p>Women are also explicitly stated to comprise a large and important part of the Terran military. While sex segregation is still strictly observed (contact between deployed men and women is limited to supervised occasions like formal dinners, and it's implied that roles like starship pilot are strictly female while others like mobile infantryman (Rico's position) are strictly male) women in the military are valued for their performance to the same degree as men. If any harassment or sexism is targeted towards servicewomen in Starship Troopers, it's not at all implied by the text. The incorporation of women into the military is explicitly stated to improve overall combat effectiveness.</p>
      <p>Which brings me to Paul Verhoeven's (in)famous 1997 film adaptation. The Dutch director refused to even finish the book, declaiming its militarism as fascist propaganda. The Terran Federation of the film is made out to be a crude caricature of the novel's Federation, treating its soldiers as cannon fodder in a war against the fierce race of "Bugs". Many of the most compelling arguments in favor of the novel's proposed system of political organization are omitted or changed to be less persuasive.</p>
      <p>In addition, the film whitewashes its main character into "Johnny Rico", a young man of presumably European descent (played by Dutch actor Casper van Dien) living in an Argentina that looks markedly more white and monoethnic than its real life counterpart. Argentina was deliberately chosen by the director for its Nazi ties and is implied to have undergone ethnic cleansing at some point prior to the film.</p>
      <p>And yet despite all this effort to paint the Federation as the film's fascist true villains, the sense of racial and gender utopianism in the movie's depiction of the military is even greater than in the book's. In this incarnation of the Mobile Infantry, not only do men and women of all races cooperate on equal footing both in training and combat, they even share barracks, locker rooms, and (notoriously) showers completely without incident. </p>
      <p>Women and minorities are entrusted with authority at all levels of the film's chain of command. Following a disastrous operation costing the lives of several infantry members, Terran military commander Sky Marshal Dienes resigns accepting full responsibility and is immediately replaced by Sky Marshal Tehat Meru, a black woman, whose reenvisioned plans of operation against the Bugs are followed without hesitation and without doubt as to her authority.</p>
      <p>The 1997 film in this way strikes me as being a product of its time. During the 90's in particular it seemed that the prevailing optimism was that drawing distinctions based on race and gender was completely arbitrary, that racism and sexism were products of ignorance and were impediments that anyone could overcome, and that a promised future lay in sight where all divisions based on identity would be made obsolete. The images that most embody this belief to me are the decorative murals I often saw in school as a child, featuring multicultural groups of children from all over the world holding hands and smiling as they looked toward a better future.</p>
      <p>At some point in the last decade, this dream seems to have fallen apart. To 21st century progressivism, racism and sexism stopped being mere obstacles to individual enlightenment and became all-encompassing intractable societal forces. The progressive ideal of organizational equity stopped being about mere colorblindness and started to stress the importance of applying an actively antiracist, feminist lens to organizational decision making. By correlation or by causation, relations between the races and between men and women seem to have increased in overt hostility significantly over the last couple of decades.</p>
      <p>What happened to this ideal of racial and gender utopianism? It seems to me like the rise of social media and clickbait journalism have coincided with a renewed hyperfocus on race, gender, and other identities in the media. With the third decade of the 21st century fast approaching, it feels like a future where race and gender divisions are rendered unimportant and racism and sexism are left in the past is more remote than ever. </p>
      <p>What factors do you all think led to the rise of envisioning this sort of harmonious future in past decades, and why does no one seem to have it mind as a goal anymore? What trends in sci-fi utopianism seem to have replaced this old envisioning? (To my knowledge, complete transhumanism and self-sorting based on chosen memeplexes seem to be two.) What other factors do you think drive current culture's hyperfocus on race and gender, and what possible future developments do you think might change this state of affairs?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>