<Post>
  <author>paanther</author>
  <date>2019-11-25T14:41:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e1b9t4/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_25/f8oz4hy/</link>
  <title>How One's Ideology Shapes Their Normal</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Your opinion of what normal people believe is kinda hard to decouple from your own ideology and what you believe.</p>
      <p>When my dad sends me random stories about what the Left is doing wrong and how this guarantees to a random Joe Sixpack that the Left is evil and therefore Trump’s gonna win again... well, absent any justification for that, I have to tell him that he can’t just put his own views in “normal people”’s mouths and demand I take his word for it.</p>
      <p>Anyone can manufacture a public - can just <em>say</em> what (they believe) normal people will think. If you hate the Left, you’re predisposed to want to manufacture a public that makes this troll op successful, and believe it uncritically without evidence, because you want to own the libs. You <em>want</em> to hear that it’s successful, that lefty people are stupid, to pat yourself on the back for your “tolerance” in opposition to them.</p>
      <p>The reason I react so strongly to it... well, there are a lot of reasons, but the main one is that when someone clearly wants to see white nationalists own the SJWs, it really feels to me like they have picked a side, and god damn is it the wrong one. The enemy of your enemy is not automatically your friend; just because they don’t like the SJWs doesn’t mean you have to seriously consider their opinions on white genocide.</p>
      <p>Maybe you’re laughing here because you’re so clearly not sympathetic to white nationalists, and you think the fact that I don’t automatically assume that should destroy my credibility. But <strong>I do not know that</strong>, and I don’t think I should just assume it. On this board/thread, like one in four responses to my comments are pretty goddamn Cursed. So to act as if it’s completely off the table, and all of us here are just neutral liberal observers, and these neutral observers just happen to virulently disagree with the Left, want to laugh at them and say they’re being manipulated, and enjoy painting WNs in a good light... laughing at their jokes... I can’t have it. Someone doing this doesn’t get to claim to be a neutral observer making neutral sociological points about what “normal people” think. You’re in this too; you have a viewpoint.</p>
      <p>I mean, the way to square this circle is to say that a large minority of this board has a troubling sympathy to very-far-right views, but a lot of people seem not to want to admit that.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</Post>