<post>
  <author>bsbbtnh</author>
  <date>2020-05-26T15:26:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/frvmzk6/</link>
  <title>The Illusions in Environmental Policy</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>We're all ready to jump headfirst into climate change policies, and yet, IMO, many policies are more about signaling we're doing something, rather than an actual solution.</p>
      <p>For instance, solar and wind. I don't believe they are realistic solutions. The amount of resources required to build them (which have to be mined) and the fact you'll eventually have to replace them. They aren't a large scale solution. Nuclear is, but almost nobody pushes it. Not even the people on the right, as a compromise. At best nuclear is used to 'test' people on the left about whether they are serious or not, but never pushed by the right to be implemented (though there are many on both sides who support it, but that doesn't seem to get reflected by the politicians).</p>
      <p>Another thing is plastic. In the late 80s and early 90s, we began this huge shift away from styrofoam. Styrofoam is an amazing material, because it is lightweight, uses little resources or energy in production, and is <em>insanely</em> recyclable. The major issue is that it wasn't 'worth' recycling, because it was so lightweight. It wasn't efficient to transport it. With many blue bin programs, that's less true today.</p>
      <p>We moved to plastic. Lightweight (not as lightweight as styrofoam), uses little resources (not as little as styrofoam), and is mostly recyclable. The issue is there are so many different types of plastic that it can be an issue when recycling. And it isn't biodegradable. But, the amount of plastic litter from the west is almost nil. We have a very efficient plastic recycling scheme. It could be better, of course. But overall it is pretty decent. And even plastic disposed in landfills is out of the environment. </p>
      <p>So now there's this push towards paper. Paper bags, paper straws, paper takeout containers. One issue is that paper is heavy, so it uses far more energy to transport. It uses far more resources to make. Producing paper causes more water and air pollution than plastic, and that's all upfront. But that pollution is 'out of sight'. And they aren't really functional. We got rid of paper bags because they sucked. Paper straws are horrible inventions. And most paper takeout containers usually end up with a wax coating that can make them more difficult to recycle.</p>
      <p>With forest management, our policies are outdated. Controlled burns are limited due to air pollution measures. Controlled burns prevent massive fires, which don't abide by our laws. It's stupid, but nobody addresses it. We fight every forest fire. Our forests are so dense, and haven't burned for so long, that fires end up being incredibly intense and destructive. We let our forests overgrow during the 20th century, falsely believing forests are carbon sinks, and now those forests are burning uncontrollably each year, and have now become net carbon emitters. </p>
      <p>Yet environmentalists fight against logging, which could be our greatest tool in climate change. They just want to plant more and more trees, and fight every fire. Trump's mention of 'raking' the forest floor really isn't that crazy. All that stuff on the forest floor builds year after year. We have forests with 100 years of dead trees, leaves, branches, etc, built up, which was supposed to burn away every few years. What do we do? </p>
      <p>Forests are so dense now. Go look at early pictures of America, and forests weren't dense. Fires kept forests relatively sparse and the forest floor clear. </p>
      <p>And yet there's no movement pushing proper forest management. </p>
      <p>Nearly every environmental cure proposed by activists and/or politicians aren't actual solutions. There are people who push for the 'right' things, but they are largely drowned out by the easy 'signalling'.</p>
      <p>For forests, we could begin essentially clear cutting forests. Burn what is left and replant. Use that wood for building. Wood becomes cheap as hell, and <em>solving climate change becomes a profitable endeavor</em>. The harvested wood sequesters carbon, while the new forests begin sequestering more CO2. Instead of what we're seeing right now, which is forests burning and releasing massive amounts of CO2. And if we begin managing forests properly, the majority of that carbon will never be sequestered in forests again.</p>
      <p>Another thing would be standardized, reusable containers for nearly every food item in the store. Similar to cans being relatively standardized and having a well developed recycling scheme. Why can't we do this with most other products? Put cookies in tins. Or plastic containers which can be washed and reused. Put a deposit on them. Do this for every item in the store, where reasonable. It doesn't make sense to have multiple layers of plastic on everything, and most of it being recyclable at best. RRR = Reduce, Reuse, Recycle, in that order. We should reduce excess packaging, but also focus on reusable packaging.</p>
      <p>Same with take out containers. They are already standardized containers. Let's make them thicker and reusable, and have city wide recycling schemes for them. You put it in your blue bin, the city collects and washes them, then distributes them back to restaurants. </p>
      <p>I don't believe we are at a point where we can actually tackle climate change, because the people in charge, and many of the activists, are pushing policies that aren't realistic or don't have much of an impact. The fact that the people who <em>say</em> they care most about the issue happen to be the same people pushing things that won't solve that issue, it makes me wonder if it is actually that serious of a problem. Or they are using an issue to achieve political goals (like politicians and activists do with every issue). At best, they aren't in a position to deal with it. Inaction is preferable to the wrong actions (see forest management).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>