<post>
  <author>Faceh</author>
  <date>2020-05-26T16:42:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/frvwbwu/</link>
  <title>Should You Cause a Political War to Win a War Game?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I have the dual problems of having mostly checked out of caring about any political activity above the state level except on a handful of issues that I still kinda worry about, and having a political knowledge 'power level' that is like an order of magnitude higher than I ever let slip anywhere other than reddit.</p>
      <p>So this means that I both get annoyed when people start to get fussy about political issues that they, personally, have almost zero chance of influencing, and I have the desire to basically nuke them with a 'truth-bomb' (I use the term a bit ironically) challenging all of the assumptions they're basing their opinion on and essentially showing how their conclusions are completely incorrect and they are better off not speaking up on that matter again until they get better information. That is, I'd much rather NOT talk about this stuff at all because it is pointless to spend time on it when we could do productive things, but if we're going to discuss it I am inclined to just go all out and make it clear that they're out of their depth so as to hopefully shut them up entirely. </p>
      <p>But in the interest of keeping the peace and my sanity I generally take a conciliatory approach. Especially because I know the 'truth bomb' tactic <em>never works</em> and will only lead them to push back harder.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Now this is interesting because I have joined up with a group of acquaintances who formed a gaming group that meets via discord due to Quarantine. Its a mix of personalities, but we have one guy who is the stereotypical MAGA Republican who uses the term 'liberal' as an epithet, shows off his gun collection constantly, will intentionally do offensive things to 'trigger' people, and you can't quite tell how much of it is in jest vs. serious. I'll give him credit for being more informed than average (i.e. he's not just repeating lines Trump feeds him, he knows the facts behind them) and being smart enough to know where the line is and to not go shooting over it far enough to actually piss anyone off.</p>
      <p>And then there's one guy who is pretty much a moderate liberal Democrat who despises Trump as a person and supports the general policy agenda of Elizabeth Warren, but also doesn't like Bernie Sanders and is pro-business insofar as his family owns a smallish local business that he works for.</p>
      <p>These two have managed to keep it civil (attribute mostly to Democrat guy being very conflict-averse even though he's an overall confident, competent person) for months so that the group has not had any explosions.</p>
      <p>However, our group has just started up a team-based game of <em>Civilization VI.</em></p>
      <p>The teams were randomly assigned.</p>
      <p>Dem guy and MAGA guy are now partners in this game.</p>
      <p>Those two are either going to synergize into a terrifying force to be reckoned with, or they're going to tear each other's throats out before we hit the halfway mark. To make things even better. MAGA guy is playing as America (of course) whilst Dem guy is playing as the <em>Arabian</em> Civilization (led by Saladin) which historically has had a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbary_Wars">rocky relationship</a> with the U.S. but perhaps more interesting for our game will likely end up adopting Islam as their in-game religion (which will look very little like actual Islam, mind). And which may require, then, America to adopt it as well. Do the math on that. Either MAGA guy refuses categorically or enthusiastically leans into it with the worst caricature of Muslims imaginable, right? So I guess.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>I am not making an ounce of this up.</strong>
      </p>
      <p>So now my question becomes: should I attempt to inflame the passions of both these men so as to try and lead to a degradation in teamwork to gain my own team a relative advantage?</p>
      <p>I'm inclined to not do so because I don't want to torpedo the group, but being honest I don't care too much about any individual members of the group and so it would be little skin off my nose if they fractured.</p>
      <p>How much meta-gaming is appropriate when it comes to exploiting culture war conflicts to win video games?</p>
      <hr />
      <p>More seriously, I think the world is in sore need of more spaces where politics are either verboten to discuss in depth, with social norms discouraging it, and places where civil discussion is mandated (like here) and actual rules with penalties are in place to encourage it.</p>
      <p>We have plenty of places where one side or the other gets to trumpet their message unimpeded, we have places like Twitter where both sides can scream at each other at the top of their lungs, but I think we've degraded the 'neutral ground' (for some parties, this was intentional policy) to the point where you can't even have a family get together for dinner without it erupting into a political war. The issue isn't one of free speech so much as it is of very poor norms of discourse that are, I think, intentionally kept this way by motivated actors.</p>
      <p>There has to be some symbolic 'cease fire' agreement that allows people spaces outside the stress of politics and where you don't have to wave your team's flag but instead focus on more meaningful, important relationships and work on preserving them.</p>
      <p>Or, perhaps, we need a place like <a href="/r/politicalcompassmemes">/r/politicalcompassmemes</a> (until that place inevitably gets compromised somehow) where everyone comes together with the knowledge that nothing they say there matters and everyone will get to dunk on each other so check your feelings at the door so you can get in on the fun.</p>
      <p>None of this will solve the problem that there is still a 'gun in the room' (namely, whoever wins control of government can force their ideals on the others) but at least that creates the space to start discussing ways to disarm the gun, or amicably separate, or mend the peace.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>