<post>
  <author>Gossage_Vardebedian</author>
  <date>2020-05-26T15:50:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/frvpttr/</link>
  <title>The Worrying Rise in Armchair Pundits</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I have been finding myself over the last few months becoming much less able to put up with people casually voicing their political views. We have a circle of friends, four or five couples, who we’ve been getting together with for a decade or two, depending on the couple. Now, regarding many of these people, I really have no idea what their political views are in general, and certainly not in particular, or even if they have any. <em>And I like it this way.</em> I have had friends who are politics and/or political philosophy junkies and I have enjoyed talking about those things with them – of course I have, I’m on here, aren’t I? But lately I have been noticing one couple who is pretty left-wing and extremely anti-Trump interjecting an occasional comment, and every time they do I want to say something. The thing is, it’s really quite rare, and yet I feel like in a way I'll have to steel myself to <em>not</em> respond. Then just a couple days ago we had a Zoom happy hour, as you do, and a couple people started discussing what we should have done re Covid-19, and one guy, who is a very good and smart guy and a good friend, but a bit of a prepper, went off on some screed for a couple minutes, and I wanted to just walk away; exit, stage left. I didn’t say anything, but I realized that what bothered me isn’t that he was wrong (he was, mostly - lots of <em>deeply</em> post hoc reasoning) but that he was so ill-informed. He thought he had all this well-curated information but basically, he’d been at home watching CNN a lot and just went from there. And I realized that what annoys me about my other friends and their anti-Trump shots isn’t that they’re wrong (in my opinion, they certainly aren’t wrong all the time – God I hate having to defend Trump). It is that they are just tossing off whatever they want to believe, or whatever received opinions they were fed by the media. Now my prepper-ish friend is coming over in a few days, and IF he and I talk about the pandemic, I’m almost entirely sure he will immediately back off some of his points upon being challenged, because he’s a smart, reasonable guy, and all he has heard up to now is that everything would have been just fine except Trump.</p>
      <p>Allow me another example. The one time I did kind of challenge one of my Trump-hating friends – I can’t remember what it was about – she just kind of looked at me with this shocked expression, and immediately said that well, she was sorry and didn’t want to talk about politics. As if the very idea that one might have some actual reasoned opinions, or even a full discussion, rather than just doing an occasional drive-by here and there, is shocking. She knows that her opinions aren’t well thought out, and she knows that she’s not prepared to discuss topic X in depth, but she still feels compelled to toss out an opinion here and there. It’s not important to her, but she finds herself doing it. </p>
      <p>And a third. My brother, who has wasted huge opportunities in his life and is now broke and divorced, and kind of hates himself, has started matter-of-factly dropping anti-Trump and anti-Republican barbs into conversation. For 50+ years he never mentioned politics, and now he does nearly every time I see him. Does he really want to discuss the economy or the Covid-19 response? No, he doesn’t. He really doesn’t.</p>
      <p>This is extremely troublesome to me. I don‘t care if you aren’t interested in politics. That’s a reasonable stance to take. I’m happy if you do care and disagree with me – and a hearty thank you to all of you here who don’t agree with my takes. What is to me a very bad and ominous thing is when people seem to care a lot but don’t have any idea what they are talking about. My father, who was a very smart guy, was nevertheless pretty completely uninterested in politics and political philosophy. Consequently, he unthinkingly voted Democrat until he got married and had kids, then voted Republican for a few decades, and toward the end of his life when my folks lived on social security and spent most of their money on health care, magically became a liberal Democrat again. That’s fine. You know what else he did? He <em>never</em> talked about politics to me or anyone else.</p>
      <p>Because of social media and the relentless, highly polarized, performative screaming on the internet and on TV, it seems that people are being taught to “care” about politics, even when they really don’t. People used to not talk about politics, but it wasn’t a difficult thing, because people just voted their wallets, or voted Dem or Repub because that’s what their parents did, or they were union or they weren’t, or whatever. Now it’s something you’re supposed to want to talk about, even if you really don’t. It’s supposed to be part of your identity, even if it isn’t. And so people feel something - fear of Covid-19, or the state of their finances, or whatever else - and then translate that into a <em>political</em> feeling, often without realizing that this is something new for them. I feel confident that the scale at which this is happening is a new thing, and that this is bad.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>