<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-05-25T20:58:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/frszb0u/</link>
  <title>The Cowardice of Life Imprisonment and Sex Offender Registries</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The Sex Offender Registry always struck me as an exercise in conflation as well as moral and intellectual cowardice.</p>
      <p>A commentator I follow once complained about people who loudly proclaim that “teachers aren’t paid enough” his response is always: “ok how much do you think they should be paid? What is the dollar amount? You can’t just write “more” on a cheque”</p>
      <p>Obviously it was incredibly rare for any of them to give an actual value. And I always found the thought experiment of making them all actually write down the value a reveal it to eachother incredible amusing. They’ll all say “More” because thats the correct socially desirable answer, but i suspect if you actually made 20 parents demanding “more” write down the value and reveal it to eachother, it’d escalate to screaming pretty quickly... Hell I’d expect 20-40% of those demanding “More” to write down a dollar amount less than the average teachers actual compensation, I can imagine a dad saying “well  thats just under what a welder makes and weldings hard work... they should make a fair bit but not as much as a welder” followed by the hippy mom (whose a teacher herself’ revealing she wrote down over 200k “well thats what a professor makes and small children are harder than young adults”.</p>
      <p>The truth is the consensus is really a polite fiction between those who just want to say “ya that seems important whatever” and those who would ultimately like teachers to be a higher category of person (see how they view teachers legitimacy to raise children vs. Parents).</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Societies attitude towards sex offender and their  restriction are similar. The restrictions should be “stricter”. But a significant portion of those demanding stricter if asked to write down the restrictions they wanted, would write down few restrictions than exist. They’re merely signalling “ya dat ders a bad thing he done”, whereas another large proportion say ”Stricter” because they really think “they should have been executed painfully or had their balls chopped off” and adding restrictions so onerous pointless and cruel that the offender, finally released after 20 years, might yet commit suicide falls under the category of feature not bug.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Tangentially  I think the slow disappearance of the death penalty has probably been one of the worst developments for humane criminal justice. If the maximum penalty you could give someone was say 10 years and after that the only option was the death penalty... well I’d expect a lot of people to get  countless decades of their lives back. </p>
      <p>For Example:  Ross Ulbrict was never convicted of a violent crime, he received a double life sentence + 40 years for running a website.</p>
      <p>Thats a death penalty, its just the method of execution is randomized between Suicide, fellow inmates, and Senescence. They still took away every day of his life he had left.</p>
      <p>Now instead imagine the judge’s only options were 10 years or the gallows. Would she have felt as confident citing Uncharged accusations and his libertarian politics to justify the harshest possible sentence? </p>
      <p>Beyond that straight violence creates a locus of resistance and vengeance. If a judge sentences 10 people to death on malicious process bullshit there’s a moment where all the families will think “that judge is going to kill my baby” followed by “that fucker just killed my baby!” (We all judge the Judges, and we all can visit the same punishments on them) </p>
      <p>By contrast when a judge sentences 10 people to life no parole and it will take decades for the full loss and horror of the situation to be realized.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>