<post>
  <author>Looking_round</author>
  <date>2020-05-20T16:52:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr98pw1/</link>
  <title>Reconsidering Effectiveness of Hydroxychloroquine</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I want to push back a little on the claims about trials claiming hydroxychloroquine is not effective.</p>
      <p>First, there are actually sound reasons to make the hypothesis that hydroxychloroquine can be a good prophylactic, or good early treatment. Please note this particular point, about early treatment. It will become important later.</p>
      <p>We know zinc traditionally is a good early treatment for respiratory viruses. I cannot outline to you the exact details on how it works, but it does something along the lines of short circuiting the RNA copying process of the virus so that the viruses that gets copied become non viable.</p>
      <p>The problem is that it's very difficult to get zinc past the cellular membrane, which is where all the copying happens. For something like that to happen, something like an ionophore is required as it helps transport the zinc into the cell.</p>
      <p>Hydroxychloroquine is an ionophore. </p>
      <p>However, as I mentioned, this is an antiviral treatment, so it makes more sense to give this early in the stage of the disease. There's no point in giving this to people in the late stage of the disease because the virus is already rampant through the body.</p>
      <p>The two studies that I am aware of examining the effectiveness of hydroxychloroquine that VA study and a later retrospective study are flawed. I would say fatally flawed. The drug was administered to people already in critical condition, which defeats the purpose, as you can imagine. Plus, it's not randomised controlled trials because the doctors are choosing who to give it to. Not only that, the tests do not have a component where they are testing hydroxychloroquine with zinc, which is a crucial part of the mechanism. </p>
      <p>I don't know what is going on behind the scenes. This seems to be such a fundamental mistake, so obvious that I'm questioning my own judgement; if I'm seeing this and everyone seems to be accepting this, what's going on?</p>
      <p>I think the two studies are far from conclusive.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>