<post>
  <author>mister_ghost</author>
  <date>2020-05-25T16:28:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/frs47kx/</link>
  <title>It's About X... Until You Disagree with X</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is rare for me, but I think this is a case where 'Motte and Bailey' actually applies.</p>
      <p>Take, as an example, Ferguson. The rage in Ferguson was about more than just Mike Brown - it led to the 'Black Lives Matter' movement, not the "Mike Brown's Life Matters" movement.</p>
      <p>If you challenged the claim that Brown was executed for being black, you would be told that you were missing the point - this is bigger than one incident, this is about a country that kills young black men for looking at cops funny, and about black people living under the constant threat of slaughter. And in the face of mounting and eventually insurmountable evidence that the police did everything right, the BLM movement stumbled not a bit.</p>
      <p>BUT if you tried to challenge the notion that black people were under threat of lynching at all times, you would run into the motte. Perhaps you pointed out that murder is rare, interracial murder rarer, and police murder rarer still. Or perhaps you brought up similar cases that happened to people who weren't black, which went basically unnoticed. Whatever you did, you were accused of distracting from the important details of what happened to Brown. Why do you care about how a community chooses to mourn a death? It doesn't affect you anyway.</p>
      <p>This case is similar: I don't think the outrage over that news story was really about DarQuan being assaulted. People are assaulted all the time, and it rarely makes headlines. If it turned out (counterfactually) that DarQuan actually was a burglar, or if the whole story were made up, the outraged redditors wouldn't just go "oh it's fine then" and settle down. The outrage is about a systemic issue, and challenging claims about that systemic issue is not off-topic or a distraction. It's taking the political claims seriously.</p>
      <p>Reminds me of the watchmen sub, tbh. That show was about politics, power and race until you didn't like the politics - then it was "the adventures of naked blue superman in the land of alien squids" and you had to stop taking everything so seriously.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>