<post>
  <author>PeterFloetner</author>
  <date>2020-05-24T18:36:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gpk0ne/smallscale_question_sunday_for_the_week_of_may_24/frou3y3/</link>
  <title>The Danger of Neonazi Organizations</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Neonazis are very good at building up hierarchical organizations if you let them, this is what fascism is about after all. They tend to use those organizations for targeted political murder and terrorism. </p>
      <p>See the for example the German terrorist group <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Socialist_Underground">NSU</a>, who where able to stay underground for 10 years while commiting at least 10 murders, 3 bombings and 14 bank robberies. To do this, they where able to rely on connections to the Blood &amp; Honour and various other local neonazi groups. A similiar group in the 70s and 80s was the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military-sports-group_Hoffmann">Military-sports-group Hoffmann</a>.</p>
      <p>What makes those groups so dangerous is the taste for <em>targeted</em> political violence combined with the ability for structured planning. Contemporary leftist groups are not structured enough to reach this level of danger, even though they are more numerous. The leftist scene consists of a myriad of different groups squabbling about random things (This is parodied in Life of Brian in the scene with the Judean People's Front vs. the People's front of Judea). On the inside, those groups are non-hierarchical and focused on consensus, which seriously hampers their ability to get shit done. What the left can do is summon a mob called "Antifa" by the media, but all Antifa does is throw stones and set cars on fire - unstructured, random violence, but nothing more. It takes a charismatic psychopath like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Army_Faction">Andreas Baader</a> to create a targeted leftist terror group, and he got a lot of help from the GDR and Arab terror groups. </p>
      <p>Let's also compare Neonazi terror groups to Islamic terrorists. Islamic terrorists are to engage in very structured violence. They have terror camps in the middle east where they train their terrorists, they plan big attacks, and then they execute them. They are able to procure weapons, knowledge and money from a variety of sources. But there are two important differences. First, their resources are offshore in the middle east, so the West can not do that much about it. Secondly, while Islamic terrorists are able to kill a lot of people, they have no endgame in the West other than 1. Terror 2.????. That's why their terrorists tend not to survive their attacks, and that makes their attacks very inconsequential in the long run. </p>
      <p>Neonazis need their rallies, their underground music festival etc. for networking. Unlike Islamic terrorists, they have to build all their infrastructure themselves in their own country. Since they cannot rely on official organizations (they would be illegal and draw attention of the Feds really fast), everything needs to be based on personal connections. This makes the big get-togethers so important for them, it is the only way to build connections between groups on a higher than local level. This is the reason why big Neonazi rallies are a danger, and why they should be banned.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>