<post>
  <author>ThirteenValleys</author>
  <date>2020-05-26T07:06:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fruk386/</link>
  <title>The Archetypal Loathing of Karens</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is the sort of <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/white-cop-caller-nicknames">archetypal story</a> in which all you have to do is change the names. Although like you said it certainly looks more malevolant this time. </p>
      <p>Saw something on tumblr earlier about how people on all sides of the culture war have zeroed in on the White Woman as the enemy. In situations like this it's leftists and liberals going all out on "Karen" (side note: man I'm glad that no one I'm super-close to has that name, otherwise I'd probably have lost it by now), but righties do it too: I see "white women ruin everything" on right-wing Tumblr and Reddit. </p>
      <p>What's more, they're even doing it for the same <em>reasons</em>, more or less. Not exactly the same words, but you can get the general picture on both sides of a white woman who struts around like she owns the place, thinks her feelings should be everyone's top priority, and throws a tantrum if her high standards aren't met. </p>
      <p>"So what? Everyone needs someone to hate, and angry, selfish, whiny bitches are a good target for anybody." Yeah, true. But I'm a cultural anthropologist and can't help myself, and I'm interested in how this meme solidified so quickly, with everyone more or less agreeing on what it means and blaming Karens for everything wrong with the world. I vaguely remember suburban white women being a group everyone was trying to get <em>good</em> with politically! The 'soccer mom' era and so forth, when white women in the suburbs were the biggest swing vote instead of a solid Dem bloc. (The mutual antagonism, in that case, mirrors the 'alt-right and dirtbag left team up to bash the center' phenomenon.) </p>
      <p>I also don't think it's trivially obvious that a truly hateable person will transcend partisanship. On both sides, I see people rush to the defense of scumbags all the time, saying they were taken out of context and the other guys are still worse. What makes Karen so universally loathed? </p>
      <p>My armchair-psych theory is that it's a response to being stifled; mentally, physically, spiritually. Online there's always some psycho or sadist lurking, waiting for you to slip up and ruin your life. Offline you're on unofficial unpaid 24/7 on-call, if you let your kid walk to a friend's house three blocks away someone will call the cops, and your Apple and Google tech is all spying on you. So people react to the demographic they associate most strongly with 'petty abuses of authority': even if you're not white, or are white and grew up without your mom, you've had some asshole White Woman teacher, or customer, or boss. </p>
      <p>I'd say this shared disdain of petty tyranny could work as a cross-tribal unifier, but I've been burned by that idea before.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>