<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2020-06-26T04:06:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fw11ved/</link>
  <title>Open vs Closed Fist Morality in Bioware RPGs</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I was a pretty big Bionerd back in the day- <a href="https://Bioware.net">Bioware.net</a> was my first english media fansite- so I have some thoughts on that.</p>
      <p>(Pardon if this runs long and gets messed up in transcription- my computer hates Reddit format and so do I.)</p>
      <p>Disclaimer/basis- I'd played pretty much all the 'modern' Bioware games post-KOTOR, between Jade Empire, Dragon Age, and Mass Effect. All roughly run on binary morality delimma designs that are usually (at least nominally) tied to ideological underpinnings. This was part of Bioware's success with its supporting character cast, who could feel 'real' by contrasting and bouncing off eachothers with different ideologies, values, and agreeing/disagreeing with the player based on what moral choices they took.</p>
      <p>For example, in Jade Empire the primary system is between the concepts of closed fist or open palm. As described by two teachers early on, these are not just fighting styles but philosophies. Open Palm is about cooperation and charity, while Closed Fist is about personal strength and self-reliance. When faced with a starving peasant, Open Palm gives the man a fish, while Closed Fist teaches him how to fish.</p>
      <p>Or that was the theory- in practice, it was loving hero or grouchy asshole, because Bioware also took the other expected inclusion of RPGs back then- that you should let the player be an utter asshole because the player should be able choose what kind of character they are rather than what sort of character a more defined character is. It's hard to explain, but the epitome of the newer idea is Geralt from the Witcher- always a gruff guy no matter how you play him, but with the gruffness going different ways.</p>
      <p>In the Bioware Age, however, an asshole you must be able to be, and so it always got tied to the less pleasant end of the morality spectrum. Closed Fist became a lot less about self-reliance and self interest and more about stealing a begger's last ten coppers or being a jerk because that would be funny.</p>
      <p>That tendency never quite went away.</p>
      <p>Pt 1 of we'll see</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>