<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-06-30T14:19:37Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hhtwxi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_29_2020/fwh6t6c/</link>
  <title>Blatanya Pesnya</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Jazz and soul also were near-exclusively black at some point, and they were not at all focused on glorifying violence. Gospel, too. Hell, black people are insanely musical, <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Black_music">look at how many genres they originated</a>.</p>
      <p>It seems that black culture, in the context of American culture and economy, has evolved to be more violent and antisocial over time. Suppose (as I think you imply) black people did not "adapt to modernity" because of HBD, i.e. they produce a greater improverished lower class which leaks into underclass and then engages in crime, and then socializes in penitentiary system. This class then affects the development of artistic sense and opinions of community at large. But it doesn't mean that they would have deterministically developed in this way, were the underclass somehow prevented from coming to exist. </p>
      <p>Case in point: Russians, despite European-level IQs and (likely) impulse control, also have a glorification of "thug culture". Our gangsters, too, adress each other with the word that may be translated as "brothas". Our genres like chanson are mostly dedicated to <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Blatnaya_pesnya">blatnaya pesnya</a>, which is to say, </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Thematically, <em>blatnaya pesnya</em> focus on injustice and oppression under a political system, depictions of prison life, and celebrations of criminal life and thieves' code of honour. These themes are sometimes  combined with <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Innuendo">sexual innuendo</a> as well as elements of <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Irony">irony</a> and humour. The use of <em><a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Fenya">fenya</a></em>, an underworld slang, is characteristic of <em>blatnaya pesnya</em> lyrics. Also known as <em>blatnoy</em> language (Russian: блатной язык), <em>fenya</em> follows the grammatical structure of the Russian language, but borrows vocabulary from <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Ukrainian_language">Ukrainian</a> and <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Yiddish_language">Yiddish</a>, as well as other languages, including <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/French_language">French</a> and <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Greek_language">Greek</a>.[<a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Blatnaya_pesnya#citenote4">4]</a> In terms of structure, <em>blatnaya pesnya</em> generally lack choruses, instead consisting of long narratives composed strictly of verses.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Reminds you of anything?</p>
      <p>Now, how did this genre come to be popular? Mass incarceration and labor camps during Soviet period, then chaos and destitution of the 90's. And today in a much safer and stable Putin's Russia, chanson is mostly dead, and zoomers who feel tough prefer America-inspired hip-hop (except we as a nation seem to lack the sense of rhythm, so the result is atrocious).</p>
      <p>Russians are not African Americans. Not nearly as criminal, at least. But in a more competitive society (say, strict market economy with average IQ of 110) we'd probably fall to the bottom of the barrel, and begin producing criminal misfits at a comparable rate, and this would usher in a revival of our chanson song. <a href="https://teksty-pesenok.ru/rus-mihail-krug/tekst-pesni-musyabufetchica/6765335/">Ahem...</a></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Oh, Myska, you buffet girl, you're just my rapture, you're just the memory of my prison days.
I remember smashing the table with an appliance when you barged into the tavern with the pigs.</p>
        <p>My friends were taken into the cop car,<br />
And I stood pretty and dressed up, but I couldn't do anything for you.</p>
        <p>But one summer evening, I took my jacket off; down the alley, slowly and at ease...<br />
You were walking around with some phony and smiling as if everyone was happy with you.  </p>
        <p>I took out the knife and peacefully stuck it in his belly, and the phony, telling me: "Goodbye," he fell.<br />
Only the prostitutes were singing at the market, and I stood alone in front of you.</p>
        <p>You're standing, a beautiful bitch on a roll, with your elbow on the railing,<br />
And accidentally, you reluctantly said so: "Go away." Yeah, whore, you killed me in me.  </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Ah, what poetry.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>