<post>
  <author>KlutzyTraining</author>
  <date>2020-06-25T17:41:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fvz44h2/</link>
  <title>Steelman of Mild Censorship</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Here  is an attempt to speculatively steelman the benefits of <em>mild censorship</em> to a movement being censored. (With an emphasis on how censorship might have some benefits for the right, since that has perhaps been where the most censorship has been occurring recently.):</p>
      <p>(Note, I'm not going to try to argue that mild censorship is a net win for censored movements, since I'm not sure about that. This is definitely a narrow essay, focusing on the benefits and ignoring the costs. If anyone wants to elaborate on the tradeoffs, that would certainly offer some balance!)</p>
      <h1>1. Hiding the ugliest voices, thereby centering the more persuasive voices in the movement.</h1>
      <p>Speaking from personal experience, when most of the loudest right-wing voices online circa 2016 seemed to me to be little better than trolls, I couldn't take the right very seriously. The loudest voices seemed to have a significant disregard for facts, and expressed a lot of things which seemed sexist, racist, and often homophobic. They only encouraged me to be even more determined as a liberal activist. </p>
      <p>Once many of those "right-wing trolls" were banned, then I could start to notice the more reasonable-seeming and persuasive voices on the right- the voices more in touch with facts, and demonstrating a clearer caring for ALL people. I don't believe I could have ever been so sympathetic to the right, if the more trollish voices hadn't been silenced. (How much the conservative movement should value "persuading people like KlutzyTraining" is another matter, but it's worth highlighting that sometimes there's a benefit there.)</p>
      <p>I also want to mention an ironic effect of banning the "trolls"- once the voices being centered were less immediately objectionable, so that I was actually willing to  <em>listen</em> to some people on the right, <em>then</em> I learned a lot of information &amp; perspectives which made me more sympathetic to the people I had previously condemned as nothing more than trolls. I could finally see a plausible basis for where the more extreme-seeming perspectives were coming from. </p>
      <p>There just first needed to be voices I could tolerate enough &amp; find to be compelling enough, so that I would actually listen to them. </p>
      <h1>2. Encouraging mental discipline, which has benefits in all areas of life, thereby increasing the overall power of the movement.</h1>
      <p>A lot of people raised in religions, especially strict religions, have to follow a lot of rules. And the practice of following rules can give them practice in being disciplined in other areas of life, like their health, job, romantic relationships, and friendships. </p>
      <p>A lot of people are starting to view the modern SJW movement as being a kind of religion, and maybe it is. It certainly has a lot of rules and rituals and requirements they place on everyone. </p>
      <p>It's possible that when movements (of any kind) are allowed to be purely emotive and undisciplined, it A) encourages members in habits which will hurt them in the rest of their lives (lost friendships, breakups, lost jobs, poorer work habits, worse marketing skills, etc.) B) if the individuals suffer, it also reduces the overall power of the movement- if lots of members of the movement lose their jobs or can't have children, the movement is hurt over the long-term, and C) makes the members of the movement less able to self-organize, or organize others, or be effective in general. </p>
      <p>I can say that as a former liberal activist, attempting to organize liberals was one of the most frustrating things I've ever experienced in my life. But, I was raised with conservative religion and other forms of rule-based discipline, so organization came more easily to me. And I could see that the right normally had less trouble being organized, perhaps due to more religiosity and more corporate jobs.</p>
      <p>In theory, enforcing mild censorship on people gives them some practice with mental discipline, which might have some long-term rewards for both the individuals and the cumulative resources of the movement. </p>
      <p>FWIW, this is one reason why some commenters on here may want to embrace the "censorship" of the moderators, as having values in their own personal lives or in service to whatever causes they believe in most of all. The practice of following rules, <em>especially when we think the rule is stupid</em>, is certainly a practice in discipline, and it might pay off over the long run. </p>
      <h1>3. Encouraging the practice of persuasion.</h1>
      <p>I doubt that all of the supposed "trolls" I mentioned earlier stopped talking forever after getting banned. Some of them learned that they just needed to practice how to be more persuasive, without resorting to types of speech which many people found objectionable to the point of "reporting it to the authorities". The results might not be clearly visible yet, but I suspect this will pay off for them over the long-term. </p>
      <p>Where people like Trump encourage raw emotion, the rules of social media companies may encourage some discipline to channel the emotion more effectively.  </p>
      <p>And to be honest, until the censorship started to seem periodically egregious (like, how on earth can the subreddit for the President of the USA not have its own functional subreddit? I never wanted that subreddit to totally dominate the front page like it had in 2016, but even at my most liberal I never wanted a subreddit for the POTUS to be <em>completely silent</em>, that just seems crazy to me), I felt sure that censorship would be doing the right a favor, when the censorship was just mild. </p>
      <p>A clearer example might be the non-violent movements of Gandhi and Martin Luther King Jr. King's civil rights actions were in a way highly self-censored. They didn't express everything they were feeling- they didn't engage in hate speech against the people they believed to be oppressing them, even when they might have felt incredibly angry. </p>
      <p>They wore suits, were well-organized &amp; non-violent, and made their points in a manner which was easy for most people to tolerate. In short, they were persuasive rather than offensive, because they had the willingness to censor themselves to achieve a greater goal. </p>
      <p>Likewise, arguably the most successful American conservative of the past 100 years, Ronald Reagan, had spent his entire pre-political career involved with persuasion in one form or another, and then he practiced persuasion extraordinarily well during his political career. </p>
      <p>I have to imagine that Reagan had at least a few offensive thoughts in his head, but he censored himself well enough to stick to the most persuasive messages, and it paid off enormously for the conservative movement. (I think Obama is another example of someone who is probably highly self-disciplined, who also achieved surprising political success.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>