<post>
  <author>questionnmark</author>
  <date>2020-06-29T23:32:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hhtwxi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_29_2020/fwf5vss/</link>
  <title>The Role of Energy and Entropy in Cultural Conflict</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Lets move away from the topical discussions or incidents of the week, and how about we talk about something a little different -- entropy and energy as it relates to economic growth and cultural conflict. </p>
      <p>The growth and complexity of human systems are the result of fossil fuel energy being input into the system. One barrel of oil has the <a href="http://theoildrum.com/node/4315">equivalent energy of several years</a> of human labour, but the specific number doesn't matter, just that it is a lot and it is critically important to human society -- especially cities which need the highest concentration of energy to maintain their relatively higher complexity. It is without a shadow of a doubt, your very life depends on this net energy to be sustained because without it there would be no human civilization as we know it. No amount of slaves or peasant farmers can compete with a farmer on a tractor because of how much more cheap and useful a tractor is by comparison. If you doubt me then you should 'walk a mile in your car's shoes'; I.E. fill your car up with gas, drive a mile away from the gas station then fill it up again. </p>
      <p>
        <em>I am not arguing for neo-liberalism</em>, but I wanted to give some cultural and economic context. There are very real limits to the growth and deployment of fossil fuels as the pollution from their use and the industries that rely upon them reached a critical state in the West around the 1970's.  Neo-liberalism is a response to the problems of the 70's, and it has done a relatively good job of maintaining stability despite the challenges faced by the economy. neo-liberalism as a concept helped move Western society beyond the hump of the 70's and kept things ticking along for 50 years, so it's not all bad even if there are some relative winners and losers due to the changes. </p>
      <p>In a zero sum system like what existed for most of human history if Bob the farmer wanted more production he had more kids to work on the field or he went and enslaved Bill and his kids to do the work on the farm whilst his kids got to enjoy relative prosperity -- a zero sum situation whereby if somebody gained then someone else had to lose. The deployment of fossil fuels created the concept of economic growth, and we are several dozen doublings down that path already, but most importantly it created a non-zero sum environment where Bob and Bill can both prosper if instead of putting Bill to work, Bob put some coal to good use instead. Our Western institutions have evolved within this 'non-zero sum' environment. </p>
      <p>As economic growth and increasing energy supply become more difficult we are entering back into a zero-sum economic system. Bob is now Bob the accountant, and if he wants to drive a new Audi and go on more overseas holidays whilst living in a nicer home then Bill the factory worker has to get less. A significant proportion of the current inequity noted in the West is due, in my opinion, to this shift. <strong>It is within this zero-sum context that identity politics becomes relevant</strong>, and the culture war as we keep discussing is a symptom of this change. When group A benefits it is almost certainly at the expense of group B, C, D etc. Young vs old; left vs right; ethnic groups and other identities vs each other etc. </p>
      <p>At this point we are only partially entering the zero-sum state because as many of you would rightfully point out technology, trade, specialization and outside resources all have incredible potential to shift the balance (yay for neo-liberalism??). I'm not trying to be a doomer as I am actually pretty optimistic that these problems can be solved. Where I am not sure is whether there is the political and cultural will as well as the intelligence and grit within politics to actually make a positive difference. A transition from fossil fuels to renewable energy at current or similar technology levels would create a jarring transition to a global zero sum system. The relative prosperity of all groups of Americans (white, black, Asian -- everyone) for instance would have to decline. Based on my experience as a previous environmental activist there are no hard lines drawn between a black person in America and a black person in Africa, so if the former has to lose so for the greater good for instance of all people then the latter's needs will take precedence -- the only consolation of course is that the white or Asian group of Americans would lose <em>relatively more</em>. </p>
      <p>We can argue all we want about any number of culture war topics, but as it stands I believe that they are frequently symptoms of a much large and more systemic trouble. As underlying tensions increase as the systems we have put in place during an unprecedented period of stability and growth in the Western world become increasingly difficult to maintain then this tension comes to the surface as inter-group conflict.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>