<post>
  <author>randomerican</author>
  <date>2020-06-30T02:22:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hhtwxi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_29_2020/fwfnp0b/</link>
  <title>Old School Feminism: Gender Abolitionists and Gender Essentialists</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>splinter from feminism</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Whoa hey now! To paraphrase Reagan: TERFs didn't leave feminism, feminism left them. That is, they're pretty much standard old-school radfems who just didn't get with the new program. Or I am/was anyway, maybe the young folks are different; I already accepted our fate long ago, so I wasn't in touch with the young folks; I didn't post on GenderCritical.</p>
      <p>Anyway, to give more of an answer to your question...</p>
      <p>For old-school radfems, the big divide used to be between gender abolitionists (Dworkin, MacKinnon etc.) and gender essentialists (Daly).</p>
      <p>For a very long time it was near-universally accepted that gender abolitionists were in direct opposition to gender transitioners. I mean, saying, "There totally are two genders; not only that, I am the other one" reifies gender, which seems directly opposed to the goal of ending it. Especially in the past when there was a lot of "I'm really a woman because I like dresses and pink and literature and I don't like pants and blue and math!" (Then there were the individuals who instead said things like, "I'm really a woman because when I'm aroused my dick feels like it's inside out and really supposed to be a vagina." Yes someone literally came onto the Ms. Magazine discussion boards and said that.)</p>
      <p>For gender abolitionists, there was a lot of feeling--I think on both sides--that we ought to be allies, after all we all shared a dislike of our assigned gender roles; but though we were approached by trans as possible allies, and though we also approached them, on our side there was a feeling of, "This structure (gender) is oppressing both of us, <em>let's defeat it</em> and instead...instead, damn it they want to reify it." For 20YearsAgo!Me, basically they were "our natural allies who were instead betraying the cause; instead of helping it, they were harming it." (IOW, what <a href="/u/maiqthetrue">/u/maiqthetrue</a><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/hhtwxi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_29_2020/fwery2s/">said</a>.)</p>
      <p>(On top of that we often saw MTFs as being in a much better position to <em>persuade men</em> on our goal of getting rid of gender if they spoke as men, rather than as MTFs. If they passed, "Men don't listen to women the way they do to other men"; if they didn't pass, "Men <em>definitely</em> don't listen to those they perceive as 'freaks.'" We wanted them to "keep their male privilege and use it for the cause," not "give it up and in the process reify our hated, restrictive gender role"!)</p>
      <p>(Also I should add that my experience was not of "observing all that, then nursing a hatred for trans people as a result." Rather my experience way back when was of, given our gender abolitionist ideas (not that we even had the term "gender abolitionist" back then!), we not surprisingly would <em>exhort</em> our trans presumed-allies to do this. "MTFs, don't transition; instead use your male privilege to fight <em>all</em> our restrictive gender roles!" Stuff like that. (Dworkin, the most pro-trans old-school radfem, said she didn't begrudge any individual doing what they had to do to survive in this imperfect world--including gender transition. I agreed. Still we both also were willing to <em>request</em> that people make different choices. That was a normal part of political advocacy.)</p>
      <p>And my experience was of these exhortations being met with then-shocking levels of hostility. At that time, most of the time when you made a political argument or polemic, if the hearer didn't want to do what you were exhorting, they'd either ignore you or just argue back. The hostility I observed and experienced was unexpected, extreme and shocking. (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/cagwnj/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_08_2019/etcc2dy/">See also</a>: "My primary concern is just how <a href="https://anti-female-receipts.tumblr.com/">disturbingly violent</a> trans rhetoric is towards women. Radfems have zero desire to hurt or injure trans women - we mostly want to be left alone. Trans women, on the other hand, openly cheer about how much they'd gleefully curbstomb us and stab us and shoot us if they get the chance.")</p>
      <p>At the time we didn't understand it and chalked it up to "male socialization" (which, see below).</p>
      <p>In retrospect it kind of does seem to fit with the theory of autogynephilia. <em>If</em> these individuals we were exhorting really <em>were</em> actually there for a sexual buzz attached to "being treated as women," then by asking them to "keep and use their male privilege" we were harshing their buzz--and that degree of hostility is <em>normal</em> for <em>that</em> type of interaction (or was then, anyway). But that's hindsight and may be biased.</p>
      <p>Alternatively, one could say today that we were requesting they choose a different reaction to dysphoria. We all (on that general political "side"), after all, disliked and objected to our assigned gender roles. Today's zeitgeist, I suppose, might respond, "Oh you radfems just didn't understand how much <em>worse</em> real trans people's <em>dysphoria</em> is than your dislike of your gender roles! Oh also some of you were just eggs and should've just transitioned." Uh...but the point is we were proposing a <em>different</em> solution to extreme dislike of gender roles than their solution of switching to the one, single, solitary other available role.)</p>
      <p>It didn't help that back then we didn't have a lot of the language we do now. Today I can express our points above. Today I can also express our points about the purpose of things like MichFest; today I can say a lot of its purpose was for people who were raised as girls to discuss that experience away from people without that experience. Today I can say MTFs upset about MichFest policies were on average larger than us, with more upper body strength than us, and with childhoods that had trained them both to resort to physical intimidation <em>more readily</em>, and also better in how to use it.</p>
      <p>Back then the only phrasing in common use to describe such things was "male socialization" and "male build/body" and so on. I think this just further inflamed these MTFs' upset at being, they felt, "told they weren't real women." I gather they believed they were fighting for a righteous cause and armed with that belief they saw no need for restraint. But they had childhood training in being willing to use intimidation and in being skilled at it, and their bodies were suited to it relative to ours, and so they did succeed at intimidating us, and there it is.</p>
      <p>(Even today it might still be difficult to express the other aspect; the aspect where flyers were spread around the site with lines like, "A hot load from my monstrous tranny-cock." Some people have a visceral understanding of how and why mention of ejaculation in, we'll say atypical, contexts--especially in "porn-style language"--can come across as, basically, a rape threat. Others don't have that visceral understanding. Sadly, well-meaning "autistic" or spectrummy types without that visceral understanding can at times fail to believe those with that visceral understanding when they express it, thus giving cover to bad actors. At the same time, perhaps well-meaning "autistic" or spectrummy types without that visceral understanding who are inflamed by what they see as their fight for justice can, perhaps, engage in behaviors that perhaps aren't intended to come across that way. BUT. DO.)</p>
      <p>Later, after we were safely defeated, younger people who had taken up identifying with the trans movement--often individuals whose personality characteristics suggested that if they'd been our age they'd have joined us instead (people who leaned more "nonbinary")--also took up some of our ideas around gender being a social construct etc.</p>
      <p>I do get the whole "it's safe now that they've been defeated" attitude, I do; but speaking personally it kinda reads as adding insult to injury. Like: "First you tar us as evil--you get people kicked out of friend groups and/or get their businesses boycotted as evil, you ruin lives--and then when you've done that, you turn around and steal our ideas!" OTOH, well hey, maybe that's evidence those ideas were right. ;)</p>
      <hr />
      <p>I can't speak to gender essentialists as well since I wasn't one. But I believe their view was that essential $gender-hood was tied to biological sex.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>