<post>
  <author>StillerThanTheStorm</author>
  <date>2020-06-27T14:16:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hdlwx8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_22_2020/fw625sm/</link>
  <title>Peterson, Pronouns, and the (Ir)relavence of Self Identification</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Jordan Peterson has an excellent lecture on this, I'll try to recapitulate his argument in my own voice. Essentially, it comes down to the claim that self-identification relies on a fundamental misunderstanding of how social roles actually work.</p>
      <p>Pronouns are not, descriptively, a matter of personal preference. Pronouns are just a specific example of the more general case of social roles and identities. These cannot simply claimed or assumed on the basis of personal preference, and others cannot simply be expected to accept them. Social roles arise as a result of an implicit negotiation between the individual and the group.</p>
      <p>Names are an extreme example, where people seem to think that anything goes, but even in this case it isn't true. It's easy to imagine a scene where a settler joins and Indian tribe, and perhaps he says that his name is Alexander. Would you expect the tribe to actually call him Alexander? Or would they be likely to say: That name is harsh on the tongue. Among us, you shall he known as He Who Came from the Sun. Somewhere else in one of these threads, someone said that to assume Japanese citizenship, you also have to take a Japanese name.</p>
      <p>As you go from names to less arbitrary social markers, the negotiation aspect becomes more explicit. A straightforward example is titles and honorifics: the title of Doctor requires the credentials. The implicit permission to lead and make decisions for a group is in much murkier territory, but again, in a group of people, individuals are as a matter of fact afforded different privileges (or permissions). An easy example is the newcomer that somebody has brought along to a group of people who has been meeting regularly for years: the newcomer, unless he is extraordinarily charismatic, isn't allowed to cut a long, drawn out discussion about where to eat short and declare by fiat that they'll go to the Italian place, whereas one of the regulars may be allowed or even expected to take on this leadership role. You cannot simply self-identify as a regular: this role is in fact policed by the group.</p>
      <p>Gender identities are so important to people that they permeate all (?) human languages. The society that constructs words like actress does not consider gender irrelevant. Being a man as opposed to a boy, or a woman as opposed to a man, or a senior as opposed to a junior (and so on and so forth ad nauseam) is simply not just a matter of how you feel, but also a matter of how you are perceived, which again comes down to which roles you are able to and willing to and expected to fill. And with this understanding of what gender really is, self identification as a standard, where the individual can compel the group to perceive them as playing specific roles regardless of whether they actually qualify for them, simply does not make any sense. This standard ultimately entails stripping these roles of meaning altogether, and is functionally equivalent to abolishing them.</p>
      <p>The project of abolishing gender roles is, I guess, fair game. Just as roles are negotiated, the roles in use by the group are subject to a sort of meta-negotiation. However, pretending that self-identification is merely a matter of courtesy is either a fundamental misunderstanding of how the roles work, or a disingenuous attack on their validity.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>