<post>
  <author>asdfasdflkjlkjlkj</author>
  <date>2020-03-06T18:52:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjo57ay/</link>
  <title>Rejecting Commercialization of "Emotional Labor"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I actually got into an argument with my girlfriend about this term a few weeks ago. She was relaying the arguments of barista friends of hers who complained that they were not compensated for their "emotional labor," by which they meant, essentially, the expectation that they interact emotionally with customers, especially difficult or socially inappropriate customers. I argued that this was <em>exactly</em> the labor they were being compensated for, and if they had a problem with their pay, they should just say that rather than acting as if the emotional side of their job was uniquely unfunded or unjust. The argument was muddled, though, by my dislike of the terminology of "emotional labor" itself, my disagreements being well expressed by <a href="/u/JosheyWoshey">u/JosheyWoshey</a> above: that the growing use of the term "emotional labor" reflects an attempt to commodify those interactions and relationships which modern human beings have typically resisted commodifying -- basic politeness, friendliness to those we see every day, generosity of spirit, and so on.</p>
      <p>What's interesting to me is that there's a contradiction between these two arguments, both of which I sincerely believe: on the one hand, I admit that a bartender or a barista is being paid to be nice to the customers, which means that their politeness is part of an economic exchange. On the other hand, I dislike the people who call want to call those interactions "emotional labor."</p>
      <p>The way I resolve the contradiction is by saying that there are certain spheres of exchange which are in some sense economic, but whose precise economic value cannot be acknowledged without the exchange itself being corrupted. To take a very obvious example, escorts often ask that clients place their "donation" in an envelope on the table rather than handing it over directly to the girl. In this way, the illusion can be preserved that this exchange is not precisely economic, a necessary precondition of emotional intimacy. To take a slightly less crass example, child-rearing is an economic exchange of the mother's time for the father's children's well-being. Because of this, it deserves real compensation. But the only time anyone actually attaches an explicit dollar value to a mother's child-rearing is when she and her husband divorce -- in other words, when the relationship has failed.</p>
      <p>We drape a cloak of mystery over certain types of exchange, because the exchange is perverted when the cloak is removed. I tip my baristas, but I do not tell them how much. I pay for my girlfriend's meals and wine, but there is no explicit understanding of this between us. This cloak allows us to sneak humane interaction into what would otherwise be purely economic, to mix personality with emotionless commodity exchange. The bartender is not just your friend, but he's also not a sympathy-bot which lends a sympathetic ear upon insertion of cash. He occupies a middle-ground where we spend much of our lives. I see the types who want to give a commercial value to this "emotional labor" as advancing the most extreme of market libertarian positions, which is odd because they're usually socialists.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>