<post>
  <author>D1m1tr1Rascalov</author>
  <date>2020-03-05T16:13:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjkd3g7/</link>
  <title>Die Linke - The German Radical Left</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Interesting culture war development in Germany: The party Die Linke ("The Left") recently held a large conference for its members to discuss its current state, strategy and policy positions. Thanks to modern technology, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/dielinke/videos">interested viewers could watch up to 7 hours of content live on their YouTube channel (German obviously).</a></p>
      <p>Some context first: Die Linke sits at the left edge of the current field of important and socially accepted parties (what you might call, in some sense, the Overton window) and is the left-most party in parliament by a significant margin. It has a controversial history, being the product of a fusion of a small Western German left-wing party called WASG and a larger Eastern German party called PDS, which was the direct legal successor of the SED, the ruling party of the former GDR. As such, its parliamentary history is rife with frictions, the CDU (chancellor Merkel's party) even refuses to work with it on any level.</p>
      <p>Today, in terms of policies, the party occupies a space similar to that of the DSA or the left wing of the British Labour party: endorsements of almost all current progressive and socially liberal causes (think trans rights, environmentalism, pro-immigration, women's rights etc.) and an aggressive stance against capitalism, starting from "the modern market economy is fundamentally broken in not just a few but almost all ways and is in need of massive state intervention" and going to ... where exactly?</p>
      <p>That is the question that a lot of people are asking themselves following a constant feed of video snippets from the above mentioned conference. The party has historically taken strong positions on the welfare state, market interventions, private property etc. that might rightly be called Socialist not just in the "Scandinavian welfare state" but also in the Marxian sense. Yet this was always done in the context of explicitly, if at times begrudgingly accepting the foundational setup of the German state: parliamentary democracy and a market economy with lots of interventions to make things more equitable. The commitment of the party, currently occupying 10% of the federal parliament and involved in several federal state level governments, to those values has now been strongly called into question. Some choice sentiments (again, all sources in German):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://twitter.com/artep21/status/1235146323126620161?s=20">The fixation on the entire parliamentary representative thing should be weakened. The job of any left wing movement with regards to parliament is to take state money and information and give it to extraparliamentary opposition groups</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://twitter.com/Hallaschka_HH/status/1235271912944783360?s=20">The success of the AfD is explained by the state enforced racism of the establishment parties like the CDU or SPD, all parties besides The Left are crypto-right</a> [Note: it was the CDU under Merkel's leadership that opened the borders to the refugees in 2015, only then the formerly EU-skeptical AfD turned right wing populist and became successful]</li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://twitter.com/Hallaschka_HH/status/1235439076339314688?s=20">A speaker mockingly describing his first time in parliament, audience cheers</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://twitter.com/Hallaschka_HH/status/1234793455945232384?s=20">Audience member: after the revolution, we will shoot the 1%. Party co-chair Bernd Riexinger: No, don't shoot them, force them to do useful work</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Attitudes like that have historically been the domain of either comically small fringe parties without any chance of getting into any sort of position of power or the above-mentioned extraparliamentary opposition. What's also new about this is that it's not just random weirdos mouthing off, but also senior party officials and large parts of the audience at this conference falling in line with radical "tear down the status quo" rhetoric.</p>
      <p>The reaction in the media has been broadly negative, but also curiously calm. Just a few weeks ago (also covered in the CWR thread), a local election of the candidate of the classical liberal FDP to the office of prime minister in Thuringia with the votes of the AfD triggered an avalanche of outrage, with the modal interpretation being that Germany had now reached a state similar to the early 30s of the 20th century. Meanwhile, this has caused a reaction of "well, that does not give the best of impressions, but what are you gonna do, sometimes things just are like that....". Media outlets seem to universally understand Riexinger's gulag analogy from above to be just a pretty bad joke, nothing more. To be fair though, there has been pushback from within the party, the former and now reelected prime minister of Thuringia Bodo Ramelow <a href="https://twitter.com/bodoramelow/status/1234849373122695168?s=20">strongly distanced himself from any radical tendencies</a>.</p>
      <p>To me, this is very interesting as it mirrors similar polarization processes all around the Western world, e.g. with the rise of the more radical part of the Bernie movement. It's difficult to say where exactly this loss of trust in the traditional institutions of the West comes from. It might be a reaction to similar movements on the right, but the actors there also see themselves as warriors against decadent institutions and elites, and in many cases (in my view) plausibly so, as at least in social matters right wingers have not had many causes for celebrations in recent times.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>