<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-03-04T16:17:03Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjgzp14/</link>
  <title>Based</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Typically, a grotesque caricature of a movement or idea will spell out an elaborate explanation of their ideas in the form of a rhetorical question, and then the "based chad" will answer with a simple, confident "yes."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Not quite: their ideas tend to amount to grossly –but ineffectually – vilifying Chad's position and presenting it as beyond the pale, in the sense of «omg do you really in the current year believe [thing]». And, well, according to <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/based-god">KYM</a>, "based" was <em>conceived</em> as a response to accusers, a deliberate inversion of original meaning:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"Based means being yourself. <em>Not being scared of what people think about you.</em> Not being afraid to do what you wanna do. Being positive. When I was younger, based was a negative term that meant like dopehead, or basehead. People used to make fun of me. They was like, 'You’re based.' They’d use it as a negative. And what I did was turn that negative into a positive. I started embracing it like, 'Yeah, I’m based.' I made it mine. I embedded it in my head. Based is positive."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>There is something to your Сonfidence-vs-Tolerance analysis, but the truth is, I think, a bit different. The brand of leftism that came to be associated with SJW is <em>extremely</em> dependent on bullying people into supporting consensus via implied (and sometimes enacted) threat of orchestrated social shunning; on offering them to trade their principles, beliefs and allegiances for continued social acceptance. It's more eusocial than collectivist. Or as <a href="https://twitter.com/0x49fa98/status/1064256128190570496">0HPLovecraft</a> puts it, «The leftist [sic] thrives on consensus procedures, it is why over-socialization its its necessary output.» That's also why "classical liberals" have become, over my lifetime, right-wing boogeymen and their appeal to liberalism evokes only sneers. People can feel this dynamic.</p>
      <p>You know, on the other side of the aisle, there's one far-right cartoon where central characters, two genuine White Nationalists who became "irrelevant" due to a personal spat with Nick Fuentes, try to restore their image and go to his party. There, both are goaded into "degeneracy" under the thin veneer of rightist socializing, with the carrot of "relevance" and the stick of being labeled "cringe" by trendy, influential zoomers. In the end, the older one (after mysteriously developing imposing physique) snaps and refuses to abide by these rules: «NO! <strong>You</strong> are cringe!» – before leaving.<br />
I believe this is the basic dynamic people perceive behind basedness. "Based" is progressively frequently invoked with regards to Bernie supporters (edit: consider also their spin with <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/photos/1714794-yeah-good-ok">"Yeah good. Ok"</a> memes, the cold dismissal of some cheap platitude); I've even seen old-school tankies such as Maoists describe each others as "based". Their beliefs do not preclude focusing on victimhood; in fact the latter group is known for supporting atrocities wholly incomparable with SJWist social media harassment, all in the name of helping the weak and downtrodden. And online, I don't think any group is particularly meek (not to mention they all overlap). What is different though (at least on the level of self-perception), is that based groups actually have some mental bases: their beliefs are grounded in some ideology they themselves know and respect, not in the distributed and collectively enforced consensus about what's thinkable and unthinkable in the current year. </p>
      <p>There's no antonym for "based". Maybe because not being based means just not having an actual opinion, being the caricature of a normie. </p>
      <p>One corollary to this is the "trad wife" memeplex, particularly <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/photos/1682125-trad-girl">this Russian image</a> where (I presume) a very woke feminist asks, frustrated, «Are you really not interested in politics and are just copying your man's political views?» – receiving, obviously, the meek but resolute "Yes". On one hand, it can be viewed as memetic propaganda of traditional gender roles, subverting the confident, independent sense of "based". But on the other, it's the apex of individualism. Trad girl here considers politics, which generate the entire identity of Woke girl, simply <em>irrelevant</em>, beneath her – because her values are traditional and so she will follow through with them, regardless of noise in the public sphere.</p>
      <p>TL;DR: being based means rejecting the premise that people who shame and may attempt to "cancel" you have any legitimate authority outside of their over-socialized bubble.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>