<post>
  <author>KolmogorovComplicity</author>
  <date>2020-03-06T19:55:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjobp7u/</link>
  <title>Corporatizing Marriage</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's even a little worse than that. Let's take this to its logical conclusion.</p>
      <p>When two people get married, they should set up a corporation. This corporation should pay each partner for the services they perform for the household, but also charge each for the pro-rated value of the services they benefit from. For, for instance, if a wife spends 10 hours cleaning the house and this labor is valued at $10/hour, she's paid $100 by the marital corporation. It charges her $50 (since 50% of the benefit of the cleaning flows to her), and her husband $50.</p>
      <p>Each spouse would pay for all their personal expenses out of their earnings, whether from the marital corporation or other sources. After all, if labor uncompensated by a monetary wage is inefficient or unjust, a transfer of money or goods in exchange for no labor is as well. Husband and wife go out to dinner? Separate checks.</p>
      <p>The marital corporation would own the home the couple lived in, and all other property the utilization of which was shared by the partners. Shares in it would be allocated based on the assets each party contributed to it. Each spouse would pay fair market rent to the marital corporation for their use of the assets it owned. If the marital corporation turned a profit (for instance if it owned the marital home outright, such that the rent paid into it exceeded expenses), the partners could draw this off in the form of dividends according to ownership.</p>
      <p>What if the couple wanted to go on an expensive vacation, but the wife couldn't afford to pay for her half on the income the marital corporation paid her for her household labor? The marital corporation could extend her a line of credit, and she could pay it back (plus the prevailing interest rate, of course), over time. Naturally, she'd also be free to seek credit from outside lenders, if they offered better terms.</p>
      <p>Divorce would become trivial; just split up the assets of the marital corporation based on ownership at the moment of dissolution. Stay-at-home partners would receive a fair wage for their labor, and it would show up in GDP statistics, the additional legibility empowering policymakers.</p>
      <p>Most people following along probably find the idea of this to be ludicrous, even disturbing. I certainly do. The more relevant point in the present instance, though, is that when you actually work through the idea of making all intra-family exchanges work like market exchanges (rather than just focusing on the lack of monetary compensation in only one particular class of intra-family exchange with reference to one gender), it's obvious the big losers would be stay-at-home spouses, predominantly women. Working spouses in most cases presently compensate stay-at-home spouses at well above market rate, they just do it in the form of goods and services (room and board, clothing, vacations, etc.) rather than cash.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>