<post>
  <author>Lykurg480</author>
  <date>2020-03-07T10:19:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjqpey6/</link>
  <title>People Who Can't Understand Math</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Math is actually where I have the most experience. In addition to being the guy to ask for help in my year, I tutored and once taught an elective.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>At least for me, I think my instinctive gut feeling - probably wrong - is that I'd expect them to have caught up some.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The problem is that many people cant understand mathematics. Ill recount the conversation that Ill propably never forget when I first realised this (this was in the class where youre normally 16):</p>
      <p>Classmate: Hey Lykurg can you take a look at this exercise?<br />
Me: Sure.<br />
C: *shows:* simplify (2x - y)^2.<br />
M: Do you remember the second binomic formula?<br />
C: Yes, (a - b)^2 = a^2 - 2ab + b^2.<br />
M: Can you apply it here?<br />
C: N-no?<br />
M: Are you sure?<br />
C: *stares at term for 2 seconds* Just tell me the answer.<br />
M: Yes you can apply it. 2x is a and y is b, so you get 4x^2 - 4xy + y^2.<br />
C: Oooh right.</p>
      <p>He then moved on to similar exercises and could do them on his own. Here you can see well what I mean: I (and presumably you) can look at a formula and learn what pen-and-paper operations it describes from reading it. Whereas my classmate, for him applying this formula is learned like juggling or some other physical skill is for us. The text of the formula is just a string associated with it, a proper name for all intents and purposes. In this case he could remember the name, but the "muscle memory" of the operation didnt trigger at first. Youve propably had a similar experience at one point. If you use a method repeatedly, you will usually develop some muscle memory for it (as pretty much everyone has for basic arithmetic), but when you havent used it for a while, you often find that you can no longer "just do it", but you need to search your memory for explicit formulas and theorems and then reason through their application to the case, and you need to do this for a bit until it comes back. This second option is simply not available to most people, and they will just not be able to do it at this point. Plus, its a lot harder to get he right muscle memory in the first place if you dont have this direct access to the correct way of doing it, so they will take far longer to form even that same muscle memory. For someone like this, maintaining their mathematical ability takes constant effort the same way maintaining the accuracy of their basketball shot does. Furthermore, its extremely hard for them to learn a new method from a book, without someone to walk them through the steps. As a result, their mathematical knowledge peaks at the end of highschool.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>