<post>
  <author>onyomi</author>
  <date>2020-03-04T04:55:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjfqnsj/</link>
  <title>The Dangerous Allure of "Standing Up for Others" Online</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I've been thinking recently about the motto of the "Against Hate Subreddits" subreddit, "<strong>A strong person stands up for himself, a stronger person stands up for others.</strong>" (their bold font) and why it bothers me quite a lot.</p>
      <p>I think it's because it encapsulates for me a very wrong and, I think, pervasive attitude at the root of a lot of CW problems.</p>
      <p>Namely, the idea that, in the current environment, online or, indeed at a corporate meeting, it's more risky, difficult, or praiseworthy to "stand up" for vague "others" than it is to defend yourself is almost entirely false (it could be a little more true if we're talking about e.g. your buddy at the same company and not a vague "other").</p>
      <p>When you explicitly defend yourself or a group you belong to you are (somewhat understandably) easily dismissed as having a self-interested, and therefore suspect, motivation. "Well, of course <em>you</em>'d say that."</p>
      <p>On the other hand, when you call for someone to be cancelled, deplatformed, fired, etc. not because he, she, or they directly, obviously threaten you, but because you're fighting on behalf of some typically vaguely defined group too weak to stand up for itself, there is usually seemingly little risk for you and significant upside in the form of wielding power over others and shaping e.g. office culture. I've never heard of someone who got fired for trying to get somebody else fired (prove me wrong, please! Hopefully it does sometimes happen, along with people who've gone to jail for provably false rape accusations).</p>
      <p>I think "Social Justice Warrior" is a great term because the word "warrior" calls attention to a specific aspect of their rhetoric and thinking we see at work in "<strong>A strong person stands up for himself, a stronger person stands up for others.</strong>" This phrase sounds very commonsensical but there's a subtle rhetorical sleight of hand: namely, it's borrowing a sentiment that is accurate in the case of a <em>physical</em> conflict (a fight), and applying it to the level of purely social struggles over e.g. who gets fired, promoted, etc.</p>
      <p>In a physical fight it makes sense to say "it takes guts to fight an attacker, but it takes real guts to fight off somebody else's attacker." This is because presumably fighting someone who was physically attacking someone else puts you at roughly the same risk as if you'd been attacked by that person yourself. It is rightly viewed as noble if, for example, you see a big, strong guy beating on an old lady and you run up and put yourself in harm's way to stop it.</p>
      <p>But this situation bears little if any resemblance to how online and institutional social "battles" play out, because <em>social "battles," unlike physical battles, are won and lost in others' perceptions of the moral righteousness of their combatants</em>. Therefore, someone with no obvious selfish motivation to "stand up" is in a much less risky position of suffering social repercussions because he's fighting from what is typically perceived as a much stronger social position of righteousness in a battle where perception of righteousness itself determines victory. Yet winning social battles on behalf of "others" still confers power, status, and other psychic or potentially material benefits on the victors. I guess the answer is to more frequently call attention to the power wielded by cancellers and the ways it can indirectly redound to their personal aggrandizement when they "stand up for others."</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>