<post>
  <author>phoneosaur</author>
  <date>2020-03-06T01:25:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjlz8ez/</link>
  <title>Present-day US vs the Soviet post-Brezhnev Gerontocracy</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The similarity of the current US political landscape to the Soviet post-Brezhnev gerontocracy is unmistakable to me. Both eras feature a death of earnest belief in the country's founding principles, widespread preference falsification, an out-of-touch elite, media censorship, technological stagnation, and waning geopolitical power. My hunch is that the "establishment" in each era resorted to increasingly elderly candidates because the pipeline of ideologically reliable young people stopped flowing. The establishment become reluctant to hand power to a new generation when that generation has ceased believing in the legitimacy of the power structure.</p>
      <p>In the Soviet Union's case, these fears were justified. When the establishment finally ran out of old ideologically-reliable people to elevate, the beloved-worldwide, hated-internally idealist Mikhail Gorbachev came to power and unwittingly destroyed (with glasnost and perestroika) the tools that the Soviet elite had been using to address the tensions caused by the aforementioned widespread preference falsification, economic stagnation, and elite indifference. The Soviet union, like a nuclear reactor with the control rods removed, promptly melted down.</p>
      <p>Is the US in the early stages of the same phenomenon? Nobody really believes in the system anymore: the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_civil_religion">"American civil religion"</a> is dead. We're living under the rule of an out-of-touch elite. Preference falsification (enforced via Twitter mobs, Reddit moderators, and corporate HR departments, not the KGB) is rampant. There doesn't seem to be a belief in the legitimacy of the current system either on the left or the right. What happens when we run out of ideologically-reliable old people? Will the likes of AOC and Matt Gaetz be our Gorbachevs?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>