<post>
  <author>twinksforsharia</author>
  <date>2020-03-06T01:30:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjlzphn/</link>
  <title>Why Coronavirus Will Likely Recur</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I keep seeing people in the community saying that SARS-nCoV2 can't stick around and become a recurring seasonal virus like the flu because the flu is actually many different viruses, and it's irritating me because it's wrong.</p>
      <p>Seasonal flus in the modern era are always H1N1, H1N2, or H3N2 (or influenza B, which is a different but related species). Prior to the emergence of H3N2, H2N2 was also a seasonal strain, but it seems to have died out. Any hemagglutinin (the H in the shorthand) variants coded higher than H3 or neuraminidase (the N) higher than N2 are animal strains that aren't transmissible between humans, and only infect humans under rare circumstances (like being a farmer of sick ducks).</p>
      <p>Where did these seasonal flu strains come from? Well, from pandemics. Like the one we're experiencing right now. After the 1918 Spanish flu pandemic, which came from a zoonotic transmission event from pigs to humans, H1N1 adapted to living in humans and became a circulating seasonal virus that crops up occasionally to the present day. In 1957, a second flu, H2N2, (probably) jumped from pigs into humans causing another pandemic known as the Asian flu. It then also adapted to circulating in humans and became a seasonal virus until 1968, when it reinfected a pig, recombined with an avian virus that also infected that pig, became H3N2, jumped back to humans, and then caused another pandemic before becoming the predominant seasonal flu strain for the following 40 years, until 2009, when our old friend H1N1 did some recombining with no fewer than three other viruses in a pig and triggered yet another pandemic!</p>
      <p>So if you got the flu this year, it wasn't influenza B, and you're not an Asian poultry farmer, there's a 100% chance that it's a direct evolutionary descendent of one of these pandemic strains which, as in the case of H3N2, can be perfectly happy mutating a little bit every year and infecting people over and over for 50 years. Unless we're lucky and SARS-nCoV2 is particularly bad at immune evasion, it can and in my opinion will do the exact same thing that pandemic flus do. If that's not enough to convince you, consider that there are already three different coronaviruses endemic to humans with exactly that life strategy of recurrent seasonal infection combined with frequent mutation for immune evasion.</p>
      <p>Also there are not only two variants of SARS-nCoV2. On average it's mutating one base pair for every two transmissions. I know which <a href="https://academic.oup.com/nsr/advance-article/doi/10.1093/nsr/nwaa036/5775463?searchresult=1">paper you're referencing</a>, and I have no idea why it's getting such play in the media. My theory is that the word mutation scares people. What they found is that there was an early split in the virus' lineage back in Wuhan characterized by two mutations that are in total linkage disequilibrium, meaning those two strains have not recombined since. Whether those two mutations do anything or mean anything or are antigenically distinct from one another is a complete unknown. There have been (number of transmissions/2) mutations in the total population of the virus, and there will continue to be more. Given enough transmissions, eventually one of them will figure out how to become antigenically distinct, if it hasn't already.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>