<post>
  <author>VelveteenAmbush</author>
  <date>2020-03-05T01:15:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjimkzj/</link>
  <title>Smuggling In Open Borders</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Oh no? <em>Definitely</em> not for open borders or anything like that! But, here's one of <a href="https://joebiden.com/immigration/">Biden's policy positions</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>End Trump’s detrimental asylum policies. The Statue of Liberty has long been a beacon to people “yearning to breathe free” around the world — including asylum-seekers and refugees. But the Trump Administration has worked against this tradition to drastically restrict access to asylum in the U.S., including imposing additional restrictions on anyone traveling through Mexico or Guatemala; attempting to prevent victims of gang and domestic violence from receiving asylum; systematically prosecuting adult asylum seekers for misdemeanor illegal entry; and severely limiting the ability of members of the LGBTQ community, an especially vulnerable group in many parts of the world, from qualifying for asylum as members of a “particular social group.” Biden will end these policies, starting with Trump’s Migrant Protection Protocols, and restore our asylum laws so that they do what they should be designed to do–protect people fleeing persecution and who cannot return home safely. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Biden will make sure that anyone who sets foot on American soil can say the word "asylum!" and immediately be granted a 9+-month stay in America while their case is heard. During this time, they'll be allowed to get a job and form connections with the community. After this time, they can simply not show up for their hearing, and then they're just ordinary illegal immigrants living in the shadows.</p>
      <p>But wait, can't they be deported at that point? Here's his answer:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>There are approximately 1.7 million undocumented immigrants from Asia in the U.S., as well as hundreds of thousands from Europe, the Middle East, Africa, and the Caribbean. Biden will immediately begin working with Congress to modernize our system, with a priority on keeping families together by providing a roadmap to citizenship for nearly 11 million undocumented immigrants; growing our economy and expanding economic opportunity across the country by improving and increasing opportunities for legal immigration; and preserve the longstanding directive of our immigration system to reunite families and enhance our diversity.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Ah, but that relies on Congress. Surely they won't agree to grant citizenship to more than 10 million illegal aliens. We can always support Biden for President on the theory that Congress will overrule his policy preferences, right? And assuming they block him, won't these bad-faith asylum seekers will be subject to deportation?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>President Biden will end workplace raids to ensure that threats based on workers’ status do not interfere with their ability to organize and improve their wages and working conditions. He will also protect sensitive locations from immigration enforcement actions. No one should be afraid to seek medical attention, go to school, their job, or their place of worship for fear of an immigration enforcement action.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>So basically, as long as they're seeking medical attention, going to school, their job, or their place of worship, they should be safe from deportation. How do they get deported, then? Like, when they go to the grocery store? Or is that also going to be a "sensitive location"?</p>
      <p>But let's back up a step. How will they make their claim for asylum? Well, good news... asylum <em>statutes</em> are meant to protect <em>specific categories</em> of individuals (race, religion, etc.) who are persecuted <em>on that basis</em> by their <em>state</em>, but Joe Biden will manage an end run around those statutory restrictions by</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>reinstat[ing] explicit asylum protections — rescinded by the Trump Administration —for domestic violence and sexual violence survivors whose home governments cannot or will not protect them.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>So if you know enough to (1) say the word "asylum" when you reach the border, and (2) during your hearing, claim that someone beat you up, or that someone raped you, in a different country far away, with the evidence lost to the vagaries of distance and decay, then it really isn't clear to me how an immigration court under the Biden administration will be able to deny your asylum claim.</p>
      <p>But isn't this kind of a crazy conspiracy theory that I'm spinning here? Sure, maybe an illegal alien will understand to say the word "asylum" when he gets here, and sure, maybe it would be easy for a <em>theoretical machiavellian genius</em> to come up with a bunch of spurious legal arguments to entitle him to asylum protections in circumvention of the plain text and purpose of the asylum laws ("even though I have no evidence, I promise I was in fear of gang violence!"), how on earth could a normal illegal immigrant, a median huddler-in-masses, a standard-issue member of the wretched refuse, come up with a legal strategy like that? Well, I'm glad you asked!</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>End prolonged detention and reinvest in a case management program. The Trump Administration has sought to circumvent the Flores agreement and hold children in detention indefinitely. But proven alternatives to detention and non-profit case management programs, which <strong>support migrants as they navigate their legal obligations</strong>, are the best way to ensure that they attend all required immigration appointments.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Does anyone really doubt where this ends up? That literally any warm body would be able to approach our border, say the word "asylum," receive a monthslong stay during which they get careful legal coaching and, in the end, be pretty much guaranteed the ability to spend the rest of his life here? Have children here and then use those children as the basis on which to receive citizenship under the guise of "family reunification"? And then pull in your extended family the same way?</p>
      <p>Isn't this just open borders with extra steps?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>