<post>
  <author>Armlegx218</author>
  <date>2020-05-11T14:26:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ghhern/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_11_2020/fq9ub41/</link>
  <title>What Do Americans Want From a President?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>What exactly do Americans <em>expect</em> from a president? I mean: what kind of government failures would actively disqualify a sitting president in the eyes of both parties as opposed to merely throwing some vague shade on him?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>These are good questions, and the answers have an interesting dependency.  Simply put: everything, therefore nothing.</p>
      <p>The American people, the vast majority of them (even the ones who literally know better because it is their job) want an accountable king.  They want this because Congress has neglected its duty to pass laws other than budgets and delegated as much authority as possible to the administrative agencies as possible.  This gives congressmen more time to fund raise and bloviate on TV so they can be reelected, while at the same time avoiding taking any stances which might be likely to a nominal supporter upset.  People should be mad at Congress, but congress is diffuse: there are two chambers, and a total of 535 people involved, and due to the nature of the beast - everyone likes <strong>their</strong> congressperson, but hates the institution.  You can't make it do anything, and there isn't anywhere to push to hold anyone accountable for anything because it is just a big pile of jello and "the buck" can be endlessly passed around - even somewhat honestly.</p>
      <p>So as a somewhat rational response, the executive has grown exponentially.  It now has the ability to make a lot of "laws" (rules, executive orders) on its own, without involving congress.  People are also ignorant about how budgets and budgeting processes work, and think that there is just a big pile of money sitting around that can be shuffled as needs and situations change.  Why didn't you buy  shit ton of PPE back in January when it would have be useful?  It wasn't in the budget, and Congress had not allocated money to do so.</p>
      <p>People are also ignorant of the structure of our government and that due to having a federal system, some things are the national government's responsibility, and others are the states'.  Many things domestically, are ultimately the state's responsibility (in the present situation, Public Health is a state and county level response, the Federal Government primarily is there to provide guidance).  The national media finds it much more convenient (and cheaper, and no need to develop local expertise) to report on national politics rather than what is happening in 50 diverse states.  They are all over the place, like herding cats! It is impossible to create a narrative.</p>
      <p>So because the reality of the situation is really complex and hard to get a good understanding of, everyone looks to the president for the answers - even when he shouldn't or doesn't have the power to address the situation.  Which may lead to the executive grabbing that power to be able to address the ask.  So, we look to the president for everything.  Because this is really useful for the other players involved (Congress, sometimes the states), no one tries to stop it, because that requires taking responsibility for it.  This might be a failure for you, and next time it might be a failure for me, but the system works well for both of us. Calling it out might make it hard to get reelected.  Better to let the lightning rod take all the heat.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>