<post>
  <author>d357r0y3r</author>
  <date>2020-05-11T19:58:35Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ghhern/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_11_2020/fqaxs4j/</link>
  <title>Starting A Conversation: Dating from the Wrong Side of a "Tribe"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>How is dating supposed to work when you're on the wrong side of the culture war inside of your "tribe"?</p>
      <p>I'm back into dating after an LTR ended, and I get decent matches/dates on the apps. My matches tend to be successful, professional women, usually grads/post-grads/doctors. They're sometimes attractive, interesting people that I could see myself getting to know better. The problem, as you might expect, is these women are usually somewhere between "registered Democrat" and "actual communist." They may have one or more photos of them at a women's march holding a sign.</p>
      <p>As someone with, uh...heterodox political leanings, I have a couple of possible strategies to choose from that I know of. My current chosen strategy is to simply mark myself as "moderate" and avoid explosive topics. It's rare that a woman starts drilling me on my voter registration or requires my anti-Trump allegiance. This strategy seems to work well as far as getting dates or short-term relationships, but at some point, it's going to slip out that maybe I sort of don't think Trump is the worst thing that has ever happened to this country. It's certainly going to slip out that I don't think white women in this country are particularly oppressed.</p>
      <p>So what are the other options? Actual conservative women aren't interested in me, and I doubt I'm interested in them. At least where I live, the out-and-out conservative women are red tribe types that want guys holding fish and posing next to deer carcasses. They want you to have a relationship with Jesus Christ. I'm so incompatible with this tribe that it's probably not even worth thinking about.</p>
      <p>From my perspective, strategy #1 is the only viable one. In my head, it feels a little dishonest, but I also tend to think that these (allegedly) deeply held political values are really just ginned-up hysteria produced by the culture war - the "values" are just fashion accessories. It's the easiest possible thing to be a generic progressive person in my social strata. Like, my match may <em>say</em> they want a pussy-hat wearing male feminist that goes to the Women's March with them but do they <em>really</em>?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>