<post>
  <author>dnkndnts</author>
  <date>2020-05-12T11:09:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ghhern/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_11_2020/fqd6vzi/</link>
  <title>Interalized Legal Formalism in Protestant Cultures</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Why do whites bear a collective guilt/burden for the actions of other whites, but blacks don't bear such a collective burden (even though black on white crime is far more common than the reverse?)</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Nobody is doing this to white people. White people do this to themselves.</p>
      <p>This is because, for whatever reason, whites - and honestly not even whites, it's mostly just protestants - internalize the legal formalism much more than other groups. Non-protestant cultures almost universally accept the legal formalism for what it is: a system of power you appeal to to try to get what you want. If the system is in your way, you lie and misdirect and complain until it stops annoying you and your tribe. If your cousin Jamal gets arrested, it <em>doesn't matter</em> if he did the thing the system is accusing him of - what matters is fuck the system because Jamal is a brother and anyone against him is against us.</p>
      <p>The idea that the system is some paragon of moral virtue and that it is <em>good</em> for you to tattle on your friends and family who violate the Law is just <em>foreign</em> to most cultures. Like if you go to Turkey or Russia or Arabia and talk like that, people would literally smack you for being such an idiot. Even the police themselves would think you're a fool.</p>
      <p>But in protestant cultures (and their mutant derivatives), trust is so high that people actually believe in the moral fortitude of the system, and when the system sins, it's as if <em>they</em> sinned, and the penance required is <em>their</em> penance. In a culture where the system is just an annoying bureaucratic power structure with no serious moral imperative, nobody gives a shit - okay, so the system did something awful to you, I can agree that sucks, but the idea that I'm somehow vicariously culpable doesn't even occur to me as a thought to think, because the system is not an external avatar of my conscience. It's just a cold, dead power structure, nothing more.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>