<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-05-15T22:24:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ghhern/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_11_2020/fqrc3ec/</link>
  <title>China's Precarious Position</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Woohoo, some geopolitics in this sub at last! Quick hot take (literally, I’m in the bath). China is in a very precarious position for multiple reasons and the US can run a soft version of containment on China far more easily than was the case for the Soviet Union.</p>
      <p>First, China is desperately short of allies and is surrounded by strategic competitors - India, Japan, Vietnam, the Philippines etc. all stand to lose if China gains regional supremacy, and are better off with the American-led status quo. This is why it’s critical for America right now more than ever to be the global “adult in the room” and use its soft power effectively. China’s only major allies are Russia and Pakistan, but both have very severe internal problems of their own.</p>
      <p>Second, unlike the Soviet Union or the US, China doesn’t have a compelling ideological export. It’s not promising to free anyone from colonialism or bourgeois capitalism. As matters stand, its foreign policy is predicated on a nationalist and chauvinist attitude that doesn’t extend to eg providing much in the way of disaster relief to its neighbours (and when it does, it comes with strings galore). At most, it can flash cash around, but its investments across the developing world face massive and probably justified suspicion.</p>
      <p>Third, it has serious economic worries of its own, specifically in overcoming the middle income trap without allowing for liberalisation of both the economic and political kind. It has problems attracting and retaining global talent and investors face political dangers of the kind that don’t exist in the US to anything like the same degree. Its economic model so far has been heavily based on export-led catch up growth after a century of underinvestment, but this has led to incredibly high expectations of continued growth among its middle classes.</p>
      <p>That’s all unsourced and expansive claims (apologies - I’m on my phone in the bath, as I say), and I have massive uncertainties concerning the future of China. But the most likely scenario to me right now is one that I think the market underprices, namely a trend towards economic stagnation, increasing authoritarianism, and increasing resentment and division among the Chinese middle classes, even while the rest of SEA takes on an increasing proportion of China’s export business. America has to walk a fine line here between scaring the world by sabre rattling while also reassuring regional allies that it’s willing to stand up to China on their behalf and gently tightening the screws.</p>
      <p>I should finally note in closing that I consider myself broadly a Sinophile, and have massive respect for China’s history and culture. But between the authoritarianism of Xi Jinping and an overconfident and overly entitled sense of destined national greatness, I think the country’s veered off the track a bit in the last decade, and a painful period of correction is in order. If the US manages things carefully serious conflict will be avoided and China can set itself back on a course towards a harmonious rise to its natural status as one of several true global heavyweight powers. But I’d predict that the US will retain the title of global hegemon fairly comfortably for several decades to come.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>