<post>
  <author>greatjasoni</author>
  <date>2020-05-18T15:56:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glwy7k/quality_contributions_report_for_may_12_2020/fr1cn9j/</link>
  <title>A Spiritually Sick Audience Admires Tony Soprano</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I think its quite clear that Jabba is more sinful. Yet he seems much more spiritually healthy. Id much rather my kid grows up to be like him than one of those organbags.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Jabba's not particularly fleshed out beyond as a cartoonish archetypal stand in for some sins. We don't see or <em>feel</em> the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a5bzImAl5JQ">consequences of his sin</a> so much as we see Carrie Fischer on a leash. Instead I'd direct this discussion to the man that keeps me sane under quarantine, Tony Soprano. (SPOILERS)</p>
      <p>Tony is vital, not lacking in balls, wise, loyal, etc. Certainly has more admirable qualities than Jabba. But in no way would I want my kid to be like him. He's absolutely disgusting. But it's not necessarily because of his behavior: murder on a regular basis, drug and sex trafficking, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZpdzI7z2Cxo">racism</a>, enabling demonic figures like <a href="https://youtu.be/eYDbiodGMKk">Ralph Ciffareto</a> (Joe Pantoliano has talked about how women would come up to him in the street and ask to feel his arms after that scene), adultery, etc. I usually root for him when he does all of those things. (Hell, I <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rm7sTC214wQ">root for Ralph</a>.) To be clear, the behavior is what makes him bad and not to be emulated. Actions matter more than intentions. But our reactions to them and what we find admirable or worth emulating, don't necessarily reflect that. Part of the argument is that it's because of our culture, but that's hard to prove.</p>
      <p>I feel a primal rush when Tony sends <a href="https://youtu.be/Ywnn0jNmDIw">Furio</a> into the delinquent massage parlor to collect. Tony waits in the car puffing a cigar while Furio beats a woman half to death and cripples a guy. Read the youtube comments. They're all about how badass Furio and Tony are, how he "seems like a Don," how they wish Furio had more scenes like this, how cool it is that Tony's reaction to the gunshot is to smile. I smile with him every time I watch the scene.</p>
      <p>This doesn't show Tony is spiritually healthy. It shows that the audience is sick. What they admire is power because there's nothing else left to.</p>
      <p>Deep down all that strength that we are prone to admire comes from a deep insecurity and he is most seemingly despicable when he shows that. There's a great scene where he can't stand that his sister is happy and finally coping with her anger issues so he conjures up the most hurtful statement possible out of <a href="https://youtu.be/biugRUTkh1c">sheer spite</a> just to see her crack. Or when he loses the fight with Bobby, which he <a href="https://youtu.be/W6ktF-y-hPU">hilariously</a> povoked, he spends the next week <a href="https://youtu.be/981wKsfogdg">obsessing</a> over it, insisting everyone else has lost respect for him, and he ends up making Bobby kill somebody as petty revenge. You beat me in a fight so I'm going to stain your soul by making you a murderer. He does something similar when he comes out of the hospital and thinks he's losing face, so he <a href="https://youtu.be/eviIklReqYE">provokes a fight</a> with the strongest looking guy in the crew in front of everyone, abuses his position as boss to win (not to mention the sucker punch), and then sociopathically grins to himself in the mirror while he's puking up blood. I also love when he takes out his <a href="https://youtu.be/CP6GbPBUVnk">degenerate gambling</a> on his wife. Just to hammer home the point about audience reaction: I can't watch any of this without laughing my ass off. Here's him derailing a therapy session to insist how <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UmY6oJmUT7s">not gay</a> he is. </p>
      <p>He's not even a particularly good boss. At least Jabba is minimally competent. Tony drives half his crew to rat, bungles multiple opportunities to avert war because of his own ego, ruins the multi million dollar development deal because he was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=chjCnTzkjOE">jealous over an ex</a> like a teenager, and ultimately he and all his associates pay the ultimate price for his incompetence. But watch the show and listen to your own emotional <a href="https://thelastpsychiatrist.com/2009/10/you_want_to_be_don_draper_you.html">sense of what is or isn't admirable</a> and you'll never notice how pathetic he is.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://youtu.be/PrwtSL4lpoQ">https://youtu.be/PrwtSL4lpoQ</a>
      </p>
      <p>I think Dr. Melfi is an incompetent who enables a mass murdering sociopath but I side with her in the above linked scene. This quote from her husband is extremely relevant here, and this is the point where she finally starts to accept it.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"Call him a patient, man's a criminal, Jennifer. And after a while, finally you're gonna get beyond psychotherapy with its cheesy moral relativism, finally you're gonna get to good and evil. And he's evil."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Tony <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2Wny96-K5y0">can't stand his son</a>, and neither can I as the viewer. But Tony is so weak he can't even  comprehend what Melfi is saying to him because he's too obsessed with his own failure to live up to his dads standards. Later we see <a href="https://youtu.be/ItzvcsD2vFE">AJ's suicide attempt</a> and Tony's immediate reaction is anger and disgust, any sense of nurturing seeps in after. I don't actually have any issues with Tony there but it's a great scene. AJ's either too dumb or too weak to commit suicide properly, the show leaves this ambiguous, but at least it gets his dads attention. The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wj5CM4nKwNw">reaction of his crew</a> is a pretty good scene too.</p>
      <p>AJ is sort of like the fatsacks, but he has this <a href="https://youtu.be/Dnyp8ya0Y8U?t=103">pseudomoralistic</a> political streak that he uses to escape from the reality of his own <a href="https://youtu.be/IaGW3qVjI4I">failure</a>. In some ways I actually admire the fatsacks more because they don't think of themselves as failures. (Although I haven't actually seen the movie in over a decade.) They're perfectly happy to enjoy their lifestyle. AJ is most admirable when he's giggling in front of that computer screen. At least there's no pretense. You don't get the same rush as the Tony/Furio scene when he's complicit in a <a href="https://youtu.be/-6UoQER02-g">hate crime</a> or <a href="https://youtu.be/Xe_vFGty7xs">mutilating a kids food with acid</a>. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The reason this doesnt lead to the Wall-E situation is that the Will is inherently directed outward, or as in the original formulation, a Will to power</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The argument in the post is that it already has. We don't live in a world of Goethes we live in a world of AJs. I'd personally argue that any notion of will directedness makes a mechanistic worldview incoherent as it would have to originate from the non material and further that the notion of "outward" can only be "out of being" which would necessitate something beyond the category of being and thus uniquely imply God. It's a classic baby/bathwater issue that Nietzsche was so keen to point out about metaphysics in general while somehow leaving this exempt. But to flesh any of that out is a side issue and better left to our other discussion which I'm still formulating a response to as the language has to be more precise. Instead I'd just say will to power is exactly what's wrong with Tony Soprano. That's all he has. I'll end with the <a href="https://youtu.be/bzVeLjj6Ao8">best scene in the entire show</a> (speaking of psychotherapists) as his brutal honesty captures what I'm trying to say much better than I ever could.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>