<post>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2020-05-12T19:47:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ghhern/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_11_2020/fqesfqn/</link>
  <title>Distorted Reality and the Cultural Salience of the Arbery Story </title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I've gotta say, even as an attorney I find the bizarre fixation on the legal minutia of this case to be absurdly jejune. It's the exact equivalent, to me, of if the crux of the discussion over the Jussie Smollet fiasco had centered around probing forays into the subtleties of postal fraud. Yes, that may be the consequential factor in terms of the legal outcome, but it has nothing to do with why it's a subject of national conversation</p>
      <p>If every single aspect of this fact pattern had been the same except that the men with guns confronting Arbury for trespass and suspected burglary were black, absolutely nobody would be talking about this. Armed black men confront and kill one another over territorial oversteps, dominance disputes, and material possessions literally every single day in this country. There are 500 homicides a year in the city of Chicago alone. <em>Nobody</em>, to a reasonable approximation, commenting on this topic here or elsewhere actually knows or cares about the intricacies of Georgia law regarding the 'immediate knowledge' predicate of a lawful citizen's arrest or whether drawing or brandishing is the standard for aggravated assault. This entire discussion, across multiple threads now, is a pat little intellectual exercise that completely misses the point of the cultural salience of this topic</p>
      <p>This is a story about race. The demonstrators, activists, media figures, celebs, NAACP, SPLC, and social media affiliation signalers are <strong>not</strong> weighing in on this case because they have a strong interest in provincial citizen's arrest prerequisites. The Arbury family attorneys have called the incident a "<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2020/may/07/ahmaud-arbery-parents-call-for-arrests-killing-song-daily-jog">lynching</a>", which was repeated by AOC who added that Arbery was "<a href="https://www.newsweek.com/alexandria-ocasio-cortez-says-ahmaud-arbery-was-murdered-being-black-demands-justice-family-1502546">murdered for being black</a>". Oscar-winner Viola Davis posted a Georgia NAACP image stating that Arbury was "<a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/B_28lWEB9r4/?utm_source=ig_embed">murdered by two white supremacists</a>". The DOJ is assessing whether to bring <a href="https://kadn.com/doj-considering-whether-to-pursue-hate-crime-charges-in-killing-of-ahmaud-arbery/">federal hate crime charges</a>. LeBron James best distilled the zeitgeist surrounding the incident with a ludicrous rant shouting "<a href="https://twitter.com/KingJames/status/1258156220969398272?s=20">We’re literally hunted EVERYDAY/EVERYTIME we step foot outside the comfort of our homes! Can’t even go for a damn jog man! [...] #StayWoke #ProfiledCauseWeAreSimplyBlack</a>". Gabrielle Union reiterated the sentiment, lamenting that her followers don't "<a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/B_3x1g4Jk8c/?utm_source=ig_embed">see us worthy of our breath</a>"</p>
      <p>The cultural salience of this story is that it advances a narrative that racism is such an enduring and pronounced force in this country that black Americans are murdered by violent racist whites simply for the color of their skin, that they live in such an environment of (warranted) fear of whites that they cannot leave the house for so much as a jog without risking their very lives. This is completely absurd. Set aside the fact that at the object-level Ahmaud Arbery was <em>pursued</em> because he was a <a href="https://twitter.com/Timcast/status/1259826280297459712?s=20">serial trespasser</a> and possible burglar who aroused reasonable suspicion from multiple neighbors by repeatedly prowling private residence construction sites uninvited, and who was <em>killed</em> because he violently and impulsively assailed the visibly armed men attempting to question him; ignore entirely that Arbery had <a href="https://www.news4jax.com/news/2013/12/09/police-man-brought-gun-to-high-school-basketball-game/">previously fled lawful pursuit by uniformed police</a> while armed, during which two officers were injured, and that he was a <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/05/08/us/ahmaud-arbery-mcmichael-arrests-friday/index.html">convicted thief</a> whom the elder McMichael had previously helped prosecute. None of that matters, because even if none of that were true the narrative being pushed here is <em>insane</em></p>
      <p>There is <strong>not</strong> an epidemic of white-on-black violence in this country, and every single conceivable stat reinforces this simple truth. Black-on-white homicides persistently <a href="https://www.usnews.com/dims4/USNEWS/0b7f032/2147483647/resize/970x/quality/85/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fmedia.beam.usnews.com%2Fc0%2F9d%2F02f99d3240a5954bc5c688f0cddc%2F160929-interracialkillings-graphic.png">more than double</a> white-on-black homicides as far as interracial killings go, and <a href="https://www.politifact.com/article/2015/may/21/updated-look-statistics-black-black-murders/">approximately 90% of homicides are intraracial</a>. The black homicide rate is approximately 8x the white homicide rate; <a href="https://www.bjs.gov/content/pub/pdf/htus8008.pdf">despite making only making up 13% of the American population, blacks are routinely responsible for approximately 50% of all homicides</a>. This data is all publicly available in the form of <a href="https://ucr.fbi.gov/crime-in-the-u.s/2017/crime-in-the-u.s.-2017/tables/expanded-homicide-data-table-6.xls">yearly FBI reports</a>, and it should be noted that white crime is overstated with regard to commonly conceptualized racial categories as most stats do not distinguish <a href="https://www.bjs.gov/content/pub/pdf/rhovo1215.pdf">higher crime latinos from non-hispanic whites</a>. With that in mind, the <a href="https://ucr.fbi.gov/crime-in-the-u.s/2017/crime-in-the-u.s.-2017/tables/table-43">FBI reports of tables for arrests for violent crimes</a> show similar trends, with blacks arrested for violent crimes at a rate of approximately 4x [whites + latinos] per share of the population. All of this is corroborated by the <a href="https://www.bjs.gov/content/pub/pdf/rhovo1215.pdf">National Crime Victimization Survey</a>, which preempts dismissals based on racial disparities in arrests</p>
      <p>Suffice it to say, the world LeBron describes where blacks are hunted and preyed upon by violent whites exists only in his head, but this delusion is perpetuated by the media using the <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/09/16/cardiologists-and-chinese-robbers/">Chinese Robber Fallacy</a> to elevate comparatively rare white-on-black violence cases like this one while steadfastly ignoring comparatively ubiquitous black-on-black violence and black-on-white violence, which, again, is consistently a far greater issue than the inverse. When white people actually are "hunted" when they "leave the comfort and safety of [their] homes" - like, for instance, this case from last Friday where <a href="https://baltimore.cbslocal.com/2020/05/10/delaware-cemetery-shooting-latest-suspect-identified-sheldon-francis/">a black suspect gunned down an octogenarian white couple at a veterans' cemetery</a> for no discernible reason - it is completely overlooked. This, in concert with <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2017/01/03/the-surprising-racial-and-gender-bias-in-law-and-order/">mass media massively misrepresenting the races of criminals</a>, gives the uninformed masses a completely distorted (and many would suggest deliberately constructed*) view of our racial reality</p>
      <p>* Sunday's arrest of a black suspect who used <a href="https://www.firstcoastnews.com/article/news/crime/mugshot-released-for-suspect-arrested-in-connection-to-threats-against-ahmaud-arbery-protests/77-b2e2ec69-2463-47c6-9d95-fe0a8cef8a44">a fake Facebook account to issue hoax threats</a> against the demonstrators protesting the Arbery killing serves to demonstrate that at least some explicitly recognize the utility of engendering a false sense of victimhood</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>