<post>
  <author>Stefferi</author>
  <date>2020-05-12T20:20:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ghhern/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_11_2020/fqewna1/</link>
  <title>American Conservatism Is a House Built Against Itself</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Somewhere around the 40s, United States made a final commitment to turn from a parochial nation mostly watching over its interests in the the Western Hemisphere to truly the leading nation on Earth, the global policeman. This was forced by a number of factors, like the Second World War and the Cold War. </p>
      <p>On the course of the latter event, US was faced with an opponent that could lay a good claim to the hearts and minds of large sectors on Earth by presenting itself as a face of progress; secular and rational instead of religious and obscurantist, internationalist and anti-colonial instead of racist and colonial, equal system serving the workers instead of a hierarchical system serving the workers and capitalists. Of course a large part of that narrative on part of the Soviets was a smokescreen, but it still presented an extremely beguiling offer to many peoples, including the vast amounts of people of color then under colonialism.</p>
      <p>This effectively meant that US, as the leading nation of the other block, had to start rethinking how to counter this, and fast. It had already made some headway in creating a kindler, gentler version of capitalism that could be counterposed to the Soviet system, but the situation down South offered ample opportunities for Soviets to recruit adherents in the Third World; when you had Soviets declaring that they oppose racists and sheriffs firehosing black people in Alabama, which of these will appeal to the decolonized Africans?</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, what obviously also worried Americans was that as societies were secularizing, educated people often saw atheism and communism as a package deal; first you leave the church, then you join the Party as the obvious representative of the most popular materialist ideology around. This happened not only in, for instance, European countries, but even the US itself.</p>
      <p>This meant that America's international role required a top-down process of creating an antiracist, secular, at least somewhat welfare-statist leading ideology for the United States to hold at least some ground in the ideological combat against the Soviet Union. Of course, despite Soviet advances, much of the world - and the US - was still religious, so particularly the secular part caused a considerable amount of trouble, and US had to still rely on religious, reactionary and racist factions around the world for the concrete dirty work of opposing the Soviets, but in fits and bounds, this project advanced. </p>
      <p>Eventual results include desegregation, Great Society and various decisions striking down religiously-included restrictions on speech, abortion and so on - all the parts of post-WW2 American liberalism that we know. All of this worked beautifully, as more and more educated people around the world started to find America more attractive than the Soviet Union, and eventually even the Soviet leadership was essentially won over, which then led to the events that brought Soviet Union down. Even after the victory of the Soviets, the same processes have continued, partly out of their own force and partly since they continue to essentially form the ideological justification that underpins America's globally dominant position, one way or another. Many of the same developments happened in Europe at the same time, often in mutual interaction with American developments.</p>
      <p>American conservatism has, at least since the 70s, been essentially built on the basis of reacting against the top-down processes that have created this liberal development, ie. opposing various laws meant to combat the inequality of racial and ethnic groups, opposing secularization and the resultant developments (gay rights etc.) and so on. However, at the same time, American conservatives would like to maintain America's dominant position and thus, globally, more often than not end up leaning to the same progressive narratives as the liberals (see, for instance, Trump taking the credit for advancing gay rights globally). </p>
      <p>Thus, American conservatism is a house built against itself and cannot stand. It can get into power by campaigning against top-down liberalism, but then cannot bring itself to actually roll back liberalism's gains out of fear that the whole carefully built foreign policy edifice guaranteeing America's power would crash down.</p>
      <p>Of course, it's possible that everything will change in some way after people fully realize, for instance, that globally speaking secularization is probably not advancing but on the retreat and increasingly major nations like Russia and India are ruled by regimes that specifically consider Western liberalism to not be something to look up to but something to combat, but we'll see what the coming decades offer.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>