<post>
  <author>Time_To_Poast</author>
  <date>2020-05-13T09:38:02Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ghhern/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_11_2020/fqgzlh8/</link>
  <title>Mottes and Baileys of "Believe All Women"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Strong disagree. I think I remember someone here writing a great post on "distributed Motte and Bailey" or something, but I can't find it, so I will just reiterate it (but worse) in my own words.</p>
      <p>The main point about the Motte and Bailey doctrine isn't that a single person is being hypocritical or dishonest. The insight given by M&amp;B is that sometimes, people will defend arguments that are weak (but leads to a conclusion they want) by playing word-games and pretending that any counterarguments are arguing against a much more moderate and reasonable stance that is superficially similar.</p>
      <p>It's valuable to point out a M&amp;B because it prevents the people arguing for the extreme position from getting away with it by "smuggling" it with the reasonable stance.</p>
      <p>Therefore, M&amp;B concept can have great utility even if no single person is arguing both sides: One group of people can make the reasonable stance popular and legitimate in the eyes of the public, while another group can utilize this new legitimacy to extend the argument further under the guise of the first position. This doesn't need to be coordinated in any way. Then, when people criticize the bailey, even the people arguing for the motte will argue in its defense, either because they actually agree with the more extreme stance, or because they don't realize they are defending a slightly different argument. Thus the discourse is functionally identical to any other case of M&amp;B.</p>
      <p>The point of invoking the concept of M&amp;B is to make it clear that bad actors are taking the reasonable stance and running with it, and if you are one of the moderate people, you should <strong>at least</strong> not take criticism of the bailey as criticism of the motte.</p>
      <hr />
      <blockquote>
        <p>If genuine intra-tribe disagreement is indistinguishable from motte/bailey, then what's the point of the concept. That the piece was published in Elle should indicate that the target audience for it was intra-group.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'm not sure I'm reading you right, but the Elle article is absolutely not intra-group disagreement. It's disagreeing with Bari Weiss, who is outgroup. The article itself is reaffirming not only the motte, but also the bailey: "False accusations is a non-issue, and any criticism of 'Believe Women' [which can be both M&amp;B] is concern trolling". Actually, the article <em>itself</em> is kinda M&amp;B-ing in the third and fourth paragraphs by conflating people being concerned about false rape accusations (arguing against the bailey) with people who are guilty of actual sexual harrassment and assault (being opposed to the motte). The last paragraph sums up the message as literally "believe all women":</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“False rape allegations” are nowhere near enough of a threat to justify derailing #MeToo and its quest to bring justice to survivors. False allegations exist—but they’re rare, they’re bizarre, and they’re easy to expose. Sexual violence, meanwhile, is neither rare nor strange. It happens every day, mostly to women. Those facts should bring some solace to any innocent man who is genuinely terrified of being falsely accused. But they also mean that when a normally trustworthy woman gives us an ordinary-sounding account of assault or harassment, she is probably not making it up. <strong>It means, in other words, that you should believe women—not because you have an obligation to ignore the facts, but because the facts say women aren’t lying.</strong></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Motte: Women should be taken seriously when accusing someone of sexual misconduct.</p>
      <p>Bailey: Women don't lie about sexual misconduct.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>