<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-05-18T15:18:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/glv7wt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_18_2020/fr18af1/</link>
  <title>Memes as Postmodern Art</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Having taken a <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ghhern/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_11_2020/fqyj6sk/">brave and controversial stand</a> against modern art as the last thread waned, I find myself suddenly inspired to make a rather roundabout partial defense of it, starting from the skeleton of a comment I made in another forum about a piece of art so good I think it belongs in history textbooks. Many of you have likely seen it already:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://i.redd.it/shsih9u43no41.png">haha protein printer goes brrr</a>
      </p>
      <p>Coronavirus has provided a fascinating reminder: disaster or not, the memes will keep pumping until the end. Not only do we live in a time where <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/eusojf/concerning_the_recent_wuhan_coronavirus_outbreak/ffr8knc/">the disaster that ends the world someday may start with us occasionally glancing at red circles on an online map</a>, we live in a time when a faceless horde will create a wave of jokes around it.</p>
      <p>Will we go down? Maybe. But at least we'll go down chuckling.</p>
      <p>That's what I was thinking about when I made that original comment. My focus now is the sheer amount of context needed to understand what's even going on in that picture.</p>
      <p>You can start with the template itself, the "money printer goes brrr" meme, and that's what I focused on initially. It started when <a href="https://stayhipp.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/brrr-440x240.jpg">the Fed started tinkering with monetary policy</a>, then went through <a href="https://i.kym-cdn.com/photos/images/newsfeed/001/789/676/39a.png">a couple of iterations</a>.</p>
      <p>And <a href="https://i.kym-cdn.com/photos/images/newsfeed/001/789/428/a01.gif">more</a> and <a href="https://imgur.com/5CRiosN">more</a>, as the Fed took <a href="https://twitter.com/moghilemear13/status/1239992005205340161">further measures</a> and the economy kept crashing <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/neoliberal/comments/fknnkg/fed_announces_another_500_billion_operation_for/">regardless</a> (with a side order of <a href="https://i.imgur.com/MxLrrWv.png">electoral politics</a>, even as <a href="https://i.redd.it/9b2mng5ktbn41.png">coronavirus spread further</a>).</p>
      <p>Other than the brilliant coronavirus variant, its peak was probably <a href="https://brrr.money/">brrr.money</a>. And then, as memes do, it spiraled more and more until most of the humor had been beaten out, and it will continue to spread a while longer.</p>
      <p>But not even that would be enough context to really understand it. You could dive into the history of the <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/yes-chad">Yes Chad</a> that was probably its immediate forebear and <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/virgin-vs-chad">its</a><a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/nordic-mediterranean">ancestors</a>, along with <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/wojak-feels-guy">wojaks</a> and I'm sure a whole lot more as well. The whole thing is complex and layered referential humor, such that to someone who's immersed in online trivialities it tends towards the hilarious while it would elicit a shrug at best from disconnected onlookers.</p>
      <p>Oh, and (skillfully rendered cell wojak aside), the piece required no real trainable skill, just a surface-level understanding of the references in play and the current situation along with a clever creative twist. </p>
      <p>In other words, it's a brilliant work of postmodern art.</p>
      <p>I'm not sure the best way to combine my feelings on one hand that high craft is a vital element in the best art with the observation on the other that a work like "protein printer goes brrr (2020)" is a culturally relevant, layered artwork enmeshed in a web of meaning that deserves recognition and preservation, even while it requires no real craftsmanship. I do think the primacy of a few genres of this sort of art is arbitrary, I do think the proliferation of art without high craft causes a fair bit of damage, and I don't have nearly as much fun wandering around a contemporary art museum as I do tracing the origin and mutations of the money printer meme, but when I think about these memes I begin to sympathize with the purveyors of postmodern art.</p>
      <p>EDIT: Of course, this also raises the possibility that the 'correct' prestige level for a postmodern artist is similar to that of a cog in the internet meme machine. Whether this suggests a place for Museums of 4chan or dissolution of contemporary art institutions, I can't say, but I know which option would lead to a more interesting world.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>