<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-04-12T15:54:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mp83aj/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_12_2021/gu9ljgq/</link>
  <title>"Often unsaid, the reason alcohol is so great is because it simply is the superior drug."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Often unsaid, the reason alcohol is so great is because it simply <strong>is the superior drug</strong>, something that becomes more clear to me the more I think about it.</p>
      <p>I honestly prefer alcohol to practically every other drug I can think of, including prescription painkillers, cocaine, LSD, shrooms, MDMA and most of all weed, which I find immensely boring and the preserve of shitty, dull people. If you offered me a glass of decent wine or a line of (perfect quality) coke, I literally can’t think of any occasion in the last decade I’d voluntarily pick the latter. </p>
      <p>Alcohol is loved not just because it’s legal, but because <em>it's the best</em>. To me, weed just makes me feel dazed. Coke makes me a shitty, overly loud conversationalist of unwarranted confidence. Psychedelics take me out of myself in a way I find fundamentally disconcerting. Molly gives me a fake feeling of empathy that leaves me a little dirty afterward. </p>
      <p>Alcohol makes me happy, works in small doses (you don’t need to be drunk/‘high’ on alcohol, or even remotely close, to enjoy it significantly), lubricates conversation without being excessive, delivers its effect quickly and for a decent period without overstaying its welcome and involves a variety of interesting flavors and tastes that add to the experience. Great wines belong with great food. A crisp, light beer after a long day of walking or working. A cocktail against a summer sunset. To me these are the pleasures of life that make alcohol so much better than other drugs that I’ve tried.</p>
      <p>Naturally the best drug will be stickier. It’s the best. Only those who somehow fail to appreciate this obvious fact end up succumbing to other substances.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>