<post>
  <note>Really not sure what to do on context, here. It's very much about and doesn't make sense without the full post above it and a separate post by the same author, but that ends up being more context than actual entry. I've included the majority here, but note that it previously started only at "I find the German public TV...".</note>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2021-04-12T12:56:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mp83aj/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_12_2021/gu8zgxh/</link>
  <title>Independent Media and State Media</title>
  <category>
    <li>media</li>
  </category>
  <context>
    <blockquote><p>Watched some <a href="https://www.ard.de/">public television</a> today. It irritated me, so I come here to vent. But my venting won't do any good to anyone, so instead I re-tell what I saw, hoping to mention both the objective bits and the culture-warry ones. I retell it from memory, having only a list of headlines to go by, not re-watching it again, so please excuse any errors in recollection.</p>
    <p>First came the <a href="https://www.daserste.de/information/politik-weltgeschehen/weltspiegel/index.html">Weltspiegel</a> (World Mirror), a journalistic affair telling us six stories from around the world:</p>
    <ol>
      <li>Serbia's vaccination campaign is completely free and freely available for anyone, even foreigners, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ana_Brnabi%C4%87">prime minister of Serbia</a> and several interviewees state that they just enjoy helping people and hope that the country joins the EU.</li>
      <li>Indian and Bangladeshi researchers, including the <a href="https://www.seruminstitute.com/">Serum Institute</a>, are trying to develop an open-source vaccine because established vaccine manufacturers fear that releasing their business secrets might reduce their profits. Both the narration and several interviewees blame first-world nations for not forcing manufacturer's to go open source.</li>
      <li>Columbian coffee farmers are struggling with climate change burning their crops and introducing new bugs to their plantations. The narration emphasizes just how dear coffee farming is to the people of Columbia, and blames first-world countries for not taking action against climate change.</li>
      <li><a href="https://betteries.com/">A start-up from Berlin</a> takes used electric car batteries and turns them into...batteries. Well, general-purpose batteries. While seemingly solid in and of itself, the idea is somewhat inexplicably heralded as an important contribution to the green energy revolution.</li>
     <li><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ceajmw/book_review_from_third_world_to_first_by_lee_kuan/">Singapore</a>'s public housing system is praised as promoting better multiculturalism, solidarity between different social classes, cleanliness, and generally being a great thing for everyone even if it took some heavy-handed nationalizations of private assets and other state actions to get there. The narration closes by wondering what could be done about high rents in Germany.</li>
      <li>Militias consistent of former policemen are terrorizing Rio de Janeiro by displacing drug dealers and extorting money from the populace. Other than killing people in general and illegally building slipshod housing that seemingly tends to collapse, their biggest crimes are paving over a nature reserve, killing a black female politician, and having some tenuous connection to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jair_Bolsonaro">Jair Bolsonaro, President of Brazil</a>.</li>
    </ol>
    <p>This was then followed by the <a href="https://www.tagesschau.de/multimedia/video/video-848491.html">Tagesschau</a> (Day's View), the gold standard for German public TV daily news. In here were several stories, not all of which will mean much to non-Germans:</p>
    <ol>
      <li>Two big men from the <a href="https://www.cdu.de/">conservative party</a>, Minister-Presidents of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armin_Laschet">North-Rhine Westphalia</a> (also the party leader) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markus_S%C3%B6der">Bavaria</a> (the leader of the Bavarian sub-/sister party) respectively, are vying for the party's candidacy for the post of federal chancellor. You know, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angela_Merkel">Merkel</a>'s chair.</li>
      <li>The <a href="https://www.afd.de/">far-right party</a> got together and compiled their election promises, which include leaving the EU and implementing very strict immigration controls. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bj%C3%B6rn_H%C3%B6cke">The leader</a> of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Fl%C3%BCgel">extra-right wing faction</a> of the party had a complete ban on family reunifications included in the program, regardless of whether it would be legal, as a signal to their voters. The narration calls him an extremist.</li>
      <li>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Districts_of_Germany">Districts</a> and some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/States_of_Germany">States</a> of Germany have vetoed the federal government's latest anti-pandemic measures, which would have, for the first time, mandated uniform measures nation-wide.</li>
      <li>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubertus_Heil">social-democrat federal minister of labor and social affairs</a> aims to mandate that all businesses must provide weekly COVID tests for their employees.</li>
      <li>17,855 new infections today, making for 129 per 100,000 people over the last 7 days.</li>
      <li>Unrest in North Ireland simmers down, politicians ask for a new deal between Great Britain and the EU.</li>
      <li>Blackout in Iranian nuclear power plant, suspicions of sabotage.</li>
      <li>Celebrations for the 60th anniversary of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eichmann_trial">Eichmann trial</a> and Eichmann's subsequent execution.</li>
      <li>Memorial celebrations of the 76th anniversary of the liberation of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buchenwald_concentration_camp">Buchenwald concentration camp</a>.</li>
      <li>Soccer.</li>
      <li>Weather. April is meteorologically confusing as always.</li>
    </ol>
    <p>Please note that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_broadcasting#Germany">German public broadcasting</a> is not tax-funded, but funded by the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beitragsservice_von_ARD,_ZDF_und_Deutschlandradio">Beitragsservice</a> (contribution service), an organization the legal state of which is a mystery to me, which is not a government agency yet is invested with the powers of politely requesting your money, and of just taking it if you don't pay up quickly enough. Whether you consume their broadcasts or not.</p></blockquote>
    <p>Inspired by this, checked out what today's stories are on Hungarian state media. (Since right-wing state bias is less frequent elsewhere.)</p>
    <p>These are my summaries of what the news segments claim (my notes as to what they signify in brackets):</p>
    <p>M1 TV news at 6pm on April 12 (30 minute program).</p>
    <ul>
      <li>In a few days Hungary will reach 3 million vaccinated people. New vaccines arriving tomorrow. [government success]</li>
      <li>Gradual opening in Europe: UK opens pubs, hairdressers. Slovaks and Czechs open their schools. [government opening is reasonable, other countries do it too]</li>
      <li>Critical COVID situation in Romania, no more intensive care beds available in Bucharest [Hungary is doing much better]</li>
      <li>Shooting in Paris: potential mafia retribution [Western Europe is dangerous]</li>
      <li>Textile factory burns down in Saint Petersburg [stuff that happens in Russia is interesting to us]</li>
      <li>Climate change may affect the Carpathian Basin stronger than other parts of Europe, govt sets goal of climate neutrality by 2050. President Áder emphasized the importance of climate change at some conference today. [environmentalism is a pet project of President János Áder]</li>
      <li>New Ford logistics center opens near Budapest with 55 new jobs, speech given by foreign minister [government supports job creation, new things are being built in Hungary, investors like us]</li>
      <li>Opposition politician denies having argued against the Chinese and Russian vaccines, although their party website still says that only those vaccines should be used in Hungary which are approved EU-wide. A few days ago he was vaccinated with the Russian vaccine. -&gt; He campaigned against it, but makes use of it himself. [Opposition wants bad stuff for the people]</li>
      <li>Opposition party DK wants international help to manage the epidemic, through an independent expert body. [Opposition trusts foreigners more]</li>
      <li>Government reaction to the above: the left should rather stop the anti-vaccination campaign. They should immediately revoke their demands to suspend the use of Chinese and Russian vaccines, without which 1 million fewer people would be vaccinated in Hungary today. [Opposition doesn't care about people's health]</li>
      <li>Opposition party LMP wants to rethink opening primary schools, and the govt should follow expert guidance. They say it may pose a risk for unvaccinated parents. [neutral tone]</li>
      <li>The left is creating uncertainty once again, regarding Chinese vaccines. They misinterpret news regarding their efficacy. The left campaigns against the vaccine, while they do vaccinate themselves. (A review of Facebook posts.) [Again, the left doesn't care about people]</li>
      <li>We expose fake news: A fake photo is spreading on Facebook about Minister Semjén, which makes it seem like he shot down some storks, but this is a lie. [Media manipulation is a hot topic, the govt wants to strike first]</li>
      <li>Sport</li>
    </ul>
    <p>The current BIG message that the propaganda machine pushes (there is always one) is summarized in the current slogan-phrase "The Anti-Vaccination Left". That the Hungarian opposition is (or at least was) openly against Chinese and Russian vaccines (in short, they are "anti-vaccination") but they are hypocrites because they accept them when they can get them. If they were leading the country, 1 million Hungarians would not be protected today (of the 3 million total vaccinated).</p>
  </context>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I find the German public TV news shows very patronizing in general.</p>
      <p>Generally everything is very cartoonishly simplified. Environment good, fighting climate change is crucial (yay Greta), nuclear is dangerous. Technocracy good, strong leadership bad. EU great (Freude, schöne Götterfunken), AfD is Nazi, Brexit insane, Trumpists crazy, solidarity great, "common European solution" is the jolly joker silver bullet (which just means big German corporate interest decides what happens), global cooperation, the condescending savior complex towards Eastern EU etc.</p>
      <p>I don't even mean these are all bad things. But the way it is presented is full of platitudes and is very binary: there are these clearly good things and everyone who disagrees just hates human rights and the rule of law. Even newscasters don't hide biases, they make faces and have this smug tone in their voice very often (like as if they think "I can't even believe such people exist"). I find it so strange that many Germans consider this unbiased and independent.</p>
      <p>Sure our state media in Hungary is way worse in the other direction, but there at least nobody thinks it's independent, it's so comically pro-right wing biased it's almost parody. People who like it, like it for being strongly pro-govt. and those who hate it hate it for the same.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>