<post>
  <author>bsbbtnh</author>
  <date>2020-09-10T09:56:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/io1iih/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_07/g4ndcv6/</link>
  <title>Writing Good and Bad Female Characters</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's just bad writing. It's the idea that in order to make a strong female character, you have to add in masculine features and do away with feminine ones. </p>
      <p>Most well written male characters have something in common, which is that they possess stereotypical female characteristics. This accomplishes a few things. First, you have self-imposed barriers. Usually these are some moral foundation which prevents them from killing the bad guys. It prevents the stereotypical 'Mary Sue' that is overpowered and just mows down their enemies with little effort. Otherwise Superman would just kill the bad guys in the first few minutes, and the thing would be over.</p>
      <p>The second is barriers that they have to overcome. A lack of self-confidence, physical weakness (and this can just be weakness in comparison to the villain), doubt, etc. The male character usually starts off without realizing these barriers, and they'll fail at some critical point in the story due to it. Then they have to work to overcome that before they can 'win'.</p>
      <p>The third is that it gives the character human qualities (especially important with superheroes). By humanizing them you allow the audience to connect with the character.</p>
      <p>Now, female characters (not all) have a fatal flaw these days, which is that the writers purposely avoid these pesky female characteristics, because they are viewed as a weakness. If you want to look deeply into it, it's not like these are inherently feminine, but they are likely coded this way because women have historically not been required to overcome them. So it became an innate feature of women, and that's how we associate them. But to remove them completely means that we eliminate the growth of a character.</p>
      <p>You end up with a character that has all the 'bad-ass' male characteristics; strength, fearlessness, leadership, independence. But not morals, loyalty, caring, loving, emotions. Definitely not purity. </p>
      <p>And the thing is, that when you put those ingredients into a blender, what pops out isn't a strong character (male or female). What you get is a generic villain; an asshole; a bitch. Most 'strong, independent woman' characters today are just villains in makeup (literally and figuratively). </p>
      <p>And that's funny too, because one of the most famous 'villains in makeup' is the Joker. In the latest film, they definitely play up those feminine characteristics in his story. In a way, he's a pretty feminine character, because he doesn't even rely on stereotypically male traits like strength. He relies more on manipulating, which codes closer to a female trait.</p>
      <p>I used to watch a show with my mom called <em>The Closer</em>, with Kyra Sedgwick. She played the chief of a major crimes unit, and she'd basically use her feminine characteristics (like beauty, flirting, manipulating) to get shit done in a way that the men couldn't. And she show emotion. But she also did the leadership thing and filled out other male traits. It was a well written character.</p>
      <p>After she left the show, she was replaced with Mary McDonnell, and the show was renamed <em>Major Crimes</em> (all the other cast was the same). Mary, though, had no feminine traits. And she came off as a complete and thorough cunt (imo) who I could not relate to, sympathize with, and certainly couldn't enjoy.</p>
      <p>If we look at Game of Thrones, Daenerys is an interesting example. We see her go through the early stages of growth, shedding her weaknesses, overcoming barriers, and having self-imposed barriers (not wanting to kill random people, for instance). And at the end, she loses that. She becomes the embodiment of 'strong, independent woman'. She sheds those female characteristics and becomes a villain.</p>
      <p>If we look to the poster child for strong female leads, that would be Ripley from Alien. And it is notable that the character (and I believe all the characters) were written with no specific gender in mind. And that is likely why we got such a groundbreaking character, which was replicated for <em>years</em>, until someone decided to rewrite the formula.</p>
      <p>So anyways, many of the strong female characters we see today, they are just villains that young women are being told to celebrate and idolize. It is <em>strange</em> that people don't seem to recognize this, and that it becomes so divisive to talk about. There has to be some sort of human psychology behind this, that is prevalent in the left/right dichotomy. From seeing racism everywhere, to seeing villains as heroes, the 'one movie, two screens' thing has to be much deeper. It's like that gender quiz from a few weeks ago that seemed to men and women. But there has to be some sort of divide that transcends sex/gender alone, or else we wouldn't expect to see so many males perpetuating it.</p>
      <p>Although maybe it is female/male divide. Mulan was written by 3 women and 1 man.  Ghostbusters (2016) was written by a male and female. And I think Star Wars had some writing committee filled with women, didn't it? Or am I misremembering some scandal? </p>
      <p>Maybe our brains are just wired to see things differently, and women see the stereotypical 'bad boy' as a hero, and want their female characters to emulate that?</p>
      <p>But the likely scenario is that written jobs are basically turning into sinecures, where they put kids of famous or well-connected people. Kids who have had little experience in life, but have all the right degrees and connections. So they get the cushy gig, nobody can say 'no', and the rich kid gets a nice royalty check for the rest of their lives.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>