<post>
  <author>Drinniol</author>
  <date>2020-09-12T21:00:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/io1iih/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_07/g4z9813/</link>
  <title>Innocuous Phrases as Political Slogans: A perfect motte and bailey</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <h1>Innocuous Phrases as Political Slogans: A perfect motte and bailey</h1>
      <p>Sorry if this has already been posted.</p>
      <p>Anyway, recently <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/insaneparents/comments/irfi4a/i_definitely_hope_i_can_indoctrinate_my_children/">this picture</a> has been making the rounds.  I'm linking it in a front page reddit thread mocking objection to it with the standard several thousand comments doing the same.  </p>
      <p>Anyway, two things immediately came to my mind.  Firstly, the fact that all these people would be howling with outrage if the sign said "All Lives Matter."  Secondly, that these types of innocuous phrases as political slogans are basically motte and bailey in a nutshell.  The motte is the literal meaning of the words, the bailey is that the words are a political slogan.</p>
      <p>Firstly, let me say that my personal view is that such sloganeering has absolutely no place in education, and I would equally object to the placement of a sign saying "All Lives Matter."  For you see, these words are more than their literal meaning, they are also a signal of political allegiance.  </p>
      <p>If you're on the All Lives Matter side, then to you "All Lives Matter" is just an innocuous, vacuously true phrase that is ridiculous to object to.  But if you aren't, it's clearly loaded with tons of additional implications due to its existence as a political slogan.  Strikingly, the situation is exactly mirrored here with the slogans in the picture, especially "Black Lives Matter."  Clearly, this phrase is literally true, and yet it is also now a political slogan, and therefore its utterance or public placement is a statement of political loyalty.  It is, therefore, very directly a form of political indoctrination if placed in a public school.  But supporters can't see this, because to them it is just a true statement.</p>
      <p>And this happens over and over again. The motte, easily defensible, is the literal meaning of a clearly correct phrase.  "Black Lives Matter," "All Lives Matter," "It's OK to be White," etc.  The bailey is all the secondary meanings and other political stances that are inextricably tied now to these phrases because they have become political slogans.  </p>
      <p>Let's do a thought experiment. It's well known that the Nazis were very much pro-natalist, and very interested in child indoctrination.  It wouldn't be a stretch to say that they might have adopted a slogan similar to, "Children are the Future."  Suppose that they had, and that this had become a well known political slogan of the Nazis.  Now, someone puts up a sign in their classroom saying, "Children are the Future."  I think this would be a VERY objectionable thing to do!  Not because the saying is wrong or bad in itself, but it is a well known political slogan of Nazism.  </p>
      <p>Indeed, how would you feel about a teacher with a prominently placed sign saying, "We must secure the existence of our country and a future for our children."  This is not literally the 14 words, and certainly its literal meaning is fairly innocuous (who doesn't want their country to continue existing?  Who doesn't want a future for their children?).  But this is clearly a political slogan for an extremely dangerous viewpoint.  </p>
      <p>And it occurs to me that exactly this happens over and over and over again.  Some politician says something that, while no objectionable in literal meaning, just so happens to be a political slogan or a thinly disguised political slogan.  Supporters, of course, claim only to see the motte: the literal meaning of the words that can not be assailed.  Detractors can not see anything but the bailey: the political slogan and all that comes with it.  </p>
      <p>And who is right?  Well, it really depends.  Sometimes people really do just say things that look like political slogans while actually just intending their literal meaning.  And sometimes people actually do dog-whistle.  Ultimately, you have to make a judgment on the intent of the person making the utterance.  Naturally, if you dislike them, you'll believe they are simply sloganeering.  If you like them, you'll give them the benefit of the doubt and say that the other side is simply putting words in the person's mouth and seeing sinister connotations that don't exist.  </p>
      <p>I now see this everywhere as a constant problem in any sort of heated political discussion.  Indeed, in these very culture war threads, I constantly see people get caught up in arguments like,  "You used such and such phrasing that is obviously (to me) a political slogan. You are clearly waging culture war."  And the other person saying,  "No you're waging culture war by saying I'm waging culture war, I'm just really saying what I mean, you're the one who can't disengage enough from the culture war to stop seeing slogans in everything."  It happens over and over again.  And I'm not sure it can really be stopped, particularly since people have begun to weaponize the phenomenon.  Consider how the OK symbol was explicitly co-opted as a political symbol precisely because it was (previously) such an innocuous and widespread thing. In the chan threads that first spearheaded the use of the OK symbol as a white supremacist symbol, it was explicitly stated that the reasoning was it was so widespread that making it a political symbol would accomplish three goals:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>If used by actual white nationalists, it would be deniable. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>It could be weaponized against non white nationalists who used it innocuously not realizing its changed meaning.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>It would make those who recognized its new meaning as a political symbol and objected to its use look ridiculous to "normal" (that is, not super politically active online) people who remembered and clung to the OK signs original, nonpolitical meaning.  </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>Increasingly, more and more apparently innocuous things are becoming politicized, to the point that it becomes almost impossible to avoid accidentally using some sort of political slogan in political discussion.  And to the person primed to see these things everywhere, they do see them everywhere.  The entire world becomes, to them, an endless cacophony of competing political slogans.  Or, perhaps, the other side becomes an endless sea of dog whistles and naked political slogans, while their side becomes the side simply speaking simple and obvious truths.  And this is true whatever side you are on, even though both sides hear the same words and see the same things, they are receiving entirely different messages.  </p>
      <p>It is, indeed, two movies playing on the same screen.  </p>
      <p>Has anyone else noticed this phenomenon?  What does it mean for the future when literal everything becomes political?  What is the next currently widespread and innocuous phrase or slang that will be co-opted as a political slogan?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>