<post>
  <author>FPHthrowawayB</author>
  <date>2020-09-11T18:20:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/io1iih/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_07/g4ujlsw/</link>
  <title>A Pedophile's Perspective on Pizzagate</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>(1) What do people in these pedophile communities think about 'pizzagate' and other high profile pedophile conspiracies?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Well it's been a thing for a while now so many sentiments have developed. To attempt to summarize:</p>
      <p>1. First there's of course obvious amusement derived from tons of new outsiders attempting to probe into "pedo culture" and getting so much wrong. There were of course the famous "pedophile logos" from "Internet hate machine"-era FBI (not that the FBI said "Internet hate machine", but it just shows how clueless the powers that be were in that time period about what went on online, including in pedo spaces) documents (which Pizzagaters to this day believe were/are some universal code that every pedo recognizes like a pedo bat signal, which couldn't be further from the truth) to which most of your average pedo imageboard fappers responded with "We have symbols?" and even many of the more serious, discussion-oriented pedos didn't know about (outside of the small clan from which the symbols emerged, which is really old Stonewall-era guys who post on ancient BBSes from the 90s). (Though interestingly enough many pedos have now started using the symbols themselves because Pizzagaters revived and spread them, making them more popular than ever before. I'd say that, as opposed to when they were first brought up in the context of Pizzagate, many if not most pedos recognize them now.)</p>
      <p>Then there's just sometimes their general cluelessness. I saw a thread on Voat once where some Pizzagate group could not figure out what "Adult ran" in a child's Instagram bio (as in "This account is ran by an adult." so that the Insta mods don't shut it down for being run by someone under 13) meant and assumed it was some secret sex trafficking code (which obviously implicates a lot of random, pretty normal parents who want to run accounts for their kids). Then there's also their common conviction that any account that posts anything involving child gymnastics, dancing, etc. must be involved in child sex trafficking or some sort of child sex-oriented conspiracy. Non-pedos in general are seen as pretty "boomerish" (like how you might think about a boomer being clueless about say online culture in general) about their knowledge of the context of pedo-adjacent stuff with Pizzagate types being considered especially so.</p>
      <p>2. So do pedos believe in Pizzagate? Well first I'll say that pedos, like most people nowadays, are politically tribal and that their broader political affiliations generally overrule whatever politics their sexuality is supposedly adjacent to or not. So there are absolutely Q-loving pedos who go visit the various Q venues to hear the latest news on the pedo cabal running the world and then go to pedo imageboards to fap (with their justification to synthesize these two behaviors usually being something like that Q fights against powerful, exploitative sex trafficker types like Epstein, not average pedos like them). (Of course they're probably proportionally less common than Q fans among the general population (as pedo boards tend to skew a bit younger in general given the greater technical obscurity of them, even if they're just say an imageboard), but they still exist as an example of pedo political diversity.)</p>
      <p>That is, there are plenty of pedos in all four corners of the political quadrant regardless of what <a href="/r/PoliticalCompassMemes">/r/PoliticalCompassMemes</a> would have you believe. This isn't to say that there aren't patterns, just that you can't speak for the beliefs of every pedo any more than you can speak for the beliefs of every gay. There are Log Cabin Republicans and plenty of politically heterodox pedos too. </p>
      <p>(For the record, pedos usually tend to naturally politically lean toward a libertarianish (ish since it's more focused on the obvious issue than things like economics or the NAP, which are two issues pedos disagree on as much as any other random group of people) version of whatever is countercultural at the moment (or more like "What's 4chan support now?" since that site was such a big influence on modern online pedo culture and therefore pedos tend to have greater than average exposure to the 4chan-and-diaspora online realm and its ongoing political discourse), so libertarianish rightism currently as PCM correctly predicts, but it's still worth knowing that many pedos have also recently shifted left, even hard left, with the hope that leftist sexual progressives will bring salvation to them as "MAPs" (which has I think grown enough to become self-sustaining and create its own new online pedo culture distinct from the rest, on Twitter or wherever it's allowed). (This has of course also brought the broader culture war to pedo spaces which is always fun.))</p>
      <p>What's the general consensus though? Well a lot of the lower hanging fruit that Pizzagate types often obsess over (since they're more accessible villains that can be fought via means like reporting them on social media), like that random child gymnastics or dance organizations or even random bootleg child modeling agencies that get a bit saucy are connected to some broader global conspiracy, are often simply too ridiculous to believe from an average Joe pedo's perspective since we simply have too much "inside knowledge" about those situations, often just from consuming their content. </p>
      <p>For example, Pizzagate types recently obsessed over a child modeling agency from Venezuela that posted somewhat sexualized content on YouTube, convinced they had discovered a small domino that likely lead to something bigger. We pedos meanwhile, having seen dozens of these types of agencies come and go, knew that there was very little chance of it being anything that big, that the response to it was (from the perspective of the broader allegations being made) simply another anti-pedo hysteria blown out of proportion. That is, I think we're naturally better (due to greater knowledge/experience) at understanding the "scale" of what events and media in this area represent whereas non-pedos often immediately freak out and assume that any random child sexualization they encounter is the biggest crime and worst thing ever and therefore must be connected to some sort of grand nefarious element (often making it difficult for us to get on board with them due to a lack of shared perspective).</p>
      <p>Do pedos think that rich people sometimes engage in the "forbidden fruit", perhaps at a higher rate than your average Joe pedo (due to easier access)? Most of them do, since obviously any pedo would be tempted and there's no reason there wouldn't be pedos among the rich. Do pedos believe in the exaggerated version of this where there are Satanic rituals sacrificing children to Moloch and a particular web of pizza places holding kids in their basement etc.? I'd say that the proportion who do is similar to the proportion of non-pedos who do (so not many), perhaps slightly lower due to how much practical those types get obviously wrong from a pedo perspective as detailed earlier. (And the mockery of Pizzagaters among pedos is louder and from across the political spectrum since it doesn't imply any real political affiliation, just laughing at a universal outgroup among pedos.)</p>
      <p>What does make pedos really bristle in relation to this issue though, and where I think there's the most widespread agreement, is when people imply that the rich/society in general are "pro-pedo" or "pushing pedophilia", since that's just transparently ridiculous from our perspective. When you look at the social/political trends that are actually obviously being pushed hard by the powers that be lately, like say #BlackLivesMatter (hopefully it's not controversial to state without further evidence that that's being heavily promoted in the mainstream, irrespective of your opinions on the value of it), how can anyone look at how pedophilia is comparatively treated in the mainstream and think there is any equivalence there? Compared to the kind of media blitzes these issues get, what do pedos get? One slightly child-sexualized but still ostensibly anti-pedo movie accompanied by massive controversy a decade? </p>
      <p>Like I've seen a lot of people here expression frustration with what they see as just blatantly transparent dishonesty when they encounter, for example, someone claim that social media sites like Reddit or Twitter are biased in favor of right-wingers (or not biased in favor of the opposite). I'm not taking a position on the claim in question, but if you imagine that frustration, that pure indignant disbelief that (from the frustrated person's perspective) someone could advocate for something so contrary to reality, that's how pedos feel when they see people claim that, actually, the monolith of society that's been massively propagandizing against us and putting millions of us in prison for decades is really on our side. So when the subject is brought up it's not uncommon to see comments along the lines of "Well good for the rich bastards but they sure aren't doing shit for us average pedos." It's an issue that instantly turns pedos into localized Bernie Sanders fans.</p>
      <p>Anyway that's long but hopefully it gives you some perspective into how pedos look at this stuff.</p>
      <p>(I'm getting close to the word limit, so I'll answer your other questions in a reply to this post.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>