<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-09-09T16:14:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/io1iih/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_07/g4k4auw/</link>
  <title>Your irregularly scheduled r/TheMotte speaking-in-tongues session</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <h2>
        <a href="https://www.geopolitica.ru/directives/ekspertiza-dugina-no-18-pragmatizm-i-gebefreniya-paradoksy-amerikanskogo-lotosa">Dugin's expertise №18.</a> «Pragmatism and hebephrenia: paradoxes of American Logos».</h2>
      <p>Or: Trump as the last bearer of original American Logos. Apr. 2018</p>
      <p>
        <em>We stand on the very brink of the end of America. Why? Because the American Logos itself is on the verge of destruction.</em>
      </p>
      <p>This is a fairly old text that I've recently rediscovered and decided to translate, because it is, on one hand, an illustrative and perhaps counterintuitive case of a hardcore Continental's perception of American philosophy (<a href="/u/motteposting">/u/motteposting</a> may object that it's a gross strawman, though), and, on the other hand, it describes well the division that, in my opinion, reaches deeper than "tribes", explains the "blue tribe" and "ex-blue tribe" Mottites; Dugin's concept of Logoi is created to explain the different ways in which civilizations create their "meanings", their axis of truth. And on the gripping hand, it's plain entertaining (at least to me it was). I do not subscribe to the harsh invective in the text below, and recommend to be easy-going about it. </p>
      <hr />
      <p>Does the USA have a philosophy? Europeans usually think that this rubbish cannot be called "philosophy", because it is more akin to feeble-mindedness and hebephrenia.</p>
      <p>Hebephrenia is a setback in the process of growing up, when a teenager remains such even after becoming an "adult", giving up responsibility and rationality. In a sense, it is true - American philosophy may well appear to be "hebephrenia".</p>
      <p>The first cliché is also partially justified: American philosophy is an extension of English (or rather Scottish) 'common sense' philosophy (Reid, Ferguson, etc.). This "philosophy" in its turn is doubtful too, as it represents the elevation of the ultimate banality to the rank of metaphysics. It serves as the basis for utilitarianism.</p>
      <p>Utilitarianism (for example, Jeremiah Bentham) is loathed by the right and the left alike, because according to it the criterion of truth is usefulness, and the meaning of life is the search for pleasure. It is disgusting and humiliating not only for a man, but even for an animal.</p>
      <p>But again it is not the American philosophy, although the names are similar: American philosophy is pragmatism.</p>
      <p>The meaning of this philosophy is not so simple. The fact is that utilitarianism, "common sense" and liberalism all recognize the existence of the object (things, the outside world) and the existence of the subject (consciousness, mind, spirit). Both of those classes exist and both meet certain criteria. Utilitarianism asserts that different relations can be established between the world of the subject - even a primitive one - and the world of the object, even the most improvized, private-owned and nominal one. But... pragmatism is something else.</p>
      <p>American pragmatism is the idea that the object and the subject are completely free and open sets. Every subject has the right to consider himself anything: Santa, Elvis, Captain America, Martian, white, black, male, female, etc. The object similarly does not have a strictly defined ontology: nobody has the right to tell an American that the reality is this way and no other way. No one and nothing can tell this: neither science, nor religion, nor authority, nor ideology. The reality is what it is considered to be by the subject, who in turn considers himself to be whoever he chooses.</p>
      <p>This is exactly what pragmatism is: both in its most pedestrian - sometimes idiotic - manifestation of the famous American ignorance, and equally so in American mysticism and American romanticism - Emerson, Thoreau, etc.</p>
      <p>But then how can one live in such a world that is completely open from both sides? The only criterion is: "it works" [in English]. It works and it works great. This is the basis of pragmatic ontology. It doesn't matter who we are, it doesn't matter what kind of world is around us: what matters is the success of the interaction of these two arbitrary sets - conventionally "internal" and conventionally "external". <em>It works ergo sum et ergo est</em>. If it works, then it is. And "it does not work" means "no dice", it may work some other time. Go ahead [in English]. It is not just retardation, it is retardation raised into metaphysics, retardation which, by the way, liberates. In principle, any epistemology and ontology can be developed on this basis – so long as is is possible to establish an interaction that satisfies that which considers itself to be a subject. This may be repulsive, but it can be charming too. Depends on how to look at it. For us, it is, of course, weird, because Russians have always gravitated toward a certain holistic ontology, either spiritual or materialistic, but certainly not pragmatic.</p>
      <p>We stand on the brink of the end of America. Why? Because the American Logos itself is on the verge of destruction. Trump and his voters are the pragmatic America. But today, the globalist liberal elites who rule it, and who in fact are the carriers of a different - emigrant - most often European Logos, impose different standards on Americans. While for pragmatists everyone can be whatever he or she wants - a communist, a liberal, a fascist, Elvis, a plant, a cat, etc., then for liberals one can be only a liberal, and preferably the left - "cultural Marxists", feminists and anarchists. This is a totalitarian imposition of what the subject should and should not be, not an American element at all. <strong>Hence the hatred for Trump: he is the last carrier of the authentic American Logos.</strong></p>
      <p>That is why the globalists will destroy America, because they started to prescribe the totalitarian norms of subjectivity. Thus, they have sharply limited the space of internal and external freedom. And they continue to do so. Hence the beginning of the new American Resistance (You are Resistance of Alex Jones or the hero of the series "Homeland" of O'Keefe, in whom Alex Jones is easily recognized). There is no reason to search there for forms familiar to Europe or even Russia: it is a specifically American Resistance. It rises in the name of protecting pragmatism, the very pragmatic spirit itself. Liberals and globalists insist on their approach regardless of "whether it works or not".  This is a completely different - completely non- American - philosophy.</p>
      <p>Here is how it is in philosophy: the Pragmatist Logos is on the verge of destruction. But... is there is no Logos, there will be no America too.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>