<post>
  <author>NotSoIncandenza</author>
  <date>2020-09-10T00:46:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/io1iih/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_07/g4ltrea/</link>
  <title>The Homogenizing Power of Academy Awards</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A couple points here.</p>
      <p>a) Academy Awards are reasonably valuable, in so far as if you are nominated, you see a moderate bump in Box Office/Home Viewing revenue, and if you win, you see a large bump. So there is a small-ish financial incentive there.</p>
      <p>But more importantly, everyone is DYING to win one (it's many people's life goal) and so trying to win Oscars are a worthy pursuit for getting anyone involved.  So you really have a much better shot at getting Bradley Cooper or Scorsese or Amy Adams or Scott Rudin or Universal Pictures (especially at a price) if they think they might win an Oscar for the product.</p>
      <p>Beyond that, due to a variety of changes in the business, it's getting to the point where "trying to win an Oscar" has become the only viable way of putting out most movies. Many Oscar movies do work financially (some make lots of money!), but the plan with most movies that aren't a franchise is not, "It's great, people will love it! And eventually it will arrive on video".</p>
      <p>It's: put it out at a prestigious festival (Sundance, TIFF, etc.); get tastemakers and critics excited, talk show circuit and magazine covers, platform release in the late fall, get everyone seeing it around Thanksgiving and Xmas, get nominated for everything, spend January and February in tuxedos, thank your mom on stage!</p>
      <p>An example to think of is A Star Is Born. Studio music-driven movie with new Lady Gaga songs and Bradley Cooper. Should very do well at any time. It was supposed to come out in March. The studio loved the movie, changed it to an October release date to load up for the Oscar run. It played the fall festivals--where it crushed--I think it got a bit of a platform release and as much hype and awards talk as possible. It ended up making 435M and got a ton of nominations. Now, I think it's a terrific movie. I absolutely loved it, as did many other people, and believe it deserved all its success. But, a decade or two ago, maybe Warner Bros. puts it out in March and they see what happens. These days, it had to receive the red carpet treatment (which totally worked!).</p>
      <p>So imagining any non-franchise movies that won't qualify for an Oscar sort of kills them before they hatch, these days. The entire Oscar circuit provides a justification and platform to release adult movies, and outside of that, you're in rough shape. (The exception to this rule is genre stuff: comedies, horror, etc.)</p>
      <p>And with that in mind, B) Many of these movies just won't get made. In fact, people won't even try to make them. To some extent, people won't even think about making them.</p>
      <p>Westerns are a good example of this. They used to be a key American genre, and having a "ten best westerns of the decade" in the 60s and 70s was not a vain pursuit. Obviously the number of Western has decreased, but as late as 2007, you have a year with No Country For Old Men, There Will Be Blood, 3:10 to Yuma, and the Assassination of Jesse James, four different Westerns ranging from good to extraordinary-- in large part because Mangold and the Coens, etc. grew up watching a ton of Westerns and created their own. Now, they are made so infrequently that millennials like Damien Chazelle or Ryan Coogler probably don't even dream of making them--they're not even a part of their dreamscape.</p>
      <p>It's as impossible to calculate the cost of things that don't happen in the movie business as it is in any other part of the world. But presumably, movies will continue on the path they're on: growing more and more homogenous and philosophically predictable and less imaginative and inventive, and the few filmmakers left who are too artistically intransigent to jump on these trends (who will probably be White guys for obvious reasons that, they can't make personal movies in the woke vein--today, I'd think of Ari Aster and the Safdies in terms of young directors like this), will probably make novel and one-of-a-kind movies that will excite people. But there will be less and less filmmakers like that, and folks from marginalized groups will be implicitly less encouraged to head down that path, which is the real shame.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>