<post>
  <author>Standard_Order</author>
  <date>2020-09-10T01:56:29Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/io1iih/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_07/g4m1v72/</link>
  <title>A few notes on QAnon</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>QAnon's "baby-eating" conspiracy recycles the anti-Semitic blood libel from The Protocols of Elders of Zion.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This sentence gave me such a headache. There was a huge subculture regarding sex and blood magick in the 20th century, beginning with Crowley's Thelema and the Ordo Templi Orientis (cf the curious case of Jack Parsons). This exploded and fragmented into uncountable shards in the 60s during the hippie movement, including Scientology, the Process Church which inspired Charlie Manson (and which later morphed into the celeb-fave Best Friends Animal Society), and the unnamed group behind the Son of Sam murders. Of course despite all the writings about worship of sex and murder, they've never been <em>conclusively linked</em> to any significant crimes!! Oookay. These subcultures didn't just disappear in the 70s; given the rife symbolism at his island and some comments from his acquaintances (eg Eric Weinstein), I have little doubt that Epstein was involved. Trafficking teenagers was far from the worst of his crimes.</p>
      <p>The blood magick subculture originated in the Anglo world but inherited (via Blavatsky and Thelema) many traditions from Old Europe, including the significance of blood in magic rituals. It's this same blood magic traditions which inspired (as concluded by an Israeli scholar, the son of the Chief Rabbi of Rome, in 2007, in the book <em>Passovers of Blood</em>) "certain criminal acts, disguised as crude rituals, [which] were indeed committed by [Jewish] extremist groups or by individuals demented by religious mania and blinded by desire for revenge against those considered responsible for their people's sorrows and tragedies," rituals which formed the basis of medieval "blood libel" claims.</p>
      <p>As it happens, all this is beside the point: despite media conflation of "beliefs of people who are into Qanon" and "Q-Level Patriot and his posts," there is <a href="https://twitter.com/MajorPatriot/status/1303816660558721033">nothing about "baby-eating"</a> in actual Q posts. Qanon is so brilliant because the poster has mastered the art of ambiguity; look at that Hitler handler message: they're not actually saying that Soros ran Hitler, they're saying that Soros picked up the legacy of the Rothschilds, and Hitler was a puppet for <em>someone</em> to start WWII for inscrutable reasons. Is Q suggesting the Rothshchilds controlled Hitler? 99% of readers might think so. But really it's ambiguous. Q disperses standard "question everything you know" conspiracy fodder about history in the most ambiguous possible way, then sprinkles in highly specific claims about the workings of the Trump administration. It's a genius op, and despite all the hubbub about Q supporters at Trump rallies, there's been surprisingly little focus on who the fuck Q actually is. This isn't some impossible historical puzzle! They're posting on 8kun <a href="https://qposts.online/"><em>right now.</em></a> I wouldn't be at all surprised if someone from the NSA was behind it after all. I hope someone will do a book on it one day.</p>
      <p>Or maybe it's just anti-Semitism all the way down. Sure. Whatever.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>