<post>
  <author>cantbeproductive</author>
  <date>2021-03-01T16:56:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lv2rb7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_01_2021/gpbdssb/</link>
  <title>Crying a river through history: the exhaustibility of sentiment</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think entertainment media has one of the largest effects on a person’s development, as it replaced religion and ritual, which previously had the largest effect on a person’s development. I don’t know if it is increased sentimentality so much as <em>expanded and directed</em> sentimentality. </p>
      <p>Medieval media was soppy in its sentimentality, lots of knights crying, but <em>only</em> regarding family, and the King, and God. Augustine cried often over his sinfulness — in one passage of the <em>Confessions</em> he found himself crying over <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=uGQq3HcOB0Y">Dido’s lament</a>, a story from the Aeneid, then realized he was crying over a Pagan love story and then started crying because he couldn’t express such sadness over his own sinful state (ironically doing so in the process). Ignatius of Loyola, one of late medieval (?) thought leaders, cried about 100 times in 40 days, as we find in his diary. In the Odyssey, Odysseus finds himself crying over homesickness and again finds himself crying upon seeing his family again, it is written that upon returning home he could have cried the entire night and that he cried like an “eagle” (so this was straight up ugly crying). Traditionally tears were considered a spiritual gift in the West, the more Godly crying the better.</p>
      <p>It shouldn’t be surprising that sentimentality and sympathy are limiting because we know that the hormone responsible (oxytocin) is also responsible for in-group bias and weariness to outsiders. This is why Odysseus had no qualms with massacring his enemies — his sentimentality rested with his family. The Medievals were fine with executing atheists and setting on crusades because their sentimentality was placed in King and God. St Teresa had such sentimentality for God and the Poor that she had none left for the individual sufferer, telling them plainly to deal with their suffering as it was a blessing from God. </p>
      <p>Nazi media was sentimental but only to healthy Germans, North Korean media is highly sentimental in regards to the Glorious Leader, and Soviet media was sentimental to the plight of the worker.</p>
      <p>This is something that runs through my head a lot because there seems to be a lot of implications. You can probably set a couple useful hard and fast rules: (1) humans have a roughly set amount of sentimentality and culture decides how it is directed; (2) media affects development and personality in direct proportion to its  resulting in the Generative Effect and Social Modeling.</p>
      <p>Per (1) we can see why a subset of radical progressives have almost no sentimentality or sympathy outside of their victimhood in-group. For instance in the case involving Smith College a lawyer put out a statement to the effect that there should only be sympathy for the Black woman who made the false accusation, and not the white victims of the accusation, because racism exists. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“It’s troubling that people are more offended by being called racist than by the actual racism in our society,” he said. “Allegations of being racist, even getting direct mailers in their mailbox, is not on par with the consequences of actual racism”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is where the famous “you’re a white male!” of years back found <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=D-3Y3NDCT-Y">its origin</a>: if all your sentimentality is placed in (mostly black) minorities, you have literally none left for any victim that is outside the sentimental purview.</p>
      <p>So how does (1) even happen? How’s it get that bad? From (2)! The way the media works today is that they are forcing you to become sentimental of only one group (minorities) and then they force you to continually to make mental associations with this victimhood. I get article recommendations on some apps and not a day goes by that this cycle doesn’t transpire: articles about how bird watching is racist, how the Audubon society is racist, how every little thing you think about is related to the omnipresent omnipotent victimhood of minorities by the victimizing White people. I was walking by a TV playing CNN yesterday, they were doing a special on Italian food in Rome and had to make a 5 minute interlude about the holocaust. Why? Well, there was a Jewish person in Rome, who made food, so naturally we have to talk about ghettos and the holocaust, <em>in Rome</em>, on a <em>travel food show</em>.</p>
      <p>Interestingly, there’s a seeming contradiction in Plato. Why did he hate poets but loved tragedies? The poets (and musicians) according to Plato made people too sentimental which got in the way of logical reasoning. Tragedy, on the other hand, <em>removed</em> the emotions from the viewer (catharsis), by acting as a safe place where a person’s sentimentality can be drained out so that they can resume being logical. This is why Greek tragedies are so abundantly over-sentimental and a somewhat rare occurrence, the pitying of the characters allows you to feel the feelings on behalf of another and be done with them. But music increases emotionality, instead of releasing it. At least this was an idea in <em>Preface to Plato</em>, I’m not sure if I buy it.</p>
      <p>It’s possible that society has determined the Minority Tragedy to be our catharsis. When all of your sentiment is placed in the Minority Tragedy then the populace has none left to consider whether we should be bombing Damascus, reducing income inequality, etc.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>