<post>
  <author>erwgv3g34</author>
  <date>2021-03-01T14:23:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lv2rb7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_01_2021/gpaunyt/</link>
  <title>You can't lower the price of real estate and not lower the price of real estate; you can't lower the cost of rent and not lower the value of houses</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There are two big problems with building more housing in general.</p>
      <p>The first is that, as <a href="/u/xkjkls">u/xkjkls</a> points out, there is a <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/gon5xs7/">fundamental</a><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/gon7vh2/">tension</a> between renters and homeowners. You can't lower the price of real estate and <em>not</em> lower the price of real estate; you can't lower the cost of rent and <em>not</em> lower the value of houses. If you build enough housing to halve the price of rent, you have presumably built enough housing to halve the value of houses, which is enough to give any homeowner a heart attack. In our cultural and financial system, in which houses are considered the prime investment of the middle class, this is a serious problem. It is not unlike when Uber came out, and <a href="https://archive.is/NUPUx">all those people who had mortgaged their futures buying a taxi medallion</a> got fucked over.</p>
      <p>Now, to be clear, I am glad Uber exists, and I realize something has to be done to lower the rents; young people can't afford to move out or raise families, and the rent just keeps going up and up. But if you support building more housing, then you support fucking over innocent, middle-class people who did the "responsible" thing and saved up for a down payment and have spent decades building equity by paying for their mortgage, and you need to <strong>own</strong> that. "Yes, it sucks that you were left holding the bag for doing the thing everyone told you was safe and mature and that worked great for everyone before you, but we can't keep raising rents forever". You know, the same sort of thing we are gonna have to tell university graduates the day we bring down the college credentialing cartel and they end up with a worthless piece of paper.</p>
      <p>The other problem with building more housing to lower rent is that high prices are the only legal way to exclude the underclass. Thanks to anti-discrimination laws and disparate impact doctrine, building <a href="https://archive.fo/UpC1n">healthy communities</a><a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20150609214555/http://thefutureprimaeval.net/when-did-healthy-communities-become-illegal/">has become illegal</a>. If you want a neighborhood free of <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/02/12/money-money-everywhere-but-not-a-cent-to-spend/#comment-183902">prostitutes, drug dealers, gang bangers, single mothers, and ex-convicts</a>, your only legal recourse is to move to a neighborhood expensive enough that they can't afford to follow you there. Likewise, if you want to send your kids to a public school free of <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/04/11/open-thread-99-25/#comment-618757">stabby</a><a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/04/11/open-thread-99-25/#comment-619084">kids</a>, then the only legal way to do that is to move to a school district expensive enough that the parents of the stabby kids can't afford to live there and pray that your politicians don't decide to bus the stabby kids into your children's school in the name of equality.</p>
      <p>So it goes.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>