<post>
  <author>Folamh3</author>
  <date>2021-03-04T16:03:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lv2rb7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_01_2021/gpnyi9x/</link>
  <title>The use/reference distinction in fiction</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's true that there's a world of difference between an artist <em>depicting</em> a certain kind of behaviour and an artist <em>endorsing</em> that kind of behaviour. People rarely watch films about serial killers and come away with the impression that the director and/or screenwriter are endorsing murdering people for gratification, even if the serial killer gets away with it at the end.</p>
      <p>So if a sitcom episode depicts sexism, how can you tell whether or not the director or screenwriter are endorsing it? Directors or screenwriters who want to keep their jobs are highly unlikely to come out and say "I think being sexist against women is good", so if you see an example of sexism in a sitcom episode, you'll have to employ a bit of inductive reasoning to judge whether or not the sitcom is endorsing that behaviour or not. </p>
      <p>For example, if the character who exhibits sexist behaviour or attitudes is a character whom the audience is not expected to sympathize with, it's reasonable to assume the show isn't endorsing their worldview (Dr. Kelso on <em>Scrubs</em> made a lot of chauvinistic or demeaning comments towards women, but the show made no bones about him being more-or-less the villain of the series, to the point of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jn4g5eR5AY0">literally comparing him to Darth Vader from <em>Star Wars</em></a>. </p>
      <p>However, if the character who exhibits sexist behaviour or attitudes is a character whom the audience <em>is</em> expected to sympathize with, that complicates things. Supposing Joe is the protagonist of <em>Show X</em> and is generally depicted as a well-meaning and likeable guy - but then he makes a sexist comment. An uncharitable reading of the show might be "<em>Show X</em> thinks that being sexist doesn't make you a bad person"; a charitable reading might be "Joe is a sympathetic character, but still flawed and imperfect; his general affability doesn't change the fact that he has backwards attitudes towards women."</p>
      <p>Or consider consequences. If a character in a show makes a sexist comment, and then it comes back around to karmically bite them in the ass at the end of the episode, it's probably safe to say that the show isn't endorsing being sexist.</p>
      <p>... <em>however</em>, a character <em>not</em> facing any comeuppance for being sexist could <em>in itself</em> be part of the intended message, as an indictment of how widespread and ingrained the writer believes misogyny is in our society.</p>
      <p>In essence, there's no royal road to figuring out the intended message of a given artistic work. Depiction of sexism (racism/transphobia/classism etc.) is not evidence of endorsement of same. A character being sexist and not facing any repercussions for it does not automatically mean the creator thinks it's okay to be sexist. A sympathetic character being sexist does not automatically mean that the creator thinks it's okay to be sexist (and conversely, an <em>un</em>sympathetic character being sexist does not automatically mean that the creator <em>doesn't</em> think it's okay to be sexist; many unsympathetic or even villainous characters nevertheless have positive or redeeming character traits).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>