<post>
  <author>Love_ls_Love</author>
  <date>2021-02-25T20:03:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/goqvdi8/</link>
  <title>Left-wing hereditarianism. (Comment removed by reddit's "anti-evil operations" team.)</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Like many here, I'm sympathetic to the central HBD thesis. By this I mean that I think it's likely that the genes that causally determine intelligence are not distributed identically in the Black and white populations in America, and this fact explains much if not most of the variation in societal outcomes we observe between Black and white people. Despite my factual agreement with these posters, however, I'm put off by the way that they casually dismiss the arguments from the left about America's reckoning with racism. In short, we hereditarians need to argue more forcefully how anti-racism is fully compatible with HBD.</p>
      <p>Here, I'd like to identify and briefly touch on how I think hereditarians could achieve broader acceptance. To put it frankly, hereditarians could like <em>actually try</em> to show that they aren't just advancing the thesis as a justification for upholding white supremacy.</p>
      <p>Personally, I identify as a <a href="https://theunitofcaring.tumblr.com/post/157999539381/also-as-far-as-i-can-tell-lots-of-the-criticism">left-hereditarian</a>. My distaste at right-hereditarians mostly comes from their wholly unconvincing denials when they are accused of being racist.  I understand that people like Charles Murray will sometimes make remarks to the effect of "of course all people have equal value" and then move on to a different topic. That's about as convincing as when Donald Trump boldly declared that "there's no one less racist than me." In other words, it's not convincing at all.</p>
      <p>Instead, here's what you <em>might</em> want to try:</p>
      <p>One: don't avoid the hard discussions about the brutal effects and aftermath of centuries of slavery. Even if <em>current</em> disparities are not mostly due to the aftermath of slavery, the human slave trade was still an atrocious crime against humanity that America has never reckoned with.</p>
      <p>I sometimes honestly get the sense from some on the right that merely making slavery illegal was sufficient to atone for its evil. This argument is morally bankrupt. If someone had literally <em>owned your entire family for generations, raped members of your family repeatedly, and brutally beat them when they didn't obey</em>, do you really think that you would "let bygones be bygones" if one day the government comes up and declares that your family is now "free"? <em>Especially</em> if what it means to be "free" is that you can technically, maybe just leave and work for another white man?</p>
      <p>Personally, I am struck in horror by the willingness of conservatives to simply dismiss slavery out of hand, as if anything that happened over 150 years ago doesn't have any relevance today whatsoever (except of course for the constitution, which should be upheld always).</p>
      <p>Two: support and fight for reparations. The moral argument for reparations is simple, and doesn't fundamentally depend on the idea that current disparities are due to systemic racism. The argument is simply that for <strong>centuries</strong>, white America stole labor from Blacks, and in many ways <a href="https://www.epi.org/publication/wage-theft-bigger-problem-forms-theft-workers/">continues to do so</a>. Paying reparations merely means giving back Black America what is theirs.</p>
      <p>I don't know what the right level of reparations might be, but I'm sympathetic to <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/pdf/10.1177/0034644620926516">this paper</a> which argues that the right level would be somewhere in the range of 12 trillion dollars.</p>
      <p>Three: accept that systemic racism is real, and has wide reaching effects. Even if the <em>primary</em> reason why Black people can't get ahead is not because of systemic racism, that does not in any way imply that systemic racism is not real.</p>
      <p>For lack of space and time, I can't go into all the ways that systemic racism affects Black America now, but I'll just briefly focus on <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2020/opinions/systemic-racism-police-evidence-criminal-justice-system/">the most clear case</a>. The criminal justice system in America is unparalleled in the world by <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/opinion/the-moral-horror-of-americas-prisons/">how often and how harshly we punish convicts</a>. <em>Do you really think this has nothing to do with racism?</em></p>
      <p>I've often had discussions with conservatives who assert that systemic racism can't be real because there are very few people are openly racist. OK sure, but why does that matter? If I claimed that society had a problem of "systemic selfishness" would it actually make sense to reply that I was wrong because "most people think selfishness is bad"? Of course it wouldn't! That's because we all know that, just because someone <em>says</em> selfishness is bad doesn't mean that they aren't actually selfish.</p>
      <p>Four: understand and repeat often that our moral obligations are just as strong no matter the current causes of current racial disparities. From the perspective of whether we should help Black people in the first place, it hardly matters at all why Black America is suffering.</p>
      <p>To be clear, it <em>is</em> important to understand the real causes of Black America's pain because that information allows us to better repair their situation. But knowing that the true cause is rooted in genetics does not in any way let white America off the hook.</p>
      <p>[Edit: The following analogy does not in any way imply that being black is equivalent to having a genetic disorder. Read up on what thought experiments are.] Consider a thought experiment: suppose that you came across someone who had a genetic disease that limited their ability to find work and live independently. Now suppose further that it is well within your ability to house, feed, and take care of this individual. I would argue that not only would it be good for you to help this person, but it is your <em>damn responsibility as a human</em>.</p>
      <p>I am in deep agreement with Nathan Robinson when he <a href="https://www.currentaffairs.org/2017/07/why-is-charles-murray-odious">wrote</a>,</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Murray treats seriously the hypotheses that attribute black poverty to things about black people (both cultural and genetic), but casually dismisses hypotheses that suggest a strong role for the massive, centuries-long crime that was perpetrated upon black people (a crime that is hardly mentioned or examined). As Orlando Patterson <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=p5XrN3Mox-0C&amp;pg=PA187&amp;lpg=PA187&amp;dq=orlando+patterson+bell+curve&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=o3UJuHKWy0&amp;sig=US53JDHNAhgFV2AJ9bT4zoCbcrs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjenbWhuf3UAhXr34MKHeyvCZ0Q6AEIMTAC#v=onepage&amp;q=orlando%20patterson%20bell%20curve&amp;f=false">put it</a>, for 248 of the 377 years of U.S. history before <em>The Bell Curve</em>’s publication, black people were “an enslaved group, physically, economically, socially, legally, sexually, morally, and psychologically, subjected not only to the exploitative whim of individual white owners but at the violent mercy of all whites, under the encouragement and protection of the predatory dominant whites.” For Murray to not take that seriously as even a <em>hypothesis</em> in explaining contemporary racial disparities suggests both a lack of empathy and a lack of social scientific neutrality.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>And I say that as someone who mostly agrees with Murray!</p>
      <p>From my perspective, I think it's exceptionally unfortunate that the truth of HBD has been, thus far, guarded by those on the political right. I often feel like crying out and asking: who else will stand up for the anti-racism in the face of the hard facts about genetic differences between populations?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>