<post>
  <note>Only part 2 was in this expert; added and merged in part 1.  Not sure on categories; it's about group labels, but far more specific to individual applications than most coteries.</note>
  <author>monfreremonfrere</author>
  <date>2021-02-26T05:18:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/gosri4d/</link>
  <title>The Relative Bluntness of Idiomatic English Versus Mandarin</title>
  <category>
    <li>coteries</li>
    <li>personal</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There’s a cluster of memes or pieces of received wisdom in Western (American?) culture that goes something like this:</p>
       <ul>
        <li>Caring too much about looks, wealth, intelligence, fame, or status is vain, low-class, bad.</li>
        <li>Worthier pursuits include passions, hobbies, causes, communities, love, faith, friendship, family.</li>
        <li>In people: Better (morally) to be capable than to be rich or clever, better to be hard-working than to be capable, better to be passionate than to be hard-working, better to be kind than to be passionate, best of all to be “good”: a good father, a good mother, a good friend, a good person.</li>
        <li>In art: Better to be well-crafted than to be expensive, better to make someone think than to merely be well-crafted, better to make someone feel than to make someone think, best of all to be a work of authentic expression, to say something, to mean something.</li>
        <li>The worth of a person (or artwork or country or culture) is immeasurable. Even individual traits — intelligence, beauty, kindness, skill, humor, charisma, perseverance, competence, knowledge — are themselves multidimensional and complex and should never be pinned down or quantified.</li>
       </ul>
      <p>These principles are observed more by the elite than the masses, more in public than in private, more in official settings than in casual settings, and more in speech than in action.</p>
      <p>Some related rules of discourse:</p>
       <ul>
        <li>Never comment on someone’s looks, wealth, intelligence, or status. (Even though they don’t matter, you might hurt someone’s feelings, because … they do actually matter? Like, a lot?)</li>
        <li>Avoid making direct comparisons of people along any axis. You may say Bob is very diligent, and Sam works tirelessly, but only a rube would make a comment (to a group of more than three) about who is *more* hardworking. No one with a college degree will ever say that one person is smarter than another. And certainly no one at all would ever say that one woman is a better mother than another, true though it may be.</li>
        <li>A movie review in the local paper says it’s “good”. (How shallow! How simplistic!) A movie review in the NYT might grudgingly allow that it’s “compelling” or that it “succeeds” in some aspect. All this is quite beneath the movie review in a literary magazine, which will leave it mostly a mystery whether the author liked the movie, though hints may be subtly dropped while commenting on the human condition. In sum, if you really <em>must</em> speak of "merit", the more elite you are, the more you must offer subtlety, false nuance, and plausible deniability.</li>
       </ul>
      <p>I'm sure some of these ideas are universal. <strong>But I want to suggest that these principles are</strong> <strong><em>less</em></strong> <strong>observed in China.</strong></p>
      <p>It’s hard to know how to make a fair comparison, since of course large segments of all societies are obsessed with appearances or fame or money. But in the following anecdata, consider whether the same would happen in your country <em>in settings of the same social status and prominence</em>. In no particular order:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>My uncle tells me that growing up, class rankings of students were posted on the wall, from first <em>all the way to last</em>.</li>
        <li>When you sign up for Weibo, the Chinese Twitter, you can pick your starter interests. Among “sports”, “science”, and the like, there is the category 美女帅哥 “hot girls and guys”. (Just the lack of subtlety was a bit jarring to me; at least call it “influencers” or “fitness pics” or something.)</li>
        <li>The Chinese take pride in <em>the</em> “Four Classic Novels” and <em>the</em> “Four Great Inventions”, pinnacles of ancient Chinese achievement. The items on these lists are common knowledge. A Chinese acquaintance recently told me about the “three greatest painters and three greatest sculptors of the European Renaissance”, reciting their names in a rehearsed way that sounded taught.</li>
        <li>Common phrases to describe eligible men include 高富帅 and 三高男, which are short forms for “tall, rich, and handsome” and something like “triple-threat men”, meaning high-income, highly educated, and tall. (Of course in English there are different phrases like “dark and handsome” or “sugar daddy” for different kinds of potentially attractive partners, but the Chinese versions just seem way too ... on the nose.)</li>
        <li>It’s normal for random people (e.g., your barber) to ask you how much money you make. If you demur, they will actually press on in asking. (“10k a month? 20k?”)</li>
        <li>Acquaintances will not hesitate to tell you you’ve gotten too fat or too skinny.</li>
        <li>To say the best-known New Year’s greeting, 恭喜发财 (Gong Hei Fat Choi / Gongxi facai), is to wish that someone get rich. It is typically translated as wishing someone a “prosperous New Year”, which softens it nicely for the Western ear, but the Chinese version is quite direct and unambiguous: “make lots of money!”</li>
        <li>The obsession with prestigious schools and their specific rankings. It’s hard to disentangle this one from the great value placed on education in general, but even Westerners who care a lot about education would be a bit embarrassed at how Chinese people will rattle off lists of university rankings.</li>
        <li>Selfie-beautifying apps are <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/12/18/chinas-selfie-obsession">reportedly</a> more extreme and more mainstream in China.</li>
        <li>That <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008_Summer_Olympics_opening_ceremony#Girl_lip-synching_to_recording_by_another_singer">infamous lip-synched performance</a> at the 2008 Beijing Olympics sung by an 8-year old who was deemed not cute enough to actually appear</li>
        <li>Take a look at the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_given_name#Common_Chinese_names">most common Chinese given names</a> and how many of them are things like “pretty”, “beautiful”, “clever”, “gorgeous”. What’s more, unlike in English, pretty much any name’s meaning is transparent to all Chinese speakers. Of course we also have “Belle” and “Bonnie” and the like, but they don’t dominate the list. Instead Western name lists are dominated by Biblical names that typically mean “God is gracious” or some such, again pointing to faith/transcendence rather than “shallow” traits.</li>
        <li>It’s common to encounter such phrases as “cultural level” 文化水平, “artistic level” 艺术水平, or “high/low quality [people]” 高/低素质. Of course we talk about similar concepts in English, but I’m drawing attention here to the use of words like “level” which make it impossible to avoid the implication that you can line everyone up from highest to lowest. (“Level” 水平 transparently derives its meaning by analogy to “water level”.)
       <ul>
        <li>Example: The CCP designates certain cities as “<a href="https://zh.wikipedia.org/zh-cn/%E5%85%A8%E5%9B%BD%E6%96%87%E6%98%8E%E5%9F%8E%E5%B8%82">National Civilized Cities</a>” 全国文明城市, which the lucky mayors are sure to add to their resumes.  Among the criteria for this designation are various economic indicators, and this: 市民整体素质和文明程度较高 “Overall, city residents are high-quality and highly civilized.” This is an awkward translation to be sure, but I'm reluctant to smooth it out since you lose part of the meaning. The nearest equivalent that could be uttered by an American politician might be “Most residents here are upstanding, law-abiding citizens,” but that elides the sense of 程度 “degree” (of quality/civilization), which directly invites quantification/comparison.</li></ul></li>
       </ul>
      <p>Possible explanations:</p>
       <ul>
        <li>
          <strong>I am mistaken about Chinese culture.</strong> I don’t speak the language well enough and haven’t been immersed in the culture long enough to discern the subtleties, to catch the intentional ironies, to grasp the humor, to hang with the elite, to distinguish high culture from low culture.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Climbing Maslow’s hierarchy.</strong> As a society’s material needs are met, it cares less and less about the things that get you material things (money, intelligence, looks) and more about finding meaning in life, or something. China is simply a less developed country.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>The Communists destroyed Chinese culture.</strong> The elevated aspects of Chinese civilization were snuffed out in the Cultural Revolution, and as society builds itself up from scratch it naturally begins by clinging to its basest impulses.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>The lack of religion.</strong> Confucianism isn’t as concerned with transcending this material world as much as Christianity or Islam, so Chinese culture is more materialistic. But then I would have thought Buddhism would have pushed in the opposite direction and sway people away from shallow pursuits.</li>
        <li>
          <strong>Random cultural variation.</strong> While the Chinese more freely talk about how fat you are or how much money you make, on other topics they are quieter. For example, the whole family and the doctor will <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Farewell_(2019_film">keep it a secret</a>) from Grandma that she is dying. What does this mean? Nothing. Everyone and every culture cares about dying, just like everyone cares about intelligence, looks, and wealth; whether it's polite to talk about them is just a convention. And it's normal for conventions to vary idiosyncratically across cultures. There's nothing deep here.</li>
       </ul>
      <p>And two possible takes:</p>
       <ul>
        <li>The mindset whose go-to tool is to rank people along superficial dimensions is terribly one-dimensional, shallow, and simplistic. It reflects a lack of individuality, spirit, creativity, and capacity to innovate. China will never overtake America.</li>
        <li>Westerners’ ever growing list of sensitivities reflects a general descent into wishy-washiness and an inability to recognize or appreciate objective reality and objective merit. The West is doomed if it fails to course-correct.</li>
       </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>