<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2021-03-01T12:09:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lv2rb7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_01_2021/gpai54v/</link>
  <title>Relitigating social norms and the Sisyphean task of the mistake theorist</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It seems to me that posters who respond to this bind by writing (2)--tarring not only individual users but also the whole sub and its <a href="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/On_Liberty/Chapter_2">Millian approach</a> to open discourse--may be engaged in a sort of cultural post-Stilson frustration.  Having abolished chattel slavery via Civil War, endured the ravages of Jim Crow, defeated the race-obsessed Nazis, and emerged from the Civil Rights Movement with renewed commitment to tolerance, values pluralism, and inclusion... <em>how the fuck are we still having this fight!?</em>  Like, <em>how many times</em> do you have to <em>beat the literal and rhetorical shit</em> out of <em>racists</em> before they <em>stay down!?</em>  Well, apparently, they think the answer is "<em>at least one more time</em>, right here in the comments!"</p>
      <p>(And if the moderators and the sub are going to give comfort to the enemy by accommodating them, why, they must <em>be</em> the enemy, and damn all copious evidence to the contrary.)</p>
      <p>I understand that frustration--I really do!  But if I can be forgiven something of an oversimplification, here, the main problem with (1) is that it expresses poor thinking that <em>might</em> eventually result in some genuine personal or social harm, while the main problem with (2) is that it directly abandons the whole ethos of the sub, which is "Hermione, not Ender."  People who post (1) in bad faith will be dealt with eventually, but they are hard cases and it's important that we take time to generate quality responses to them.  People who post (2), however, are not hard cases.  Their violation of the rules is probably <em>less bad</em> for the sub, ultimately, than (1), but unless we want the sub to degenerate into the low-effort back-and-forth sniping that characterizes most spaces on social media, we have to respond to (2) much more swiftly and decisively.  (Which, unfortunately, has been difficult lately due to low moderator availability--but we are working on that problem too!)</p>
      <p>Because you can't actually beat racism (etc.) the way Ender beat the Buggers.  It hasn't got kidneys to kick.  There's always someone new, who hasn't heard the arguments yet, who hasn't had the formative experiences, who hasn't been personally subjected to an effortfully-outstretched hand.  You could <em>temporarily</em> correct wrongthink by simply murdering everyone who disagrees with you, and we mostly reject that approach because it is horrifying--but also because it is only ever a temporary fix, and such a high cost cannot be borne for it.  There is no argument so perfect that it stays won forever.  So as frustrating as it can be to carefully relitigate matters as new people appear in our communities, so long as new people and new ideas are permitted, and so long as every idea is potentially new to <em>someone</em>... you either commit yourself to patience with and tolerance for one another and one another's arguments, or you spend your life with a perpetual sneer marring your face as the world, inevitably, forever fails to meet your expectations.</p>
      <p>The Motte is not a platform for racists, or whatever else its shortsighted, hateful critics accuse it of being. It <em>is</em> a platform for wrongthink, insofar as we do not ban people simply for expressing weird or shady thinking. And it is a group of people who have all more-or-less agreed that we're happier talking to polite people with bad ideas, than to mean people with good ones.  Certainly it is my experience that many people with bad ideas eventually become people with good ideas, but I have known precious few people with cruel, disdainful dispositions who ever became <em>nicer</em>.  Indeed, it is all too common for people to only get crueler, the longer the world disappoints them.  If there is something we can do to help polite people with bad ideas become polite people with <em>good</em> ideas, why--that is a change I would like to see in the world.</p>
      <p>So, that is my long-winded explanation of my thought processes in last week's HBD threads.  And even now, part of me whispers, "why bother? The people who agreed with your moderation either already know all this and needed no explanation, or disagree with all of this but agree with your moderation for bad reasons.  Conversely the people who disagree with your moderation either assume for their own reasons that you are lying, or simply dislike you enough to assume the worst anyway."  But my own principles dictate my response to that whisper: even the disdainful are friends waiting to be made, if only I could find a way to persuade them to think past their prejudices.  That's what it is, to be a committed <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/24/conflict-vs-mistake/">mistake theorist</a>: to recognize the conflict theorists for what they are, and to reach out anyway, to the best of one's ability, in spite of the potential costs.  Not because I think everyone is or ought to be a mistake theorist, or because I think everyone is acting in good faith, or because I think there are no costs or problems with this way of doing things--but only because it's the only thing I've ever done that seems to genuinely make the world an (albeit infinitesimally!) better place.  So that's what I've been doing, and what I plan to keep on doing.</p>
      <p>And every second I have to spend slogging through the mud with people doing (2) <em>even though they must know it is not permitted</em>, is a second I can't spend fixing (1).  And if your response is "but you wouldn't fix (1) anyway," you're wrong--I have in the past.  I'd like to do it in the future, too.</p>
      <p>....aaaaand in the time it took me to write this, <a href="/u/Bingleschitz">/u/Bingleschitz</a> managed to <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/lv2rb7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_01_2021/gpagays/">condense it into 21 words</a>.  Well, we all have our talents.  Sorry brevity isn't mine.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>