<post>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2021-03-03T02:29:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lv2rb7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_01_2021/gphn173/</link>
  <title>The impact of bureaucracy on COVID-19 vaccination approvals</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/doses-of-astrazenecas-covid-19-vaccine-pile-up-in-europe-amid-government-restrictions-11614715968">France finally approves AstraZeneca's COVID-19 vaccine for seniors</a>
      </p>
      <p>For those not following this story, AstraZeneca is a British-Swedish pharmaceutical giant that is contracted for more vaccine doses than any other company - some 3+ billion doses, nearly 1/3 of the 9.6 billion total doses reserved by various governments. On Dec. 8, Oxford published the results of AstraZeneca's Phase III trials in <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20">The Lancet</a>32661-1/fulltext) demonstrating that its vaccine had 90% efficacy when distribution followed a certain low dose -&gt; standard dose protocol and that adverse events were balanced across the active and control arms in the studies, i.e. the active vaccine did not have safety concerns. The data was submitted to regulators, and the UK government approved the vaccine by Dec. 30, followed by regulatory authorities in more than a dozen other countries</p>
      <p>However, in a feat of immense bureaucratic incompetence, certain other governments have issued limited approvals excluding one core group from vaccine access: seniors (age 65+), the <a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#demographics">very demographic that comprises &gt;80% of COVID deaths</a>. This ignominious list includes Germany, Italy, and until today France. This decision was not based on any data suggesting the vaccine is ineffective for that age group, and <em>certainly</em> not due to any data evidencing risk of adverse effects for that age group - especially given that many <em>millions</em> of doses have been administered at this point, disproportionately to seniors (quite appropriately). Rather, the decision is based only on the fact that only 2 serious cases happened to emerge out of the 660 participants in the 65+ age band control group of the trials - making it difficult to ascertain the efficacy of the vaccine at that age range in a vacuum</p>
      <p>Now, as a personal participant in Pfizer's Phase III clinical trials, I've been very critical of the trial structures - in part, because of just this reason. The trials consist of enrolling tens of thousands of people, dividing them into vaccine and placebo groups, and then waiting until you hit a certain number of positive cases before unblinding the data and seeing what proportion of the cases were in each trial arm. This is an extremely slow and expensive process <em>that fails to generate very much useful data</em> - the AZ trials went from July through December without generating meaningful data about the vaccine's efficacy on by far the most crucial age group. Even in the better received trials, the stated efficacy is a loose statistical inference and the shared trial design of very limited testing unless you report symptoms means the trials fail to determine if the vaccine prevents asymptomatic cases - a crucial piece of information for crafting policy</p>
      <p>On the other hand, a challenge trial where just 500 volunteers were introduced to the contagion could experimentally demonstrate true efficacy and real data across all demographics very swiftly, shaving many months off the approval process and saving hundreds of thousands of lives and trillions of dollars in economic activity - at the expected cost of fewer than a handful of lives, 2 or so if the vaccines worked (they did). None of our regulators managed to approve running challenge trials - despite <a href="https://www.1daysooner.org/">tens of thousands of willing volunteers</a> - until <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02821-4">October 2020</a> (to begin in 2021), because they were unable to shake off the institutional inertia and procedural habits that they were in the customs of adhering to. In the sage words of Curtis Yarvin, borrowed from another context: regulators operate according to <em>process</em> and not <em>mission</em>; they are not given resources and ordered to solve a problem with them; rather, they have standard procedures to execute properly and correctly. And so, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/moderna-designed-coronavirus-vaccine-in-2-days-2020-11">a vaccine that was developed in 2 days in January 2020</a> took nearly a year to get approved during a mega-emergency pandemic despite clear pathways to <em>more</em> scientifically rigorous data via controlled experimentation in a fraction of the time</p>
      <p>Anyway, back to our current dilemma. The AstraZeneca is shown to be safe for seniors. It is shown to be very effective for other demographics and nothing within the trial suggests that it <em>would</em> be less effective for seniors - the poorly designed experiment simply failed to generate enough data to that effect. But if we allow ourselves to look outside the trial, we can see that The Lancet published in December a study showing laboratory results clearly experimentally demonstrating "<a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20">similar immunogenicity across age groups</a>32466-1/fulltext)". And it must be stated that even if the efficacy of the vaccine <em>were</em> reduced in the elderly, they would still benefit the most from inoculation - a 10% effective vaccine given to those 65+ would save more lives than a 100% effective vaccine given to under 50's given <a href="https://bmcpublichealth.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12889-020-09826-8">mortality differentials</a></p>
      <p>Yet leaders, regulators, and governments are specifically withholding the vaccine from the group most in need - because rather than thinking logically and scientifically, they are slavishly beholden to a specific quasi-scientific <em>process</em>. They are only capable of sanctifying one excruciatingly slow, exorbitantly costly path to approval - no matter how much blood and treasure is lost by their obstinate refusal to simply rationally consider the evidence, they hold robotically, mindlessly firm against thinking outside the rudimentary paint-by-numbers lines. Germany's Angela Merkel - who has a <a href="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Angela-Merkel">Doctorate in Quantum Chemistry</a> - cannot break free of this mental prison; even intelligent leaders with domain specific knowledge are slaves to the rigid processes that our bureaucracies view as the One True Path, all other evidence be damned. If these regulators were at all concerned with achieving positive outcomes, they would acknowledge that the process is a formality and that <strong>data speaks for itself</strong></p>
      <p>In what should come as absolutely no surprise, England came out today with findings showing that, yes, the vaccine is <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/health-56240220">similarly highly effective in seniors</a>, just as the original immunogenicity findings affirmed. In response, France has now allowed seniors to become vaccinated - a full <strong>2 months</strong> after the UK; due to the previous policy, just 273,000 AstraZeneca doses have been administered in France out of 1.7 million received by the end of February. In Germany, only 240,000 of 1.45 million doses had been used by February 23. Meanwhile, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/k3pgku/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_30/ger3zfr/?context=3">our feckless and criminally incompetent American FDA</a> refuses to comment on the life saving vaccine until a new trial is conducted, <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-health-coronavirus-usa-astrazeneca/emergency-u-s-authorization-for-astrazeneca-covid-19-vaccine-likely-in-april-idUSKBN29420M">setting expectations</a> for an April approval - more than 3 months after the UK's approval. All the while, our vaccine distribution proceeds at a crawl, averaging 0.3% of our population per day, with leaders <a href="https://www.unz.com/isteve/cdc-maybe-our-vaccine-priority-philosophy-of-diversity-inclusion-equity-you-trailertrash-needs-a-bit-of-a-rethink/">unable to even agree on basic precepts</a> like <a href="https://www.flgov.com/2021/01/12/cdc-to-reverse-course-and-follow-floridas-lead-prioritizing-seniors-first-for-vaccinations/">prioritizing the elderly</a>. A spectacular failure from start to finish, with our scientific intelligentsia apparently bereft of champions who can step in and apply simple common sense at any stage of the process</p>
      <p>More and more, I'm left to conclude that Gregory Cochran was right - <a href="https://www.unz.com/isteve/there-is-no-inner-party-obama-let-his-18-year-old-daughter-intern-for-harvey-weinstein/">there is no Inner Party</a>, just myopic bureaucrats all the way down</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>