<post>
  <author>SnnapaaGrin</author>
  <date>2021-02-27T18:52:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lphu6c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_22/gp1zaez/</link>
  <title>Different approaches to Constitutional interpretation, and how they relate to the political spectrum</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Soap box, Ballot box, <del>Jury box,</del> Ammo box.</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I am sure that many of you are familiar with the above quote/sentiment. Regardless of the order in which the boxes should be used, I have come here to proclaim that the jury box no longer exists. In truth, it has not existed for a long time; but I do not feel that most people are sufficiently aware of this fact or the magnitude of its implications. </p>
      <p>Almost no one in the legal system (judges, academics, lawyers, legislators) has any idea what <em>the</em> law is nor even what <em>law</em> is in the first instance. The people running the show are entirely unaware that there is a fundamental and coherent system of law in the US, nor do they know its constituent elements, how those elements apply to certain functions (legislation, adjudication, etc.), how to deal with edge cases, or anything else. </p>
      <p>First, an example. The case <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/docket/docketfiles/html/public/20-157.html"><em>Caniglia v. Strom</em></a> will soon be argued in the Supreme Court. There, the issue is whether the police can use the "community caretaking exception" as justification to enter, search, and seize items within a house without a warrant. In brief, the "exception" states that if an officer has a reasonable suspicion that he can perform an act that will "reduce" "potential harm" to the "community," then his action does not violate the Constitution. In <em>Caniglia</em>, the officer in question believed that he could reduce potential harm by entering a man's house without a warrant, and against his express refusal to permit entry, to seize his firearms. Below, the First Circuit held that such an act was perfectly permissible, and obviously not a violation of the Fourth Amendment, or any other amendment or right, because the officer believed his actions would reduce potential harm to the community. </p>
      <p>For background. I will state that the First Circuit's opinion in <em>Caniglia</em> is obviously unconstitutional for a whole host of reasons. It violates the Fourth Amendment, among others. It violates Article III, and other elements of the Constitution and the common and statutory law which govern the power of a judge; phrased more simply, the judge fundamentally lacked the power to issue the decision in the first instance, regardless of whether or not the decision itself was unconstitutional. The holding "police can enter your home at any time if they have a reasonable suspicion that they could reduce potential future harm to the community by doing so" is without a judge's power. </p>
      <p>Now, the lunacy of this decision, and it is lunacy, is not the point of this example. The point of this example is that a whole host of state and federal courts agree with the First Circuit. </p>
      <p>More importantly still, is the fact that decisions like these are absolutely common place. Why? I offer two reasons.</p>
      <p>One reason is what this community would understand as "mistake theory." As I stated above, most people in the legal system, even at the highest levels, have no idea that America has an organized and principled system of law, those that do, do not know its most basic elements or limits. Those that have an idea of its basic elements have no ability to apply those elements, because they lack any sort of coherent or consistent framework for doing so, or for evaluating another person's claim of legality.</p>
      <p>I am in a position to know that this is true at the highest levels of the American legal academy. Professor J Doe is a world-class expert in J Doe's field. I once asked Professor Doe to explain how Professor Doe approaches the question of "interpretation." For the lay audience, this question is equivalent to the question "what do you believe is the correct method to determine whether some proposition or action (X) is legal/constitutional?" A charitable paraphrasing of Professor Doe's honest and in-depth response was that "there are certain principles that are associated with the Constitution, and those principles are important, and impact the question of constitutionality, and must be applied, but only appropriately." This was Professor Doe's full, top-to-bottom, detailed explanation of how Professor Doe believes one should determine whether some act or proposition is legal or constitutional. I double checked that this was Professor Doe's true opinion by reviewing all articles that Professor Doe has ever published, and confirmed that Doe's entire publication history lacks any defined, detailed, or coherent means of determining constitutionality. This is like a chemistry professor saying that a complete statement of his understanding of the reaction that occurs when baking soda encounters vinegar is that "certain sub-elements of the atoms which comprise the two substances change places when the substances touch." </p>
      <p>Professor Doe's complete lack of a framework is bog-standard for the legal academy and applies to all disciplines. Those few individuals who have frameworks rarely have ones worthy of the name. This situation is not surprising, as law students are taught almost exclusively about what judges or professors have said <em>about</em> the law, instead of being taught the law itself. This same lack of understanding is also true of most judges.</p>
      <p>This is a problem because no one has any idea how anything is supposed to work. This state of affairs is inconsistent with the rule of law. We do not have the rule of law if most participants don't know what the system is, what they are allowed to do, or what happens when another fault is introduced to the system. This is how we get to a place where people arrive at a decision like the First Circuit in <em>Caniglia</em> with a straight face.</p>
      <p>The second reason is what this community will recognize as conflict theory. While most people involved in the legal system have no idea about its most basic parts, many simply don't care. An increasingly large fraction of people simply do not believe in the concept of law or in the concept of rule of law. </p>
      <p>Essentially all American theories of constitutional interpretation fall into two categories. (See, e.g., 113 Nw. Univ. L.Rev. 1243). The first category contains theories that incorporate the principles of fixation and constraint. The principle of fixation holds that the semantic content, or "meaning," of a law is fixed at the time it was ratified or enacted. For the Bill of Rights, this would be 1791, but for a statue it would be the time at which the statue was signed into law and became effective according to its provisions. The principle of constraint holds that judges are constrained by the meaning of the law; aka, judges have to follow the law just like everyone else. Theories which follow these two principles are defined, rightly or wrongly, as "originalist."</p>
      <p>All other theories fall into the second category, defined as theories which lack either the principle of fixation, the principle of constraint, or both. Now, consider what this means. A theory of interpretation is a method of determining legality. A theory which lacks the principle of fixation holds that the meaning of a law, which defines what it is for a thing to be legal, does not need to be the meaning that was actually made a part of the law, it can be something else entirely. A theory which lacks the principle of constraint permits judges to flatly ignore what the law says. Both outcomes are more or less the same: there is no such thing as law. At least not to judges. These theories are defined as "living constitutionalism;" and living constitutionalism is almost exclusively left-leaning.</p>
      <p>Essentially, living constitutionalist theories are not theories of "interpretation" or of the law at all. They are obfuscatory justifications for normative political arguments. They do not argue what the law <em>is</em> or what the law <em>requires</em>, they argue only about what the law <em>should</em> be or what non-legal social outcome is desirable. This is obvious on the face of every living constitutionalist work of which I am aware. </p>
      <p>As I said, living constitutionalism is increasingly popular. All law schools hold frequent and regular workshops where faculty gather to hear an author present a paper or work in progress. At one top school, the number of papers heard by the faculty that apply living constitutionalism is north of 70%, with expressly left-leaning papers commanding a similar percentage of attention. </p>
      <p>A colleague sent me a paper that has recently made the rounds at the top schools. The premise of the paper is that the existence of a Supreme Court is a stumbling block for the implementation of progressive policy goals and so it must be eliminated or reduced. Note, not <em>the</em> Supreme Court, but <em>a</em> Supreme Court. Therefore, the paper surveys, catalogs and analyzes the most likely means by which progressives might eliminate or otherwise neuter the Supreme Court. The authors identify themselves as progressives, and make their purposes plain at the start of the paper. </p>
      <p>This paper was shopped around to the best schools in the country, so the authors' ideas could be critiqued and improved by the rest of the progressive intelligentsia. Purely political, total-culture-war. And not a hit of connection to the law, beyond the fact that the methods proposed involved the "law," at least according to the idea that the law is whatever one wants it to be. </p>
      <p>If you thought that you might need to rely on the jury box at some point in the future, you should revise your plans. That ship has sailed. Without a meaningful legal system in the technical sense, I have no idea how the country can continue. Nor do I have any idea how this problem can be repaired. I'm not sure if the circumstances that would result in most of the participants in the legal system having any idea about how it works, regardless of what that system is, can exist without some sort of social/national cataclysm.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>