<post>
  <note>Not a fan of this post, for reasons Gemmaem gives rather succinctly.</note>
  <author>wlxd</author>
  <date>2021-03-02T19:59:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/lv2rb7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_01_2021/gpga2vl/</link>
  <title>"Human Biodiversity" As Another Step on the Linguistic Treadmill</title>
  <category>
    <li>coteries</li>
    <li>moloch</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The whole notion of "HBD" was exactly invented as a new, clean well. It was introduced as a new, untainted term, so that there is a water hole people can gather around, and exchange ideas and observations. However, it was soon noticed that these ideas are wrongthink, and so the water hole was promptly poisoned.</p>
      <p>Consider, as a contrast, the notion of "eugenics". Today it is thoroughly associated with something evil, and widely condemned by everyone, left and right, pretty much much on par with "racism". At the same time, if you look back at when this term was originally invented and became popular, you'll find that all kinds of smart, good-meaning people were eugenists back in the day. In fact, modern statistics has been invented by eugenists, for the purposes of eugenics, and so was population genetics. </p>
      <p>The principal founder was Francis Galton, who introduced statistics as a scientific tool, and he did so precisely for the purpose of studying psychometry (the field he also invented) and genius. He invented the notion of variance/standard deviation, introduced correlation and regression as statistical tools, and first discovered regression to the mean. These are, today, most basic foundation of all quantitative science. All invented for the purposes of eugenics. By the way, Galton happened to be a grandson of Charles Darwin, which is, in context of his eugenics ideas, a very interesting <em>coincidence</em>, isn't it?</p>
      <p>A second father of modern statistics, Karl Pearson, was a student of Galton, and his work was also on eugenics. He was strongly inspired by Galton, and after his death, he prepared a three volume biography of his. His contributions were, among others, Pearson's correlation coefficient, the fundaments of statistical hypotheses testing, the notion of p-values, the chi-square test, and the principal component analysis. All of these are, again, workhorses of all modern science.</p>
      <p>However, the single most important figure in 20th century statistics was Ronald Fisher, who not only, according to Anders Hald, "almost single-handedly created the foundations for modern statistical science", but did the same with modern evolutionary theory and population genetics too. He was the most important figure in the field of evolutionary biology after Darwin. And he just so happened to be a founding Chairman of the University of Cambridge Eugenics Society. Funny how that works, isn't it?</p>
      <p>Why were all those great, productive minds enamored with something so morally repugnant and widely condemned as eugenics? How is it possible that they not only held such views, but in fact promoted them fully in the open, creating Eugenics Societies, and getting other famous and accomplished people as members, including Winston Churchill, John Maynard Keynes, Margaret Sanger, and even John Harvey Kellogg, the one of breakfast cereals fame? </p>
      <p>As far as I can tell, this was an outcome of unfortunate association with Nazi actions, but I think more important factor was the relentless agitprop on the side of intelligentsia, which found a fertile soil among Christian believers, who also objected to eugenics, but for other reasons. The reason I blame propaganda is simple: there is nothing that's seriously morally repugnant in the basic idea to eugenics. It might conflict with some particular moral systems, especially that of many Christian groups, but that hasn't been an obstacle for social change and widespread adoption, or at least toleration of an idea. I mean, birth control? Abortion? Divorce? These are some things which are more immediately socially significant than eugenics is, and they also encountered forceful opposition, and yet here we are. </p>
      <p>No, the reasons I blame propaganda is that it is not true that being associated with murderous regime is a death knell for an idea, and you need only to look at socialism/communism for an example. The intelligentsia attacked eugenics for their ideological reasons, stemming from post-war, anti-colonial, equalitarian postmodern theories, and Christians simply saw no reason to oppose it. </p>
      <p>Just to preempt the objection: there certainly have been morally repugnant actions which used eugenics as justification. For example, I consider forced sterilization to be morally repugnant in many (but not all) cases. However, using good principles to justify wrong actions is a constant theme of most of recent history, and it's definitely not true that it always impinges negatively on the principles. At the same time, there are plenty of completely harmless, consensual, IRB-passing ways through which one might promote eugenics. So no, there is nothing innately repugnant in it to most people (most people in fact typically find eugenics rather natural and desirable, if framed in terms not invoking Pavlovian reactions), it's all just a smear.</p>
      <p>As the eugenics well has been thoroughly poisoned, the notion of HBD was introduced, which is clearly not the same thing as eugenics, but it is centrally located inside the same cluster in the space of ideas. Alas, that cluster has been deemed wrongthink by intelligentsia, and the HBDers will share the fate of eugenicists of the past -- or worse, as eugenicists have at least been recognized by their non-explicitly-eugenic contributions. HBDers of today will not get it, instead  they are cancelled on sight.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>