<post>
  <author>Ame_Damnee</author>
  <date>2020-09-05T12:43:55Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ijs526/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_31_2020/g448fx8/</link>
  <title>A Deep Dive Into A Few Polls</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Half said they felt less safe, including 54 percent of women and 50 percent of independents. Asked whether having Biden as president would make them feel more or less safe, a plurality of respondents said more safe, including pluralities of women and about a third of independents.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>That's some weaseling with figures there.</p>
      <p>So 54% of women respondents said they felt "less safe" with Trump as president.  But an unknown percentage which is still more than 50% also said they would feel less safe with Biden as president.</p>
      <p>"A plurality" of women is "a large proportion of the respondents but less than 50% so not a simple majority", yes?  So less than 50% of women respondents would feel more safe with Biden as president.</p>
      <p>So I'm taking two things away from this: (1) You can slant the results whatever way you want.  You can make it "54% of women feel less safe with Trump as president" (oh noes!) but equally you can make it "Fewer than 50% of women would feel more safe with Biden as president" (yikes!)  (2) whatever the reason those women are not feeling as safe, Biden ain't the cure so maybe Trump is not the problem?</p>
      <p>I never in my life believed Trump would ever manage to become President of the United States, so my jaw was hanging as unhinged in disbelief as the jaws of everyone else the morning after the election when the results were rolling in.  But honestly, the more I see of these pre-emptive "Biden's bad results explained away, or, Bad Polls What Bad Polls? And besides it's all Trump's fault!" articles, the more I am coming to the expectation that we will get Make America Even Greater: Trump Administration II.</p>
      <p>EDIT: Okay, just for pig iron because I am that bitch, I went looking for that Quinnipac poll to see if I could pull some figures out of it.  I am taking it that the "Wednesday poll" mentioned above is the "September 2 national poll" on the Quinnipac website.</p>
      <p>Here's a juicy plum from the <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/national/release-detail?ReleaseID=3671">press release</a>:</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>MORE SAFE, LESS SAFE  </p>
        <p>Fifty percent of likely voters say having Donald Trump as president of the United States makes them feel less safe, while 35 percent say it makes them feel more safe, and 14 percent say it doesn't have any impact on how they feel.  </p>
        <p>Forty-two percent of likely voters say having Joe Biden as president of the United States would make them feel more safe, while 40 percent say it would make them feel less safe, and 16 percent say it wouldn't have any impact on how they feel.  </p>
        <p>"While the president has been pushing the issue of safety to the center of the presidential campaign, it raises the question: Who most has your back, the current administration, or the challengers? As racial strife, a seemingly endless pandemic, and an economy on life support unnerve Americans, voters foresee a more reliable lifeline in the Biden Harris ticket," added Malloy.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Now that's not splitting it into "women 'n' minorities", but there's not a clear majority who think Biden will make them feel all warm and snuggly cosy safe.</p>
      <p>50+35+14=99% for Trump question, so 1% don't give a damn about the question at all.</p>
      <p>42+40+16=98% for Biden, so 2% are not bothered either.</p>
      <p>So let's have a look.  Okay, yes, more people feel unsafe under Trump than under Biden - 50% against 42%.  On the other hand, while 8% is a good difference, neither is it <strong>massive</strong>.  Whoever is elected, somewhere around half the country is not going to feel safe.  So far, so party politics.</p>
      <p>35% would feel more safe under Trump, 40% under Biden.  Again, not a huge difference and again, whoever gets in, more people are going to feel less safe rather than more safe.</p>
      <p>14% against 16% don't think it'll make a difference, and heck we may as well throw the unconcerned 1-2% in with them. So nothing there.</p>
      <p>I am not seeing huge reasons for literal fear-mongering there no matter who your guy is.  Maybe that's why the article went for the "women 'n' minorities worst off!" angle with it.  Otherwise, the results seem to boil down to "the half of the electorate that support the losing party candidate don't like the winning party candidate" which is not something strange, new or startling in politics.</p>
      <p>Most of the <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/images/polling/us/us09022020_udmp37.pdf">polling</a> seems to break down like that - someone experienced in American poll results explain this one to me, how you get 58 out of 84 and 95:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Likely voters say 58 – 38 percent that the country is worse off than it was in 2016, the year of the last presidential election. Republicans say 84 – 15 percent the country is better off, Democrats say 95 – 4 percent it is worse off, and independents say 60 – 36 percent it is worse off.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>(Is this how they derive the figures?</p>
      <p>84+4+36 positive = 124/3=41% things are better</p>
      <p>15+95+60 negative =170/3=57% things are worse.)</p>
      <p>Ochre Party says things going swell with their guy in charge!  Taupe Party say it's a hellhole!  Desert Sand Group says everything is awful (but no indication whether they think it would be less, more or the same if other guy gets in)!</p>
      <p>Is anybody really shocked, shocked to learn that the Republicans think "good", Democrats think "bad"?  An overall 16% think the country is worse off - if the parties in power were switched, do you think we'd be getting the same results?  Was there a similar poll back for Obama's second term?</p>
      <p>Let's wade into the favorability stats because oh momma, the figures are one thing but the descriptive language is doing its utmost to shill for one side over the other.  I thought polls were supposed to be neutral?</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>FAVORABILITY RATINGS: BIDEN AND HARRIS  </p>
        <p>Biden receives a mixed favorability rating, as 45 percent have a favorable opinion and 48 percent have an unfavorable opinion. For Democratic Vice Presidential candidate Kamala Harris, 40 percent of likely voters have a favorable opinion of her, 34 percent have an unfavorable opinion, and 25 percent haven’t heard enough about her.  </p>
        <p>FAVORABILITY RATINGS: TRUMP AND PENCE  </p>
        <p>Likely voters give Trump a negative favorability rating with 56 percent having an unfavorable opinion and 41 percent viewing him favorably. Vice President Mike Pence’s favorability rating is also underwater as 47 percent of likely voters have an unfavorable opinion of him and 38 percent view him favorably.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Let's take the figures before I start the literary criticism.</p>
      <p>Biden: favourable 45%  unfavourable 48%</p>
      <p>Trump: favourable 41% unfavourable 56%</p>
      <p>Bigger difference in those who dislike Trump (56-48=8%) than those who prefer Biden (45-41=4%).  Another way to look at it: both candidates are more disliked than liked, with larger margin for Trump (because he is more polarising) - 3% more dislike Biden, 15% more dislike Trump.  Yet that is "mixed" for Biden and "negative" for Trump.  Technically yes, but Biden too has a higher (if closer) unfavourable than favourable rating.  Negative for them both, I think, is better (if you're not putting your thumb on the scale for one over the other).</p>
      <p>Battle of the Veeps next.</p>
      <p>Harris: favourable 40% unfavourable 34% who she? 25%</p>
      <p>Pence: favourable 38% unfavourable 47% (but at least <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wL5rVZJ0RNQ">you have heard of me</a>)</p>
      <p>So Harris, surprisingly, comes out on top here: slightly more favourable rating (40-38=2%) which is not a massive lead, I'd put them both there or thereabouts on this.  The unfavourability is the big one: 47-34=13% of a gap.</p>
      <p>So between Biden/Trump, unfavourable = 48% to 56%, 8% more dislike Trump, and Harris/Pence, unfavourable =47% to 34% , 13% more dislike Pence, Pence beats his boss on being disliked.  I don't know if I would or would not call that "underwater" for Pence; again, both he and Harris have similar favourability.  It depends what way those uninformed of her existence 25% would swing to Harris if she were more or less liked.</p>
      <p>Maybe Trump should change his VP!  (I think Pence is suffering from the "dour Evangelical gay torture camp" rep which isn't so near to what the man is; at least, he had no problem hosting our gay Taoiseach and boyfriend for Paddy's Day in <a href="https://www.thejournal.ie/conversion-therapy-ireland-bill-ban-3903038-Mar2018/">2018</a> and meeting them again in <a href="https://www.independent.ie/videos/world-news/watch-us-vice-president-mike-pence-meets-leo-varadkar-and-marr-barrett-38462479.html">2019</a>).</p>
      <p>And maybe the Dems should switch who is headlining their ticket!  Biden has 45% to 48% favoured to disfavoured while Harris is 40% to 34%.  More people (allegedly) like Harris, so she beats her boss as well!</p>
      <p>Still, Harris has that 25% don't know me from a hole in the ground/don't want to admit to knowing me handicap, which will need a lot of making up if the whole point of picking a biracial woman as running mate was for representation and appeal to women 'n' minorities.</p>
      <p>All the rest of the issues? Split about how you'd expect along party lines.  Coronavirus, though, may not be the winning horse it's being touted as above:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>CORONAVIRUS OUTLOOK  </p>
        <p>Overall, likely voters are evenly split on whether the coronavirus situation in the United States is getting better, getting worse, or staying about the same. Thirty-three percent say better, 32 percent say worse, and 32 percent say the same. Along party lines, a majority of Republicans, 64 percent, say it’s getting better, while a majority of Democrats, 56 percent, say it’s getting worse. Independents are mixed: 38 percent say the same, 32 percent say better, and 27 percent say worse.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>So mostly the same numbers of potential voters say "better/worse/the same".  Not seeing the big winning edge on the pandemic for Biden there, which is probably why the article jumps polls to the CNN one.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>