<post>
  <author>Demonwaffle</author>
  <date>2020-08-27T12:25:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ifiyso/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_24_2020/g30k4y4/</link>
  <title>If You Have To Shoot Someone, It'll Be Quite a Few Bullets</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I had the opportunity to shoot a gun in a police station and talk to some police officers a while back (Germany here so handguns are not common at all). The officer obviously has a bias (he’s an officer), but at least in Germany the cops don’t go around shooting tons of people. Low double digits annually if that. </p>
      <p>Nonetheless this was his point: You aren’t supposed to shoot someone unless you believe they pose an imminent threat to you or someone else. So it is always going to be an insanely high adrenaline situation. And the thing that he said was: with a handgun, you can’t tell when someone has been hit. They don’t all lie down like in the movies. Theres not necessarily a spray of blood or a jerk, even with hollow-point ammunition. He showed us the impact hole of the bullets on the front of the targeting wall we were shooting at. They were tiny. 
According to him, skin is stretchy and closes back over a wound to a certain extent (haven’t verified this but seems plausible). And people wear clothes. So basically you don’t know if and how bad someone is hit until they lie down and stop moving. </p>
      <p>We were shown body cam footage. An officer tries to reason with a heavily drugged and aggressive half naked man with a huge knife. They are in a residential neighboorhood. The man continuously advances on the officer who backs away and tries to reason with him. This goes on for multiple blocks, until backup shows up. The officers try to triangle box the man with the knife. He realizes what is happening and starts running at the police officer, sort of in an arc starting maybe at 15m away. The officer first moves as if to holster his gun, brings it back up and fires at the man half a dozen times from about 5 m distance. The whole time he is yelling for the knife wielder to back off. The knife wielder actually tackles him. There is footage from the backup showing the wrestling. The officer on the ground has lost his gun. One of the backup officers tases the suspect, who flops over. The first officer scrambles away and reclaims his gun. He then slowly approaches the prone man who is still clutching his knife. The man then leaps up swinging at the officer. Both him and the third back-up fire at the man about half a dozen times each, who proceeds to slow down and slowly tumble down. He is later found to have almost all the bullets inside him. </p>
      <p>So fifth hand anecdotal evidence here but:</p>
      <p>If you have to shoot someone. It is going to be quite a few bullets.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>