<post>
  <author>Denswend</author>
  <date>2020-09-04T10:11:54Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ijs526/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_31_2020/g3yrc8v/</link>
  <title>Bedlam and Competition of Violence</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There was a comic called <em>Bedlam</em> or Madder Red or something like that which was about not-Batman, not-Gotham and not-Joker but from a point of view of a "cured" Joker. There's a flashback in which not-Joker takes a group of school children hostage, kills them, mocks the people, and ends in custody. Now, he knows that they're going to jail him, he knows he's gonna escape, and he knows the situation will happen again to the detriment of law abiding citizens. He then ponders the absurdity of keeping and protecting someone who is clearly not-well, who will never stop, and who is an absolute detriment to community in the most objective sense that there can be. He then says that when the people realize this absurdity, they will eat them [the justice system] alive. Bizarre when you consider that this is the point of view of not-Joker who got better, but not so when you consider that his "treatment" was hardly in accordance of medical standards of "do no harm" and legal system. </p>
      <p>To a digress, lynchers <em>do</em> face consequences of their actions if their lynching was unjust, from the relatives and friends of the aggrieved. There's no shortage of tribalism, even today. It's a hope that faith in a neutral observer, an impassioned executor, will reduce the retaliatory action and break the circle of violence and hence you have the legal system. The addition of this legal system transforms the mere retaliatory retribution (no matter how just it is, or it is perceived to be) into a just <em>and legitimate</em> action and hence the axiom "the state is that which has monopoly on legitimate use of physical force". Whether the legitimate (and therefore justified) use of physical force manifests itself in death, mutilation, imprisonment, or other form of punishment culturally differs and matters little (well, it matters to the extent that the act of punishment be conducted in a manner that broad legal system considers it legitimate) - elaborate euphemisms hide the intent, but the ultimate assumption of "I feed on your energy" remains. An act of "lynching" which may or may not have viable justification backed into it, is inherently divorced from the aforementioned justice system. This differs from the usual deviant behavior like rape, murder, theft, etc in a sense that it unconsciously seeks to <em>usurp</em> the reason for existence of the legal system. And legal system like any other requires energy to exist, confers status (that is more often than not positive relative to the median), extracts toll. If I pay taxes for the common good, one of those being access to protection of the state from violent entities, and there is no protection of the state from the violent entities leading me to have to provide my own protection - why do I pay for a service I do not get? If a king rules because his rule brings prosperity and protection, but there is no prosperity and no protection - why is he a king? From the point of view of your average citizen, vigilantism is less preferable to the rule of law due to inherent unpredictable nature of vigilantism and retaliatory action that said vigilantism can provoke, but from the point of the state and people in power who <em>derive their power from monopoly on legitimate use of force</em>, there is competition in areas that absolutely must not be. </p>
      <p>This is exemplified in anarcho-tyranny, which is less a form of government, and more succinct descriptor of a failed government. To give a brief overview, government fails to provide protection to law-abiding citizens against unsavory elements (be it failure to enforce laws or failure to persecute, for whatever reasons may be)  but enforces overly strict tyranny upon law abiding citizens. 1984 NYC Subway shooting is a prime example of consequences of anarcho-tyranny:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Bernhard Goetz stated that three years before the incident, he had been attacked in the Canal Street subway station, while transporting electronic equipment, by three youths who attempted to rob him.[9] The attackers smashed Goetz into a plate-glass door and threw him to the ground, injuring his chest and knee.[10][failed verification] Goetz assisted an off-duty officer in arresting one of them; the other two attackers escaped. Goetz was angered when the arrested attacker spent less than half the time in the police station spent by Goetz himself, and he was angered further when this attacker was charged only with criminal mischief for ripping Goetz's jacket.[11][10] Goetz subsequently applied for a permit to carry a concealed handgun, on the basis of routinely carrying valuable equipment and large sums of cash, but his application was denied for insufficient need.[11] He bought a 5-shot .38-caliber revolver during a trip to Florida.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Furthermore, government is usually made up of human elements, and human elements have distinct inclinations and beliefs of what they can and cannot do, of what they're allowed or forbidden to do. An anarcho-tyrannical government may act against unsavory elements with less zeal because of various reasons - maybe it believes it cannot or should not punish them, maybe the punishment is insufficient (what does a fine and a loss of status in the polite society means to someone who collects government checks and has no desire to join polite society), maybe it fails to grasp the problem. But anarcho-tyrannical government still believes it has a right to enforce laws on law-abiding citizens, who do make pretensions at being in polite society, who want to participate in legitimate economic transactions. There is a plan, so to say, and that plan is that the law abiding citizens, the hoi polloi, the nervous Bernard Goetzs shut up, do as they're told, and obey the state. Reading wiki article about his it's jarring how closely the situation mirrors today. When the nervous pick up guns, that signals a problem. So vigilantism is a reaction to the perceived anarcho-tyrannical government, and when vigilantism comes in a context that polarizes people, when it's controversial, this signals that a large amount of people believe that the government is anarcho-tyrannical, that it is fundamentally, illegitimate. This comes as a shock to people who would prefer the status quo for various reasons (maybe they benefit from mandarin rule, maybe they're untouched by failure of state, I dunno), this comes as a shock to governmental elements because it questions what should not be questionable and represents a Jenga event, something that may or may not precipitate a disaster. To that extent, a disgusted reaction against vigilantism is a good reaction against vigilantism, because vigilantism is a sign of anarcho-tyranny, a failed state that necessarily implies the justification for dismantling the state and persecution of governmental elements that perpetuate anarcho-tyranny much how the fact that concentrated hydrocholoric acid damages skins implies the fact that you shouldn't bathe in it. And what happens when a corporation that holds a monopoly on something dies? Competition crops up, selling various different versions of that monopolized something. Power abhors a vacuum. </p>
      <p>The thing is that competition of violence is a very scary thing.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>