<post>
  <author>gattsuru</author>
  <date>2020-09-08T05:09:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/io1iih/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_07/g4exn0l/</link>
  <title>How have the Ballot Box and Soapbox Failed?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>How have the ballot box and soap box failed?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>As a trivial example: </p>
      <p>Defense Distributed tried to publish a proof of concept in 2013.  They were immediately hounded down.  Their 501(3)c mysteriously did not go through.  Their merchant processors, in the shadow of Operation Choke Point, <a href="https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1028008414939623425.html">shut down their other, undisputedly lawful sales</a>, and they were only able to retain their last bank as long as they do not let anyone know its name.  Their website was blocked under force of law, through arguments not supported by the text of the law nor in compliance with the constitution, and in the end not only was the central content itself blocked through official, <a href="https://twitter.com/jonst0kes/status/1026187162776166401">so were discussions about that censorship</a> through 'private' actors who get subpeona'd by Congress every year or two.</p>
      <p>Well, it was not merely bad policy, but unconstitutional, and more over <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernstein_v._United_States">unconstitutional</a> on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AACS_encryption_key_controversy">well-established grounds</a>.  The policy was even established in violation of the Administrative Procedures Act (or at least how it's enforced against Red Tribe changes).  Except it ended up taking nearly four years to get to the point of an actual day in court, after expenses that would have beggared most, and there was no end in sight then.</p>
      <p>((This process is not unique to this case: the Obama administration managed to keep various aspects of the <a href="https://taxprof.typepad.com/taxprof_blog/2018/06/the-irs-scandal-day-1869-in-meeting-with-lois-lerner-mccain-staffer-requested-financially-ruinous-au.html">IRS</a> and <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2019/05/08/politics/fast-and-furious-settlement-doj-house/index.html">Fast and Furious</a> scandals in judicial limbo for the better part of a decade, too.))</p>
      <p>But he won, in the ballot box.  The DoJ <em>says</em> it wasn't the Trump administration telling them to settle, but shortly after the Trump admin came in the DoJ settled.  Where they once were fighting tooth and nail to bleed DefDist dry.  It wasn't a <em>good</em> win, as DefDist would have to wait 45 days to apply for a license to do the thing that should be unconstitutional to license or set waiting periods for, but it was a win, right?</p>
      <p>Except, in the end, that didn't seem to matter.  Where DefDist's request for a preliminary injunction was thrown away despite the high chance of success, states arguing against allowing DefDist to publish gained nationwide injunctions readily despite iffy positions on not just the broad legal arguments but even questions of standing and jurisdiction.  <em>The states used a 10th Amendment claim in federal court and someone actually took it seriously, because their lawyers sure as hell didn't</em>.  Some of the procedural hi-jinks went from bizarre to <a href="https://dl.airtable.com/.attachments/07868961e2818ef90fe0da390705d1ad/7130a721/WashingtonvDefenseDistributedPetitionforEnBanc.pdf">the comedic</a>; one politician is spending New Jersey's tax money to argue that he isn't subject to Texan jurisdiction just because he threatened to arrest a Texan, by name, who is in Texas, over a thing done in Texas.</p>
      <p>They're <em>still</em> fighting this shit.</p>
      <p>If you ignore the political side, it doesn't 'matter'.  The rule doesn't prohibit shipping a thumb drive directly to your door, attempting to block the concept didn't work, the behavior it does prohibit federal law is horrible at preventing so much as making examples of.  And even the safety concerns that the gun-grabbing states are trying to motion around are more threatened by the contents of the average Home Depot than the typical 3D printer.</p>
      <p>But that really just highlights it.  The point <em>isn't</em> the visible argument, or some theoretical safety benefit.  The point is to crush anything that puts the lie to their political aspirations.  And <em>that</em> works fine. Defense Distributed won't be demonstrating that the laws don't work, because the only thing they <em>do</em> is stop people from pointing it out.</p>
      <p>Heller still can’t own the handgun that started the whole thing, in the same time that took us from <em>Lawrence</em> to <em>Obergfell</em>.  Gun owners stopping to piss in Albany still risk arrest, and the ballot box didn’t matter.  Neither did it stop a Virginia Governor from declaring gun-specific states of emergency, or the federal government from retaining transaction records. The less said about Penn preemption the better.  Remington is subject to a nuisance civil suit under the theory that their advertising is tortious, despite federal law specifically prohibiting that theory, and despite the actual bad actor not having purchased a product from them or their agents, or even there being any evidence he'd seen their advertising. The duly enacted laws against each and every one of these behaviors neither stop them nor even require bad actors to spend capital or time challenging them.</p>
      <p>It's not merely that these were costly wins, that the victors didn't get everything they wanted at once; that's a normal part of politics.  Nor that they were contested, or risked being rolled back if not guarded under constant vigilance.  It's that the central cases and specific matters that they supposedly focused on didn't count: they were wins on paper only.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>