<post>
  <author>JTarrou</author>
  <date>2020-09-06T11:53:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ijs526/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_31_2020/g48269e/</link>
  <title>What Should the Federal Government Do When Local Governments Refuse Help?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I propose a question: what, if anything, should the federal government do for citizens that live in places where the local governments refuse to try and stop this behavior?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Not a got-damned thing. The people in those communities are best situated to know what they want, and also to get it. They voted those local governments in, and were they displeased enough, they could replace them in weeks. Every town, every city, every locality gets the quality of government they want and deserve. This was what the citizens of Minneapolis wanted, and this is what they got. It's not what I would have wanted, and I'm sure it's not what everyone in the city limits wanted, but it is what the people who cared enough to form the local government wanted, so here we are. Mencken's Democracy, and all that. This is what things should look like. We should have towns and cities doing obviously mad things because they are run by people whose ideas are unconnected from reality. We should then expect there to be some long process of correction over time. The urge to fix everyone and everywhere <em>right now</em> should be resisted. Either one believes in local control, in which case local governments have to be allowed to make mistakes, or one does not. I am firmly on the side of local control. If the citizens of Minneapolis, or any other city riven by violence, rioting and looting care to make changes, there's an election coming up and I have no doubt there's someone running with ideas about how to fix things.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>edit: For those whose objections will inevitably be along the lines of "the local governments are too entrenched", this process can take a long time and in the meantime, people can create parallel governments to serve their needs. We saw this in some neighborhoods in Chicago during the riots, which organized their people and kept the violence out. Of course, this was subject to the same failure modes of everything else, but it worked for the purpose intended. This is the beautiful thing about social change. You don't have to wait for the process, you can make your own process. But what you want has to be what most people want. The problem is that people mistakenly believe that everyone wants what they want, but no one goes along. So they want the feds to enforce what they want, because it's not popular enough for people to organize around. The minute someone wants a higher level of government to enact their policies, you can be absolutely certain that they know, deep down, no one wants their policies.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>edit 2: I say this as someone who has come to the conclusion that no one wants my policies. I feel you. But "freedom" must mean on some level the ability to enjoy the consequences of one's actions, good or bad.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>