<post>
  <author>Krytan</author>
  <date>2020-09-03T15:01:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ijs526/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_31_2020/g3ur8ib/</link>
  <title>Violence: A Binary Switch or a Scale?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm not sure I agree, but it does bring up an important point about the use of force and physical violence. </p>
      <p>A lot of people seemingly believe violence is just totally fine and part of the fabric of life, and violence can only be responded to with similar levels of violence. Beatings, fistfights, flying kicks, etc, all just part of the rich tapestry of life's experiences and a real man restricts himself to responding in kind. I'm not trying to set up a straw man here, this idea isn't solely restricted to modern day liberals, obviously, it was the idea among many varied groups in the past from the Irish to the Americans settled in the Appalachians. If you had lost a fist fight and went and got a gun and shot the victor dead that would be well past what was acceptable. </p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>Other people believe violence is a binary switch. Either the situation has not devolved to violence and we are all just peacefully talking, or it has devolved to violence and lethal force is acceptable, because it's easy to kill or permanently injure someone with even a single punch and you have no idea where the madman who just violated all civilized norms by initiating violence will draw the line. I know a lot of people who carry, and absolutely ZERO of them get into physical fights. Part of this is the people for whom carrying is more attractive might be the people who think they wouldn't' be able to physically repel an attacker on their own, but also, in the training, you are told repeatedly that if you are carrying a gun it elevates the risk of a physical confrontation so you should avoid all physical confrontations unless you believe deadly force is appropriate, because since you have a gun, you've brought deadly force to the table. Even if you don't plan to use it, it can be taken away from you and then used. So, for example, you can't just shove some dude for getting in your face, harassing your girlfriend, or whatever. Even if these things would be normally totally acceptable in society. </p>
      <p>The latter model leads to less physical violence but higher costs to the violence that does happen. </p>
      <p>Now, clearly, different groups of people will benefit more from the different models (initiating violence justifies the victim to respond only with proportional violence) vs (initiating violence justifies the victim responding with deadly force)</p>
      <p>If you plan to initiate a lot of violence, you benefit from the first model. </p>
      <p>If your 'side' is more numerous, you benefit from the first model (you are unlikely to lose or be seriously hurt by a fists only confrontation)</p>
      <p>If you are a young strong healthy physically fit male, you benefit from the first model (most sectors of the population you can pretty easily dominate in a one on one confrontation)</p>
      <p>but...</p>
      <p>If you are elderly, sick, small, short, disabled, etc, you benefit much more greatly from the second option (you aren't going to win a fist fight, and even a plain old fist fight has an excellent chance of severely injuring you anyway. So a society where every fist fight is possible to to lead to the deaths of one of the participants is all upside, no downside to you)</p>
      <p>If you don't go around initiating violence, the second model is better for you. You don't want physical confrontation in your life, at all, and raising the costs of it is good for you, as you don't intend to engage in it. </p>
      <p>If you expect to be on the smaller side in any street fighting, the second model is better for you. You may not be able to win a street fight based on pure numbers, but being armed is a great equalizer.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>