<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2020-08-28T03:51:33Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ifiyso/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_24_2020/g33m8u5/</link>
  <title>Nietzche's Ideals and the Progressive Christ</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So the conservative Christian Answer (I’m not a theologian so kinda butchering it): Christ’s divinity and engagement with old testament teachings render him a continuation of the old testament prophets and kings, He is merely an insurgent King of the jews leading them to prosperity and the conquest via peaceful methods of the roman empire and its pagan values. In essence Christ is similar to David (slayer of Goliath) he violates the norms of ancient conquest so as to advance the kingdom of god. His end goal however remains the advancement of virtues and values  consistent with those prophets, he is not overturning the old testament merely providing the  method by which it can spread and survive under pagan occupation. Thus Jesus’s ultimate success is Emperor Constantine’s conversion t obeing a saintly christian and that all the kings of europe likewise converted.</p>
      <p>Jesus isn’t  remarkable because he overturn the kingly, noble virtues of antiquity and ancient Israel, he is remarkable because he is able to rebuild that so much stronger and greater from so little. And his sacrifice is Justified in that he ascends to the kingdom of heaven and provides a path for his followers to ascend. Jesus isn’t rejecting classical virtues and Aristotelian ideals... he’s just living up to them from an incredibly limited spot.</p>
      <p>Just as the Entrepreneur who starts with 1 penny and manages it to grow it 100’000% to $1000 has lived up to and in many respects exceeded one who starts with $10k and manages to end with $1m (10’000%)...So does jesus exceed but not reject the standards of the ancient Isreali prophets and kings.</p>
      <p>By contrast Progressives focus on the “rich man/eye of needle”, “blessed are the weak”, “my kingdom is not of this world”... ect. Idea of jesus. In essence the fact that kings, emperors and rich men come to embrace his teachings is a corruption of his teachings, Jesus is a rejection of the classical ideals of strength, will, intelligence and  courage. The weak, the unsure, the dull, and the meek: those are the truly virtuous! Those are the ones you should aspire to be! Those are the good people! To be strong, smart, ect. Is to be wicked. To be a king or leader or richer, or someone who multiplies his talents, that is vicious and evil. Essentially the envision Jesus as John Lennon singing <em>Imagine</em>.</p>
      <p>Now you can cite your various source the parable of the talents suggests one reading, the sermon on the mount suggests another ect.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Where Nietzsche is interesting is he thinks the progressives are right about who Jesus is and what he taught... its just he agrees absolutely with the conservatives that there is nothing redeemable in such a figure. He is a wretch who cannot be redeemed because he views his wretchedness as virtue and virtue as wretchedness. For Nietzsche (depending on your reading) the great project is rejecting Christianity, its moral codes and its descendant philosophies (communism ect.) and instead recapturing the classical virtues and ideals in a way that can move in the world. To get beyond the slave conceptions of “Good and Evil” (in contrast to mere good and bad (as found in classical lit, good to be. Healthy, bad to be sick, good to be beautiful, bad to be ugly, ext.))</p>
      <p>I kinda think American culture approached Nietzsche’s ideals in the 80s achieving styles in fashion, music, lifestyle, ect. That nearly rejected slave morality and style, only to be torn down again be slave ideals... compare glam/hair metal, or the booming workout culture, muclebound action heroes expressing their raw confidence and will to power in witty one liners, or insert anything 80s with the profound self-consciousness and cringing meekness of 90s culture. A profound aesthetic rejection of shame and meekness: massive muscled men wearing makeup, growing their hair lavishly long, and filling the room with aggressive bragging Machismo, huge sounds, and fans screaming adoration... got replaced with Kurt Cobain... who then killed himself whining about his aesthetics and bemoaning the corruption of selling, a musical martyr to pretence, self-consciousness, shame, and meekness if one ever existed.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>