<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2020-09-01T14:09:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ijs526/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_august_31_2020/g3l8mff/</link>
  <title>The Troubles and the IRA: A Rant</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>In the very early years of the Troubles, the IRA was split. One faction had been carrying the torch of armed revolution since the 1920’s- they were the mad bombers of the 1930s, the pathetic wannabe guerrillas of the 1950’s. They were a collection of old men worn out from prison sentences, young idiots with more passion than sense, and over educated hardcore socialists. They had never acknowledged the division of Ireland, and so maintained the the Army Council in the South was the proper management for these new riots kicking off in Belfast and Derry and so on. These riots were not Marxist uprisings, but protests against sectarian discrimination in housing and employment, and against the gerrymandering that prevented the Catholic community from ever hoping to end them by normal politics. The riots got worse and worse the more it became clear that they weren’t working; the Orange State, augmented by Protestant rioters, preferred bats wrapped with barbed wire to talking it all out. And the worse the fighting got, the more willing cop killers sprang up looking for leadership, which the IRA based in the Republic of Ireland would gladly provide.</p>
      <p>The other faction was, well, the community leaders who sprang up in the middle of the riots. Working class young men, mostly, experienced street fighters who knew their way around Molotov cocktails and brick fights, who knew the tricks of how to neutralize riot gas and how to form a proper barricade. These guys weren’t super into Marxist theory that the old guard in the South had spent thirty years perfecting. They just wanted to fight, and the idea of submitting to a bunch of college educated dickheads who never threw a brick in their lives was intolerable.</p>
      <p>The IRA split over who should be in charge of the newly formed urban insurgency. The Official IRA, based hundreds of miles away, was less militant, less willing to resort to brute force. They were also explicitly Marxist. The Provisional IRA, based in the very neighborhoods that were under siege, were extremely militant and willing to resort to terrorist tactics. They were Marxist in the loosest sense possible, but hardly committed about the international struggle.</p>
      <p>In the opening years of the struggle, the OIRA and the PIRA killed each other off in a death struggle to see whose vision got to be ascendant. The British State just kinda watched amused as these psycho Irish Nationalists got into gunfights on the street.</p>
      <p>In the end, the PIRA won; they were better attuned to the demands of the Northern Irish Catholic community. The OIRA was more tone deaf when dealing with the locals, and what public demand for violent action there was backed the local boys who lived down the road instead of ancient guerrillas who lived in Dublin.</p>
      <p>One such case, in retrospect the absolute nadir of OIRA military activity, may illuminate things a bit-</p>
      <p>There was a young Irishman named William Best from Derry. Best was a one of the boys, a fellow street fighter who’d been rioting and getting his head knocked around just like everyone else. When Best joined the British Army, nobody batted an eye- the fight up to that point had always been a local affair between Protestor and Orange State, between local gangs. The British Army as an institution was still perceived as neutral. But while Best was gone training, the Army deployed to Derry and <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloody_Sunday_(1972">gunned down</a> 26 civilians, killing half of them. The OIRA issued a blanket order to its supporters to kill any soldier they could.</p>
      <p>When Best came home on leave...</p>
      <p>The very next morning, 400 local Catholic mothers marched on down to the Official’s headquarters in Derry in broad daylight to scream their ears off about shooting local boys who hadn’t done anything wrong. The OIRA called off their orders to go on the offensive, and never resumed fighting again. Though technically they were still a Marxist insurgency, they didn’t actually do anything except deplore and declare things for the next fifty years (up to the present day). The fire of Provisionals sucked up all the oxygen in the room- the gun shipments, the funding, the volunteers.</p>
      <p>One interesting offshoot was small band of fanatical Marxists who split from the OIRA two year’s after Best’s death to resume fighting. The Irish National Liberation Army (INLA) was explicitly Commie, aimed at wrenching Northern Ireland free from Britain’s grasp to form an independent socialist republic that would eventually subsume the Republic in the South too. So, not terribly realistic. But the INLA had a fierce reputation for competence- between 1972 and 1998 (when the massive popularity of GFA halted their attacks), they racked up a respectable body count for their size, attacking their fellow OIRA and PIRA revolutionaries, Orange cops, British soldiers, Protestant terrorists, and random civilians caught in the blast radius.</p>
      <p>I am aware I didn’t exactly address your interest.</p>
      <p>I just don’t get to rant about this stuff very often.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>