<post>
  <author>motteposting</author>
  <date>2020-09-08T00:08:05Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/io1iih/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_07/g4e5l20/</link>
  <title>Don't Root for an American Civil War or Collapse</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Don't Root for an American Civil War or Collapse</strong>
      </p>
      <p>This week, I'd like to open things with a post that is part plea, part polemic. My primary message is this: bona fide, protracted internecine conflict in the US is a catastrophic failure mode from any reasonable perspective, even that of a committed rightist (which I happen to be); by extension most things that raise the temperature of American civil society, especially acts of lawlessness and violence, have very bad expected returns for everyone.</p>
      <p>First of all, I regard most all instances of rooting for a civil war or a nationwide collapse into CHAZ-style lawlessness as pathetic LARPing of which one ought to be ashamed. The palpable enthusiasm which I've seen for the widespread collapse of the most basic institutions of American society, an event near-certain to result in millions of casualties, could make a vulture visibly blush (and their skin is already red!). If we get to the point where law and order break down nationwide, then it's a near-certainty that hospitals, emergency services, and basic utilities will be largely incapable of functioning too, and on a similar scale. The excess mortality from the subsequent collapse of the medical system, in and of itself, is hard to imagine. Therefore, I am baffled at how some people can take such a massive loss of life so lightly, much less count it as a "win". It's a matter of fact that wide-spread collapses of basic governance institutions are among the most destructive events within the historical record, in terms of both life and loot (see e.g. Scheidel's <em>The Great Leveler</em>). But you can rule the ashes, I guess; that is, if you survive <em>and</em> come out on top, which is a truly <em>enormous</em> IF.</p>
      <p>In addition to all of that, if you're a rightist like me, it's very likely that you wouldn't even get the outcome that you want out of a civil war or collapse. First of all, not counting those cases where USG intervened (since USG certainly won't be intervening here), righties are batting maybe 1/10, 1/5 tops, for protracted, bona fide right-left civil wars in the modern era. When was the last time that a right-wing faction won a proper civil war? Franco in 1939? Not to mention that there are exactly zero cases that I can think of in the past 80 years where real-deal civil wars or state collapses have improved anything on net. But maybe some people take South Sudan or Angola as shining exemplars; I don't know. That would make about as much sense as anything else I've seen from those who look forward to such a catastrophe within their own borders.</p>
      <p>Second, although I've seen very little discussion of this point, I think it's incredibly naive to suppose that any major civil conflict within the US would just be Americans versus Americans. What country <em>doesn't</em> have an interest in influencing the outcome of a US civil war or institutional collapse? What government <em>wouldn't</em> kill to have some effect on what emerges from the rubble of the global hegemon? Not to mention that plenty of nations have plenty of reason to play both sides and deliberately drag things out, so as to delay any re-establishment of US power as long as possible. Moreover, all of the major military powers which I think might be liable to intervene in such a conflict (e.g. China, the remainder of NATO, Russia) seem much more likely to be hostile to exactly the sort of right-wingers who would tend to egg on a possible collapse, perhaps even more so than to their leftist opponents. For the vast majority of these rightists are strong nationalists who would fight against any efforts to make (parts of) America a puppet or client state of a foreign power, which happens to be the ideal outcome of any foreign intervention in this scenario. And let's not even get started on what could go wrong with the US nuclear or biological arsenals, whether because of foreign actors or domestic ones. </p>
      <p>(EDIT: Regardless of whether you think that the end of US hegemony is to be welcomed or mourned (I personally fall largely into the former camp), the outcome which I am describing is that of a new Great Game, in which the corpse of the American Empire is picked apart by squabbling major powers who are at best mutually indifferent and at worse mutually hostile. This is not, I think, a scenario where the dethronement of America at all makes up for negatives of the ravages of war, the carving out of spheres-of-influence, and the international intrigues over spoils.)</p>
      <p>If the US collapses into civil war or "anarchy" of the sort I'm talking about, we're not looking some fast-and-easy Pinochet-style  regime change. What you'd have on your hands is a continent-sized Syria, except this time USG's WMD's are in play too. Not to mention the potential spillover effects upon the rest of North America. But, hey, if you regard Somalia or the DRC as great success stories, I guess that's your prerogative. However, I am tired of seeing people pretend that the ignition of such a conflict in the US is, in and of itself, a cut-and-dry "victory condition." Many, many innocent people would die, including many children, and it's not at all unlikely some of those we love would be among them. So it's frustrating when I see people online being glib about the prospect of taking these lives in their hands; that shows a lack of maturity, to say the least.</p>
      <p>I doubt that any of the people at whom this post is primarily aimed have the power to significantly influence whether some conflict comes about or not, so maybe that's why they're being flippant, but it just goes to show that they shouldn't be within a thousand miles of any sort of influence anyway. It's clear that they don't think of what they're talking about as something deadly serious, and that makes them LARPers. But it's innocent lives that they're LARPing with.</p>
      <p>Consequently, I would say that our actions going forward should be calibrated as far as possible not to raise sectarian temperatures. Self-defense is one thing, but offensive tactics are another entirely. I don't actually think that civil war or a widespread collapse of law and order is very likely, because I don't think the US ticks very many of the same boxes as the countries which have sustained protracted civil conflict or collapse in the modern era. But these outcomes are still tail-risks and their downsides are so unutterably massive that they should command our utmost seriousness and attentiveness. </p>
      <p>Anyway, I'm interested to hear what everyone else thinks. And I apologize if my tone was unnecessarily harsh at points: my aim is purely to emphasize the absolute necessity of treating these scenarios with the caution and care which they categorically demand.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>