<post>
  <author>cae_jones</author>
  <date>2021-03-11T19:59:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/m0abd1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_08_2021/gqlz9n2/</link>
  <title>Peaking in 1996</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I feel obligated to say something about this, what with fixating on 1996 ever since 1996... but I'm kinda stumped, because it just feels like a list of things that happened, some of which typify a negative trend. It seems like it'd be trivial to do the same for 2007 (iPhones, Naruto, Google buys Youtube, housing market and the signs of the 2008 financial crisis, Harry Potter ends, "IT's OVER NINE THOUSAAAND!", etc). What would falsify this thesis?</p>
      <p>The only bits that stick out to me as having predictive value, rather than just being "cultural milestone happened", are the corporate and regulatory shenanigans, which dramatically changed the entertainment and information landscapes. Cable news networks, the shift in focus from family content to chasing focus group fads, oligopolies, etc.</p>
      <p>I mean, I personally caught myself enjoying 1996 so much at the time that it became the standard by which I judged everything that came afterward. And, indeed, nothing that came afterward has quite lived up to that standard. But me personally fixating on something I like is meaningless so far as cultural trends go.</p>
      <p>I have been wondering about things in this category, lately, though. Lots of videos of old commercials and whatever cartoon blocks don't get copyright-stricken, lots of weird, irrational paralysis on preserving my recordings of Fox Kids (I think I can't shake the "they can't deteriorate if I don't check" stupidity -_- ). It's become clear to me that corporate profit shenanigans had a ton to do with most of the things I enjoyed from pop culture. When I think about salvaging all that, I then have to realize that it was all profit-driven, basically just people with ideas throwing them at people with money until a marketable product resulted. The incentives lead inexorably to our current "10,000,000 channels and nothing to watch" situation. And I can't convince myself that rewinding to &lt;favorite year&gt; and installing heavily armored gatekeepers would help... because I wouldn't mind turning my ideas for pointless entertainment franchises into more than flailing notes and crappy drafts / skits / games.</p>
      <p>I wonder if maybe we just overplayed our hand, or somesuch. the things we <em>could</em> do with the immense growth following WWII were not long-term optimal. But it's so complicated and poorly understood and not very well defined at this point that I'm not entirely sure what that really means. I keep coming back to the 50s and 90s being weird mirrors: both following a major victory (WWII / The Cold War) that required loads of innovation and dramatic economic empowerment. There's a sweeping narrative about what just happened and what it means for history and the future. Loads of culturemantic regulation of entertainment that sparks creative backlash and weird counterculture. Both have a new form of mass communication (TV / Internet). Both have nostalgic weirdos at risk of claiming that rewinding to their favorite decade and staying there is what the world <em>really</em> needs.</p>
      <p>The key difference is that the Boomers had the the Cold War to motivate. Millennials had ... Environmentalism, I guess? And Captain Planet and Al Gore did those no reputational favors (except with me, because I was the weirdo who didn't mind being preached at by the Planeteers, but w/e). In the 50s and 60s, goals were plentiful, attainable, and not competing with superstimuli for attention. In the 80s, 90s, and 00s everyone who was earning profit off the previous generation of opportunities was showering their children and grandchildren with the closest they could get to post-scarcity luxuries. And that was profitable for fun-corp, so fun-corp got good at selling fun. And then my goal in life apparently became to create a timewarp to 1996 am I talking about Western Civ or myself? :-/</p>
      <p>I have no idea what any of this <em>means</em>, in terms of the current status of culture. But it doesn't really feel like it's still 1997. It feels like fun-corp accelerated, theInternet gotinvolved, and we're in a soulless "update-or-die" period. I think we might be destroying preferences for anything staying updated, because inevitably an update will invalidate a preference, and update-or-die. </p>
      <p>I thinkmaybe we just need GPT5 and cheap access to personalize everyone's cultural experience, and be done with it. Something could fix whatever's screwy, but I'm so lost at this point that it seems like "hunker down and hope for the Singularity" is all that seems manageable.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>