<post>
  <author>cantbeproductive</author>
  <date>2021-03-12T19:38:54Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/m3cddt/friday_fun_thread_for_march_12_2021/gqq2tyn/</link>
  <title>Translating the New Testament in search of theological insight</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There are a few things that bother me and this will be very jumbled.</p>
      <p>The word used in the Bible for "repent", as in what Jesus commands, is "metanoeó", which appears to mean <em>change of heart</em>. It does not seem to mean, or even necessarily imply, regret or sorrow, which is denoted by another word. Tertullian wrote "in Greek metanoia is not a confession of sins but a change of mind." There is no necessary element of sorrow or regret in metanoeó. This is why when called to repent, people simply left what they were doing and followed Christ. They didn't have to experience some sufficient amount of sorrow or despair, they simply <em>changed their direction</em>. That's it. </p>
      <p>The word for regret and sorrow is metamelomai. Similar, but distinct. This is what Judas did before he killed himself. Judas felt sorrow, but didn't change his heart. So the call to repentance has nothing to do with sadness over past sins <em>by necessity</em> in the Gospel account. You can experience sadness and sorrow over sins, and not get any closer to Christ, in the true and original understanding of the Bible. Now, "Godly pain/sadness" can lead to repentance (change of heart), but this is even qualified as to preclude regret in Corinthians: "sorrow toward God works conversion [repentance] to salvation without regret, and the sorrow of the world works death." </p>
      <p>So for something this big to be, if not a mistranslation, an imperfect translation, is unsettling.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Next I'm wrangling with how "temptation" is translated. In the Lord's prayer, the word for temptation is actually more akin to "trial": So, do not lead us to trial, but keep us safe from evil". Why is this important? Because the "time of trial" adds an important dimension, specifically referencing Jesus' trials -- not just his temptation in the wilderness but also his entire trial and crucifixion. "You are those who have stood by Me in My trials", he says before the Last Supper, which of course makes no sense if we are to mean his temptation in the wilderness, but makes sense if we are to "carry our cross" and experience trial for his sake. It is a reference to all of the hardships Christ went through, not just his passive resistance to temptation. </p>
      <p>We read in Corinthians that "No temptation has overtaken you but such as is common to man; and God is faithful, who will not allow you to be tempted beyond what you are able, but with the temptation will provide the way of escape". Here it should read "trial", but even the word "escape" is wrong!</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"No <strong>trial</strong> has overtaken you... God will not allow you to be <strong>tried</strong> beyond what you are able, but with the trial provide you <strong>the end</strong>." </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The word for "escape" means "the end" or "the outcome". This is fitting with the Gospel theme of trials not being <em>escaped</em> from but withstood, e.g. in Hebrews we read "These trials will show that your faith is genuine. It is being tested as fire tests and purifies gold—though your faith is far more precious than mere gold. So when your faith remains strong through many trials, it will bring you much praise and glory and honor on the day when Jesus Christ is revealed to the whole world."</p>
      <p>And we know that "escape" is wrong here because the same word is used the Book of Wisdom</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Let us see whether his words be true; let us find out what will happen to him <strong>in the end</strong>. If to be just is to be God’s son indeed, then God will take up his cause, will save him from the power of his enemies. Outrage and torment, let these be the tests we use; let us see that gentleness of his in its true colours, find out what his patience is worth. Sentenced let him be to a shameful death; by his own way of it, he shall find deliverance.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Would the word "escape" fit in here? The word means "outcome", "end", or "going out through". There is no "escape" of the trial. Did Jesus "escape" his trial? There is the <em>outcome</em>, the resurrection. How do you miss such an obvious allusion to Wisdom? The same fucking word is used. The passage even mentions the sentence to a shameful death and the Son of God.</p>
      <p>And the word "escape" is used in Hebrews, the same Hebrews I mentioned above, </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Remember those who led you, who spoke the word of God to you; and considering the <strong>result</strong> of their conduct, imitate their faith.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <hr />
      <p>That we have "trial" right and not just "temptation" is important because it's nestled in the Lord's Prayer, and I think (theologically) that the Lord's Prayer was designed to be a cheat sheet for the most important milestones in the Life of Christ. "Thy Kingdom Come" references the half of all parables which concern the Kingdom of God; "thy will be done" adds to this, and references the words before the Passion; the "daily bread" (another mistranslation I'll ignore) refers to the whole Body of Christ and also to the seed/wheat/bread parables; the forgive us our trespasses in reference to the Golden Rule not only found in Beatitudes but elsewhere. So naturally we have left, "lead us not into temptation", which I allege refers to all trials generally, but then we have "deliver us from evil", which surely refers to the crucifixion and resurrection (e.g. "Giving thanks unto the Father Who hath delivered us from the power of darkness, and hath translated us into the kingdom of his dear Son"; and during the crucifixion he is even mocked when someone said "He trusts in God; let God deliver him now, if he desires him. For he said, ‘I am the Son of God'"</p>
      <p>(Also to <a href="/u/HlynkaCG">/u/HlynkaCG</a>)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>