<post>
  <note>Underlying original post was a now-deleted /u/georgemonck post.  Not sure on the media category; it's about a book, but it's not about books.</note>
  <author>Cheezemansam</author>
  <date>2021-03-12T18:00:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/m0abd1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_08_2021/gqppvnm/</link>
  <title>The Brutality of Antebellum American Slavery</title>
  <category>
    <li>civilization</li>
    <li>media</li>
  </category>
  <context>
    <p>The other side being that the brutality of slavery has been exaggerated, that for most people most of the time it wasn't that different than being a serf or factory worker in other parts of the world. The main difference was that it was more paternalistic, so yes slaves would sometimes get beaten (back then children would also frequently get lashed) but also they would be taken care of in situations where a Manchester factory worker would be treated as disposable. The amount of forcible rape of slave women has been exaggerated, with many of the women sleeping with their maters out of attraction, as a female secretary is often attracted to her powerful boss.</p>
  </context>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Edited: Slavery. So a few days ago there was a discussion about slavery and whether it's <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/m0abd1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_08_2021/gqc0hnh/">brutality had been exaggerated</a><del>This part came across unnecessarily as a personal attack so I rephrased it.</del> High effort, to be sure.
      <p>And they cited three books, one of which was <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n5/mode/2up">The Negro Family in the United States</a>, as a general citation and specifically citing chapter IV for the "forcible rape has been exaggerated..." statement. So I have been reading through the book and I feel <em>compelled</em> to share.</p>
      <p>So lets read through the evidence that was provided for these statements.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n97/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #1</a>: A woman who was not a slave had her son sold because the father was a slave.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n99/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #2</a>: A woman was ordered whipped because she had sex with a slave.</p>
      <p>Also the same paragraph discusses how black slaves were made to have sex with white individuals so that their female mulatto daughters would make more appealing prostitutes. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>That physical compulsion was necessary at times to secure submission on the part of black women, both slave and free, is supported by historical evidence and has been preserved in the traditions of Negro families. (Page 65)</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n101/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #3</a>: A man writes about how his great-great-grandmother was forced to put her head into a fence and conceive his great-grandfather.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n101/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #4</a>: A woman had to bear a scar (one of many) above her right eye from a violent rape. Her resultant mixed race son was treated a bit better than other slaves.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n101/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #5</a>: I... lets just quote it.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Thomas James, Jep's second son, had cast his eyes on a handsome young negro girl, to whom he made dishonest overtures. She would not submit to him and finding he could not overcome her he swore he would be revenged. One night he called her out of the gin-house, and the bade me and two or three more, strip her naked; which we did. He then made us throw her down on her face, in front of the door, and hold her whilst he flogged her with the bull-whip <strong>cutting great gashes of flesh out of her person, at every blow, from five to six inches long.</strong> The poor unfortunate girl screamed most awfully all the time, and writhed under our strong arms rendering it necessary for us to use our united strength to hold her down. He flogged her for half an hour, until he nearly killed her, and then left her to crawl away to her cabin.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n103/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #6</a>: A slave woman inadvertently informed a man that her wife was in bed with a hired mulatto cook. She ended up being whipped by the wife in revenge. I <em>do not</em> understand how this supports the claim that slave women... 'tactically' submitted to the advances of masters in order to better themselves.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n103/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #7</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The following incident is from the life of Bishop Loguen's mother, who was the mistress of a while man near Nashville, Tennessee: "When she was about the age of twenty-four or five, a neighboring planter finding her alone at the distillery, and presuming upon the privileges of his position, made insulting advances, which she promptly repelled. He pursued her with gentle force, and was still repelled. He then resorted to a slaveholder's violence and threats. These sturred all the tiger's blood in her veins. She broke from his embrace, and stood before him in bold defiance. He attempted again to lay hold of her-and careless of caste and slave laws, she grasped the heavy stick used to stir the malt, and dealt him a blow which made him reel and retire. But he retired only to recover and return with the fatal knife, and threats of vengeance and death. Again she aimed the club with unmeasured force at him, and hit the hand which held the weapon, and dashed it to a distance from him. Again he rushed upon her with the fury of a madman, and she then plied a blow upon his temple, which laid him, as was supposed, dead at her feet."</p>
        <p>But it appears that, aside from the prestige of the white race and the material advantages to be gained, these slave women were as responsive to the attractiveness of white males as the latter were to the charms of the slave women. <strong>Hence, slave women were not responsively to the approaches of all white men and often showed some discrimination and preference in the bestowal favors.</strong></p>
        <p>
          <strong>Hence slave women were not responsive to the approaches of all white men and often showed some discrimination...</strong>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This woman fought off an escalating violent attempted rape multiple times, and this conclusions here is that "Slave women were not responsive to the approaches of all white men"? </p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n105/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #8</a>: A girl is married (in secret from her master). The master finds out and has her whipped, repeatedly, (to the great despair of his wife who liked the girl) until she eventually fled to the north.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n105/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #9</a>: A slave who had a relationship with her master was meant to be freed in his will. In revenge for this, after the masters death the wife reversed this and had her sold off, and sold each of her children to different plantations to further torment her.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n107/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #10</a>: Multiple slave women fell victim to a master's charms before "became victim of his unbridled passions". They would in turn face the wrath and revenge of his wife, who punished them out of jealousy. One such punishment "<strong>had slaves hold a negro girl down while she cut off the forepart of the victims feet</strong>'.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n107/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #11</a>: A young girl was sexually targeted by the son of the master, to the dismay of her family. Eventually this young man arranged for her to be sold away from her family once he was done using her. The girls father begged to be allowed to bid and purchase his daughter but the master refused.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n109/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #12&amp;#13</a>: Widows and Heirs-in-law successfully got a mistress removed from the benefits of a will.</p>
      <p>The book then discusses who mulatto slave children were not necessarily treated well by their master, including being treated like "pets" and being treated like animals being thrown bones from the dinner table.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n111/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #14</a>: At an auction the heirs of a master sold his slaves after he died, including mulatto slave children who were by blood their own sisters and brothers. Sisters and brothers selling their sister and her children.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://archive.org/details/negrofamilyinthe031737mbp/page/n113/mode/2up?q=repelle">Anecdote #15</a>: A slave was purchased by a wealthy businessman and made his wife. Soon after her acquisition he went down to Mexico and emancipated her.</p>
      <p>The book references a speech by Andrew Johnson (gov. of Tennessee), where he chided the hypocrisy of refusing equality of Negros despite the abundance of mulatto children they obviously conceived with their slaves.</p>
      <p>It then finishes the chapter by discussing Captain Ralph Quarles who, among other things, treated his slaves relatively well and sort of advocated for the eventual emancipation of slaves (though through individual masters, not by federal fiat). He was ostracized for these views. About 6 pages are dedicated largely to this account (just to be clear, despite the brevity of this summary).</p>
      <hr />
      <p>So my question is how, <em>how</em> can someone read this and conclude</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>the brutality of slavery has been exaggerated, that for most people most of the time it wasn't that different than being a serf or factory worker in other parts of the world</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>or that</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The amount of forcible rape of slave women has been exaggerated, with many of the women sleeping with their maters out of attraction, as a female secretary is often attracted to her powerful boss.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>So I was a bit skeptical about these claims so I actually spent the time to read through this citation and <strong>this</strong> is what I read as evidence. Flesh being stripped off of your back. Multiple accounts of extremely violent rape. Masters selling off their own biological children, and siblings selling their sisters/brothers into slavery. This is very much common knowledge but <strong>citing this as evidence</strong> that the brutality and rape of slavery has been exaggerated?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>