<post>
  <note>Did not remove the NSFW link, but that's probably something that needs to be considered.</note>
  <author>Gen_McMuster</author>
  <date>2021-03-10T14:54:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/m0abd1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_08_2021/gqg8l7u/</link>
  <title> The Nascent Division Between "Sex" And "Gender"</title>
  <category>
    <li>culture</li>
    <li>personal</li>
  </category>
  <context>
    <p>You're still heterosexual, because the experiment demonstrates that you are attracted to feminine gender expression</p>
    <p>YOU yourself are almost certainly entirely attracted to perceptible gender expression and not chromosomes.</p>
  </context>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Are we talking about sex or gender? Throbbing cocks and square jaws are secondary and primary <em>sex</em> characteristics not aspects of gender expression, gender is the social performance.</p>
      <p>Broadly speaking, Heterosexual males are attracted to the <em>heuristic</em> of female <em>sex</em> expression. Which is an oversimplification, but at the same time so is boiling it down to gender, which is incoherent to cultures who do not seperate sex from gender, which is literally all cultures prior to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender">1970s</a>, hence why all the language on attraction and mating that arose prior to this time refers to <em>sex</em> and <em>sexuality.</em></p>
      <p>Your hypothetical perfect trans woman is not attractive to the median straight male because they have feminine gender expression. Feminine behavior, skirts and the like are attractive to me, but they're not attractive in and of themself when put on just any<em>body.</em> A perfect feminine social performance without female primary &amp; secondary sex characteristics isn't attractive to the ah... median heterosexual male. Though this does of course have um... <a href="https://twitter.com/FemboyLover0w0">exceptions</a>[NSFW]. Rather, this theoretical character is attractive to the median straight male because of the other pattern she fits.</p>
      <p>These patterns of Tits, Jaws, Hips and Dicks are attractive because <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sex">Sex itself</a> (gamete function; sperm/egg in humans) is invisible. What's visible to us are those patterns of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexual_characteristics"><em>sex characteristics</em></a> which are downstream of sex. </p>
      <p>(Aside: Im not talking about chromosome's because they're a red herring, they <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sex-determination_system"><em>determine</em></a> sex, they're upstream of both the gametes and the sex characteristics, you can broadly intuit that any argument with a transphobe or trans rights activist that hinges on chromosomes is going to go nowhere fast as they don't matter to us, they matter to our cells.)</p>
      <p>Your hypothetical "perfect" trans person is completely phenotypically female (in a way most women aren't, even) except for the part that all of those phenotypes are purpose-built to support, the gamete. She's a perfect match to the heuristic, without embodying what that heuristic evolved to indicate to horny hominids. It's the steak vs perfect flavored plastic replica steak example used above, you can't fault people for "falling" for the replica steak but you should still believe them if they express a preference for "real" steak. <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/tag/the-map-is-not-the-territory">The Map is not the Territory</a> after all.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>The real conversation to have is gender even a seperate quantity, or rather is it a Tertiary sex characteristic. Gender is <a href="https://arcdigital.media/what-is-gender-identity-10ce0da71999">probably real</a> and likely mostly baked into the cake at birth, hence why trying to raise kids opposite of their birth sex <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Reimer">goes poorly</a>. Imagining gender as another sex characteristic downstream of sex in the same way as cocks and jaws isn't right, as it's quite plastic, but not <em>infinitely so</em> as evident by what happened to poor David Reimer and as evident by the glut of <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/fvsrae/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_06_2020/fmvu861/">legitimate third genders</a> that aren't just unique social categories for homosexuals. The median pattern across societies is 2 genders with similar roles reemerging across independant populations, and <a href="https://poseidonawoke.files.wordpress.com/2016/04/naxalt2.png">the median defines the pattern</a>.</p>
      <p>Understanding Gender as downstream from sex, just further downstream from hips and tits with an additional "cultural operator" on the value squares a lot of circles. </p>
      <p>Namely the broad <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convergent_evolution">convergence</a> of gender roles across cultures which developed their memes independently of one another, tenancies like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Male_expendability">male expendability</a> and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Women-are-wonderful_effect">wondrous qualities</a> of women are near universal to humanity, buried deep in our cognitive patterns, belying that there's more <em>there</em> there than mere socialization. </p>
      <p>This also ropes in the trivial observation that we do find aspects of gender expression attractive, unifying them under the broader mosaicine heuristic of sexual attraction. It's mostly reliable signal that points towards the person you're looking at being a potential mate. In other words: </p>
      <p>
        <em>Monke see skirt/titty/<a href="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/98KnORXP31k/maxresdefault.jpg">tummy</a>, Monke's amygdala intuits eggs to inseminate.</em>
      </p>
      <p>The skirt, the titty and the tummy all reside under the same umbrella and serves the same purpose, even if the wires are capable of crossing in innumerable and wonderful ways.</p>
      <p>Looking at what we call Transgender through this lens; they could be said to be individuals who are born with a sex characteristic (the internal conception of gender) out of line with their sex, this isn't novel, the sex determination system is messy as hell and produces pattern errors all the time, the sub-clinical aberrations we call "masculine women" and "feminine men" while the errors of clinical significance we call <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intersex">intersex</a>, it could be argued that the condition of being Transgender is a subset of the latter hence why the clinical therapy's afforded to trans people primarily operate on their sex characteristics. Though this is a far bigger and spicier conversation than I can go into here, so instead I'll leave this thread of thought for future development.</p>
      <p>TLDR: Gender as a concept divorced from sex and thought of as a pure essential quality determined by culture is a quirk of the blank-slatist thinking underpinning the concept as it was formulated in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Money">50s</a> and refined it through the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender#Etymology_and_usage">70s</a>, be careful with how you wield it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>