<post>
  <author>LawOfTheGrokodus</author>
  <date>2021-03-10T06:05:53Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/m0abd1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_08_2021/gqf3ht5/</link>
  <title>Two cheers for the deep state</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I don't grant that the red tribe is a powerless minority. Thanks to a two party system and FPTP, they are the most powerful minority in the world.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Oh, I don't think they are. They have a lot of political power, and given how Republican politicians often use it, I would like them to have less.</p>
      <p>But I'm not talking about Republican officeholders, just about the red tribers themselves. Even in democracy (and even with the benefits our particular system affords e.g. rural Wyomingers), the individual doesn't hold much power. And I think from their perspective, the analogy isn't bad. Going a bit beyond what I endorse, but to a point that I believe most red tribers would accept, the government isn't democratically answerable. Doesn't matter if you vote for Reagan or Bush or Bush or Trump, career civil servants and the inertia of the state will carry on the same as they would no matter what. The deep state abides.</p>
      <p>I do think there's some truth in this, but I don't think it's all bad. The lack of robust institutions and systemic inertia generated by checks on the ability of a single election to radically change the course of a country are what led to Yahya Jammeh assuming dictatorial power in Gambia, for an example close to my heart. I do think Trump had sufficiently dictatorial instincts for things to go very, very bad if he'd been elected in a country with weaker institutions. That Trump was too impatient, impulsive, and set in his ways to grasp the levers of power doesn't necessarily reflect a difference between him and the folks who did become dictators, but perhaps instead a difference between the systems. This is to say, had Jammeh somehow been elected president of the US, I don't think he would have managed to claim the powers he did in Gambia, and perhaps if Trump had been elected president of Gambia, he would have turned out like Jammeh.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, one other way the institutions of democracy in Gambia are weaker than they are in the US is that the populace has less democratic entitlement — they don't have the sense Americans do that the national government is supposed to represent them and their interests. I could imagine the notions of the deep state leading to a quietism that undermines this popular as opposed to institutional check against dictators.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>