<post>
  <author>VOC_Cartographer</author>
  <date>2021-03-10T22:04:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/m0abd1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_08_2021/gqi049f/</link>
  <title>The Lockean principle of "enough, and as good, left in common for others."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>What else would ancapistan be if not anarchy?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Feudalism. One ponders the distinction between monarchical pretenses to holding a kingdom as private property in which all subjects are mere tenants bound by feudal contract and anarcho-capitalist landlordism, except in scale. The supposedly voluntary aspect of this system compared to serfdom à la "just make your own property" falls apart under inspection for reasons elaborated upon by Henry George over a century ago. </p>
      <p>A fact now mostly forgotten is that the presence of free land was a crucial component in early liberal political economist's justification for the principle of private property rights. In Ricardo's era, the existence of the New World's seemingly endless supply of unowned land ripe for Lockean homesteading made "if you don't like it, leave" a compelling argument. Regard for the indigenous inhabitants, being savages outside the scope of the social contract, was not given much thought. The Principality of Sealand has undertaken the noble effort of proving Locke's thesis still coherent in a world without Terra Incognita, but alas, I find the venture unconvincing. </p>
      <p>In what sense is a man lacking any means to sustain himself without the bondage of contractual servitude free? I side with Jefferson on the absurdity of this notion.</p>
      <p>EDIT: A common verbalism offered on this point is that "work or starve" is a fact of biology. But of course the objection is not, <a href="https://i.redd.it/285clhxrba361.jpg">as the strawman goes,</a> to caloric requirements, but that I must sell my liberties to the propertied to meet them, an arrangement arbitrarily codified and forced upon me by threat of violence. The genesis of land ownership is the theft of the commons and the profiteering from that which one had no hand in producing. To wit, a racket.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>