<post>
  <author>weaselword</author>
  <date>2021-03-13T15:03:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/m0abd1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_08_2021/gqsxweq/</link>
  <title>Whether a female academic was fired "not only for soliciting feedback on her performance regarding diversity, equity, and inclusion, but also for soliciting the said feedback using the kind of speech patterns typical of women."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I find the <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/getting-serious-about-diversity-enough-already-with-the-business-case#:%7E:text=A%202015%20survey%20of%20Harvard,leads%20to%20improved%20financial%20outcomes.">second HBR article by Ely and Thomas</a> particularly interesting as it applies specifically to the Sellers firing case.  The article is written from a progressive perspective, and it argues that a company that wants to see any benefit from diversity of its workforce must implement appropriate changes in its corporate culture and practice:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Companies will not reap benefits from diversity unless they build a culture that insists on equality. Treating differences as a source of knowledge and connection lays the groundwork for such a culture. But as part of that process, firms may have to make financial investments that they won’t recoup, at least in the short run, and more will be required of top leaders, managers, and rank-and-file employees alike. <strong>Everyone will have to learn how to actively listen to others’ perspectives, have difficult conversations, refrain from blame and judgment, and solicit feedback about how their behaviors and company practices might be impeding the push for a culture that supports learning, equality, and mutual respect. Developing those capacities is no small feat in any context; it is even more challenging for people working across cultural identity differences.</strong> But teams that truly embrace the learning-and-effectiveness paradigm will come to understand that homogeneity isn’t better; it’s just easier. They’ll realize, too, that the benefits of diversity arise as much from the collective work of developing those key capacities as from the collective learning they enable.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I have highlighted the part that is particularly applicable to Sellers.  Sellars, <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/us/georgetown-law-fires-professor-reprehensible-statements-black-students-viral-vide0">in her resignation letter</a>, characterizes her remarks as "inarticulate reflection of long soul searching": which fits very well with Ely and Thomas's call for companies establishing corporate culture where employees "solicit feedback about how their behaviors and company practices might be impeding the push for a culture that supports learning, equality, and mutual respect":</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In a resignation letter Sellers provided to Fox News, she wrote to [Georgetown Law Dean] that she is "deeply sorry for my hurtful and misdirected remarks."</p>
        <p>"While the video of this incident is an excerpt from a longer discussion about class participation patterns, not overall grades, it doesn’t diminish the insensitivity of I have demonstrated," she continued. "I would never do anything to intentionally hurt my students or Georgetown Law and wish I could take back my words." </p>
        <p>"My comments were the inarticulate reflection of long soul searching. I must do better to understand and address these issues," Sellers added. "I am committed to doing this for myself and also looking for ways I can combat racism in the Georgetown community.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Her remarks were made in conversation with a more senior professor, and they fit very well with Ely and Thomas's call for companies establishing corporate culture where employees <em>"solicit feedback about how their behaviors and company practices might be impeding the push for a culture that supports learning, equality, and mutual respect".</em>  So at the very least, we recognize that by promptly firing Sellers, Georgetown University law school strongly discourages their instructors to examine their behaviors and solicit feedback regarding diversity, equity and inclusion of under-represented minority students.</p>
      <p>Moreover, any proper analysis of the power dynamics of this incident would consider, firstly, that Sellers is an adjunct professor (the most exploited group of college-level instructors), and secondly a woman.  The promptness of her termination would, of course, not happen if she was working under a different kind of academic contract.  And I think the fact that she is a woman is also potentially relevant here.</p>
      <p>The Georgetown U's Black Law Student Association (BLSA) <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1k8WdnOboHlX9H2Lh5ofjDGygjCeUnAYgYICBGBK4GIk/preview?pru=AAABeEX3l-w*CAspuWtE4GovlL7jQwPIpg">argued for Sellers's termination</a> by assuming that her emotional expressions in the context of discussing performance of a Black student constitutes evidence of actionable bias against Black students:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>These racist statements reveal not only Sellers’ beliefs about Black students in her classes, but also how her racist thoughts have translated to racist actions. Professor Sellers’s bias has impacted the grades of Black students in her classes historically, in her own words.   </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Here is the sum total of the objectionable remarks from the Sellers recording, according to BLSA:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"You know what? <strong>I hate to say this, I end up having this angst</strong> every semester that a lot of my lower ones are Blacks," Sellers says. "Happens almost every semester <strong>and it's like ‘oh come on.'"</strong>  Sellers then briefly laughs before saying: "I get some really good ones but there are also usually some that are just plain at the bottom, <strong>it drives me crazy... so I feel bad.</strong>" </p>
        <p>She stated regarding this Black student, “...when he did talk, they were a bit jumbled. It’s the best way I can put it, it’s like okay let me reason through that what you just said.” </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I don't know the speech patterns of Sellers, specifically.  But in general in US, women tend to have the kinds of speech patterns that include a lot more personal feelings and emotions(highlighted), and phrasing statements in a hesitant, explorative way (e.g., "they were a bit jumbled.  It's the best way I can put it").  </p>
      <p>If the law school agreed with BSLA's argument and fired her solely on the grounds of the way she expressed herself in this recording, then Sellers got fired not only for soliciting feedback on her performance regarding diversity, equity, and inclusion, but also for soliciting the said feedback using the kind of speech patterns typical of women.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>