<post>
  <author>yellerto56</author>
  <date>2021-03-09T03:59:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/m0abd1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_08_2021/gqaiw6h/</link>
  <title>The use of "women" as an applause light amidst the conceptual erosion of gender</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So!</p>
      <p>It's that day again. You know, the day we celebrate on March 8.</p>
      <p>That's right, it's the Orthodox commemoration of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Women%27s_Day">Apostle Hermas of the Seventy, Bishop in Philipopoulis</a>. Blessed be his name.</p>
      <p>And Google have seen fit to commemorate this holy day with one of their doodles. Or maybe not. It's... something about hands? A picture of white and black hands clasped together? Is today the anniversary of Loving v. Virginia? No?</p>
      <p>Oh, wait. Right. It's International Women's Day again. Why was that in no way obvious from that video? All we saw were hands? Is this because women have hands?</p>
      <p>So every year, International Women's Day marks an occasion for <a href="https://www.internationalwomensday.com/Activity/12552/Remember-when-McDonald-s-flipped-the-golden-arches-for-IWD">burger companies' corporate messaging</a>, <a href="https://globalnews.ca/news/7683800/burger-king-womens-day-kitchen-tweet/">outrage over burger companies' corporate messaging</a>, and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L9GpZvavv8w&amp;ab_channel=%D0%90%D0%B4%D1%80%D0%B8%D1%8F%D0%BD%D0%9D%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%BE%D0%B2">pegging</a>. Everyone takes the opportunity to note what percentage of certain occupations are women (though they never argue that women should make up a lesser percentage of jobs where they're already the majority). But crucially, in recent years despite all this talk of women no one can agree just what they are anymore.</p>
      <p>I mean don't get me wrong, plenty of people have consistent definitions of womanhood. But the voguish definition of womanhood encompasses <a href="https://d30womf5coomej.cloudfront.net/c/f4/82/2b/cd/4039437f906a45f4a4c040df5aa2a317.jpg">anyone who identifies as such</a>, which is very nice and tolerant and progressive and all, but what it means to identify as part of a group with no other set characteristics has never been adequately explained.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, the idea that only adults designated female at birth can claim the title of woman is so very  déclassé. The TERFs have made that idea their property, and no one is very fond of TERFs apart from other TERFs and JK Rowling. </p>
      <p>Goodhart's Law states that when a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure. And commissions, committees, and combobulations with the aim of setting gender parity as a target have flourished over the past several decades. Perhaps someday we will finally see women in every office and vocation, but by then any attempt at an accurate count will be down to statistical inference. Are fifty percent of this workplace's employee's women? Who are we to make assumptions about how they identify?</p>
      <p>Happy International Women's Day!</p>
      <p>(Disclaimer: not intended to make fun of anyone's gender identity so much as to rib corporate messaging and the use of "women" as an applause light).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>