<post>
  <author>ArgumentumAdLapidem</author>
  <date>2020-06-14T21:31:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h8ntxg/smallscale_question_sunday_for_the_week_of_june/fuu6dp0/</link>
  <title>A Quick Guide to IKEA and Furniture Quality</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>+1 for IKEA. The good IKEA stuff is as good as any kit-built furniture. The bad stuff is worse than Target/Walmart.</p>
      <p>I think something that is under-appreciated is that even within IKEA, there are different levels of furniture quality. I have some IKEA furniture that is holding strong 7+ years later, even after heavy daily use, such as kitchen table chairs. (In fact, the only thing I've retired is a LACK coffee table, which I knew was garbage when I bought it, but I just needed something cheap at the time.)</p>
      <p>Mostly, it boils down to material.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>The cheapest level of desks, for example, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/woodworking/comments/9r6l34/ikea_cardboard_and_particleboard_sub_veneer_lol/">literally have cardboard inside</a>.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The next level up is fiberboard. Fiberboard as a catch-all for a lot of different materials, from wood-fibers-held-together-with-resin (LDF/MDF), to particleboard, something that I can only describe as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Particle_board">wood sponge/styrofoam</a>. But in all cases, you have some amount of wood product being held together by glue. Particle board is the cheapest, and can barely take a screw. MDF is a much higher-quality material, and is much heavier. It can be directly painted, and has no discernable grain. The quality of MDF can also vary, and warp due to humidity, but I've had no problems with IKEA MDF.  MDF gets a bad rap - if used properly, its a very stable and strong material. Even mid-level Italian furniture uses MDF.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The next level is plywood. It's light and strong. Great for drawers and such.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>After that is solid softwoods, basically pine.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Then you have solid hardwood. I doubt you'll find any at IKEA.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Almost all fiberboard products have a veneer on them. Some are practically stickers, others are "thick veneers", which are usually 1/16" thick (~1.5mm), and can be sanded. Thick veneers are totally legit, even high-quality furniture makers use engineered wood.</p>
      <p>Then you have the hardware. In general, the stamped metal IKEA hardware is pretty good. Hinges are strong, rails are smooth, et cetera. But they also have cheap plastic stuff as well.</p>
      <p>Of course, you have to assemble it well. IKEA's quality control is very good. The pilot holes are usually exactly where they should be, and the boards are usually perfectly square. But even if the pilot hole through the veneer is correct, particleboard is so weak that a screw inserted at the wrong angle will happily drill and tear whatever hole it wants. Don't over-tighten. Make things square, plumb and true.</p>
      <p>So just inspect the materials to make sure you're getting the quality level you want. Those kitchen table chairs, for example, are solid pine and MDF. No veneer, they're painted. Unfortunately, they don't make them anymore.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>