<post>
  <author>AugustusPertinax</author>
  <date>2020-06-11T07:17:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gyvay9/george_floyd_protest_megathread/fto8smp/</link>
  <title>A Deep Dive Into Police Killings</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>(<strong>VI) Actions taken to reduce police killings might have much worse consequences than is commonly understood</strong></p>
      <p>So, we already have a relatively small problem that receives a large amount of attention. On top of that, proposed remedies to this problem might lead to much bigger problems than the ones they intend to fix. Namely, by reducing the power and scope of the police they may lead to increases in violent crime. Given that homicides kill far more people (~10,000-15,000 a year) than police killings (~1,000---1,200 a year), we should weigh small percentage changes in the former against large percentage changes in the latter. </p>
      <p>Note that I'm hedging my position here: I'm not saying that this is necessarily or uniformly the case, because I don't think that's what the evidence shows. I'm simply saying that it is <em>a</em> risk that should be <em>considered</em>, particularly given that homicide is a much more serious threat to the lives of Americans, especially including African-Americans, than police killings are (<a href="https://ucr.fbi.gov/crime-in-the-u.s/2018/crime-in-the-u.s.-2018/tables/expanded-homicide-data-table-1.xls">~7000</a> vs. 300 in a typical year for the latter specifically). </p>
      <p>The most recent/relevant evidence for this is the so-called "Ferguson Effect" identified by <a href="https://www.city-journal.org/html/ferguson-effect-lives-14919.html">Heather Mac Donald</a>, an approximately 25% nationwide increase in homicides from 2014-2016, concentrated in major cities with substantial African-American populations like Chicago and Baltimore. In one estimate, this led to ~4,500 excess murders in those years.</p>
      <p>The most recent academic analysis I've seen of such phenomena is <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w27324.pdf">this one</a> by two Harvard economists which found:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>This paper provides the first empirical examination of the impact of federal and state "Pattern-or-Practice" investigations on crime and policing. For investigations that were not preceded by "viral" incidents of deadly force, investigations, on average, led to a statistically significant reduction in homicides and total crime. In stark contrast, all investigations that were preceded by "viral" incidents of deadly force have led to a large and statistically significant increase in homicides and total crime. We estimate that these investigations caused almost 900 excess homicides and almost 34,000 excess felonies. The leading hypothesis for why these investigations increase homicides and total crime is an abrupt change in the quantity of policing activity. In Chicago, the number of police-civilian interactions decreased by almost 90% in the month after the investigation was announced. In Riverside CA, interactions decreased 54%. In St. Louis, self-initiated police activities declined by 46%. Other theories we test such as changes in community trust or the aggressiveness of consent decrees associated with investigations -- all contradict the data in important ways. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>To take a more long-term perspective, criminologist Barry Latzer in <em>The Rise and Fall of Violent Crime in America</em> presents convincing evidence that the massive nation-wide spike in the violent crime rate in the 1960s that lasted until the 1990s, in which the homicide rate doubled and other violent crimes increased by as much or more, was partially driven by the under-capacity and relative leniency of the criminal justice system in the late 1960s/early 1970s. Arrests and sentencings went down even as violent crime increased. (Though Latzer notes that there were at least 2 other plausible contributing factors and that crime rates don't move linearly with punishment rates.) </p>
      <p>(<strong>VII) The excessive focus on police killings is taking attention away from the coronavirus, which is currently considerably more important</strong></p>
      <p>As an example of why these distortions are significant, consider how they've warped the discussion and perception of the coronavirus. There are currently massive Black Lives Matter protests going on the US, with hundreds of thousands of people participating. The protesters are not practicing social distancing, and thus, as e.g. an <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2020/06/america-giving-up-on-pandemic/612796/">article</a> in the left-leaning magazine The Atlantic which is very sympathetic to the protesters admits, they pose a serious risk of transmitting the coronavirus. </p>
      <p>The New York Times recently <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/07/us/Protest-coronavirus-george-floyd.html">quoted</a> one expert on the virus as estimating:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In what he called a back-of-the-envelope estimate, Trevor Bedford, an expert on the virus at the Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, wrote on Twitter that each day of protests would result in about 3,000 new infections. Over several weeks, as each infected person infected just under one other person on average — the current U.S. transmission rate — those infections would in turn lead to 15,000 to 50,000 more, and <a href="https://twitter.com/trvrb/status/1269786156616433664">50 to 500 eventual deaths</a>.     </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>If the protests eventually lead to 300 deaths from the coronavirus per day, in one day they will have killed more people than the police kill African-Americans who die in police killings in a year. If they continue for 5 days, they will kill more people than the number of Americans who are killed by police in year. If they continue for 10 days, they will kill more people than the police kill in 2 years. Even if the protests were successful at reducing police killings by 100% in the ~2 years before a vaccine is developed, which seems highly unlikely, they would not be worth it in that case. </p>
      <p>This is why basic numeracy---why knowing the difference between 10 and 10,000---is important. Based on the availability heuristic, many people at the protests, I would suspect, likely believe that the coronavirus, which has killed 100,000 or more Americans so far this year, and police killings, which have killed less than 1,000, are comparable threats. </p>
      <p>(<strong>VIII) Conclusion</strong></p>
      <p>Let's pause to add all this up again. Police killings result in the death of a relatively small number of Americans, a modest share of whom are African-Americans. Many or most of these  relatively small number of killings are justified, and the per capita disparities between ethnic groups are consistent with unbiased policing given the considerable per capita ethnic differences in violent crime rates. Attempts to remedy this problem can result in worse problems, and the massive attention paid to it is distracting from at least one currently much more important problem. </p>
      <p>You might reasonably agree or disagree with these contentions, but I think it's hard to say that they should be outside the bounds of reasonable debate.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>