<post>
  <author>bearvert222</author>
  <date>2020-06-13T04:43:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gysmxy/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_08_2020/fuoaohu/</link>
  <title>The Weird Dynamics of Conservative Moviemaking</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There are people doing this. One example are the Kendrick brothers, who made tremendous amounts of money making inexpensive Christian themed films like Fireproof and Facing the Giants. Fireproof only cost $500k to make, but has grossed $34 million. Sherwood films generally follows this example; very low cost indie films aimed at a Conservative Christian market, but they make quite a bit of money. There's even a streaming service called Pureflix that specializes in showing them.</p>
      <p>I think Tyler Perry's Madea movies are the same for conservative blacks. Generally they can't command large budgets but they earn their money and then some, and keep getting made. </p>
      <p>For pure conservatives, Dinesh D'Souza has been putting out really bad documentaries, and David Zucker did "An American Carol."</p>
      <p>From my experience though when I cared a lot about Christian pop culture, there are some serious issues.</p>
      <p>The problem is that for all the talk, Christians (and I think conservatives too in a sense) really don't care about art beyond tokenism. I mean the mass audience. There are actually a few who do, and who try to make decent quality works. <a href="https://www.enclavepublishing.com">Enclave Publishing</a> for example is probably the only real Christian publisher left willing to do SF/F at all, and while it's not earth shattering stuff, it's pretty decent b-grade and c-grade SF. Not left behind level dreck. I remember Buzz Dixon, who used to write scrips for GI Joe in the 80s tried to make Christian manga through realbuzz studios. It was kind of meh quality, but its readable, and some were pretty decent. Goofyfoot Girl was one. Serenity had bad art, but it actually tried to tell a real story about a nonbvelieving girl from a single parent home meeting a youth group.</p>
      <p>But every time they try, the audience just doesn't seem to care and doesn't support the works. They'll buy the odd "event blockbuster" now and then; Frank Peretti's This Present Darkness, Ted Dekker's Thr33, Left Behind, etc. And there's a narrow amount of genre fiction for the people who do buy them, mostly romance novels for women. Even Harlequin makes them, in their Love Inspired line. But everything else is like this black hole of not caring, and the few authors that are Christian and quality have to go to secular publishers most of the time. </p>
      <p>They just don't seem to do art that way. If they do, they usually can't shut up about Tolkien and Lewis, and I notice conservatives into art usually are similar. Art to them is the Canon. It's such a small range of "approved" works, and a lot of wannabe creators who can't find people to care. Even videogames; video games is the one media where Christian artists don't even exist. There really only was Doug TenNapel, creator of Earthworm Jim, and he really only puts out his faith subtly in works aimed at the mass media, or on the net.</p>
      <p>It makes it really hard to be either if you happen to enjoy pop culture. If you ever read Guy Gavriel Kay's book Tigana, its about a ruler so angry at a nation of people he blots out their nation to the point where people are magically prevented from even saying its name. It kind of feels like that for christians/conservatives into pop culture. Your nation is scattered and you can't even talk about it.</p>
      <p>So while the market is there, you really have these weird dynamics preventing any one from taking off in it. I htink with conservatives its the same way</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>