<post>
  <author>Botond173</author>
  <date>2020-06-09T09:56:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gysmxy/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_08_2020/ftgmmlw/</link>
  <title>The Woke USA is a Speeding Locomotive With No Brakes</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>In my view, not only is there an obvious parallel, but the one crucial difference between the two makes the ongoing Great Awokening much more ominous. John Derbyshire has briefly <a href="https://johnderbyshire.com/Opinions/RadioDerb/2017-04-07.html#06">discussed this</a> back in 2017. </p>
      <p>Namely: the communist state that Mao had built had a power structure with the necessary capacity and willingness to rein the Red Guard in and eventually dismantle their influence and power. Mao never made the decision to really do that, which was the one thing that enabled the Cultural Revolution in the first place. </p>
      <p>But the Red Guard were never able to capture that power structure, in fact, they never had the support of any state institution or any influential social group, to the extent those had even existed in a Maoist regime, and probably never had the support of even a prularity of the people, let alone a majority. And since that power structure was left intact, and was always accessible to the moderates of the Party, the Red Guard was repressed without much resistance once their sole enabler/protector on the top of the state hierarchy died in 1976.</p>
      <p>Compared to that, the power structure of current Western societies is either captured / held hostage by the forces of the Great Awokening, or is controlled by groups that have zero willingness to rein them in, let alone oppose them. The same applies to any public or private institution with tangential influence and power. The Great Awokening is not credibly threatened by anyone or anything.</p>
      <p>In other words, the communist Chinese state was (and is) a locomotive with working brakes. In a sense, its armed forces and party apparatus functioned as checks and balances, with the power to oppose and suppress a force even as great as the Cultural Revolution. In contrast, the USA is a speeding locomotive with no brakes at all. </p>
      <p>Keep in mind that even in circumstances such as those, the Cultural Revolution roughly had a 15-year run. Its instigators were not repressed until 1981, the trial of the Gang of Four. The main Red Guard leader in Beijing, Kuai Dafu, was not formally punished for his acts <a href="https://books.google.bg/books?hl=hu&amp;id=J5QbQpQTegwC&amp;dq=kuai+dafu&amp;q=kuai+dafu#v=snippet&amp;q=kuai%20dafu&amp;f=false">until 1983</a>.    </p>
      <p>For these reasons, I'm sure that the Great Awokening has the ability and likelihood to eventually cause much more destruction, ruin and suffering than the Cultural Revolution ever did.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>