<post>
  <author>dnkndnts</author>
  <date>2020-06-13T00:44:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gysmxy/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_08_2020/funolz5/</link>
  <title>Whence the Demarcation Between Porn and Story?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Tangentially, another thing that's always amused me in this area is the hard demarcation we have between pornographic content and non-pornographic content, despite the fact that nearly everybody watches both. In any mainstream cinema, if there's a sex scene, it looks nothing like the sex in porn or real life. It's full of wonky camera angles deliberately obscuring all the body parts critically involved in intercourse, and the movements and conversation are all obviously fake. And it's <em>always</em> like this. You either tell a serious story and exclude all explicit sexual content, or you go full porno and depict only explicit sexual content with no serious attempt at a story. Even venturing into indie territory where mainstream criticism and MPAA do not apply, I cannot name any non-exclusively-pornographic film <em>at all</em> that dares to show an erect penis.</p>
      <p>In my opinion it's honestly kind of immature. Our artistic talent cannot even conceive how a depiction of actual sex would fit into a real story; or, conversely, our pornographers cannot conceive how to frame their sex in a narrative setting that isn't less facepalmingly fake than a "3 men walk into a bar..." joke. The closest I've ever seen anyone come to attempting to balance these two worlds is Japanese dating sims, and even that is only with cartoon depictions, not live actors, and they come with all the weirdness baggage that everything from Japan has.</p>
      <p>In some sense, I think this universal strict demarcation is unhealthy. If we outright banned porn, then we could just write it off as "well we don't talk about that", but because porn is freely available and everyone watches it, we don't have that excuse. This demarcation is in some sense a loud but tacit statement that you're either looking for long-term platonism or you're looking for sex, and that it's apparently inconceivable that a person would in fact be interested in both. And I kinda disagree with that at a very fundamental level.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>