<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-06-10T03:50:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gysmxy/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_08_2020/ftju6cg/</link>
  <title>Losing Trust in the Left and Becoming Politically Homeless</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Or more generally, you've spent the last decade talking about how straight white men were to blame for everything, and within the past few weeks have adopted a "us against the system" attitude, so <em>I fundamentally don't trust you</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Just to pull on this thread a bit - the trust issue is one that really worries me. I've spent most of my adult life as some kind of liberal or centre-leftist, and in the wake of the last week, it's getting to the point where <em>I don't think I can ever trust the left again</em>. And that's a problem because I'm technically some kind of centre leftist.</p>
      <p>I guess it would have been around 2010ish (?) I started hearing about some issues with free speech on the left and chatting about them with friends. Yes, we agreed, it's not great, and it raises complicated issues. But there were bigger priorities - climate change, fixing the economy, regulating big tech. And then as the decade progressed, and the (political) climate got chillier, and the ideology got stricter, and the policies got more extreme, I started to get more and more concerned.</p>
      <p>And by ~2015, a few of my friends were too. Around this time I'd occasionally share a link about left-wing censorship with a left-wing friend and they'd say "yes, it's really not great, campus culture is getting pretty extreme." But the message was that beating Trump was the most important thing, and besides, Hilary was a moderate, and pretty soon we'd get back to bread and butter issues. <em>Come on, trust in the movement</em>. But of course, Trump won, and like Russian history, somehow things got worse. Those same friends now became the self-styled resistance, and their message was one of urgency: "look, are you really going to pick fights about who's allowed to talk on college campuses when we have a president who's locking children in cages?" It was around that point that I really started to feel serious distance from most of my left-wing friends, not because I disagreed with them on that specific object-level issue, but because it had become really hard to have a proper discussion about most issues with them. Disagreement about anything risked making me look <em>treacherous</em>. But I still broadly trusted them - these were just high pressure times, right?</p>
      <p>Shortly afterwards there was the Toronto van attack, and a friend of mine posted about how the incident was really about incel culture which was in turn about male entitlement (I believe her comment began with "Men: fuck you. This what male entitlement gets us - dead women."). When I tried to push back a bit on that narrative - suggesting first that incel culture was really weird and secondly that it was more about despair and alienation than entitlement - I was very aggressively and rudely shut down by multiple people. There was to be no discussion on this issue. This was not a science lab. This was a law court, and we had decided on our case. What the fuck was I doing raising objections to it? Nonetheless, I had some sane sensible friends still strongly involved in left-wing politics  ("it was probably just the wrong time to have that discussion," one of them suggested about the above incident). So I could still hang on to a sliver of trust.</p>
      <p>And... then came the last week. My remaining leftist friends were enthusiastically on board with the narrative: white supremacy, dismantling the police, protests take precedence over quarantines, black people dying every day, blood on our hands if we don't act immediately. Some of these were people who just a couple of years earlier I'd still been able to have a serious conversation with about, e.g., the dangers of cancel culture or competing notions of trans identity. Now it genuinely feels to me like it would be a personal risk if I were to, say, raise questions with these people about the extent to which disproportionate number of black Americans killed by police is a function of racist officers as opposed to differ crime rates in different communities. I’m not even talking about coming in with pre-defined conclusions, I just couldn't even safely ask that question. And dear god, if I ever even hinted at having doubts or uncertainties on social media, I'd be fucked.</p>
      <p>So I don't think I can ever really trust the left again. And I'm not just talking about some amorphous movement, sadly; I'm talking about specific real people who have been and in some cases still are friends of mine. I can't have a frank conversation with them, and their reassurances about 'a few radicals' in the movement turned out to be bullshit. And they're now fully signed up - from twitter bios to social media profiles - to an agenda that ten years ago they'd have said was some kind of right-wing delusion.</p>
      <p>So I don't think I'll ever feel safe in a left-wing movement again. Hell, I don't think I'll be able to <em>fully</em> relax in a conversation with my remaining left-wing friends for quite some time; what if I twitch in the wrong way when politics comes up? I'll have some lines prepared, of course, but that's no way to live. And yet I'm also largely not conservative by disposition, and some of the policies I most ardently support are very unlikely to be part of any conservative manifesto, ever. So I guess I'm politically homeless from here on out, and the only place I can safely talk politics (besides with my wife) is on anonymous internet forums like this.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>