<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-06-12T19:03:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gysmxy/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_08_2020/fumma40/</link>
  <title>How Much Sexualization in Society is Appropriate?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There's <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/gyvay9/george_floyd_protest_megathread/fum1qo5/">a discussion over in the other thread</a> about sexualisation in MTG cards and I wanted to offer a few quick thoughts on what degree sexualisation in society at large is tolerable or appropriate. Are sexy billboards, videogames, movies, etc. something that we should be concerned about? How strictly should professional dress codes discourage wearing more sexy or revealing clothes at the office? Is it a bad thing if e.g. a celebrity famous for their musical or sporting achievements obtains career success from doing sexy photo shoots?</p>
      <p>Obviously this debate is as old as the hills, and in short, my instincts 100% align with what I take it <a href="/u/darwin2500">u/darwin2500</a> is suggesting in the linked thread, namely that "sexiness" is fine as long as it's equal opportunities sexiness (i.e. we get <a href="https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/ChainmailBikini">chainmail bikinis</a> for everyone, not just the female characters). The basic idea here is that we should be sex positive: sex is good, natural, and we shouldn't try to suppress or ignore the fact that it's fun and pleasing to look at semi-naked bodies. This is classic 90s liberalism, and as I recall, its main foes at the time were (i) fairly intellectually shallow religiously-motivated prudes ("you can see the outline of his penis, it's scandalous!") and (ii) radical feminists concerned about 'objectification'.</p>
      <p>I don't have much sympathy for either of these lines. I won't go into why I don't take the prudishness line too seriously (though see Argument 2 below), but I'll briefly comment on the objectification line specifically to say that I think it's a giant motte and bailey. I really tried to find a more charitable reading, but basically the only prima facie plausible and persuasive readings I've seen trade on a huge equivocation in the Kantian notion of how it's bad to treat people as means rather than ends. On the one hand, that could mean being totally insensitive to people's well-being and feelings and ignoring the fact that they're a sentient being. This is how we think of psychopaths and shitty people who treat customer service personnel like dirt. Call this the <em>Strong Reading</em>. On the other, it could mean interacting with a person in a way in which you're <em>primarily aware of them</em> as a means of satisfying some need. This is what all of us normally do when we interact with Uber drivers or pizza delivery guys or baristas or whatever. We're not thinking of them as robots who we don't need to care about at all but the only reason the interaction is happening at all is because we want something from them. Call this the <em>Weak Reading</em>.</p>
      <p>So basically it seems to me that when men sexualise women or people sexualise people we're usually just objectifying them in the Weak sense. But then we do that all the time and it's not problematic. But the classic objectification arguments rounds that up to objectification in the Strong sense, which <em>is</em> problematic. But there's no a priori reason to think they're connected or that the one leads to the other; anecdotally, it seems like the coffee shop regular who interacts with the barista every day (and thus regularly objectifies her in the Weak sense) is if any likely to be a bit <em>more</em> empathetic than the out-of-towner who barks out their order rudely because they don't know how humans are supposed to treat each other in these situations. Maybe there's an empirical case to be made here about how Weak objectification leads to Strong objectification but I've not seen anyone really giving it persuasively, and I <em>have</em> looked.</p>
      <p>So I reject the objectification argument against sexualisation, and as I say, my instincts are 100% supportive of equal opportunities sexualisation: give me boobs, butts, bulging jock straps, and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Warhammer40k/comments/d8kkxp/probably_the_only_custodes_ill_ever_paint_if_the/">gleaming abs</a>. But those are just my political and aesthetic <em>instincts</em>, as I say, and I think there are at least three much better arguments against sexualisation that get way less play than the objectification line, so let me quickly summarise them.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(1) Asymmetrical gender preferences.</strong> It makes total sense to me that the optimal comfortable level of sexualisation in an all-male context is going to be way higher than in an all-female context. It's like decorative cushions and throw pillows - even if men can appreciate them aesthetically and might enjoy having a few around, the average man has far less need for/appreciation of them than the average woman. I think it's the same with sexualisation. Sure, a straight woman might enjoy some chiseled abs sometimes, and a gay woman might enjoy some decolletage, but compared to a gay man and a straight man respectively the vast majority of women won't be anything like as obsessed with looking at the relevant bodyparts. If this is right, then more sexualised environments mainly benefit straight and gay men. But do they harm women? Well, maybe. Outside of the right context, a lot of women seem to find sexualisation not just uninteresting but kind of gross. On top of that, it's not crazy to think that greater acceptance of sexualisation will have uneven outcomes for men and women. For example, the majority of men are heterosexual, so to the extent that wearing more sexualised clothing is acceptable in the workplace and can be used to win friends and influence people, the incentives to wear it will disproportionately fall on the shoulders (and plunging necklines) of women. While this may sound like a good deal for women ("dress sexy for social benefits"), in fact I suspect a lot of the relevant social goods are intra-gender positional goods where women are mainly competing with other women. This can lead to a "sexy tragedy of the commons" situation where basically women who would prefer not to dress sexily feel pressure to do so in order to keep up with their colleague who always wears the slutty dresses. This may sound like a rarefied situation but speaking to female friends this happens a lot and I think it explains one of reasons many women slut-shame each other. So I take this argument somewhat seriously.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(2) Hypersaturated reward mechanisms.</strong> I'm kind of fascinated by the "purity right" at the moment, which is a weird coalition that seems to have come together from tradcatholics, bronze age pervert fans, /fit/itzens, nofappers, groypers, and a few others, which is very anti-porn and focuses on how our society drives people to relentlessly coom and consoom. A lot of it is based on disgust and memes (<a href="https://i.kym-cdn.com/photos/images/newsfeed/001/859/101/a76.jpg">some of which are pretty good</a>), but the best general argument I've heard from these guys is that our society is full of hyperstimuli in every domain - food, drink, videogames, porn - and this is the cause of a bunch of problems from obesity to erectile dysfunction to the collapse of the traditional family. I think this is basically the generalised version of the core of Stephan Guyenet's argument in <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/04/25/book-review-the-hungry-brain/">The Hungry Brain</a>, and I've seen some feminists actually give similar takes about porn (minus the coomer memes). According to this line of thought, sexualisation typically is bad for us because it's usually a form of hyperstimulation, and hyperstimulation is bad for us for a bunch of reasons including e.g. the fact that it makes us engage in pathological behaviour and makes it harder to get normal reactions to regular stimuli. Again I definitely take this argument seriously (even if I don't always like the broader political framing).</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(3) Down with the kallistocracy.</strong> Sexualisation is bad because it benefits good-looking people and stigmatises unattractive people, and good-looking people already enjoy massive unearned advantages in our society. This is a weird argument that hardly anyone seems interested in making except occasionally Incels but I actually think it's a really substantive point. As I think I've mentioned before, I was pretty overweight as a teenager, but when I lost weight in my late teens/early 20s it turned out I had a good jawline underneath, and the resulting differences in my experiences and how people treated me were <em>huge.</em> I'm straight, for example, but because I had a lot of gay friends in my social circle and had a pretty boy face and twinkish body (eheu fugaces labuntur anni) I got lots of perks as a result, e.g., an almost-stranger giving me the $400 nearly new graphics card he was going to sell because I think he wanted to impress me (hey, he knew I was straight!). The idea that being attractive has massive benefits is one that has considerable empirical backing and it's also common sense; 30 Rock in particular had some great sketches about '<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=15MwhPv3Ud4">The Bubble</a>', and the masterful Ted Chiang wrote <a href="https://canvas.wayne.edu/courses/102861/files/3959556/download?download_frd=1">an amazing short story about it</a> (seriously, really thought-provoking read). Anyway, the point about sexualisation here is that it heightens and makes more salient differences in attractiveness between individuals, which already result in unearned benefits for the good-looking and undeserved costs for the ugly. So to the extent that we're egalitarians, we should oppose it the creeping influence of sex in our society.</p>
      <p>I think all three of these arguments against sexualisation are better than the objectification line. My instincts are still 90s sex-positive liberal, but these three definitely give me pause, such that my reflective verdict on sexualisation is still up in the air. As always, I'm very curious what others make of these arguments, whether I've missed any big ones, and more broadly what the pros and cons of more or less sexualisation in society are.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>