<post>
  <author>DrManhattan16</author>
  <date>2020-06-12T05:37:02Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gyvay9/george_floyd_protest_megathread/fukjjca/</link>
  <title>Learning from Camden's 2013 Police Reform</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>What should we learn from Camden's police reform of 2013?</strong>
      </p>
      <p>One point of contention in the current protests is what exactly the idea of "Defunding the police" would look like in real life.
Some are mocking the protesters for thinking that getting rid of the police will solve the issues the protesters claim they want to solve. In response,
pro-"defund the police" have rallied around a specific city and it's actions regarding the police force. </p>
      <p>Here's a <a href="https://twitter.com/QasimRashid/status/1270556673514618880">Twitter</a> example.</p>
      <p>One from <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-06-04/how-camden-new-jersey-reformed-its-police-department">Bloomberg</a>.</p>
      <p>One from <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/06/09/us/disband-police-camden-new-jersey-trnd/index.html">CNN</a>.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.governing.com/topics/public-justice-safety/gov-camden-disbands-police-force-for-new-department.html">Governing</a> has an article from 2014.</p>
      <p>I especially recommend you read the 2014 article, it was written in a time when Camden was not in the eyes of the nation to this extent.</p>
      <p>But what exactly did Camden do to get this attention and be upheld as a beacon of what applied "Defund the police" might look like?</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Back in 2013</strong>, the city was in dire straights economically. According to the <a href="https://nypost.com/2020/06/09/camden-nj-did-police-reform-right-not-that-radicals-will-pay-attention/">NY Post</a></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In 2013, state and local officials dissolved the old Camden Police Department and reconstituted it as the Camden County Metro Police. They did so for both programmatic and fiscal reasons.</p>
        <p>Camden is one of the poorest in cities in America, and the Great Recession exacerbated its chronic economic woes; the city was able to provide basic municipal services only thanks to massive state aid. At the same time, crime was rising, and the department had been hit hard by scandals involving corruption and abuse.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>But even before 2013, we had evidence of economic issues. The <a href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2193971/Camden-police-disbanded-270-officers-fired-amid-budget-crunch.html">Daily Mail noted in 2012</a></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The architects of the plan say they'll be able to put 400 police officers on the streets of Camden -- a dramatic improvement over the 270 who currently work the city, the Camden Courier Post reports.</p>
        <p>But, it's still less than the nearly 440 officers who were on the force just two years ago.</p>
        <p>Last year, Camden was forced to cut 168 officers, one third of its ranks, as a result of the budget crisis. It faced the prospect of cutting even more this year.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>CNN and other left-wing sites attribute the disbanding to police corruption. The <a href="https://www.aclu.org/press-releases/camden-agrees-pay-35m-victims-police-corruption">ACLU reported</a> that it had filed a suit in 2010 that resulted in a $35 million dollar payment in damages to 88 people who had been convicted due to planted or fabricated evidence.</p>
      <p>Perhaps these factors would have gone out of the public eye in another universe. But in our's, something very bad happened. The Camden murder rate for 2012 reached the unprecedented peak of 65 people. I don't think people understand just how appalling this must have been for the city at the time. Camden was literally called the Murder Capital of the USA by the Governing article I posted above, but this number was beyond anything in recent history, and I will prove this later.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>In came 2013</strong>, and the city decided enough is enough and <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/chris-christie-camden-police_n_2025372">worked with Gov. Christie</a> to disband the entire police force. There are a few things they did differently with this new force. Firstly, the police department's jurisdiction was expanded beyond the city to some neighboring areas, from what I understand. This led to it being more of a county police instead of a city police. Secondly, they rewrote the union contract to prevent cops from getting easy jobs off the streets, and cut pay as well. Most laid-off cops were rehired during process, including the former police chief, but many new people were also hired, taught by the veterans. Thirdly, they were able to be more selective this time, most likely to select for greater competency and against corruption.</p>
      <p>I want to remind anyone reading that this is just my way of numbering them, not a way of ranking their priorities.</p>
      <p>Anyways, now that we have the actual history done, let's move on to the second part of my post.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>It is claimed or implied that disbanding the police department has led to decreases in violent crimes. At the very least, you will see people claim that the murder rate actually went down in Camden after the police disbanding/reform of 2013.</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I wanted to see if this was true, so I searched for Camden crime reports. After getting nowhere, I found help from the state of New Jersey. Many thanks to their Dept. of Law and Public Safety for providing clear and easy to read crime statistics for their cities, including one Camden.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1_hnAxhnBRRAlqdbjrfq5_n6dsqDqJA6P/view?usp=sharing">Here is a link to a spreadsheet I made.</a> I expect an upvote from each and every reader who made it this far simply due to how long it took to manually search and copy crime values from scanned pdfs.</p>
      <p>Upon graphing the four types of violent crimes: murder, rape, robbery, and aggravated assault, I saw some things of note.</p>
      <p>Firstly, the city was understandably very reactive when the news came out of 65 murders in 2012. That is the peak of all our data going back to 1989. </p>
      <p>Secondly, there is no trend I can possibly think of when reading this. It fluctuates a lot, with the average murder count in a year being roughly 38. You can see the spike in 2012, but unless someone far more knowledgeable in stats comes by and corrects me (not that unlikely), I feel confident in saying there is no conclusion of future trends we can draw from recent historical data. </p>
      <p>This makes the claim/implication that Camden's murder rate dropped after their police reforms a statement that provides very little insight. "Camden's police department reformed in 2013 and the 2019 murder rate is now 25" is true in the same sense that "The sun rose in the east all of 2013 and the 2019 murder rate is now 25". It's technically true, but the implied positive and causal link does not appear supported by the data.</p>
      <p>If we expand our vision from murder to all four types of violent crime, we still get "it's complicated". We can see that rapes have declined overall, but their lowest point was in 2002 with 45, and the numbers seem to by climbing up now. If we look at robberies, we might be able to conclude that the reforms dropped a stable robbery rate. Lastly, if we look at aggravated assaults, we see a very small decline in the average and post-2013 the data still fluctuates too much to say anything conclusively.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>It is also claimed that Camden's excessive force complaints have declined significantly, possibly by 95% since 2014.</strong>
      </p>
      <p>It was reported in 2015 by <a href="https://www.inquirer.com/news/inq/complaints-rise-under-camden-police-20150425.html">The Inquirer</a> that Camden's complaints were rising against trends of other counties in NJ. This claim is likely true as well, but until I can find the aggregated counts, I can't really say one way or another. This is a really good thing if true.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>To conclude</strong>, I think Camden and its crime rate is predictably getting misunderstood. There is simply no way, in my opinion, to say that the murder rate went down <strong>because</strong> of the 2013 disbanding. We would need to wait maybe 4-5 more years before we got the bare minimum of data I would like to make a possible conclusion here. Pro-"defund the police" people aren't wrong to say that reforming the police department didn't result in crime exploding here. But the caveat here is that Camden already had downward or stagnant trends in its crime rates.</p>
      <p>I would like for comments on how I can improve my collected graphs. The link above should let you comment, so you can comment here or on the sheet. I already have one idea, that being comparing Camden to the national average or its fellow NJ cities.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>