<post>
  <author>DuplexFields</author>
  <date>2020-06-14T15:26:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/h8i55c/for_fucks_sake_stop_abusing_the_redblue_tribe/fut2qm1/</link>
  <title>Grey Is the Warmest Color</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I heartily disagree. Grey is the perfect color. The concept maps well to the personality of fandom geeks, and I would expect a study to result in a significant match to the high functioning side of the autism spectrum. So let’s revisit Scott’s first mention of the Grey Tribe:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>(There is a partly-formed attempt to spin off a Grey Tribe typified by libertarian political beliefs, Dawkins-style atheism, vague annoyance that the question of gay rights even comes up, eating paleo, drinking Soylent, calling in rides on Uber, reading lots of blogs, calling American football “sportsball”, getting conspicuously upset about the War on Drugs and the NSA, and listening to filk – but for our current purposes this is a distraction and they can safely be considered part of the Blue Tribe most of the time)</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Scott’s focus in the (in)famous essay was ingroups and outgroups, but doesn’t even attempt to define them for the Grey Tribe. I’ll go ahead and do that now:</p>
      <p>Grey Tribe members don’t get socialized in the same way as other children. They become teachers’ pets, seeing that relationship as the most important in the classroom. At recess, they’re picked last for kickball, and are teased for no reason that they can discern; they just seem to be the natural prey of bullies. Consequently, their outgroup are Mean Excluders: people who they perceive as arbitrary gatekeepers, bullies, or people who don’t want to converse; people who’ve already made up their minds. (And while this matches decently with the Blue Tribe outgroup, and usually leads to political alignment, they hate politics itself with a passion. More on that in a moment.)</p>
      <p>Grey Tribe members don’t fit in socially, because they’re not joiners. They won’t give up their own individualism to become part of a larger group because they keep hearing people in the group espouse beliefs or biases antithetical to their hearts. More than that, other people simply don’t seem to be interested in the same type of things they are: geekery. Or more precisely, <a href="https://tomsmith.bandcamp.com/track/rich-fantasy-lives">rich fantasy lives</a>. And meeting another Grey Tribe member at a fan convention and having a surprisingly memorable half-hour conversation about why, precisely, the Enterprise-D can’t transport people through Romulan shields, they feel like they’ve been friends forever. But this isn’t their ingroup; this is their tribe.</p>
      <p>So who is their ingroup? Clever people. People willing to see and create new possibilities, people willing to examine everything and build something because of what they discover. Isaac Newton, Thomas Jefferson, Nikola Tesla, Linus Torvalds. People for whom Truth and Logic are the noblest ideals, whatever the result may be.</p>
      <p>Consequently, the Grey Tribe skews libertarian because their political policy focus isn’t on What Works Because It’s Fair (Blue) or What Works Because It’s Safe (Red) but on What Works Because It’s True. Finding a balance between Fair and Safe isn’t a centrist desire to stop arguing or form a compromise that makes everyone lose, it’s a search for a golden ideal that will finally, finally get the Mean Excluders, who act like football fans rooting for their team, to <em>actually listen for once</em>.</p>
      <p>The Blue Tribe owns academia, and have made great strides in convincing the Grey Tribe they’re the same group <strong>and should vote progressive</strong> because the Grey Tribe tends to be in the Red Tribe outgroup <strong>and that’s unfair</strong>. The Red Tribe, meanwhile has Rand Paul, Ted Cruz, Jordan Peterson and Alex Jones, who appeal to the thinkers and truth-seekers with very different approaches which boil down to the same message: you are being manipulated and used by Mean Excluders <strong>who want socialism</strong> and it won’t end well if you give in. <strong>They both use the Grey ideal of Truth for their own ideals of Fairness or Safety, which they believe Grey Tribers share deep down.</strong></p>
      <p>Three political wills, three tribes, not two and a half. The Red Tribe is from Mars, the Blue Tribe is from Venus, and the Grey Tribe is from Vulcan.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Edit: after writing this, I realized I’d made the same political/tribal conflation OP was calling out. My corrective edits are in bold.</strong>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>