<post>
  <author>Gloster80256</author>
  <date>2020-06-13T19:26:48Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gyvay9/george_floyd_protest_megathread/fuqacdq/</link>
  <title> Feudalism Died With the Advent of Gunpowder</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think feudalism as an organizing principle died with the advent of gunpowder.</p>
      <p>EDIT: Expanded explanation</p>
      <p>
        <em>Feudalism is a hierarchical system in which the warrior caste controls and defends territory and extracts a rent from it. With gunpowder, a warrior caste becomes untenable and the system loses all appeal compared to management through centralized bureaucracy.</em>
      </p>
      <p>The knightly warrior caste which gradually emerged in Europe (with considerable aid from the Church) was operating on a sort of a gentleman's agreement: The knights spent their entire youth training for combat. Well fed, in top shape, skilled with weapons and heavily armored they totally slaughtered any peasant militia they encountered in close combat - and when the pros crossed blades, the loser generally wasn't killed: As a hostage, he was way more valuable and besides - it's all a good sport, no hard feelings between us, the nobility. After all, if we were to perish, who should look after the commoners?<sup>1</sup></p>
      <p>Gun powder changed all that. Now any band of peon noobz could not only face professional warriors with some chance of success - but worse, blow the knights to pieces en masse in the process, as practically proven during the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jHJHtvMcBKA">Hussite wars</a>, which not incidentally probably enriched the military vocabulary with the words pistol (form "píštěl" = 'a flute', 'a whistle; a simple, light hand cannon, predecessor to the musket) and Howitzer (from "houfnice"; "houf" = 'a troop', 'a gaggle', implying that the weapon was employed in firing shot at bunched-up infantry).</p>
      <p>The warrior nobility (at least on the continent) couldn't sustain its numbers in the new combat environment and as a result neither its political influence. And since the unwashed peasants with guns were additionally cheaper, the state power turned to centralized professional standing armies instead - and that obviated the need for any feudal intermediaries. With rising literacy, growing influence of the cities and better communications technology, the sovereign could rule the territory directly, which gave rise to the absolute monarchies in France, Austria and Prussia, where the vassals no longer presented any serious competition to the king and were relegated to the role of office holders and officers within the bureaucratic apparatus of the central authority.        </p>
      <p>Today, the battlefield logic remains and is further strengthened by the existence of complex weapon systems supported by massive industrial pyramids. Procuring an aircraft carrier is not best executed on the level of a fiefdom. Sot here is just no advantage in creating a chain of powerful, independent players with private armies, jockeying for an optimal position vis-á-vis the throne, when the authority can just execute everything through loyal central command. Maybe once we get to the dimension of the solar system - lords paramount of individual planets within a larger empire, Dune-style, might make some sense.   </p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>1 This is highly simplified - there were instances of mass death of knights in battles (e.g. Crécy, where the blind, old John of Luxembourg was said to have charged uphill against the hail of English arrows, proclaiming "May God see to it that no king of Bohemia ever flee from the field of battle!" opening the succession to his highly competent and successful son, the future Holy Roman Emperor Charles IV. When Frederick V of the Palatinate, then dubiously reigning as a king of Bohemia, fled from the battle of the White Hill in 1620, it signaled the beginning of the Thirty Years War and end to Bohemian sovereignty...) However, it still captures the predominant custom of war in which the professionals generally survived and the caste thus wasn't being continuously depleted. </p>
      <p>Ping to <a href="/u/orthoxerox">u/orthoxerox</a> and <a href="/u/stolbinksiy">u/stolbinksiy</a></p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>