<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T10:34:51Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsiiy8d/</link>
  <title>Humiliation - The Biggest Driver of Rage</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Humiliation is the biggest driver of rage. </p>
      <p>Thus, the honor killing, the cuckold beating up his wife’s boyfriend, the woman who divorces her husband only after his two decades of adultery have been publicly revealed - because now that humiliation, once private and now no longer so, affects her social standing amongst her friends. </p>
      <p>Someone here wrote a good post a few days ago that made a relevant and valid point - <em>black people will never accept being the American underclass</em>. It doesn’t matter how much welfare or housing or scholarship funding you offer, it doesn’t matter how they’re policed, it doesn’t matter how well-meaning any white liberal is. The protesters are right here and I agree with them that their anger is not illegitimate. Look at how angry, how furious, white nationalists get online because they believe they live in a country ruled by Jews (even though, if this were the case, the Jews would have furnished them with often very prosperous middle class existences). Material prosperity isn’t enough to sate them. The very idea that they could be under the rule of another people is humiliating and horrific for them. </p>
      <p>Many African Americans sense that even newer immigrants are above them on the totem pole. Figuring out where you are on the social hierarchy isn’t hard - think back to high school. And being low down is a humiliation, a deep one. </p>
      <p>When you live in the poorest neighborhood in town (as your ancestors have done since the great migration), in a nation in which the number of your people who have achieved the greatest honor in your society (billionaire status) can be counted on the fingers of one hand despite you making up 14% of the population, when the big stores in your neighborhood are owned by white people (through their 401ks that you don’t have) and the smaller ones are owned by more successful minorities, you notice. When almost all of the small number of your people who achieve any success are effectively entertainers (whether athletes or musicians) for white people, you notice. Whether you’re seen as scum or a charity case doesn’t even matter, both are humiliating, the latter perhaps even more so. </p>
      <p>This doesn’t mean the above impulse can’t be suppressed. Plenty of countries have successfully oppressed minority populations for centuries. But the resentment will <em>never</em> go away.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>