<post>
  <author>bsbbtnh</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T14:00:47Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsiz6xk/</link>
  <title>The Businesses that Won't Rebuild</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Let's talk about the future. "Businesses will rebuild." Except... Why? Even if you have an insurance payment coming your way, you just watched your hard work get burned to the ground while the nation cheered. I hope I'm wrong about this, but if you are a forward-thinking person, committed to building infrastructure that will serve a community into the future, and that community demonstrates resoundingly that they do not share those values... I would be inclined to take the payout and set up my shop somewhere else. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Even if they get an insurance payment, for full replacement value AND business loss, they still might not rebuild.</p>
      <p>Some of the hardest hit businesses are retail and hospitality. Those industries are being <em>crushed</em> right now by COVID-19. National chains are going belly-up. Small businesses have been steamrolled. What little was left is now up in flames. For many small business owners, this will be a blessing. Because operating at 50% (or less) capacity, with all the restrictions and extra duties (primarily enhanced cleaning) isn't going to be profitable. </p>
      <p>With a global recession (and possibly a depression), it's bound to get worse. The uncertainty of the next year or two is going to be unprecedented. All that money will provide a nice little safety net to weather that storm, or to retire in a nice, rural community. For many, this payout is going to be <em>considerable</em>, as they likely started their small business on a shoestring budget and have funneled every dollar back into it. </p>
      <p>Large businesses like Target are unlikely to put millions towards rebuilding in the midst of a pandemic/recession. They are going to use that insurance money to pad their bank account, just in case. Even if they rebuilt immediately, some of these places would require over a year to tear down, rebuild, and stock. And in some places, the permitting processes and dealing with NIMBYs can extend that considerably. I don't think any company is going to want to risk starting construction before November, because of the risk that some people may riot if Trump is re-elected. </p>
      <p>Another thing is that WFH (work from home) has more or less proven itself worthy for many jobs. Many middle and upper-middle class folks may no longer be tied to a specific city. So not only can they choose the suburbs, they can head to the boonies, or halfway across the country. Their dollars will stretch much further. </p>
      <p>These riots will just push that needle a little bit further. We may see some genuine white flight on top of this. And other minorities who have the means.</p>
      <p>And consider that cities and states are in a dire place with massive deficits and shortfalls because of the global pandemic. Now these places are going to have to add rebuilding to it. An unpopular expense is going to be buying a bunch of new police cars, building new precincts, the massive bill for the overtime from these riots, etc. And I imagine there are going to be a lot of lawsuits filed over the actions of the past few days.</p>
      <p>All this is funded by taxes, primarily property and sales taxes. And if people flea the cities, and jobs vanish, and businesses never reopen, that tax base is <em>gone</em>. Not for a couple years, but for decades. Property values will plummet which will require them to raise taxes to an eye-watering amount. This is a Detroit-level crisis that could hit a dozen or so major cities in the US.</p>
      <p>The rich could also flea, probably to cities that aren't as impacted. And since the rich pay the majority of taxes, that could be a death sentence for many cities and states.</p>
      <p>Someone posted in last week's thread a WaPo article about how Ferguson still hadn't recovered from their riots (article was from 2018). Considering the current economic climate, I'd expect a longer recovery.</p>
      <p>And one last thing. The people likely to benefit are conservative areas. As a bunch of 'outsiders' poor into small-town America and red states for the cheap cost of living, they are going to be bringing a bunch of money, high incomes from WFH that funnel into those communities. So while blue states begin crumbling, and liberal cities turn to ghost towns, the rest of the country will be seeing a boom, a revitalization they've never seen. And I <em>guarantee</em> these folks aren't going to suddenly wish for higher taxes in order to pay for the mismanagement of the cities they had just fled.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>