<post>
  <author>CDO_Cubed</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T22:01:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fskkk7y/</link>
  <title>Starter Packs Teach You to Dodge Stereotypes</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Somethings I've noticed about the Internet which I don't see much discussed is how it facilitates education about stereotypes and leads to people actively attempting to avoid them. This is perhaps most apparent on starterpacks, where various "types" of people are stereotyped, often from a critical perspective. The reader is reminded that they don't want to be like "that person," whether it be basic sorority girl, white trash guy, libertarian male college student, rich international student who wears too much designer clothing,  upper/middle/lower class Karen, person who likes Joe Rogan and Jordan Peterson, etc. Even as society increasingly vocalizes discomfort with stereotypes, the taxonomy of "types" of people discussed on the internet are ever growing. Political compass memes demonstrates some of this in the political realm, but the four quadrants are not nearly enough to cover the number of "types" of political actors that I have become aware of from browsing the internet. Each has its own subcultural and you can basically predict what they will say about any given topic, down to specific arguments, by just observing the relevant forums for awhile. Another good example is the taxonomies that the incel/pick-up artist communities have developed about different types of males and females as they relate to the dating market.</p>
      <p>This was already facilitated to some extent by TV, but the Internet has greatly accelerated the process of stereotype generation. What I find more interesting in myself is a greater tendency to engage in "stereotype avoidance," by which I mean that whenever I come across some negative stereotype online whose features I partially recognize in myself, I find myself avoiding displaying such features in the future. One good example is the "cringy" libertarian young guy stereotype, perhaps best exemplified by the phrase "AM I BEING DETAINED." Another is that of the "clueless white person," which involves using well meaning but loaded statements such as "I don't see race," and (when referring to a black politician) "he's quite articulate," and in general I make a special effort to adopt the proper terminology and turns of phrase in the social justice sphere as they evolve so as to avoid stepping on a land-mine; I often find that the biggest impediment to having a conversation on social justice topics is accidentally making an argument which includes some phrase on whose problematic nature some academic has written an article. Saying "I don't see race" is just the sort of thing an uninformed but well-intentioned white person might say, but it also puts them in a category of "bad people" from a social justice perspective, so it is important to learn such phrases and avoid them. The rabbit hole goes deep. Making any request of a person of color during a discussion can be interpreted as expecting them to "perform emotional labor," or "educate you about your racism," so it is important monitor your statements closely as you don't want to be perceived as the type of person who would be clueless enough to expect such a thing. But if you mess up, it is important how you apologize, because if you try to explain yourself or express remorse or how bad you felt, these are other forms of racism perpetrated by clueless white people. There is also the stereotype of the person who constantly complains about "SJWs" or is constantly outraged about speaker cancellations on college campuses, and I have found myself doing less and less of this over time. To be clear, it is not the mere fact of having concerns about free speech on campus, which I do, but rather being associated with a particular subculture associated with "person who constantly complains about SJWs and free speech on campus", which along with these surface level features have certain cultural associationsthat are hard to put into words, which seems the thing to avoid. I no longer express opinions about the relative importance of the hard sciences vs other fields (don't want to come across as a STEM-lord, after all). This even applies to fashion, where I have through the internet become aware of particular articles of clothing that signal certain stereotypes, such as cargo shorts and square toed dress shoes, which I now actively avoid but did not previously associate with anything in particular. In general, I have found myself gradually sanding off the "rough edges," and actively avoiding attempting to say or do anything that could possibly classify me as some stereotype or other, and politically speaking in my case this applies to both left, right, and even centrist stereotypes. This has even extended to vocalizing self awareness when doing something potentially stereotypical, or saying something to indicate that I am doing it ironically, because somehow if you recognize what you're doing is stereotypical the stereotype often no longer applies in the eyes of others. </p>
      <p>Now, my assessment is that I have actually benefited from this. Prior to actively browsing the internet, I was highly socially clueless, saying what in hindsight were politically inflammatory things, demonstrating various forms of nerd-related "cringy-ness," etc. This has mostly gone away because I have learned what to actively avoid doing and saying. The internet is great at critiquing your behavior in a way that most people around you will not. I am not going to conclude that the net effect of the effects I have outlined above are good or bad, though they certainly hurt one form of diversity, namely certain types of "cluelessness," and as society becomes more aware of these stereotypes it becomes easier to bash eachother over the head with them. "He's just a cringy libertarian type." "She's just a crincy SJW type." People know exactly what you are about, everything that you will say, your opinions on a broad range of issues, and can basically dismiss you out of hand because you have pattern matched something in their personal outgroup. I know that I have rambled a lot, with lots of personal anecdotes, etc, but I find the mass construction of stereotypes quite fascinating and under-discussed, so if anyone has any other examples or observations related to that topic that would be great.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>