<post>
  <author>georgioz</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T09:26:02Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsieuw9/</link>
  <title>The Faux Poor Look in Disbelief as America Burns</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>And here's where it gets scary. Millennials own less assets than boomers did at this point in their lives. They also appear less likely to inherit any real assets -- it is all more likely to get absorbed by the nursing homes. Which means that all of them -- not just Black -- are going to feel like strangers in their land.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I disagree a bit with the inheritance part. Overall during last 50 years or so the wealth of US households increased by around 50%. On top of it the average number of children decreased from 2.33 in 1960 to 1.92 in 2019. So the average wealth per child increased by around 80% during last 50 years or so. </p>
      <p>Now there are huge swings in wealth. For instance before 2008 financial crisis the median household wealth was at its historical high of $140,000 while currently it is only around $100,000. Also the distribution is not equal - 80th percentil in USA is around $500,000 the upper quintil is $370,000</p>
      <p>But make no mistake - in the upcoming years millennials are about to inherit all the wealth accumulated by boomers. We are talking <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jackkelly/2019/10/26/millennials-will-become-richest-generation-in-american-history-as-baby-boomers-transfer-over-their-wealth/">$68 trillions by 2030</a>. As a comparison the crushing student loan debt is now around $1.6 trillions. Millennials as a whole will become by far the richest generation in US history - at least 30% or so of them. </p>
      <p>This is one of the reason why I strongly dislike the whole income inequality story. Scott Sumner has nice series of articles about this. The income inequality is myopic as it discards the story of a person over their lifetime. Imagine you are born into firmly upper middle class family as an only child - to a doctor and attorney let's say. Imagine you also opted into doctor's carrier. If you are student you will be counted as among the poorest households. Scott Sumner used a nice example - second poorest city in USA is Athens, Ohio. Because it is student city full of campuses and children of middle-class parents. So the story is that fresh graduate from school has student debt and just entry salary. In her 30ties she however starts to earn more income and by 40ies she will firmly set herself into upper middle class. On top of it maybe in her 50ies or 60ies she will inherit wealth from her parents. </p>
      <p>The point is that in no time in her life can this millennial child considered as anything but firmly upper-middle class. She has social status and safety net of parent's income and wealth/ At the beginning she has lower income herself and negative wealth thanks to student debt. However this is natural progression and as she gets older she uses her human capital to accumulate financial capital or real estate worth probably in millions. </p>
      <p>So back to the original story. I can see why poor people riot. However this really has to be viewed as multidimensional story. There are "poor" people who are destined to become millionaires thanks to their "privilege" - of education, social status or simply inheritance. The real story is something like bottom 30% of really poor - people with bad employment prospects and from poor families without wealth - against let's top 30% - people with good jobs and from families that have assets. </p>
      <p>However it has to be said that it was always so. In 1960 the wealth threshold for bottom 20% was around $2,000 in today's dollars. Today it is around $5,000. So if anything the actual situation "improved" for these people. What is different is that instead of "American Dream" story we now have woke narratives of opression and grievances. Narratives propagated by priviledged woke children of journalists and professors in academia and so on. Even these children were cuddled by fictive narratives of top 0.1% or whatnot. No, you are the real class enemy. The real money is not with top 0.1%. The money is with top 30% - the ones that accumulated capital over their lives but also the future top 30% - the doctors and professors and lawyers and programmers and successful small business owners.</p>
      <p>These people now look in disbelief as America burns. They have their world turned upside down - they were friends of oppressed, were they not? They have friends of colors - their colleagues, successful Indian programers  and Ivy leage black graduades. Guess what the precariat does not care. They are not your friend just because you follow some inane and naive cultural rituals on twitter. No, it is not Trump alt-right provocateurs that turned your world upside down. This is direct result of the narrative nurtured over past decades. This is what it looks like when powerless express their anger.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>