<post>
  <author>Gloster80256</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T17:28:04Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsjmu0d/</link>
  <title>On Jenga Events</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I would like to propose a term: A Jenga Event.</p>
      <p>In the same way any single removal of a block might result in the collapse of the whole structure - but the vast majority won't<sup>1</sup> - Jenga Events <em>might</em> plausibly result in catastrophic political or diplomatic shifts but generally just blow over without much impact.</p>
      <p>I had a precursory discussion here on this topic around the time of the Iranian incident earlier this year, in which I argued that the sole fact that nothing ultimately came of this one particular instance of escalation did not automatically indicate the move was risk-free. I thought it was a Jenga Event and the block merely got successfully removed, like many times before.</p>
      <p>The purpose of the term is to denote a category of situations lying between "I'm sure this is nothing." and "I confidently predict this will end our civilization." The cataclysmic potential is there, but it most likely won't be realized. The snake didn't bite - but maybe we should stop poking at it with our foot.<sup>2</sup></p>
      <p>I think the current riots are a Jenga Event.</p>
      <p>And the mechanism distinguishing them from all the past riots of the past (some of which were surely also Jenga Events turning out dud) is their direct connection to the political fault line. There are scissors at work here: Most worryingly, no unified national perception on the meaning of the situation seems to be forming. My liberal friends and digital peers see it on the whole as a brave stand against an important problem - and therefore support it's continuation. My conservative set sees little more than senseless riots and looting and wants a swift end to these events, by escalating force if necessary.</p>
      <p>And I'm seeing both sides continually tribally consolidating, the Right under the banner of "Order!" and the Left flying the flag of "Justice!", each utterly abhorring the fact that the Other will evidently rather stand with "Chaos!" or "Tyranny!" And since it's happening after four years of increasing political polarization, in the middle of an epidemic, on the eve of an economic crisis, this could turn into a self-perpetuating Existential Struggle - "With us or against us, until total victory!" The reasonable center, arguing for proportionate reforms and no more looting, might get peer-pressure-peeled away from both sides into irrelevance. It won't be about George Floyd or any other specific cause anymore - it will turn into "Taking back the country from the fascists!"/"Defending the country from an anarchist revolt!" (And there will be plenty of footage to show, of Antifa as well as authority overreach.) And it's still going on! People are still in the streets, with overworked police, frenzied media, indecisive Federal Government and organized, armed activists and provocateurs. This could truly blow up.</p>
      <p>Maybe. Who knows. Probably not. Probably the cooler heads will ultimately prevail and the people in the streets will get tired of it. That's why I'm so happy to see the instances of communities getting together for a big cleanup and some psychological healing. There is a good chance the block will be taken out and placed on top with no real trouble. But boy, is the payload there. Our hand needs to be super steady.<sup>3</sup></p>
      <p>1 I haven't been able to find a definite statistical answer, but my best guess is that the median number of moves before a collapse lies somewhere around 25, implying a roughly 3-5% <em>average</em> probability for a block. Then again, the individual probability is definitely not linear. Then again again, the same holds true for society: successive blows compound (even if this metaphorical tower does posses some self-healing capacities.)</p>
      <p>2 Conversely, things like wildfires, hurricanes or even mass shootings typically aren't Jenga Events because the probability of them leading to a war or a revolution <sup>i</sup> "on their own" <sup>ii</sup> is tiny.</p>
      <p>i Which are the only real existential threats to powerful modern states, barring supervolcanos, magnetic-pole reversals and such. I think that's quite an achievement on our part.</p>
      <p>ii Nothing happens in isolation. Ji ji muge.</p>
      <p>3 Unless you are of the accelerationist persuasion. In which case - please explain to me, how is the status quo so terrible that it warrants a civil war in a nuclear superpower.</p>
      <p>EDIT for typos</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>