<post>
  <author>majorcyst</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T17:26:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsjmm69/</link>
  <title>Reflections on a Positive Protest Experience</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>At the age of 36, I attended my first protest yesterday: the George Lloyd anti-brutality rally/march in Denver.</p>
      <p>I may not have time to respond to replies or debate, but I wanted to offer the below thoughts as a different perspective from what is typical for the sub. I hope the below is taken in good faith.</p>
      <p>For political perspective, I consider myself left-libertarian, but I've glided increasingly leftward since 2016.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Personal Experience</strong>
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>I joined the rally/march casually. I'm skeptical of BLM, but it's abundantly clear that U.S. police culture is broken. I attended the rally out of curiosity, and joined the march after being impressed by the peaceful crowd and atmosphere. We marched from the Capitol to around Coors Field and back.</li>
        <li>The protesters were a diverse bunch, with a core of young white professionals. I found the general vibe charming; energized but peaceful. Most protestors seemed casual and not particularly prepared. There was a strong sense of community, with cars honking in support as we marched and college-age kids running around offering water and snacks.</li>
        <li>Almost everyone was masked, but the six-feet rule was violated constantly. A Covid resurgence is guaranteed, and the charge of haphazardness on the part of protestors is valid.</li>
        <li>There was no indication of violence among the daylight marchers. The march's 'spokesman' twice read a long MLK passage emphasizing nonviolence, urging us not to provoke the police. I realized during this that I had subconsciously pre-judged this young black man for looking 'thuggish', but his heart was in the right place, and shame on me for presupposing otherwise.</li>
        <li>I left the Capitol before the 8PM curfew, but the night crowd was different in composition. More male, more young, lots of home-made armor. Some dingbat brought an airsoft rifle to the cops' alarm, but this was the only quasi-violence I saw before heading home.</li>
        <li>This morning, there's plenty of graffiti around Capitol Hill. There are citizens cleaning and picking up litter, most of them protesters themselves. Cleaners are avoiding the government buildings, apparently due to police request. Naturally, the media is mostly showing footage of these public buildings, giving the impression that the neighborhood is in disarray, when in truth some streets look better than they did before the protests began.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>
        <strong>General impressions</strong>
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>I'm bewildered at how many folk hold protesters to a higher standard than expensively-trained and comically over-equipped police professionals. I've seen footage of protesters tackling and borderline arresting looters; I have yet to see good police arrest or even scold their trigger-happy comrades.</li>
        <li>I'm disgusted by police behavior nationwide. Anecdotally, I've found cops to be arrogant and audacious even in benign situations, but their reactivity this past week is beyond the pale. Even if the protests began foolishly, they've since proven that U.S. police culture is utterly broken — this is why I'll continue to support the protests.</li>
        <li>If I had to hazard a guess as to the core problem, it's that police work naturally attracts a higher-than-average percentage of supremely toxic people, but little-to-nothing is done to address this problem (for a host of reasons). I don't think training or oversight are solutions: you are not going to educate away malignant personalities. My libertarian pipe dream is that we end the drug war and other victimless crimes, eliminate half of all police positions, and double the pay of those remaining to attract and retain doctor-quality talent. None of this will happen.</li>
        <li>I have zero tolerance for looters, but there's a gulf between my emotional reaction and those of my more conservative countrymen. As disgusted as I am by a torched business, it's a blip relative to my disgust at widespread police malfeasance. I wonder if we're not verging on emotional / gut-level / value-level difference here. I value life &amp; liberty over property at a very high rate; if looting and torching all ~1,800 Targets in the country could somehow reduce police brutality by half, let em burn. Thankfully, this is not the choice before us.</li>
        <li>Lastly, I'm depressed, tired. The tribal lines are clear, and those in positions of power will do nothing to hold the unraveling center. I expect the mostly older voting populace to pearl-clutch by way of re-electing 45 this November. I don't believe social collapse is at hand, but I more strongly believe that divisiveness will accelerate — and if we've descended into pure cynical tribalism, into a pure defect-defect paradigm, then I see no choice except to fall in line with a left that I find half-unhinged but capable, at least, of flashes of benevolence.</li>
      </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>