<post>
  <author>nomenym</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T06:13:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fsi2gc2/</link>
  <title>Reinforcing Negative Patterns: Police Brutality and Black Underclass Culture</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Frankly, it’s kind of amazing that cops are not more prejudiced against blacks, especially young black men.</p>
      <p>There’s a particular subculture comprised mostly of black males where criminality and hostility toward the police is normalized and even valorized. I want to call this the black underclass culture. Although it is by no means exclusive to the economic underclass, it has a way of dragging people down there eventually.</p>
      <p>Internet Nazi trolls like to point out that only about 13% of the population is black, and yet crime victim surveys imply that blacks are responsible for about 50% of crime. But this doesn’t really go far enough, because the vast majority of that crime is actually committed by black males between the ages of 15 and 40. That’s only about 3% of the population. We can probably shave off a few more fractions of a percent by isolating the markers that identify someone as part of the black underclass culture. There are salient features of accent, slang, and fashion that this subculture adheres to, and they can reliably be used to identify its members. It’s really the whole package (rather than just race, sex, and skin color) which is informative.</p>
      <p>My impression is that black males who don’t belong or seek to escape the black underclass culture, and especially those who abhor it, conspicuously countersignal their membership to avoid the being lumped in with the same stereotypes. By these means, they avoid most of the inconveniences and prejudices that members of this subculture must endure. These black males are disproportionately well-educated, and are more likely to live and work in mostly white communities.</p>
      <p>It’s probably a safe bet that members of the black underclass culture have a lower average IQ than blacks as a whole, so we’re probably looking at something in the 80-85 range. This is quite low. There really aren’t very many opportunities for people like that, especially when they belong to a subculture which is antagonistic toward authority, obsessed with honor, prone to violence, and awash with drug addiction. Moreover, the high achieving blacks who emerge within these communities are quickly whisked away by the education system and jealously sought after to fulfill corporate diversity quotas. In the process, the black underclass culture sinks deeper into its sicknesses.</p>
      <p>Police officers aren’t anything special: they’re not especially well-educated, have pretty average IQs, and are often themselves a product of dysfunctional communities. As quite normal people who notice patterns and form stereotypes, they can’t help but be aware that the black underclass culture produces a massively disproportionate amount of the crime they deal with on a day to day basis. Moreover, this culture is uniquely antagonistic and uncooperative, frustrating efforts to enforce laws and bring criminals to justice.</p>
      <p>Black males in the black underclass culture are highly destructive of their own communities, and the social norms and mores they adhere to can be brutal. They kill each other, and they do it a lot. Police officers are regularly exposed to the worst of it—they’re called out to deal with the aftermath of the executions, drive-bys, overdoses, burglaries, etc. they will see a lot of really horrific and heartbreaking shit. Most of the time, they know who is probably responsible, but there isn’t much they can do. Even if a cop does make an arrest, and even if they’re quite sure they’ve got their man, it’s quite possible for them to see a suspect they arrested that morning back on the streets, and up to no good, by the afternoon.</p>
      <p>There are normally community groups full of older men and women begging the police to do more. They don’t want their grandchildren, who they are raising, to grow up to be like their dysfunctional sons and daughters. The police can sometimes make arrests, but often the arrest itself is really the extent of the punishment. I suspect that many cops instinctively try to make arrests as unpleasant as possible, because there is already so little deterrence as it is, and it is the one thing they actually have some control over.</p>
      <p>Cops are also human. I was told a story about some cops who found two guys literally burglarizing a house on Christmas Eve; they were caught red-handed, wrapped Christmas gifts in their arms. When they saw the patrol car, they dropped the gifts and ran. When the cops caught up with them, the cops absolutely took the opportunity to, let’s say, use excessive force. I have no idea if the burglars were black and it wouldn’t matter. Fact is, this was probably police brutality, but how many people would care in this instance?</p>
      <p>The cops who found these burglars could reliably assume this wasn’t a one-off. In fact, the cops would expect these burglars had already been arrested, probably for a previous burglary. Moreover, they were probably responsible for other reported burglaries in the area. It is also highly unlikely that this Christmas Eve was their last burglary, and the cops who found them probably wouldn’t expect it to be. How would you feel in this situation? Perhaps you have complex abstract consequentialist arguments about the rule of law and due process, but remember that most police officers are not especially good at complex abstract thinking—most never even went to college.</p>
      <p>Many people seem to think that the problem with police brutality is that the cops don’t care enough about the communities they’re policing. While I think this is sometimes true, just as often the opposite is the case. The cops do care, but they’re also frustrated. They get angry and upset, and they push the limits of what they can get away with. The trouble is that such harshness can start to feel normal, and sometimes they cross the line. It also allows genuinely sadistic cops a lot of leeway, because the baseline is already so severe.</p>
      <p>The black underclass culture also seeps into the policing itself. How do police earn the respect and deference of young men in the black underclass culture? The same way the young men in that culture do—by demonstrating toughness. It’s the law of the jungle out there, for Pete’s sake! Respect and fear are entangled, and it’s hard to get one without the other.</p>
      <p>Threats of violence and physical domination are much more normalized as a way to resolve conflicts in underclass cultures, black or white. I’ve a redneck friend who always tells me about the literal fights that break out whenever his family get together, because I guess it just wouldn’t be a family get together without at least a couple bloody noses. When a cop finds himself interfacing with such a culture, especially when he is from such a culture himself, I think they inevitably pick up some of the local customs. Cops want to be taken seriously, so what do you do with a culture where you likely won’t be taken seriously until you escalate to physical force?</p>
      <p>I actually think most cops successfully decouple race itself from the black underclass culture. While they may develop an inappropriate suspicion and callousness toward young black men, they’re often motivated by the pleas for help by other black residents in the same community. Furthermore, black and white police officers seem to behave pretty similarly, and they appear to support one another without much disagreement about these issues.</p>
      <p>Of course, the big question is why does this dysfunctional black underclass culture exist, and why does it have such a bad relationship with the police? The framing I have given above largely implies that the aggresive policing is a response to the black underclass culture, whereas the popular narrative says that the black underclass culture is a result of the aggressive policing, particularly with regard to the war on drugs. Personally, I think each reinforces the other, and the issue of which came first is entangled in history. Whatever the initial cause, it’s much easier to be pushed into a hole than pushed put of one, i.e. I don’t think removing aggressive policing will necessarily solve the problem even if it helped create it.</p>
      <p>There may be some low hanging fruit that might improve the situation on the margin, but I don’t expect any big solutions. I dream of a world where being a police officer is a prestigious career, attracting highly competent and intelligent people, but we’re getting further from that dream every year. The fundamental problem is that when you have whole subcultures and communities with sub-85 average IQ, regardless of race, it’s going to be highly dysfunctional by the standards of a modern industrialized nation.</p>
      <p>Oops, I didn’t mean this response to get so long.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>