<post>
  <author>solomute</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T13:36:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsiwtry/</link>
  <title>A Resident's Account of the Minneapolis Riots</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>More on the Minneapolis riots:</p>
      <p>So, the overall timeline goes like this. The first night felt like just a normal protest. Minneapolis has a lot of these because the politics here lean very Woke, I think largely because the population is very majority white, and in a Blue city that creates a lot of vulnerability to white liberal guilt that manifests as overcompensation. Anyway, normal protest. Police dispersed the crowd with tear gas after some folks started throwing rocks and smashing the windows of the police station. Some people started damaging surrounding property. There are conspiracy theories about who these people are and what their motives were but they're just rumors in a sea of misinformation. I thought this would be the end of it, since that's usually how it is. A friend of mine blocked me on Facebook because I characterized it as a riot. She yelled at me about how her friends were there and they were peaceful protestors and how dare I call them rioters. Maybe calling it a riot at that point was a little far, but there was definitely property damage at that point and that's my general threshold for calling a protest a riot. Anyway.</p>
      <p>Night two, the protestors returned and there were more of them. This was the night that Minneapolis started burning. This in itself was pretty horrifying to me, but even more horrifying was seeing friends cheering the flames. I couldn't, and still can't, understand how someone can see their city burning and say it's a good thing. I just can't. All I can do is write it off as some weird artifact of Social Justice culture where anything that a minority does is Automatically Good and opposing it makes you racist. If that thing is obviously, blatantly bad, then celebrating it acts as a signal of your true commitment to Social Justice. Or something. Around the middle of the night I realized the economic implications of burning the city down and starting talking about them to people who were condoning the rioting. Got accused of being a heartless racist who cares more about property than human lives more times than I can count. Got blocked by a ton of people. Really cleaning up the 'ole friends list up here.</p>
      <p>Night three, the flames were worse. I watched buildings collapse on the livestreams. It felt like the apocalypse, watching images of people burning our city to the ground and laughing without a care in the world, as if they weren't going to wake up the next day and have to look at the ashes under sunlight. And more maddening was seeing people on social media, cheering without a thought for the true implications of what they were seeing. This is the night the police station was captured and burned down.</p>
      <p>Around this time, feeling a bit confrontational, I messaged a friend of the person who had blocked me on Facebook two days earlier, saying "[name] blocked me for calling it a riot. I'll take that apology now." That person blocked me too. Petty? Sure, but it felt good.</p>
      <p>The next day, the government charged and arrested the officer who had knelt on George Floyd's neck. In a move that will surely be remembered by future authority figures confronted with demands from leftists, protestors shifted the goalposts and said it wasn't enough. The governor declared a curfew. It was <em>flagrantly</em> violated, to say the least. I think even more people might have gone out than the previous nights. I think folks were emboldened by the lack of law enforcement response the previous night, they knew the government didn't have enough force to stop them, even with the arrival of the state police. The city burned some more. A press conference was held in the middle of the night where the mayor delivered what I thought was an excellent speech, impassioned and eloquent, begging everyone to stay home and let law enforcement stop the looting and arson, suggesting that the looters were white supremacists from out of town and that the true people Minneapolis cared too much about their town to hurt it. The governor delivered a speech repeating the plea to stay at home, and the claim of out-of-town nazis. In Atlanta earlier that day, Killer Mike delivered a jaw-droppingly eloquent speech begging people to stay home.</p>
      <p>I woke up the next day with a stress headache. Sentiments on social media seemed to be to the effect that the governor's and mayor's speeches were "tone deaf," and making fun of the mayor's emotional state, or rather what they perceived to be hammy acting. Folks were curiously silent about black community leaders joining the call to stay home. You would think that the folks who preach about Listening To Black Voices would actually, yknow, listen to black voices. Anyway, this caused me to start seriously worrying about another day of escalation and mass noncompliance with the curfew, and the possibility of riots spilling into the residential areas. I'm a firearms enthusiast, so I have a bit of a collection of weapons, but I had never, ever had to seriously confront the idea of aiming them at anything other than paper. I gave my roommates impromptu lessons in firearms handling, which they greatly appreciated. One of my roommates went online right there and ordered himself an AR-15 and a thousand rounds of ammunition, "for the next one." One positive thing to come out of this is definitely going to be the fact that gun control is a dead issue for at least another election cycle. If there is one.</p>
      <p>However, our fears turned out to be unfounded. Protests at night were limited to small groups, quickly and efficiently herded into corners and broken up or arrested. I realized as I looked at how much the nighttime protest groups had shrunk that something brilliant had happened. Folks had criticized the mayor's and governors speeches, but the idea that the people causing all the destruction were out-of-town nazis caught on like wildfire. All of a sudden, just like that, sentiment for the rioting turned from favorable because of the perception that it was committed by an in-group, to unfavorable because of the perception that it was committed by an out-group. People stayed home, only a few small groups went out that night. I've never been more happy to be wrong.</p>
      <p>News stations the next day fact-checked the claim of out-of-town nazis and found it to be false, most of the arrest records had Minneapolis addresses. Which implies that shifting the blame to the nazis may have been an intentional move that they knew would play on in-group/out-group biases. Or it might have simply been misinformation hitting their desks. If it's the former I'm seriously impressed, that wouldn't have occurred to me.</p>
      <p>The next night, last night, was the first night I spent not glued to a screen with worry. Minneapolis finally feels like it's settling down, just a few final stragglers to mop up. I have a few friends who are still committed to going out and protesting at night even though literally nobody, even the people they're protesting on behalf of, want them to. Hopefully in a day or two we can begin aid to people who have been left stranded in a food desert, and public services will resume.</p>
      <p>I don't think the story has really been told of what it's been like to be here but not involved in the protesting, just in the middle of it and hoping it doesn't try to sweep you in. It's a much more boring story, but I think the most human one. It makes me wonder about people caught up in civil unrest or war in other times and places. My political views on war have shifted more pacifist than they even were previously, and I was pretty damn pacifist already. I've decided to re-examine my views on gun control in light of seeing people burning cities for fun and realizing that those people are allowed to own guns too (my previous views were based on the notion that most people who are capable of living independently are functionally responsible people). My preference for civil order has definitely strengthened. And my sleep cycle is fuuuucked.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>