<post>
  <author>solomute</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T10:50:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsijw9q/</link>
  <title>The Futility of Riots</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>By and large these anarchist revolutionaries have not thought their anarchist revolution through past the "burn it all down" stage, and I've seen many activists who are personal friends of mine (including one who is in the now-famous picture of the police station burning) back way the hell down on their accelerationist rhetoric in the last couple days as the true implications of "burning it all down" have sunk in. It's very easy to tear things down, but building things up is difficult and mundane, and has historically been most successfully accomplished by the very capitalists that the nation has just thrown a gigantic middle finger to. Again, I hope I'm wrong, but there are areas that were destroyed by the riots of '67, which today are still largely ghettos of boarded up storefronts, and I fear that Minneapolis will be the same.</p>
      <p>I can hear the replies now, "property is not as important as human life! Fuck your capitalism if it means the deaths of unarmed black people!" Except, the most prosperous and peaceful societies in the world, "socialist utopias" like Denmark and Sweden, are actually regarded as the most capitalist societies on the planet. The problem with capitalism in America is that there are *too few* capitalists. The folks running around burning shit don't have an ownership stake in society, no investment in its success, and that's why they don't care if it burns. A robust social safety net, universal health care, government-funded paternity and maternity leave, debt-free postsecondary education, and other "socialist" policies free people to take risks, make investments, and start their own businesses.</p>
      <p>What does this have to do with black lives? The graph of "economy prosperity vs. homicide rate" is a line. Economic prosperity and trade is the single greatest force for peace that the human race has ever discovered. Destroying the local economy of Minneapolis will plunge its already-struggling minority communities into further poverty, and poverty breeds crime. The economic ramifications of the destruction of our city will kill more black people than police brutality ever would have, and the tragedy is that in 10 years, this spike in black deaths will be blamed on "white flight" or "gentrification," rather than the fact that black people burned down their own city and it never recovered. Again, I hope I'm wrong about that, but the historical evidence is clear.</p>
      <p>So the question becomes "well, maybe it's worth it in the short term if it produces justice and police reform in the long term, we've made it clear that if police reform is not pursued then cities will continue to burn." Historically, rioting pushes voters to the right. The '67 riots elected Nixon. It would not surprise me if many purple states, even the solid-blue Minnesota, flip red in November. Voters who have just experienced a major breakdown in civil order strengthen their preference for strong civil order, and so law-and-order conservatism will win at the ballot box. Our mayor and governor are almost certainly going to get massacred at the polls when they come up for re-election, and the mayor has been the one taking the strongest and most concrete steps for police reform of any mayor in decades. The law that will almost certainly convict the three bystander officers in Floyd's death, a law which requires officers to intervene in unlawful behavior by other officers, was passed by Mayor Frey (the reason they haven't been charged is because the statute will not have been violated until Chauvin is convicted). The next mayor will not be nearly so progressive.</p>
      <p>On top of the fact that the rioting will almost certainly backfire politically and end up electing a lot more "tough on crime" conservative politicians, it's extremely questionable whether it was necessary to produce a favorable outcome in this case in the first place. "The legal system does not provide instant gratification" has become a favorite saying of mine in the last few days. The legal system moves slowly, there are numerous protections intended to prevent hasty and impulsive police work from imprisoning innocent people, and for better or worse, those protections protect the guilty as well. It is tragic that black people too often don't survive to get the benefit of those protections, and that is a valid thing to protest, but that is not a valid reason to abandon those protections and convict the officers involved solely via the court of public opinion. The protestors would have the legal system discard the very protections that preserve justice for so many innocent people who get caught in it. Meanwhile, the behavior of the city and the police department in the first day after the killing demonstrate a commitment to taking the incident seriously. Nearly every former police officer in prison right now for crimes committed in the line of duty spent the duration of their investigation and trial still nominally employed by the police department. The MPD apparently thought that the four officers involved in the killing fucked up so badly that they were fired the very next day. Anyone who has ever worked in government, who knows how hard it is to fire people, knows how miraculous this is. MPD knew it was bad, and they acted quickly and decisively in the direction of justice on the very first day after the killing, before the protesting even started.</p>
      <p>However, rather than acknowledging this, protestors took it for granted that justice would not be served, before justice even had the opportunity to even start getting served, and started rioting when they didn't immediately get their way. The last policing controversy in this city, the shooting of Justine Damond, ended with the sentencing of the officer involved to 12.5 years in prison, but which required the patience of a two year process to achieve. Cooler heads needed to prevail and recognize that a lack of justice for Derek Chauvin was never a foregone conclusion, but we needed to be patient and let the legal system do its work. Instead, our country is burning down.</p>
      <p>Sorry for the wall of text, but the issue is complex and nuanced and it's an enormous tragedy to me that Twitter has reduced politics to opinions that can only be expressed in 280 characters. It's tragic that so many people believe that destroying civilization is the answer, and that not being in favor of that is somehow being in favor of police brutality. It's tragic that George Floyd died, but bigger tragedies are not the answer to that. That's all from me.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>