<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2020-06-01T19:13:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gueibb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_01_2020/fsjzzsh/</link>
  <title>Reflections on Antiriots: The Next-day Cleanup</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Thanks for sharing your experience. I'm glad to hear it was mostly positive.</p>
      <p>As a complementary point, I'll provide my own experience joining what I considered to be a political event of my own. I've been calling it an antiriot, but it's more commonly called the next-day cleanup. For political perspective, I'm most easy to place in the center, leaning left or right a bit unpredictably on an issue-to-issue basis. I consider myself pro-civilization, which is hopelessly vague but as good a marker as I can get. I expect we'd agree on a lot of specifics, but my emotional reaction is largely opposite to yours.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>My personal experience:</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Downtown wasn't nearly as bad as I assume many other cities are, but there was graffiti everywhere and a good number of broken windows. By the time I got there, a lot had already been boarded up, and people were still carting boards around to some of the more affected places. I swept up the glass from a couple of broken windows. </p>
      <p>There was a sense of community and camaraderie among the cleaners similar to the one you report among the protesters. Water being passed around, people slowing down to take photos as they drove by, so forth. Two separate times, building owners came out to thank us for cleaning up—the second when he noticed me cleaning in front of the building across the street from him, after which he called its owner to let them know. Some of those who cleaned were likely protestors, and if so I'm happy I could work alongside them. I doubt any of the ones spraying graffiti and breaking windows came back the next day to build things back up, though.</p>
      <p>It was probably 70-80% women. Lots of cleaners overall—enough that most of the glass and trash was taken care of quickly. The graffiti was a bigger problem, and I didn't have supplies to help with it, but it will come off with time. Cleaning up gave me a massive emotional boost and relieved a lot of the low-lying tension I've been feeling. It was good to see reminders of people committed to building things back up every time they get torn down. </p>
      <p>
        <strong>General impressions:</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I don't know how the peaceful part of the protest went. I wasn't there, but I assume it was much like yours. I only got to see the destruction that followed in its wake. A lot of people online reported that it was peaceful until the police escalated. I have a hard time trusting self-reports from any parties with these things, but I know it wasn't the police breaking windows or covering downtown with graffiti. If I had to hazard a guess, that's why onlookers are holding them to a high standard: the police aren't the ones smashing and looting the cities. The police aren't the ones people see as they wander through their wrecked downtowns.</p>
      <p>My instinct as to the problem with the police is that it's in a reinforcing vicious cycle. On my Mormon mission, I had a companion once who wanted to be a prison guard. He said it was because he wanted to beat people up. Someone is always going to be needed to do police work. If culture dissuades good people from becoming police officers and improving the institution from the inside, who's left? The more anti-police sentiment builds, the worse I believe the institution will become. That's one reason I'm wary of the protests, even though I'm seeing the same brutal/nasty bits you are.</p>
      <p>The emotional gulf you mention is key.  I have a hard time sorting out truth from propaganda with the cop abuses. Some seem real. Some seem distorted and exaggerated, others deliberately provoked. In all of them, the loudest voices react with the same fury, which inclines me further towards skepticism. The riots are clearer-cut. The moments that have touched/inflamed me most in all this are <a href="https://twitter.com/thauserkstp/status/1266766315911622663?lang=en">this</a> video of a Minneapolis woman heartbroken by the riots, <a href="https://twitter.com/_butterf1y_/status/1266875042656378880">this footage</a> from the Rodney King riots, and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-uqOM94RJVc">this</a> video of a Muslim store owner watching helplessly as his store is looted. My disgust at the riots overwhelms all other emotions here, <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fs7r9hr/">in part for ideological reasons and in part because I believe they will devastate their areas for years or decades to come</a>.</p>
      <p>It's not about property for me. It's about the sheer difficulty of building and maintaining civilization, and the feeling that it can all come tumbling down with ease if we grow careless and complacent. It's about social trust, damaged institutions, and decaying cities. I don't believe rioting is a way to achieve productive change, and I believe the damage of the riots is drowning out and overwhelming the good of the nonviolent protests. Enough people have died or been seriously harmed by the events of the last few days that I have a hard time deciding whether police brutality has had worse effects. This all seems to me to be compounding harm with harm. </p>
      <p>I'm also depressed, also tired. I'm in the center that's unraveling, and I see little way forward with either left or right. I worry that these riots will give Trump a law-and-order-style boost, reelecting him and deepening divisions further. <a href="https://www.facebook.com/barackobama/posts/10157802011441749">Obama's statement</a> is one of the best I've seen, and I have some hope that people will listen to him, but I refuse to cheer either a left or a right that seem to either give free rein to their worst impulses or provide cover for those who do. I'll continue standing with those of all groups who strike me as pro-social, altruistic, and determined to build and maintain something meaningful. But the chasm widens, and as tribalism deepens I'm left without one to call my own.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>