<post>
  <author>4bpp</author>
  <date>2020-03-13T21:40:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ffprqc/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_09_2020/fkfjacd/</link>
  <title>Is White Supremacy Inherently Self-Defeating?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This reminds me of a blog post I read a while ago (but can't find again now) that pointed out that in any given Western country, ethnic nationalists/white supremacists tend to be the least aligned with the "white culture" whose superiority they espouse and most similar to the foreigners they want to keep out (on measures of socioeconomic success, ingroup favouritism, violence...). If openness and lack of ethnic solidarity is an intrinsic feature of Western culture(s), how would one even go about constructing a lasting "pure" Western society? Can we be sure that the sequence of steps we take to reengineer Western culture to adopt the levels of ethnic consciousness (is the time ripe to reclaim the term <em>asabiyyah</em> yet?) would not erase its competitive advantage, making any variant of white supremacy inherently self-defeating?</p>
      <p>More disjointed points:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>I am unconvinced that in a "self-loathing West vs. array of ethnostates" setting, the ethnostates actually could leverage their derived minorities against their parent states in the way you suggest. In my experience, any $nation-Americans' purported association with their nations of origin is largely one-sided and completely superficial. Chinese people's ethnic pride is incompatible with Asian-American activism (try telling your racist Chinese uncle that you went to protest against cultural appropriation of kimonos at a museum) and some African-American interest groups were actively attacking universities for admitting too many actual Africans, thus watering down their activist base.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The premise of "strength in diversity" has not been conclusively disproven, even if the corporate bullshit version of it doesn't seem very convincing. The strongest empires to come out of Europe (Spain, England, Ottomans?) seemed to be more diverse <em>before</em> they even started expanding, though of course correlation/causation. If "the West" were ethnically purified down to white people, would it with its average IQ of 100 actually win against China with 107+? On the other hand, the self-loathing West has been winning so far, and the most successful countries have been even more self-loathing than the Western average.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>"White" is an American ethnic construct that still holds very little sway in Europe outside of places that have been completely perfused with American memes. Two decades ago, Germans still outgrouped Poles and Russians as much as they outgrouped Turks and any Africans. Go further back, and Jews and other European ethnicities got the same treatment. It does not seem far-fetched to argue that the circumstance that the West can form large-tent power blocs at all (EU, US) is owed to its lack of ethnic consciousness: restore it, and instead of getting any large "white" ethnostate, you'd get lots of small ones with the character and impact of Hungary. These would be lined up against ~1 billion Han Chinese.
I'm sure China would find it easier to divide and conquer <em>that</em> than to stoke tensions in what the West currently is.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>