<post>
  <author>brberg</author>
  <date>2020-03-12T17:43:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ffprqc/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_09_2020/fkbl5pa/</link>
  <title>Instinctive Misconceptions About Bloomberg and Wealth</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I mean, is it really that fantastical?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Yes. Total household wealth in the United States is about $100 trillion. Dividing that equally would yield about $300,000 per person in theory, though in practice the value of this wealth would crash hard as a bunch of newly kind-of-rich people tried to cash it in to buy consumer goods.</p>
      <p>Even putting aside the disastrous consequences of doing this, there is literally no amount of redistribution possible that can even theoretically make every person in the United States a millionaire.</p>
      <p>Looking at it another way, the aggregate after-tax income of the top 1% of filers is about $1.5 trillion per year. If all of that were redistributed, it would yield about $4,500 per person. This is about 30% of the new spending Bernie Sanders is proposing.</p>
      <p>This idea that huge amounts of additional tax revenue can be raised from the rich is pure fantasy. The things Bernie Sanders is promising are simply not possible. If you want Nordic levels of spending, you have to do what actual Nordic countries do: Heavily tax the middle class.</p>
      <p>Edit: Recall that what Gay and Williams said was "true" was a claim that Bloomberg could, with 1% of his wealth, make everyone in the US a millionaire. As embarrassing as they should find this, the much bigger issue here is that the fact that they found this even remotely plausible betrays a mental model of the US economy so far detached from reality that they cannot possibly reason about the topic.</p>
      <p>They shouldn't have had to do the math. If someone tells you Bloomberg can make everyone in the US a millionaire with 1% of his wealth, it should be immediately obvious to you that that can't possibly be true.</p>
      <p>Edit 2: On this topic, I'm starting to wonder about the extent to which support for left-wing politicians is driven by misconceptions like this. If that were true, arguments for huge amounts of redistribution would start to look pretty reasonable. And I see stuff like this a lot. A day or two after Williams and Gay figuratively soiled themselves on national TV, a Facebook friend (read: vague acquaintance) shared a claim that Bloomberg spending $500 million on his campaign proves that "the 1%" can fund all of Bernie Sanders proposed new spending "without breaking a sweat." It had 30+ likes and literally nobody pointing out that this is obviously false. There was that time Ocasio-Cortez claimed that single-payer health care could be paid for by cutting waste and fraud out of the military. People who don't pay enough in taxes for the government to break even on their K-12 educations think that their meager tax dollars are subsidizing billionaires. I've seen people claiming that all we have to do to pay for Sanders' proposed spending is cut "corporate welfare."</p>
      <p>I realize that the hard left is a thing, and some people really do want to just confiscate 90+% of everything the rich have, and optionally stick their heads on pikes. And I do think some major misconceptions about economic theory plays a role there. But I'm starting to realize that a lot of people have a lot of beliefs about basic facts that are demonstrably wrong, often by orders of magnitude, or with the sign reversed. What I can't figure out is whether those incorrect beliefs are fueling the embrace of left-wing politics, or whether the embrace of left-wing politics is causing some people to unthinkingly accept as true all manner of ridiculous factoids that appear to rationalize their ideology.</p>
      <p>I'm aware that there's a similar phenomenon on the right, and I have the same question there, but I have much more personal exposure to things that leftists get wrong.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>