<post>
  <author>HavelsOnly</author>
  <date>2020-03-10T14:13:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ffprqc/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_09_2020/fk3yul0/</link>
  <title>An Argument Against Dog Ownership</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Inspired by the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ffprqc/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_09_2020/fk1ykz1/">thread below</a> about millennial despair, in particular how rebuttals mentioned dogs as substitutes for children. This post is exploratory and an attempt to test some ideas I can't really test anywhere else.</p>
      <p>"Must like dogs" is an extremely common tag line in online dating profiles where I live. Large hip tech city, obviously. I like dogs. I don't like dogs. I don't know. It's complicated.</p>
      <p>The most accurate thing I can say about dogs is I feel sorry for them. My immediate family didn't own dogs growing up, but my extended family had farms or large acreage plots with 3-5 dogs running around all day. They eat, sleep, shit, and run around exploring with their pack hours a day whenever they want.</p>
      <p>Compare to city dogs. Mostly live in matchbox apartments. A typical weekday is likely 9-12 hours home alone. You can't run. You can't shit. You are bored out of your fucking mind. Your human comes home and walks you for 15 minutes on a leash. It's the highlight of your day. Human is tired and eats dinner in front of the TV while you get scratches. Maybe you sleep in the same bed as your human. You're probably pretty tired after an entire day of mostly not moving /s.</p>
      <p>Weekends if you're lucky, you go to a dog-friendly park. Maybe you get off leash. Maybe you never get off leash because you're too spazzy around other dogs/humans. It's completely understandable to be spazzy. You are chronically understimulated. One of your only opportunities to get energy and action in life is by "misbehaving" or harassing strangers.</p>
      <p>When I walk past someone with a dog and the dog is just pulling as hard as s/he can at the leash to pounce on me, you can't think that's instinct. No animal in the wild thinks it's a good idea to go fuck with something 3-30x it's bodyweight. It's pure boredom. The dog is just trying to stimulate itself before it's forced back in front of the TV to watch The Office again.</p>
      <p>A common rejoinder is that "s/he's a rescue". This is supposed to shut down all discussion about the dog's QOL or behavioural issues, as if all their behaviour forever and ever is explained by their dark past. I guess, no matter how shitty a life your dog has, it's better than getting put down at a shelter. Okay, maybe, but we wouldn't think a really shitty neglectful foster home is morally praiseworthy just because it was better than some worse alternative.</p>
      <p>There's a laundry list of other topics like neutering, diet, training, etc that I won't elaborate on. There's enough grey area for people to get away with justifying whatever happens to be easiest for them, obviously, but I hope it's also obvious that there are many many ways in which the life of a dog is diminished compared to.... other normal living organisms...</p>
      <p>And one of the saddest things is that all of this seems to be a feature, not a bug. When the dog is deprived and understimulated and you are the Gatekeeper of All Things Good in the world, the dog bonds with you. Hard. Needs attention and affection from you, with every fiber of it's being. I think people take great pleasure in this kind of hobbled dependence.</p>
      <p>Again, I feel very sorry for dogs, and am growing a ton of animosity towards dog owners. I know dog owners are "normal" people, but, you know the banality of evil and all that.</p>
      <p>Am I the only one who feels this way? Am I way off base? Is dog ownership actually good? Is a dog living in a matchbox apartment actually a good life? Most people are in love with their dogs. Like a family member! But city dogs live with less freedom than actual prisoners. They exist only in a way that is convenient to their owner, and have freedoms and joys only insofar as their owner finds palatable.</p>
      <p>I fully expect hella backlash from this. I'm heartless. I know. But it seems like a black stain we're all supposed to ignore because it fills a hole for city people. Lack of companionship, lack of children, etc. I understand those holes, it's just I'd rather be lonely and unhappy than buy a companion, bond by inducing Stockholme syndrome, and spend the next decade playing prison warden.</p>
      <p>I'm aware this language is hyperbolic, but I also think it's accurate. Again, happy to be proved wrong. Like I said this post is exploratory. Just following a trail of thought.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>