<post>
  <author>mister_ghost</author>
  <date>2020-03-13T04:34:05Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ffprqc/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_09_2020/fkdcav1/</link>
  <title>The Central Question of Mask Economics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>That sort of addresses the supply side issues, but doesn't really fix the demand-side ones. A day-of speculator adds the same value as a high price at a store. They nudge towards a reasonable distribution of goods, because people to whom the goods are more valuable are more willing to pay a premium price.</p>
      <p>Take our current situation: masks are scarce. We do not have enough masks that everyone can have as many masks as they want. I do not have any masks, because I think the price is too high when they're mitigating a fairly low risk for me personally (I'm a healthy young man). I didn't forego a mask out of altruism - if masks were the normal price and accessibility, I would have bought some - but it was hard enough for me to get them that I decided it wasn't worth it. As a result, people with more need for masks than me have access to the masks I would have bought. Without any kind of central planning, anyone having to assess my true need for a mask, nothing. Just prices.</p>
      <p>The canonical example is that on a hot day when all the fridges are broken, no one should be buying ice to keep their beer cool. If you don't raise the price, they might as well. If suppliers don't raise prices to meet demand, they turn access to scarce goods into a lottery - if you're lucky enough to get to the ice store quickly enough, you get ice. It's not an efficient distribution.</p>
      <p>(the common proposal to fix the ice problem is a rationing system where you can only buy a certain amount of ice, but that has serious drawbacks. Different people have different requirements for ice. Some people have insulin they need to keep cold, others have a good supply of non-perishable food. Flipping a coin to see which one of them gets ice is a bad solution, as is giving them both the same amount of ice)</p>
      <p>All (most) economics problems start with "Not everyone can get everything that they want. How do we determine who gets what?" Your idea for bringing supply up is good, but it doesn't really answer the question. It makes shortages less likely, but it doesn't help us determine who gets what in an efficient way.</p>
      <p>Lord knows mask markets have issues - people don't always accurately price their need for masks (a healthy hypochondriac might outbid a 70 year old with COPD), and healthy wealthy people might need a box of masks less than the average person, but they need $400 <em>a lot</em> less than the average person. For some extremely poor people it's not a question of desire - they might be happy to drop $400 on masks but they don't have access to that kind of money. I know it sounds like I'm being flippant about people dying, and maybe my tone needs work, but deciding who gets left wanting a mask and not having one is <em>the central question of mask economics.</em> "everyone gets a mask" isn't really a viable solution, and sets off alarm bells - handwaving away scarcity and declaring that there will just be enough to go around is a warning smell of economic populism. </p>
      <p>Empirically, markets seem to do a pretty decent job of what they're supposed to: they distribute more masks to people who need them more and fewer to people who need them less. I don't know how well centrally planned systems work in this regard, but assessing everyone's need for masks and distributing accordingly is a valid approach as well. In cases where everyone's needs are similar or identical, flat rationing is a very good idea.  But just having enough masks isn't a real plan, or at least not an economic plan.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>