<post>
  <author>naraburns</author>
  <date>2020-03-13T19:26:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ffprqc/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_09_2020/fkf5pgh/</link>
  <title>Is Western Studies "White People Studies"?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>People will form identity over anything, and trying to force a common "White" identity strikes me as reductive and ahistorical.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>What do you think "Western Civilization" refers to?</p>
      <p>As an academic who occasionally teaches the history of (Western) philosophy, I am sometimes accused by enterprising students of promulgating "old white male supremacy" because I don't talk enough about the Chinese, or sub-Saharan Africans, or the like.  It is more broadly true that courses focusing on Western art, writing, etc. have fallen into disfavor among a certain stripe of academic.  If you check the job listings for liberal arts scholars you can often see a huge number of Africana and Chicano and Asian Studies notices rounding out the Women's and Queer Studies posts.  There is a real demand for professors to teach something that <em>isn't</em>, on a certain "Woke" view, white identity.</p>
      <p>I would <em>like</em> to argue that Western Studies is not <em>really</em> "White People Studies" as it is sometimes accused of being--but I can't deny that if you trace Western civilization from Mesopotamia to the Mediterranean to greater Europe, pretty much everyone worth mentioning will be old-definition "white" (i.e. Indo-European) from 3500 B.C, onward, and new-definition "white" (i.e. Europeans) from about 500 A.D. through the sixteenth century at least.  Moreover, beginning in the sixteenth century <em>western</em> Europe, specifically, spends centuries dominating the globe; at this point the main reason Western history stops being "White People Studies" is because Europeans conquered the world.</p>
      <p>What makes the discussion tricky, I think, is that this is pretty good ammunition for the people who specifically don't want Western Civilization to be a part of their curriculum: it <em>is</em> in some sense "White People Studies," and if they are not themselves white, there is a good chance their ancestors' culture was largely overwritten by Western influence at some point.  So on one side we have the putative Woke positions that Western Civilization shouldn't be taught, but also that there is no such thing as a true "white culture" or "white identity," and on the other we have the rising resentment of white identitarians who seem to agree that Western Civilization <em>should</em> be taught, but also oppose the growth of analogous courses focusing on Black or Asian or American civilizations.</p>
      <p>I think we're all better off acknowledging that most of human history is a story of overlapping-but-distinguishable racial groups developing in overlapping-but-distinguishable ancestral environments, only recently (beginning ~1492) brought back together through the development of various technologies, and even then mostly in the Americas--Europe and Asia and Africa remain comparatively ethnically homogeneous.  However this seems to have proven to be a hard thing to acknowledge both for people who are more concerned about laying claim to some kind of racial superiority, and by people who are more concerned with wielding ancient injustices as cudgels against their neighbors.</p>
      <p>Though I suppose when you say "currently the amount of cultural similarity between, say, a Californian and a Russian is almost nil" this should be perhaps taken as a sign that you're using the word "culture" to indicate something much shallower than the deep civilizational norms and values to which I have applied the term here.  (Though, Russia is a special case anyway, as their inclusion in "Western Civilization" is a bit historically fraught.)</p>
      <p>Well, drawing lines around big groups of people is always challenging, and indeed is something I like to avoid whenever I reasonably can.  So I am actually a bit agnostic on the answer to the question of whether there is such a thing as a "white identity," but only to the exact extent that I am agnostic on the answer to the question of whether there is such as thing as a "black identity," or an "Asian identity," or even a "Chinese identity"--likewise various non-racial or national identities, for that matter.  So maybe, after all that, what I ought to ask you is--you think "White" identity is "reductive and ahistorical."  Are there other non-individual identities that you do <em>not</em> find "reductive and ahistorical?"  What are your criteria for bounding those?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>