<post>
  <author>Ninety_Three</author>
  <date>2020-03-17T02:55:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fjfnxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_16_2020/fkpmjyi/</link>
  <title>Pushback and Details on a "Bill to End Encryption"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <em>Technically</em> it's not a bill to end encryption. It's a bill to form a committee to propose best practices that must be approved, which if not followed would suspend a company's Section 230 lawsuit-protection in certain child porn or exploitation cases. That's wordy and technical, so I understand why it always gets summarized the way you did, but if we're being alarmist it's important to understand exactly what the alarm is over.</p>
      <p>The distinction between "banning encryption" and "opening up legal liabilities that make encryption not worth doing" is important for several reasons. It lessens a lot of the constitutional issues that  might be raised from an explicit ban, but it also doesn't actually ban encryption. They could pass the most draconian set of best practices imaginable and there's still the possibility that when Google or whoever get sued for having an encrypted chat client, the courts say "No that's stupid, Google aren't any more responsible for this harm than Smith &amp; Wesson are to blame for someone getting shot." The whole thing could be a non-issue.</p>
      <p>Of course this is technology regulation powered by a moral panic, so it's far from guaranteed that courts will do the sensible thing, but it could happen. On the other hand, "You'll get sued and there's a significant chance you lose because the court is dumb" creates most of the same incentives as "This is illegal", so anything short of certainty is going to make people worried. On the <em>other</em> other hand, this framing takes "You'll get sued" as a guarantee and it's not. You'd need a case where someone was provably harmed by some company providing an encrypted chat client or whatever, and that's not trivial to come by. Maybe some terrible set of standards get passed, everyone ignores them, and nothing changes because it's hard to enforce them.</p>
      <p>The next reason to not be concerned is that once the law passes, they still have to vote to approve the committee's proposals before the law does anything. The place everyone should be raising a fuss is at that vote: right now people are complaining over a set of standards that don't exist and might well be perfectly reasonable (though if you listen to Attorney General Barr talk about encryption, there are obviously people who don't want this to be reasonable). Realistically, there are obvious tactical reasons to oppose the bill now: it takes time to drum up opposition, politicians are slow to respond to anything, and there might be a "foot in the door" effect from allowing the bill to pass.</p>
      <p>But all of that is haggling over whether this is <em>really</em> banning encryption. The best argument I've heard in favour of restricting encryption <a href="https://www.lawfareblog.com/earn-it-act-raises-good-questions-about-end-end-encryption">was from Lawfare</a>. It points out that Section 230 existing at all is kind of unprincipled: most other industries don't get this protection from lawsuits, why should the internet? This is just judging Google by the same standards we apply to Ford or Walmart, what's wrong with those standards?</p>
      <p>From here you have several options. Maybe you think the whole system of lawsuits is terrible and you have a principled opposition to applying it to any company. Maybe the courts are unusually incompetent when it comes to technology, and we should trust their ability to control Google less than their ability to control Ford. Maybe the nature of communications technology means that restricting it causes much more collateral damage than restricting Ford's ability to make cars that might explode, so we should have Section 230 on the grounds that it enables technology that enriches us all.</p>
      <p>I think all of that nuance is necessary to understand this legislation, and your average piece of coverage contains maybe 20% of it. I'm not going to end this by telling you what to think, because the conclusion you reach depends heavily on exactly what standards you expect the government to set, but you should think <em>more</em>. Especially try listening to people outside the "Save encryption!" bubble, because arguments are soldiers and you should not trust those guys to give you an accurate picture of the situation.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>