<post>
  <author>personimprov</author>
  <date>2020-03-14T19:55:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ffprqc/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_09_2020/fkiawfy/</link>
  <title>Ceteris Paribus, Video Games Are a Waste of Time</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I am surprised that so many people are replying with some variation of:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Leisure is leisure -- no type of leisure is better than another. It's not a waste of time if it's fun.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In my opinion, this is a wrong way of looking at leisure, psychology, and time in general. It betrays an errant way of thinking about life that is harmful to personal development, human progress, and our culture. It's actually a big deal. I'm going to try criticize it based on some reasonable principles.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>Humans have the power to shape what they find enjoyable. This is usually accomplished by investing a small number of hours into a new activity, and then finding at the end of the investment that the activity is actually rewarding. Someone who never went rock-climbing pushes themselves to try it a couple weekends, and suddenly they get pleasure from it naturally and look forward to doing it every weekend. This applies arguably most hobbies, e.g. dancing, painting, music, reading. A decade ago I forced myself to start reading for fun. Now I can honestly read hours a day for fun, and am taken aback when I hear about people finding it difficult to start a reading habit (until I remember that at one point I had to force myself). Most people have experienced this with exercise or with going to a party.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The contemporaneous pleasure of an activity is no good indicator of whether the activity is worth doing, as humans easily fall into quick pleasures which are regrettable or harmful, like drugs or gambling. With gambling, opiates, and amphetamines, the pleasure is immediate but fleeting, and you are left with disappointment of having done the activity. For gambling, the activity is not worth doing because you lose money and time. For drugs, the activity is not worth doing because you lose money, time, and health. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Humans existed a very long time without video games, and during this time humans had just as much fun as today. None of them believed that they were missing something just because they didn't have video games. In fact, for most of history, even card and board games were considered vanity, not to be done in excess if at all. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>If (1) is true and (2) is true, then reason dictates that we should choose our leisure based upon its ancillary benefits. Because if (1) is true, then we should try first activities that benefit us beyond the contemporaneous pleasure; and if (2) is true, then we should be skeptical of relying of contemporaneous pleasure in dictating worthiness.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Implying (4), we should look for activities that provide the most <em>longlasting</em> pleasure. When you compare video games with most hobbies, video games are clearly inferior. If you instead take up a sport, then the ancillary benefits are physical health, mental health, social bonding, and possibly sun and nature exposure. If you take up art, then the ancillary benefit is a lifelong "game" that never gets boring with a skillset that can constantly be improved upon, and which is also scientifically more relaxing than video games, while allowing an outlet for limitless creativity. If you take up music, the same applies.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>From (5), we must conclude that it is objectively foolish to play video games, unless there is some extenuating circumstance that modifies the implicated ancillary benefits. For instance: your brother lives 500 miles away and you want to bond with him. You're probably only left with video games as an option, and so video games are the correct choice. But ceteris paribus, video games are a waste of time -- even worse, they're a waste of potential.</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>