<post>
  <author>TheSingularThey</author>
  <date>2020-03-08T05:29:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjwte1g/</link>
  <title>Musings on Normiefication</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Well, what makes a normie a normie? Seems to me like it's actually a <em>lack</em> of activation of a lot of self-preservation systems. You don't walk around all day worrying that the guy next to you might kill you. At least not seriously so. But then you ship off to a warzone for a few years where that <em>is</em> a realistic possibility, and your nervous system adapts. Then after you come back home you find yourself almost murdering someone for a slight that in civilian life would be trivial but which in the context of you serving as part of a military occupation force could herald catastrophe.</p>
      <p>I guess the question is how to toggle that off again. Seems like it doesn't work so well for a lot of people. Then there are the other issues, like how intense situations create powerful bonds. Anecdotally, a friend of my brother's was shipped off to afghanistan and got shot, and all he could talk about when he was here for rehab was how he couldn't wait to get back to his unit. How the best moment in his life was the first time he experienced combat. And so on. Do people even <em>want</em> to leave that? Then there's the issue of how they may not have the skills to integrate back into civilian life, and there are the cultural issues, and all sorts of other problems.</p>
      <p>And when you're in a dangerous situation (like a gang, or a war zone), you <em>have</em> to adapt to it. Your life literally depends on it, if not today, then maybe tomorrow. Your psyche is very well-tuned to properly prioritizing such concerns, so you recognize that this is the most important thing for you to spend your time figuring out. You're very motivated to doing that right.</p>
      <p>Getting back to civilian life seems much harder, in that sense, perhaps paradoxically. Your brain isn't screaming for you to calm down right now or else you're gonna die, so you're not able to motivate yourself as well. Especially while there's another part of your brain screaming at you that actually no you shouldn't calm down and that it's really good to be on edge all the time because look at all these times that it plausibly saved your life.</p>
      <p>Anyway. There definitely are a lot of major hurdles to overcome to re-normiefy yourself. And probably, some people just can't do it, just like some people just can't hack it in a gang or in a war zone. We're all tuned slightly differently and sometimes those relatively small differences can make or break you.</p>
      <p>If I had to guess though, I'd guess that it's probably easier to normiefy someone if you do so in a new environment. E.g., take the city gang member and move him to into the middle of the boonies. All the systems that were so perfectly tuned for a city environment should be more relaxed in that setting, making normiefication easier.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>