<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-05-05T10:49:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/n3pe45/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_03_2021/gx0fsp7/</link>
  <title>We Wanted a Real Plague</title>
  <category>
    <li>moloch</li>
    <li>flux</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The truth is that we wanted a real plague. I mean, societally. Plague is cleansing fire, it’s redemptive, it brings us together, it burns the old to make way for the new - which is especially appealing to radicals of all kinds. </p>
      <p>And we got...a really, really shit plague. A plague that we could have done nothing about and ended up like...I guess India now? (Except with many many more hospital beds per capita, albeit with an older population.) And sure, India isn’t doing “well” right now but like, at most the hospitals and morgues will be full up for a couple of months and 1% of the population will die, and then we’ll move on. </p>
      <p>Real plagues killed people of all ages. During the Black Death, it wasn’t uncommon for whole towns to be wiped out to the last man (as even survivors starved), and big cities like Milan, Paris and London lost 50-80% of their populations. Four fifths of everyone you’ve ever known - many of them young and fit - dead. Versus a tiny number of sick and old people dying. . I remember Andrew Sullivan, early last year, talking about AIDS, but the thing is that if you were a young, urban gay man in the 80s, you probably knew many young healthy men who died of it. Among that small community, the death rate was pretty high. </p>
      <p>This disconnect - between a plague that radicals <em>always</em> thinks society ‘deserves’ (the deserved plague is possibly the oldest radical trope) and the reality of modern medicine and the fact that this basically a slightly stronger version of the common cold that kills barely anyone, causes extreme levels of bizarre behavior, including fondness for lockdowns and strange hystericizing of risk. Hypochondria and neuroticism being more common on the left exacerbate this, of course. </p>
      <p>But really it’s about plague, and it’s about rebirth. And if it turns out the plague is actually not a plague at all, well, maybe you need to pretend that it is.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>