<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2020-03-03T23:18:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjesmbd/</link>
  <title>The Secret of Biden's Success</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Happy <a href="https://nypost.com/2020/03/03/biden-asks-for-support-on-super-thursday-in-yet-another-blunder/">Super Thursday</a>, everyone!  I'd like to say a few words about Joe Biden, but before I do, I'd like to give my California friends a brief reminder that even if you're not a registered democrat, you still might want to turn up and vote today, since there are <a href="https://ballotpedia.org/March_3,_2020_ballot_measures_in_California">a bunch of local ballot measures</a>, and there's a possibility that the primary will result in only democrat voters turning out to decide those ballot measures.  (It's the kind of thing that makes one wonder if some folks are trying to engineer certain election results by putting these measures on the ballot today instead of saving them for the November ballot, when more republicans would be turning out.)  Now, back to our usually scheduled programming:</p>
      <p>After seeing some of our favorite characters of the season written off the show, Joe Biden decided to get everyone back together for a reunion episode.  On the eve of Super Tuesday, Amy, Pete, and even our old pal Beto O'Rourke showed up to announce their support of Joe Biden.  With a decisive win in the South Carolina primary, Biden's price on prediction markets has surged in the past two weeks from a measly 10¢ to an impressive 56¢, putting him at the head of the pack ahead of second-place Bernie Sanders' 39¢.  It's a real tide shift, and it's had me wondering -- is everyone putting their money on the right horse? </p>
      <p>While I think that all of these things are important, I think they are lagging indicators of genuine support: other candidates dropping out to endorse Biden, and being popular in prediction markets are <em>symptoms</em> of a candidate being successful more than they are causes.  So, what is the secret of Joe's success?</p>
      <p>I think that Joe's most significant endorsement of the past few weeks came not from Amy or Pete or Beto, but from Jim Clyburn.  He might not have the brand recognition of Beto, despite being far more significant in terms of his impact on American politics: Jim Clyburn is the House Majority Whip who represents South Carolina's 6th congressional district.  If you were trying to win South Carolina, Clyburn is <em>the</em> single most important endorsement you could hope for -- and, given how quickly momentum has swung in Joe's favor after the South Carolina primary, perhaps the most important endorsement of the entire primary season.</p>
      <p>Jim Clyburn is a leader who, with an endorsement, can deliver thousands of votes to a particular candidate.  He's an actual power broker -- wielding "power" in perhaps the  realest sense of the word.  He's an "influencer" in the classical sense: his endorsement can actually persuade people to vote in a certain direction.  Sanders has <a href="https://www.vox.com/the-goods/2020/1/24/21080573/hot-girls-for-bernie-sanders-emily-ratajkowski">"Hot girls for Bernie"</a>, but Joe Biden is friends with community leaders.  We often toss around the word "establishment democrat," but here we see a very real manifestation of what that means.</p>
      <p>Joe Biden has been a politician ever since 1972.  He has spent nearly half a century in congress, and in that time he's shaken a lot of hands and made a lot of friends, something that Bernie Sanders doesn't have.  When Hillary Clinton said of Sanders that "<a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/479097-clinton-weighs-in-on-sanders-nobody-likes-him-nobody-wants-to-work-with-him">nobody likes him</a>," Hillary wasn't talking about voters; she was talking about other politicians.  Her actual words were: "He [Bernie] was in Congress for years. He had one senator support him. Nobody likes him, nobody wants to work with him, he got nothing done."  Joe Biden, on the other hand, was such a well-liked face in congress that in 2008, Barack Obama chose him as VP (probably to shore up his own weakness as a freshman senator: Barack Obama knew that he had the support of voters, but not of DC power brokers.  Adding Biden to his administration ameliorated that problem.)</p>
      <p>Of course, Bernie Sanders may not need the endorsements of powerful people -- he seems to be getting plenty of votes without their help.  But I think the word "endorsement" has been kind of devalued by headlines like <a href="https://www.refinery29.com/en-us/2019/11/8864761/ariana-grande-bernie-sanders-endorsement-concert">"Ariana Grande Endorses Bernie Sanders In Cute Instagram"</a>, and South Carolina might serve as a reminder that there are community leaders who can, with an endorsement, get their congregation to move in a certain direction -- and those community leaders are more likely to have ties to establishment democrats with a long history of getting things done in congress than a socialist named Bernard Sanders. It's good to have popular support among people who will turn out to vote for you, but sometimes being friends with the right people can deliver those votes just the same.</p>
      <p>A second point: It seems kind of wild that, in the span of 2 weeks, Biden has surged from 10¢ to 56¢ in prediction markets.  Maybe this is a case of people rationally responding to new information and changing circumstances, but in the past I've <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/ey1zdz/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_03/fgk8tep/">posted</a> about how prediction markets are better at taking the temperature of Extremely Online types than they are at predicting actual results, and this seems like it may be an example of that: for the Twitter crowd, Biden's success seems to have completely caught them off guard.</p>
      <p>Of course, it's not just the Twitter crowd; it seems to be nearly the entire online journalistic class that.  How did Biden manage to <a href="https://gfycat.com/dimpledamazingfireant-joe-biden-politics-creep-funny">sneak up from behind and catch them off guard</a>?  Michael Tracey, <a href="https://spectator.us/media-clueless-coverage-biden-candidacy/">writing for the Spectator</a>, put it like this:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Take a look at some of the exit poll findings [the night of the South Carolina primary]: Biden won 62 percent of South Carolina voters who never attended college. Yes, many of these people are older black voters. But more significant than race is educational attainment, in this key respect: you will encounter almost nobody working an elite media job who has never interfaced with the higher education system. However, people who have never interfaced with the higher education system comprise a significant portion of Biden’s support base. Hence the flustered and confused reactions to his rousing victory.</p>
        <p>Online political journalism is dominated by graduates of elite American colleges and universities between the ages of 25 and 45, who constitute the diametric opposite demographic of Biden’s core support base. I would hazard a guess that the vast majority of people running political magazines, newspapers and websites in the United States have roughly zero Biden supporters in their immediate peer group. So of course this dynamic will lead to analytical failure in assessing Biden’s appeal.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In seeing Biden's popularity among non-college educated voters, I'm reminded of Trump, whose support among voters (to the point of winning a general election) also caught the journalistic class off guard.  As Trump famously said in 2016, "<a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/voices/donald-trumps-i-love-the-poorly-educated-isnt-actually-a-bad-mantra-and-attacking-him-for-it-is-a6895026.html">We love the poorly educated</a>" -- and they, in turn, loved him, if the voting results are to believed.</p>
      <p>In trying to more accurately prognosticate election results, it may be worth considering: which voters are you ignoring?  Who is outside your bubble?  (I am guessing that a lot of the people here who, much like the online journalist class, don't spend much time interacting with old people and people who aren't college educated.)  What important signals are you underweighting?  (If you were following South Carolina and this post is the first time you're reading about Jim Clyburn's endorsement of Joe Biden, perhaps you are paying attention to the wrong signals.)</p>
      <p>I'm not being the least bit ironic when I say that I follow politics like I follow sports.  Political news leaves me about as informed as sports talk radio, which is to say, consuming it usually leaves me dumber than when I turned it on.  I'm okay with that, because while Twitter doesn't reflect reality, it is very entertaining. But if you're trying to actually understand the world and make predictions about elections, it's important not to mistake trending hashtags for actual signal.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>