<post>
  <author>Dangerous_Psychology</author>
  <date>2020-03-04T04:13:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjfmz6s/</link>
  <title>On Conservative Black Democrats</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>85% of African Americans vote democrat.  What a lot of people fail to realize is that this does not mean that 85% of African Americans are <em>leftists</em>.  Heck, it doesn't even mean that 85% of African Americans are left-of-center on most issues.  In fact, what it means is that you have a large constituency of African Americans who would identify as fairly centrist or even conservative who nonetheless vote democrat.  (There are historical reasons for this that have more to do with party politics; the democrats have certainly made it a priority to appeal to African American voters in a way that republicans haven't.)  That means that of the 85% African Americans who get labeled as "democrat voters," you have a lot of people who "break rank" and don't actually support the D's party line when it comes to individual issues like immigration or abortion.  (85% of African Americans vote democrat, but only 63% identify as "pro choice," meaning that there must be quite a few pro-life black people who vote democrat.)  And it's hard to get a large part of those "democrat" African Americans -- a significant portion of whom aren't left-of-center to begin with -- to embrace an openly socialist candidate.</p>
      <p>Right-leaning white people register as republicans, and thus aren't part of the democratic primary process.  But you have quite a few right-of-center black people who are registered as democrats, who then get to enter the democratic primary vote with their right-leaning sensibilities.</p>
      <p>While this is obviously a problem for the dirtbag leftist wing of the democrat party, I'd say this is an even bigger ideological problem for the wokes, who are left with two choices that seem at odds with each other: either they listen to the African American voters (following the logic that white people need to shut up and elevate POC voices), in which case the black voters choose a candidate like Biden, or they go with a woke-approved who <em>they</em> (the wokists) believe will do a better job of supporting African American interests, which is pretty condescending since it is in effect saying that black voters cannot be trusted to choose the candidate that best represents their interests.  (Usually they'll try to cloak this in language that suggests that minorities have somehow been tricked into supporting the wrong candidate, which is also condescending in its own way, but sometimes they actually give up the game by literally saying <a href="https://www.resetera.com/threads/i-look-down-on-minorities-who-support-trump.167256/">"I look down on minorities" who support the wrong candidate</a>.)</p>
      <p>That the democrats have succeed in winning a large number of centrist and right-leaning black voters over to their side such that black people are now considered a "democrat voting bloc" certainly helps them in general elections.  But it also means that the democrats' ranks are now filled with a large number of centrists and right-leaning folks, which is something that leftists (both the woke variety and the Chapo types) are probably going to find counter-productive to many of their goals, including getting a "democratic socialist" on the ticket.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>