<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-03-03T03:07:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjbzgs4/</link>
  <title>Abusing Appeals to Context</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Just a quick mini-rant about a frequently sneaky tactic I see often used in CW debates, namely appeals to context. So imagine Person A and Person B are debating something Celebrity C said. Person A says C's remarks are terrible [or equally: not so bad]. Person B then replies that we should look at the context of their utterance, and this reveals that they are in fact defensible [or equally: terrible].</p>
      <p>I have a great friend - one of my absolute BFFs - who's a master at this. She and I are having some hot debate and she then says 'ah, but remember the context', and proceeds to recast our discussion in a different light by framing it around, oh, I don't know, trends in 80s homosexual life in New York, or Turkish nationalist frustrations following World War 1, or whatever. I'm usually impressed by this because (i) appeals like "let's think about the broader context" have this allure of maturity and wisdom and deepness to them, and (ii) I'm aware that I tend to take a narrow legalistic attitude to issues (I'm an arch 'decoupler' in the <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/7cAsBPGh98pGyrhz9/decoupling-vs-contextualising-norms">decoupling/contextualising</a> dichotomy), and while this is sometimes helpful, it can also stop me from understanding where others are coming from.</p>
      <p>Anyway, while I love this friend to bits, she is also a rhetorical beast, and it slowly dawned on me a couple of years ago that appeals to context are one of her best tricks. In short, once she says, "let's look at the bigger picture", she's initially doing something non-adversarial in providing useful background information, which puts you at your ease. But this lets her reset the context and framing of the issue in a way that favours her case. And of course, there are myriad different ways of contextualising and framing an issue to suit your case.</p>
      <p>To illustrate, imagine tomorrow a recording surfaces of an imaginary celebrity "Bill" saying some nasty racial slur. What are some varieties of context that we could use to frame the issue in our favour? Some core examples -</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(1) Speaker context</strong>: what kind of person are we dealing with? Do they have a reputation for being silly or playful or extrovert or kind or vicious or racist?</p>
      <p>
        <em>"Everyone knows Bill has a reputation for having very right wing views about race. This scandal should be seen in light of his character, and it's utterly damning."</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>(2) Utterance context:</strong> what was the precise discursive context in which this remark was uttered? Was it an argument? Was it a joke? Was it 'locker room talk'?</p>
      <p>
        <em>"But come on, Bill used the slur in a jokey friendly way in a conversation with an old friend that was specifically about the amazing cultural achievements of that racial community. That's what matters here - it's clearly innocent."</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>(3) Societal context:</strong> regardless of who was talking and how things went down at the time, how is this incident likely to be interpreted? What associations does it trigger for the broader public? What kind of normative structures have we built up around this?</p>
      <p>
        <em>"Even if we grant the dubious claim that the conversation itself was innocent, think about what that word means to millions of people who hear it and have to relive trauma associated with hearing it as abuse directed at them, perhaps even accompanied by violence; nothing happens in a vacuum, nor should it be judged in one."</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>(4) Historical context.</strong> When was this said, and how were things different then? What things were salient at the time that we may have forgotten about?</p>
      <p>
        <em>"You're forgetting something critical here. This recording comes from 2003. That may not sound like a long time ago but it really was. That word didn't have the same connotations back then that it does now."</em>
      </p>
      <p>These are general purpose rhetorical contextual tools that can be applied to almost any scandal of this kind, and many others. I leave as an exercise to the reader to fill in how these contexts could all be used positively or negative in relation to, for example, Trump on Charlottesville, Biden's "handsiness", Sarah Jeong's comments about white people, Dawkins on eugenics, Larry Summers on women in STEM, etc..</p>
      <p>Of course, contexts really do matter, and if we were being really rational and systematic about this, we'd help ourselves to all the information about context we could get our hands on. But that's not how arguments work - usually, one or two framings of the situation loom large in the discussion and whoever's frame dominates gets to set the agenda that their interlocutor has to respond to ("well, look, I'm not sure Trump is all that much a racist..." or "look, I'm not sure it was ever okay to touch women the way Biden does...").</p>
      <p>I don't know exactly what to recommend or how to respond to this. It's not like there's a "context fallacy" that you can just point to. But I think it's worth noting the dialectic force of appeals to context and how they can be used sneakily and rhetorically. I guess if we were really trying to be rational we'd agree to lay out a bunch of different contexts in advance and try to decide which are relevant before moving to object level issues, but that's not exactly practical. So I'd welcome ideas about how to respond to these moves and how to think about them in (heh) the broader context of arguments and discussions in the culture war.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>