<post>
  <author>GPoaS</author>
  <date>2020-03-02T14:59:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fj9wecy/</link>
  <title>An Early Warning of Coronavirus</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I have no intention of coming back here, as you all have made it abundantly clear that I am not wanted. But this is more important than stupid internet drama, and so I am making this post:</p>
      <p>I have been following Coronavirus news for the past month and am convinced this is the real deal. I would put about even odds on <em>several million Americans dying of this disease in 2020</em>. We are at a point right now were the exponential growth is going to start getting noticeable, and I expect to hear about 1,000 - 10,000 confirmed cases by the end of next week, unless the government continues to double down on "don't test don't tell" (although I think that will fail if they try). </p>
      <p>This is a disease where, <a href="https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/who-china-joint-mission-on-covid-19-final-report.pdf">per the WHO report</a>, one in every 5 infected needs hospital care or else they will very likely die. This is a disease that <a href="https://www.commondreams.org/news/2020/02/25/cdc-says-americans-should-brace-significant-disruptions-amid-warnings-coronavirus">will infect the better part of half the planet</a>. Those two numbers alone imply a very, very, very bad conclusion. </p>
      <p>The reported death rate for elderly people is 10-20%. Everyone, phone your grandparents. Tell them that you love them. Urge them to be safe. Make your peace with the fact that you will likely lose them this year. </p>
      <p>Do not make the mistake of thinking you are invincible if you are young and healthy. The reported fatality rate for &lt;40 y/o is only 0.2%, but they have not reported the hospitalization rate, and see above re "need hospitalization but will not get it"</p>
      <p>In the same linked WHO report above, they state openly: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Much of the global community is not yet ready, in mindset and materially, to implement the measures that have been employed to contain COVID-19 in China. These are the only measures that are currently proven to interrupt or minimize transmission chains in humans. Fundamental to these measures is extremely proactive surveillance to immediately detect cases, very rapid diagnosis and immediate case isolation, rigorous tracking and quarantine of close contacts, and an exceptionally high degree of population understanding and acceptance of these measures.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>China effectively declared martial law, confined hundreds of millions of people into their homes for a month, and arrested and forcibly brought to quarantine centers anyone who did not comply. The WHO is stating openly that "These are the <em><strong>only</strong></em> measures that are currently proven to ... minimize transmission". <em><strong>Expect some level of public quarantine or lockdown to begin in this country, I would estimate, within one month</strong></em>. Prepare yourself accordingly. Have the supplies on hand to not have to leave your house. Prepare yourself <em>psychologically</em> for that eventuality. </p>
      <p>If you haven't already, it might be too late, but now is the time to prepare. The scenario to prepare for is "can't/shouldn't go outside of my house for 1+ months". It is safe to assume that, barring temporary interruptions, utilities will stay on. It is safe to assume that emergency services will be helping, but it is not safe to assume they will be available, as they are likely to be stretched much too thin. You can make judgement calls on your specific situation but as a rule of thumb:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Have one month's food on hand. Shelf-stable is ideal, but it is probably safe to assume your fridge will keep running. One day's food is anywhere from about 1200 to 3500 calories, depending on your gender, your level of fitness, your level of sedentariness, and how much extra body fat you're carrying. Do not neglect nutrient balance, although the easiest way to hedge this is multivitamins</li>
        <li>Have one month's water on hand. Rule of thumb is 1 gal per person per day but that assumes no tap water available for cleaning/cooking. Tap water should be available and safe. You don't need to buy bottled water for this. Buy six-gallon jugs from REI or equivalent and fill them up at home. </li>
        <li>Keep your car tanked up. Best plan is probably shelter-in-place but having mobility is a good option</li>
        <li>Have a supply of basic medications and first aid. You should already have this. Specific recommendations: NSAID, anti-histamine, Guaifenesin (thins mucus), antibiotics ointment, anti-diarrheal.</li>
        <li>Stockpile as much of your prescription meds as you can, or plan to have to quit them (since doc won't give me a 90 day supply of adderall, eg).</li>
        <li>Have a supply of cleaning and hygiene stuff. Soap. TP/Paper Towel. Bleach. Etc</li>
        <li>Have emergency radios. The internet should stay on but if it doesn't, its good to have alternatives</li>
        <li>Have implements for self defense and prepare yourself to use them. Guns are ideal, but if you aren't capable with them then they're more danger than they're worth. Hopefully it doesn't come to this, but your ill-prepared neighbours might do something desperate two weeks into a lockdown, and police will likely be too busy to stop it</li>
        <li>Link up with local friends. Have explicitly pre-communicated disaster plans. Plan to link up at a safe, defensible location (I recommend whoever has the biggest house, link up there). More trusted friends = more safety, and more people = less psychological distress in a disaster</li>
        <li>Have a good supply of things to do. We're all likely going to be stuck inside for a long time. Buy some books. Get a musical instrument. Drawing supplies. Whatever you like</li>
      </ul>
      <p>For much of the above, this is worst-case planning. Supplies will likely still be available, intermittently, but you're preparing to make sure you can cover any gaps or interruptions. You're setting yourself up to not have to go out to the grocery store twice a week when the epidemic hits your neighbourhood in force. Additionally, emergency response supplies will be limited, and if you can remove your dependency on emergency services you free up bandwidth for others who cannot. </p>
      <p>Another thing regarding prepping: Do not tell others IRL that you are doing this. Many people still seem unwilling or unable to accept that this will be bad. They are not preparing. They think this is a joke. You can try pushing them at the margins but they're not really going to understand until it's too late. And when it's too late, they will realize they don't have supplies, and they need supplies, and they might start making poor decisions in desperation. If they know you're sitting on a stockpile, that's a target on your head. Best case, you have to tell them to fuck off, because you only have enough supplies for you and your family, and you have to live with that sinking feeling in your chest. Worst case, you have to make them fuck off, with up to and including lethal force. Much easier to not give them a reason to fuck on in the first place. </p>
      <p>Be aware that even if this disease turns out to be a dud in the US, if it is quickly contained (unlikely) and less lethal than expected (unlikely), there has already been massive damage done to our economy by what has happened so far. <del>In the past week, 18 months worth of growth has been wiped out. I personally have lost about $40,000 across my investments and retirement, to put a number on it.</del> (EDIT: I was eyeballing it from the DJIA but I didn't actually run the numbers. Further, it's bounced back up a bunch today, so this specific claim is no longer true) China more-or-less just turned off for a month. All the industrial and commercial inputs they manufacture stopped about six weeks ago and haven't started again yet. US manufacturers are running out of inventory on hand and can't make more without inputs from China. There's talk of medicine shortages in the near future, as ~80% of our pharmaceutical inputs and finished products come from China. A recession is inevitable, and many of us will likely lose our jobs, at least temporarily. </p>
      <p>Now is the time to get serious about putting your personal survival plans into action. The authorities call this 'social distancing'. Cancel all travel plans through airports. Avoid public gatherings. Work from home if you can. Minimize your exposure and risk as much as possible. It might not be strictly necessary yet, but the disease has a 1-2 week time delay between infection and symptoms, so it is unclear how many people are walking around sick right now. Based on intuition and eyeballing I would say no more than <del>10,000</del> (EDIT: 5000. I am being too pessimistic) pre-symptomatic people in the country, right now, mostly centered around existing outbreaks in major cities. On the other hand, things can change very very quickly, and if you start putting these plans into action <em><strong>now</strong></em>, you can prepare yourself psychologically and you can be ready to react quickly. </p>
      <p>The coming months are chaotic, frightening, and unknown. Be smart, be prepared, be ready. Be kind and help each other, but be prepared to make very hard decisions. Be aware, and ready to respond to very rapid changes in your community. </p>
      <p>Finally, as a personal note: if anyone knows where I live, and also lives here, please drop me a DM. It will be important in the coming months to build trustworthy offline connections.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>