<post>
  <author>Iron-And-Rust</author>
  <date>2020-02-29T20:54:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f8me2d/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_24/fj4jeso/</link>
  <title>The Functions Of Humor</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm not gonna claim to be an expert on humor, and probably there are different distinct types of humor, with a more viral-type being harder to synthesize.</p>
      <p>But a lot of humor is quite predictable. You take a dangerous thing. Then you push it as close to the edge as you can without it actually becoming dangerous. Like a joke that <em>almost</em> sounds racist, but isn't. The actual social dynamics at work there are opaque to me, but for whatever reason this is a reliable way of generating humor.</p>
      <p>A lot of humor seems built upon an exploration of danger, actually. If I had to speculate right now on the spot, I'd say it has something to do with 'play'. Animals 'play', to practice for similar non-'play' activity, and they laugh or send laugh-similar signals with their bodies etc., while engaged in it. During 'play', you get something similar enough to the danger to prepare you for the real thing, but not so similar it seriously hurts or kills you. But you want to find the balance. Like a kid jumping off a small ledge. Then he climbs up and jumps of a slightly taller one. Then a slightly taller one. Until he reaches a height that he deems too scary. Or he falls and hurts himself. And through this exploration, he discovers his limits and abilities.</p>
      <p>Humor seems some extension of this. You're probing for where the borders are drawn, where the lines are. So you know where people stand on things. So you know what you can and cannot say, without embarrassing yourself. That way, you don't end up walking through life terrified of possibly saying something that ruins your life because you don't know what those things might be. Like a child who's jumped off a few ledges and figured out when he should be worried about one and when he shouldn't be.</p>
      <p>Humor clearly also has some communication-aspects. Or maybe that's not humor, but <em>laughter</em>. Conspicuously, most laughter isn't related to 'humor' <em>per se</em>, but to awkwardness. Like, you turn a corner in the grocer, and nearly step into someone. You both laugh for a fraction of a second and carry on with your shopping. Laughter seems to signal "<em>it's okay, don't worry about it</em>". That's why you laugh when you fall over without hurting yourself. You're saying "<em>it's okay, don't worry about it</em>". That thing that looked dangerous wasn't. Even if it was extremely embarrassing, you'd probably put on a laugh just to pretend it didn't bother you, in hopes of avoiding or mitigating the embarrassment. You'd also react differently to someone laughing 'with' you (e.g., when you fell over, they looked at you to see your reaction and started laughing after you did), and someone laughing 'at' you (e.g., when you fell over, they started laughing right away, and if you didn't laugh but signaled pain instead they laughed even harder).</p>
      <p>Anyway. Humor's not a topic I'm too well-versed in. But I think clearly, it has a lot of predictable aspects to it that allow you to reliably generate some parts of it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>