<post>
  <author>j9461701</author>
  <date>2020-03-01T00:43:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/f8me2d/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_24/fj53n7b/</link>
  <title>Modern Arts Detachment From Reality</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Video from Vox defending all white paintings:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9aGRHOpMRUg">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9aGRHOpMRUg</a>
      </p>
      <p>I don't think the interviewee does a good job explaining herself. It's your monthly attempt to be classy, so you go down to your local art gallery. You come across dozens and dozens of different paintings of insane and dizzying complexity and depth, that can take tens of minutes to really take in. The truly complex pieces can literally be dissected for hours. You do this again and again, extracting each painting's 'story' as you go,  and then suddenly you're confronted with...nothing. Or a triangle. Or some splotches. Your mind starts firing widely, grasping for some kind of connection or meaning after you've trained it so hard to do that on the other pieces but it eludes you because these canvases that give so little direction on how or what to think. <em>That</em> sensation you're feeling is the point of these works. They work in the context of a lot of other art, but in isolation look ridiculous. The context of an art gallery utterly changes the emotions the art conjures. The artist is painting with the white space, so to speak.</p>
      <p>To use a related but similar example, look at these paintings:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/3/3a/Mccollum_100ps.jpeg">https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/3/3a/Mccollum_100ps.jpeg</a>
      </p>
      <p>Any one in isolation has no business being in a serious art gallery. It's just a flippin' black square. But put them all together, use the overall impression of all the paintings together as your artistic palette, and suddenly it goes from boring to highly evocative. It looks gross and weird and vaguely like something off <a href="/r/trypophobia">/r/trypophobia</a> (don't click if squeamish), going from boring in isolation to uncomfortably emotional in totality. </p>
      <p>But I don't agree with the whole video. I think my criticism of modern art isn't that they make or display these paintings, but that they are unwilling to acknowledge they require meta-knowledge or a specific context to not be stupid. And attempting to deceive the public with gibberish and fast talk rather than bluntly say they're an art gallery in joke, and not a big deal. </p>
      <p>I'd like to connect it to another video I saw, from super eye patch wolf, about fake martial arts:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gjbSCEhmjJA">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gjbSCEhmjJA</a>
      </p>
      <p>Martial arts evolved away from real world utility, into its own highly ritualized little reality. The ability to win fights mattered less and less compared to achieving spiritual or tournament goals, and over time it becoming increasingly abstract and ritualized. But then came the MMA movement, and the resurgence of 'real' martial arts -  whose only arbiter of validity was "Would you win a fight using this style?". The connection with the art world, at least from the way I see it, comes from the old-school martial arts unwillingness to acknowledge what they were. The old martial art community had to invent excuses and justifications and that left it massively vulnerable to woo, as the above video explores in detail. Instead of just saying "Ya we're mostly a way to exercise and relax, with a bit of safe sparring thrown in. If you want self defense there's a boxing studio 2 doors down".</p>
      <p>Both communities strike me as quite similar in their trajectory and experience - going from highly practical and utilitarian (in a world without cameras, artists are the only way to preserve visual reality for posterity) to losing their original purpose due to technology (camera, gun), to evolving away from utility-related concerns into a realm of pure abstract pleasure and exploration. Before falling into bullshit once they'd become untethered from real world concerns. </p>
      <p>It makes me think perhaps this is inevitable - any field, if not held to real world metrics rigorously enough, inevitably disappears up its own butt. Perhaps it is only the constant pressure to sell tickets that keeps movies from becoming an hour of blank screen, and perhaps it's only the need to create profitable mass market albums that prevents <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pq-kjp1dCDU">hypnoskull</a> from dominating the charts (oh god why did I listen to a hypnoskull song when I already had a headache!?).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>