<post>
  <author>MacaqueOfTheNorth</author>
  <date>2020-03-03T08:51:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/fc76p9/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_02_2020/fjclno3/</link>
  <title>Signaling, and the Line Between Flirting and Harassment</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I have a theory that one the reasons men do things that women, to a wildly varying extent, consider sexual harassment, is that the very fact that they could get them in trouble is why they do them. The idea is that men must do something to show interest in women, and women are always going to consider the most forward of these approaches to be harassment if they're unwanted.</p>
      <p>The reason women do this is to discourage men who aren't both confident in their own attractiveness and willing to take risks, from approaching them, while providing a way for those who do have these qualities to signal it. Women have an incentive to selectively enforce the rules and shame unnattractive men who violate them while men have an incentive to carefully flirt with the boundaries of whatever the rules happen to be.</p>
      <p>It explains why there's such a grey area and no clear rules. Sexual harassment seems to vary from harmless flirtation that is necessary to get anywhere with most women to pretty bad things that most men agree is wrong and many men are surprised to hear happen, but which attractive or high status men seem to get away with to a shocking degree. The rules are both unclear because of their selective enforcement and unclear in order to enable the selective enforcement.</p>
      <p>I wonder if the reason these stories build up for years and then suddenly explode is that, for a time, women choose to let them get away with it, but when circumstances change and the man in question's sexual market value starts to decline, some women find he no longer can get away with what he once could. Other women, seeing that there is common knowledge of the man's fallen sexual market value, are now encouraged to show that they too don't accept this behaviour, in order to protect their own sexual market value.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>