<post>
  <author>AnythingMachine</author>
  <date>2019-12-18T19:14:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fbbakre/</link>
  <title>Sharing Articles on the Future of Progressive Politics</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Just today I've read two pieces, one <a href="https://www.newstatesman.com/politics/uk/2019/12/tony-blair-s-speech-future-labour-and-progressive-politics-full-text">very good and perceptive, but very unlikely to be understood or absorbed by anyone</a> and one <a href="https://www.lareviewofbooks.org/article/pinkers-pollyannish-philosophy-and-its-perfidious-politics/">vitriolic and poorly thought through</a>, but its audience will probably think is very brave. First, Tony Blair gave his thoughts on Labour's election catastrophe.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>we  need urgently a new policy agenda for progressive politics. At the  heart of it will be understanding and mobilising the technological  revolution, the 21st-century equivalent of the 19th-century industrial  revolution...  </p>
        <p>We  need policy for the future. Radical but modern. The agenda of the far  left is not progressive; it’s a form of regression to an old statist,  tax and spend programme of the Sixties and Seventies. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Like many other intellectuals and politicians, Blair can see the storm clouds that lie ahead this century, and that the current Labour Party is utterly unequipped to deal with them. You know who agrees with him? Boris Johnson's chief advisor, Dominic Cummings. I mentioned this <a href="https://dm.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/fazkkul/">last week</a>.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And for those of you who read this blog and are most concerned about  climate change and AI, a new high-risk high-payoff research agency,  modelled on ARPA and funded by an unprecedented DOUBLING of the basic  science budget, is in the Conservative manifesto.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Maybe they should go away and make a new political party. That would be quite a sight. Now for the other thing I read; I promise these tie together. The other thing Blair pointed out is that as long as Labour refuses to care or respect people's aspirations, and tries to tell them what they should 'really value' and that the current order of things isn't good enough.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>It  explicitly rejected the anti-Western worldview of the far left and was  on the side of people who were patriotic about their country.  </p>
        <p>It  was not – for all the caricature since we left office – a project of the  metropolitan liberal elite.  It assembled a new coalition of  traditional working class voters, aspirational voters who had previously  turned to Margaret Thatcher, and it fused together the progressive vote  that had been split in the previous century.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The other article I read was another, very belated attack on Steven Pinker's <a href="https://www.lareviewofbooks.org/article/pinkers-pollyannish-philosophy-and-its-perfidious-politics/">Enlightenment Now</a>. It basically just rehashes a bunch of arguments and not-really-arguments people have brought up to oppose the claim that things have basically gotten better over the last three centuries and, roughly speaking, we can say its because of Enlightenment Values. Since the author hasn't said much new, I won't either. A lot of this is copied from an old post I wrote two years ago.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Pinker writes that Hume, among others, was “all too aware of our  irrational passions and foibles,” and devoted himself to overcoming  these “sources of folly.” <a href="https://www.lareviewofbooks.org/article/pinkers-pollyannish-philosophy-and-its-perfidious-politics/#_edn8">[8]</a>  I suppose Pinker must have a different David Hume in mind; this can  hardly be the one who wrote: “Reason is, and ought only to be the slave  of the passions, and can never pretend to any other office than to serve  and obey them.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>One of the more entertaining things  about reading negative reviews of Pinker's book is the fact that most of  the 'philosophers' who accuse him of misunderstanding the enlightenment  don't seem to have a very good grasp of it themselves - for all that  the commentariat keeps laughing at him and calling him <a href="https://youtu.be/vZQJFbrqjUY">unsophisticated</a>  , Pinker seems to have done way more reading of the primary sources  than they ever did - the book is full of quotes both of the  enlightenment philosophers themselves and of modern analytic  philosophers like Nagel. The smug reviewers would do well to brush up on  their Kant and Hume and Mill.</p>
      <p>That David Hume  quote that 'Reason is ... the slave of the passions', which everyone seems to reach for as if it's the only thing h e ever wrote, doesn't mean that he was  an irrationalist (Hume was just making a very early  statement of the orthogonality thesis, that goals and reasoning are logically independent, he was very, very keen on relentlessly applying  reason to solve ethical or philosophical problems), or that Marx and  e.g. Mill both employed the same concept of 'progress', therefore the  enlightenment ideal of progress led to the Soviet Union, both of which  are so obviously wrong that I'm amazed they made it into a serious  review. These are the kind of mistakes that would get a failing grade on  an A level philosophy paper.</p>
      <p>I've even seen reviewers that claim to be philosophers bring up the whole  'Nazis were a product of enlightenment humanism' canard - I can just about see how a writer that hasn't read up on the subject could mistake Marx's Hegelian dialectic idea of progress for the Enlightenment liberal  rational problem-solving sort, but anyone that says the Nazis had roots in enlightenment humanism is just lying.</p>
      <p>I'm amazed at how little philosophy  the ""philosophers"" that write for these magazines seem to know. I've  read just two books on Hegel and the very first thing that pops out is  how utterly divergent he is from the enlightenment ideal of progress  through incremental problem-solving. Hegel's version of progress is  Mind/Spirit resolving contradictions through a dialectical struggle,  then reaching a new understanding of itself, as part of a historical  process with the goal of obtaining absolute knowledge. That's not a kind  of progress that Kant or Mill or the American founding fathers would  recognize.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Writing in the <em>Guardian</em>, Jason Hickel dismantled the most discussed of the graphs, which Pinker reproduces in <em>Enlightenment Now</em>, purportedly showing the decline in “extreme poverty” since 1820. <a href="https://www.lareviewofbooks.org/article/pinkers-pollyannish-philosophy-and-its-perfidious-politics/#_edn17">[17]</a>  Pointing out, among other things, that “real data on poverty has only  been collected since 1981,” and that enormous economic transformations  such as the passage from subsistence to wage-based economies make  meaningful long-term comparisons tricky at best, Hickel wrote, “There is  no actual research to bolster the claims about long-term poverty. It’s  not science; it’s social media.” Roser, Pinker, Gates, and the Davos  set, Hickel concluded, were singing a neoliberal triumphalist anthem  about free market capitalism saving the world. <a href="https://www.lareviewofbooks.org/article/pinkers-pollyannish-philosophy-and-its-perfidious-politics/#_edn18">[18]</a></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Needless to say, this isn't actually the case. Rationally Speaking had a whole <a href="http://rationallyspeakingpodcast.org/show/rs-234-dylan-matthews-on-global-poverty-has-fallen-but-what.html">(very good) episode</a> discussing Hickel and very politely said he was full of nonsense. I said this about it, and there's a pretty good old thread <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/amyesc/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_04/efv7ym4/?context=3">explaining that he's wrong</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>There's a lot of very strong insinuation that Pinker deliberately lied or misled by using the UN's poverty line, and also this <a href="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/59bc0e610abd04bd1e067ccc/t/5c5770a7fa0d6079fea29b4c/1549234352447/Percent%2BMinus%2BChina.jpg?format=500w">rival graph</a>  apparently arguing that the percent of people living on below $7.40 a  day has barely changed (if you ignore china). I'm not sure about the  sources, and the author's tone and writing is so unbearably annoying I  don't think I can be fair to him - c.f. 'mansplaining from  billionaires'. $7.40 also seems exactly cherry-picked to ignore all the  progress we have made. If you take a look at <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/uploads/2013/12/Global-inequality-in-1800-1975-and-2015.png">this graph</a>,  you can see the 'Camel's hump' of median income has surged from nothing  to right below $7.40. It's as if we were all in a 20 km race, we're  just under halfway through and Hickel decided it would be fair to round  down to the nearest 10km, so we've traveled 0km so far.</p>
      </blockquote>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>