<post>
  <author>Artimaeus332</author>
  <date>2019-12-16T21:39:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fb5q9xs/</link>
  <title>A Perspective on the Buisness Culture and Wokeness</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>At some point in the last decade, this dream seems to have fallen apart. To 21st century progressivism, racism and sexism stopped being mere obstacles to individual enlightenment and became all-encompassing intractable societal forces. The progressive ideal of organizational equity stopped being about mere colorblindness and started to stress the importance of applying an actively antiracist, feminist lens to organizational decision making.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I want to push back on this a little bit, because most of the progressive spaces that I've moved in have not really adopted the idea that racism and sexism are intractable social forces that are embedded in our institutions and that #revolution is the only chance for equity.</p>
      <p>For evidence, I'm currently a student at the business school at Yale, which is about as progressive and woke of a culture as you'll find anywhere other than a liberal arts college. However, the attitudes about race relations in this space are not especially pessimistic, and certainly are not sources of interpersonal friction. The space actually looks and feels a lot like StarTrek and Starship Troopers.</p>
      <p>I think, to understand the disconnect between my experiences an the popular image of wokeness, it's important to understand that there are different strains of woke, progressive criticism, one of which is taken seriously by these organizations, and the other of which isn't.</p>
      <p>The first strain of criticism goes roughly like this:</p>
      <p>Business culture fails to be as inclusive as it purports to be because its connective tissue-- all of the subtle, informal, unspoken norms that govern day-to-day interpersonal relationships-- are built upon upper-middle class white culture, and are therefore much less work to adopt if that is your cultural background.</p>
      <p>The official position of the school is that this criticism is valid, and that it is therefore important for our students, as future leaders in their professional organizations, to be cognizant of ways this might unintentionally alienate or exclude people from other cultural backgrounds and take some effort to avoid doing so. Hence the 3-hour diversity training that I had to sit through during orientation. Hence some avowedly feminist and anti-racist HR policy. Hence title IX.</p>
      <p>These policies are certainly not beyond criticism, but their underlying goal is to bring the culture of our professional institutions closer to the StarTrek ideal. This is the objective of the woke professional managerial class (which I suppose I'm training to be a member of), and within its own spaces, it's pretty successful.</p>
      <p>Of course there's another line of progressive thinking, which is that our institutions are irredeemably white supremacist hetero-patriarchal whatever, and won't ever be equal unless they are torn down and re-built.</p>
      <p>But in my experience, basically nobody actually takes this criticism seriously, at least outside of organizations that are specifically dedicated to progressive political activism. Everyone has certainly heard it-- progressive activists are nothing if not loud-- but it sort of rolls off people's backs. They will nod earnestly and acknowledge that the fight for racial equity is challenging and say that "it's important that we listen to the voices of the marginalized", so that we know how to make our culture more inclusive (i.e. pivot back to the StarTrek model).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>