<post>
  <author>byvlos</author>
  <date>2019-12-16T22:22:23Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/e85hvr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_09/fb5v5eh/</link>
  <title>Skepticism Regarding Voting System Reform</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I have a few thoughts.</p>
      <p>My first thought, and by far my most important position: under democratic systems, everyone is constantly trying to manipulate the process in order to benefit themselves. This is extremely bad, because not only is it unfair bias to one side or another, but it undermines faith in the impartiality and fairness of the democratic system as a system. Consequently, this should be disincentived with extreme prejudice, <em><strong>even if it means you end up with a less-than-optimal system</strong></em>. Consequently, I <em>heavily</em> privilege the status quo, for no reason other than the fact that it is the status quo. The nation under which I vote (Canada) currently has a FPTP system. Therefore, I want it to keep the FPTP system. If it had a PR system, I would want it to keep the PR system. </p>
      <p>But that's kind of a cop-out answer, so I will give my two other defenses of FPTP. Note that I am not trying to argue that these are the most important things, or even that FPTP is the best system. My position is more like "I think FPTP has these important benefits, I think proposed alternatives do not, and I don't think people are properly accounting for this when they argue".</p>
      <p>FPTP gives two important benefits: it refuses to reify the political parties, and it is geographically-based. </p>
      <p>Reification of political parties: despite what virtually everyone seems to think, under a FPTP system you are not voting for a party, you are voting for a person. I think this is important. For one, I still believe in having a personal connection with my rep. Maybe this sounds kind of crazy to Americans, but back home, there's something like ~50k voters in my riding. All the politicians who were running in my riding came and gave presentations at my highschool. I could just phone up my MP and talk to her directly, no leaving a message, no going through an intermediary. Having that personal connection to the MP is important and significant to me. It's my impression that things are changing in Canada, but I still feel that in many districts, the right person can flip voters to whichever party, because enough people still care about the person over the party.</p>
      <p>But more important than that is the lack of reification in and of itself. In a FPTP system, because you are voting for individuals, parties are fundamentally emergent properties. At the end of the day, I can run for an election, and I can be a member of any party or I can be a member of no party at all, and in principle I am treated the same either way. (In practice I am discriminated against if I am not a member of an official party, in terms of election spending and campaign regulations. But strictly speaking that is part of the campaign, not part of the election itself, and in any case I think this is bad). </p>
      <p>Under any form of PR, you must necessarily vote for parties over people (because how could you proportionally distribute seats <em>amongst parties</em> if nobody votes for parties). Which means that the election has to formally recognize parties as things that you can vote for. Which means that someone, somewhere, gets to decide which parties are "real" and which parties are not. And that injects a bias into the system. A bias for the incumbents, which in my mind is the worst possible kind of bias to inject. The whole point of democracy is that it gives us a peaceful way to remove bad rulers. Anything that biases the electoral system into giving existing rulers an easier time staying in power than new rulers coming into power goes against that principle. </p>
      <p>(Note: I am aware that the typical argument against this, in favour of PR, is something along the lines of "come on, you don't actually believe that? Of course everyone is just voting for parties. Pretending they aren't doesn't make it so". To that all I say is "no, it's everyone else who is wrong". I am perfectly aware that this is true, and it is a compelling argument. Still, I'm sitting here saying how I think things <em>should</em> be, not how I think things are)</p>
      <p>Geographic basis: right now, when I go to the polls, I am voting for someone who represents my neighbourhood, in a very literal sense. The voting area is an area that's roughly walkable (and certainly bikeable), an area that has a coherent identity, and that might plausibly have interests that are cross-aligned with the interests of other neighbourhoods. Under a FPTP system, my neighbourhood might end up with a representative that only got 40% of the popular vote, but <em><strong>my neighbourhood</strong></em> ends up with <em><strong>a</strong></em> representative. </p>
      <p>This is important, because I come from the Canadian equivalent of flyover country. My entire province only has like 10 seats. Ontario has 125. The interests of my province are routinely ignored at the federal level, as we don't number enough to matter in any meaningful way. However, we still get representation via the fact that 10 of those seats are filled with people <em>from here</em>. Maybe they are forced to vote party line (again, I hate parties), and that sucks. But when they propose legislation, they can keep our point of view in mind. Should any of them get cabinet positions, they can represent our interests where they can. </p>
      <p>So say we switch to a proportional representation system. We have a vote. The way it breaks down, say the liberals get 200 seats, the conservatives get 100, and the NDP get the rest. So now the liberals get to distribute those 200 seats amongst 200 liberal MPs, the conservatives amongst their 100, and so on. Who do they distribute them to? Do they distribute them to the people in my region, who are seen as backwoods farmers and hicks, who live a thousand miles from Ottawa, who are political outsiders who don't know how things go? Who, by virtue of being so geographically distant, have never gotten in to the inner circle of things? Or do they distribute those seats to 200 of the 1000s of party faithful who live in major urban centers like Toronto, or major seats of political power like Ottawa? 1000s of political operatives who have put in the time, have learned How Things Are Really Done, have proven their loyalty to the party, etc etc etc. The answer is obvious.</p>
      <p>So maybe you add some kind of condition to the PR that it still has to maintain the same distribution of seats amongst the provinces, and so I still get my 10 reps or however many. This still isn't good enough for me, because <em>who decides which specific individuals</em> are going to represent us? The federal parties, of course! It's not my province! It can't be my province, because there is no unified body representing my province at the federal level that exists with the authority to make these decisions! The only body representing my province that has the legitimacy and authority to decide which <em>specific individuals</em> get those seats is <em>the electorate itself</em>. And that just reduces back down to FPTP picking individuals in individual ridings. </p>
      <p>PR necessarily shifts the fundamental electoral unit from a geographical area to the federal parties. And, if it's not obvious already, I think parties are really really bad, and I think federal governments are also bad. I do not want them to have more power over my neighbourhood and my community, I want my neighbourhood and my community to have more autonomy and self-determination. I want my community to fundamentally represent its own interests, instead of having its interests dictated to it by an organization (political party) that is headquartered fifteen hundred miles away. </p>
      <p>Now, I realize that it is kind of unfair to say that PR is bad because it has these drawbacks. Because PR is a specific system designed with a specific intention to solve specific problems, and the problems it solves are not these ones. Further, the problems it solves are very real problems with FPTP, which do exist, which piss a lot of people off, and which (obviously) FPTP is not going to solve. At the end of the day, it's a fundamental difference in values and goals between me and the PR people. I want to burn the parties down and salt the earth so they can never grow again, and I want people who I personally know being the ones who exercise power and influence over what happens to my neighbourhood. I don't want political parties using my neighbourhood as a pawn in their games. PR people, at least from my perspective, are basically saying "hey they're going to use your neighbourhood as a pawn in their games either way, so if we at least formally recognize that and make some proper rules, their games won't suck so much".</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>