<post>
  <author>crazycattime</author>
  <date>2019-12-20T04:26:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fbfokmh/</link>
  <title>On the Slow Adoption of Ideas</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I glad you posted this.  I have an objection that I don't quite know how to articulate so let me know if anything comes across weird or uncharitable to you.</p>
      <p>I don't think "y'all started it" is the right framing here.  Generally, I think leftists are the aggressors in the Culture War and I think that comes from their natural position as the group that's taken up the mantle of pointing out cracks in society.  If the Right says "all men are created equal", it's the role of the Left to say, "that includes women and non-whites, too, right?"  Similarly, it's the role of the Right to keep that within reasonable and prudent bounds given the state of the culture, so it's fair to respond, "sure, but it doesn't include dogs and horses."</p>
      <p>In my toy model above, this back and forth is a friendly discussion/negotiation about how to tweak society to minimize harm and maximize harmony/freedom.  In the real world, it's partisan snarling and accusations of satanic communion.  Moreover, humans have come up with some remarkably evil and sadistic ideas throughout history that don't always appear so at first glance.  Worse, both sides have members who will cheerfully abuse any rule or norm and as far as I can tell this has been the case for all of recorded history.  So, no, we didn't start it, you didn't start it, Cain started it.  Everyone sucks here.</p>
      <p>Similarly, this:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Bluntly put, you guys lost because <strong>your ideas were and are unpopular</strong>.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>isn't really an accurate picture of how this stuff happens.  Slavery is super unpopular now and for a long, long time, it was quite well accepted.  In fact, it's still going on in some parts of the world.  Women being able to vote or read or drive were ridiculous ideas that only gradually became near-sacred norms and still aren't universally practiced.</p>
      <p>Gay marriage was not at all popular for a long time, too.  "You guys" had and have good ideas and ideas that are unpopular, stupid, and wrong, just like "us guys."  Which ideas eventually gain broad support (or even tolerance) is a function of the merit of the ideas, the skills and Will of the proponents, and the hearts and minds of the fickle populace.  The people against gay marriage lost because the pro- side, though a mixture of lawfare, persuasion, and exposure, convinced a critical mass of the populace that, "eh, let the gays get married, nbd" was a tolerable path forward.  Put another way, "gays should be able to get married" was not such a prima facie popular idea that people needed nothing more than hearing it to adopt it.  The pro- side had to <em>make</em> it popular enough to lead to a Supreme Court ruling that forced the anti- side to concede the legal grounds.</p>
      <p>The way you phrased your "bluntly put" statement makes it sound like your ideas were self-evident and overwhelmingly popular from inception.  It's closer to the truth to say that you didn't convince as many people as you dragged, kicking and screaming, into tolerating your ideas or facing legal, social, and financial sanctions.  If it "was and is" "popular" it wouldn't have taken 30+ years and a lot of groundwork for it to take hold.  500 years from now maybe people will think gay marriage is as ordinary as tortillas, but it's not the kind of thing that develops naturally without a lot of careful stewardship, especially in the beginning.  Here and now, though, the "bake that cake" wars rage on.</p>
      <p>On top of that, there's a big gulf between "gays should be allowed to get married" and "I want to see gay stuff" or even "I don't mind seeing gay stuff."  TV is helpful here.  The married, heterosexual couple on Leave it to Beaver had two twin beds in the master bedroom.  It wasn't until Star Trek that a white dude could kiss (no tongue!) a black chick on screen.  It wasn't until Buffy that two girls could kiss.  Homosexuality used to provoke profound disgust reactions in a whole lot of people and still does for some, even though they're happy to support gay marriage in the abstract.</p>
      <p>If "your idea" is that gay people in the US should be allowed to get married, it looks to me (from what I remember the last time I looked) like that has the enthusiastic support of 40% of the population, the grudging acceptance of 10-30%, with the remainder still firmly opposed.  If "your idea" is that "homosexual sex/affection is totally normal and not at all gross", well, I think support for that is a whole lot lower.  Lesbian porn may be super popular, but two male porn stars even kissing and it's shunted to "bi/gay", which is decidedly less popular.   And maybe younger kids aren't as squeamish as Boomers, but I still don't see a lot of organic, enthusiastic support for two dudes to make out in the club (not counting gay clubs).  (Is there any data on this at all?  Is it at all common for two guys to kiss in public at a typical college or high school party?)</p>
      <p>All of this is to say that boiling this down to "your ideas" or "our ideas" are more popular fails to account for a whole lot of back-and-forth that was crucial to both developing and selling those ideas in their ever-changing form to the general public.  The "liberal ideas" crowd may be culturally dominant right now, but there's a large collection of unconvinced people who are more and more resentful that the culturally dominant are being dicks about it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>