<post>
  <author>j9461701</author>
  <date>2019-12-17T21:26:29Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebw8kd/us_military_supremacy_is_being_rapidly_eroded/fb8nxvx/</link>
  <title>Contra The Erosion of US Military Supremacy: The Accumalation of Weaponry</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="https://theconversation.com/chinas-military-might-is-much-closer-to-the-us-than-you-probably-think-124487">It's more like 74-75%</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>This largely results from historical accumulation of weaponry and bases when the U.S. was the clear hegemon. Going forward, the balance of military capabilities is going to shift rapidly. Consider this chart of military spending at PPP adjusted for inflation. For reference, in 1988, the USSR was 50% of the U.S. level.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Barring the introduction of some revolutionary new technology that renders all other weapon investments obsolete, the historical accumulation of weaponry is a massive advantage the US isn't soon to lose. China has 28 J-20s, the US has 450+ F-35s and 187 F-22s. The US has 11 super carriers, China has one regular carrier. </p>
      <p>But even if China were to magically negate the US material advantage (say every American carrier spontaneously sinks), America has decades of experience integrating complex weapon systems seamlessly on multiple levels, and in producing high quality military hardware. </p>
      <p>The Soviets obtained detailed information on US submarine propellers in the '70s due to the Walker spy ring, which should have enabled them to replicate the technology. But they couldn't, because the Navy - in conjunction with private enterprise - had spent years developing the extremely precise machining equipment necessary to produce them. Bereft of the engineers who'd worked on the project and the exact machinery the Americans had used, the Soviets could not replicate America-level propellers despite having been handed a step by step instructional guide for the process. The ability to construct state of the art propellers was diffused among hundreds of engineers and naval officers, and there is no real shortcut to stealing that ability - you'd need to develop your own propeller program and build up a similar level of implicit knowledge in your naval institutions. </p>
      <p>But that's just the building side of things, let's talk about the using:</p>
      <p>The Battle of Khasham was a masterwork of interweaving fire support from a dozen different platforms seamlessly, from attack choppers to tube artillery naval aviation, with a tempo of operations no other military on Earth could hope to match. That kind of skill takes decades to build up, and has to be ingrained into the culture of the military itself. No one performed experiments and isolated the exact precise thing every person on a flight deck needs to do to maintain X sorties in a day. Instead it's the product of experimentation and tinkering by every crew member, who in turn pass on their accumulated knowledge to their replacements and so on and so forth until US carriers are able to do things other navies could not hope to replicate. </p>
      <p>This was always the British advantage, historically. Their crews could simply do more than the navies of any other nation, and so even in scenarios were they were ostensibly out gunned or out numbered they could expect to come out on top.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.mitpressjournals.org/doi/pdf/10.1162/isec_a_00337">A paper I read</a> described this as a move from codifiable to tacit knowledge. It's easy to write down the steps to produce a radar set, and once you get those steps anyone in an enemy organization can implement them. But modernly technological and military advantage is gained through improved tacit knowledge - knowledge that can't be written down and stolen. But instead knowledge that organically builds up among engineers, officers, scientists, etc. and becomes "Common knowledge" in the industry. </p>
      <p>It will be decades before China can replicate America's tacit knowledge advantage - heck, it will be years before they're able to built Russian-quality jet engines let alone Russian-level fighter jets. Let alone, yet again, <em>American</em> quality fighter jets.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>