<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2019-12-17T14:45:52Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fb7m76e/</link>
  <title>Alsace-Lorraine and the European Identity</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I once went on a trip to Alsace Lorraine and met a dude who had grown up there.</p>
      <p>He had an interesting narrative vis a vis European identity.</p>
      <p>As anybody who’s checked up on French-German relations knows, the rich chunk of land on the Rhein wedged between Germany and France was passed back and forth between them like a bong in a hippie bus for two hundred years or so. Accordingly, the residents of Alsace-Lorraine found themselves under new management every generation- first having French banned and being raised under the German thumb, then having German banned and being raised French, and so on and so forth. Alsace Lorraine therefore turned out neither French nor German in culture, but was instead imbued with a kind of proto-nationalism about their local culture. Like Quebec, or maybe Texas- part of a whole, sure, but defiantly distinct because of the history.</p>
      <p>Then WW2 happened, and that localism took quite a turn. Hitler grabbed Alsace-Lorraine after beating the French army. Because of the disputed history, the Nazis treated the residents of Alsace-Lorraine differently than the residents of France proper. The French were conquered, but the Alsace-Lorrainers were <em>integrated</em> German citizens under Nazi rule. That means they were subject to conscription. Anyone who refused on principle to serve the Reich, well, refusal to enlist with the Wehrmacht when your number comes up means your family gets shot.</p>
      <p>A lot of Alsace-Lorrainers wore German uniforms in France, aimed their rifles at French citizens. There were a lot of hurt feelings and harsh words for the turncoats after the war was over. Alsace-Lorrainers were seen as collaborators and Not Real Frenchmen. The guy telling me this described a vacation he took with his parents to Marseilles in the 1960’s when he was a small child. They had to hide the fact they were from Alsace-Lorraine to avoid harassment and abuse.</p>
      <p>As a result, the generation who grew up in the wake of WW2 did not view themselves as proud and distinct Alsace-Lorrainers. Fuck, no. They were French patriots; they bled red white and blue, sang themselves to sleep with La Marseillaise. Overcompensation in the face of questioned loyalty, you see.</p>
      <p>But the generations after <em>that</em>- the generations my new buddy came from, who grew up in the seventies and the eighties and the nineties- grew up in the EU. They could pop across the border any time they wanted, spoke three languages well and two more passably. They grew up with free trade, hung out with Poles and Italians and Spaniards and Irishmen all working in the same office, didn’t need to change money when they went on vacation to Greece or Belgium.</p>
      <p>The recent generations from Alsace-Lorraine don’t view themselves as being French first and foremost. They’re European.</p>
      <p>Obviously that could not possibly be a universal worldview in France, let alone all of Europe. But it seems perfect reasonable that that is how a <em>lot</em> of mainlanders see things.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>