<post>
  <author>sinxoveretothex</author>
  <date>2019-12-19T21:52:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fbermsx/</link>
  <title>Law as A Reflection of Society</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is a very good point although I'm surprised to see you make it.</p>
      <p>That is to say, as one of the resident progressives on this subreddit, I'm fairly certain that I've read you endorse anti-discrimination views if not laws. I can't say for certain at the moment and don't want to put words in your mouth so feel free to disagree with that assumption if you like.</p>
      <p>Should an employer be allowed to not hire any gay or black or woman (or for that matter any white male) without the government punishing them for discrimination? Presumably, those gays and what not are still free to find employment elsewhere?</p>
      <p>I guess we could squabble over the difference between a "speech act" vs an "administrative act" (is entering in a contract more or less of an action than a speech or expression of a belief in whichever form) but I don't think that's a good place to debate: we can make it so an employer hires anyone but fires people when it discovers they are in a homosexual relationship, say (which is still currently an instance of illegal discrimination on the part of the employer).</p>
      <p>Anyway, the more general point I'd make is that laws are a reflection of the will of society or at least of the will of some power within it (whether that power is elitist, popular or whatever else). In that sense, there's no hard line between governmental punishment and societal punishment. You can still express whatever belief while being jobless or even while getting <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2106476/">threatened to not come back to the grocery store</a>, true but so can you while ordered to pay tens of thousands of dollars in fines or while in prison, etc.</p>
      <p>It's interesting, I think, to notice how we sometimes think in somewhat incompatible ways in different situations. I think, for example, that your line of reasoning in the current legal context in Western countries has the effect of severely curtailing the freedom of expression of entrepreneurs and larger business owners. In a sense, they're still allowed to publicly express their beliefs, they're just not allowed to act on it in the context their own business. Yet, I'd have to hand it to you that your line of reasoning also is protecting employers from discriminating on the basis of the expression of (legally unprotected) beliefs.</p>
      <p>I've been thinking for some time about this whole thing and I think there's a very reasonable explanation for why we seem so inconsistent: being consistent without first having a mechanism to force your opponent in turn just means you're handing them victory. That is to say: if we want to say that the government cannot deny anyone their freedom of association, it means we're arguing for being allowed to fire people for TERF beliefs… but it also gives business owners the right to discriminate however they please. Meanwhile, your opponents are still allowed to support TERFs while wanting to discriminate in employment too because they made no commitment to denying freedom of association; their only goal is to not have to deal with trans or whichever other group.</p>
      <p>In effect, this is a very perverse coordination problem: it's a coordination problem where the participants are adversarial to each other so they don't just not care about benefit to the other, they have an incentive to prefer situations where the other is worse off. And the benefit to coordination is long-term, abstract and hard to commit to: I want my enemies punished but do I really want to ignore the ideological Geneva Conventions to hurt them?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>