<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2019-12-19T16:03:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fbdu6dq/</link>
  <title>Part 1: On Maya Forstater and J. K. Rowling - Rifts in Feminsm</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A ruling has been returned in the case of charity worker Maya Forstater, whose contract with her employer was not renewed due to accusations of transphobia. You can read the ruling <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/12P9zf82TicPs2cCxlTnm0TrNFDD8Gaz5/view">here</a>, but be warned it's a Google Drive link. This is a landmark case for the UK, and is drawing a ton of attention in all the predictable spheres. I've read the case and an unhealthy dose of the reactions, so I'll summarize the key elements. Given the heat of the topic, in this post I intend to lay out the facts in neutral tone, with any personal analysis coming later. </p>
      <p>If you prefer other sources, you can refer to <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2019/dec/18/judge-rules-against-charity-worker-who-lost-job-over-transgender-tweets">the Guardian</a> and <a href="https://medium.com/@kathleenstock/i-am-a-professor-of-philosophy-employed-at-a-british-university-in-a-philosophy-department-a038ac89aad0?">this viral Medium post defending the worker</a>.</p>
      <p>Maya Forstater is a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/law/2019/nov/15/researcher-defends-tweets-on-trans-rights-at-employment-tribunal">"gender critical" feminist</a> who tweeted and spoke extensively in line with those beliefs. Her core claims, as stated by her:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“I do not believe it is incompatible to recognise that human beings cannot change sex whilst also protecting the human rights of people who identify as transgender”</p>
        <p>“I believe that it is impossible to change sex or to lose your sex."</p>
        <p>“In most social situations we treat people according to the sex they appear to be. And even when it is apparent that someone’s sex is different from the gender they seek to portray... it may be polite or kind to pretend not to notice, or to go along with their wish to be referred to in a particular way. But there is no fundamental right to compel people to be polite or kind in every situation.”</p>
        <p>“In particular while it may be disappointing or upsetting to some male people who identify as women to be told that it is not appropriate for them to share female-only services and spaces, avoiding upsetting males is not a reason to compromise women’s safety, dignity and ability to control their own boundaries as to who gets to see and touch their bodies.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>And her stated intent with regard to specific behavior:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Of course in social situations I would treat any transwomen (sic) as an honourary female, and use whatever pronouns etc...I wouldn't try to hurt anyone's feelings but I don't think people should be compelled to play along with literal delusions like "transwomen are women"</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>She got in trouble with her workplace, the Center for Global Development, largely over her responses to two people: First, <a href="https://www.standard.co.uk/news/uk/gender-fluid-exec-named-on-list-of-top-100-women-in-business-a3942896.html">"Pips"/Philip Bunce</a>, a "gender fluid" business director who made news after being ranked on a Financial Times list of top 100 women in business. Bunce is male and has no desire to transition, but enjoys crossdressing and sometimes presents as a woman at work. Maya sharply criticized Bunce on Twitter for accepting the award and made it clear she did not consider the individual a woman.</p>
      <p>Second, she referred to <a href="https://genderdesk.wordpress.com/2019/05/16/gregor-murray/">Gregor Murray</a>, a Scottish city councillor who goes by they/them pronouns, as "he" on Twitter (<a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EMJcxIJXkAE-VSX?format=jpg&amp;name=900x900">a better picture of Murray</a>). Murray responded with a "very strongly worded complaint" to the Scout Association. In response, she made clear her belief that Murray is a man and that she reserves the right to use "he" and "him" pronouns to refer to males, but may choose to use alternative pronouns as a courtesy. According to her, calling Murray "he" in that case was a result of forgetting Gregor's preference for "they/them" pronouns and was not intended to cause harm. </p>
      <p>Accompanying these was a series of tweets around the standard array of talking points: pronouns, sports, medical screening. None were particularly aggressive in tone, but they were unambiguous on her position.</p>
      <p>The judge provided two core reasons for ruling against her:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>On balance, I do not consider that the Claimant’s belief [that sex is immutable and binary] fails the test of being “attain a certain level of cogency, seriousness, cohesion and importance”; even though there is significant scientific evidence that it is wrong. ...However, I consider that the Claimant's view, in its absolutist nature, is incompatible with human dignity and fundamental rights of others.</p>
        <p>The Claimant's position is that even if a trans woman has a Gender Recognition Certificate, she cannot honestly describe herself as a woman. That belief is not worthy of respect in a democratic society. ...Calling a trans woman a man is likely to be profoundly distressing. It may be unlawful harassment. Even paying due regard to the qualified right to freedom of expression, people cannot expect to be protected if their core belief involves violating others dignity and/or creating an intimidating, hostile, degrading, humiliating or offensive environment for them.</p>
        <p>I conclude from [her dispute with Murray], and the totality of the evidence, that the Claimant is absolutist in her view of sex and it is a core component of her belief that she will refer to a person by the sex she considered appropriate even if it violates their dignity and/or creates an intimidating, hostile, degrading, humiliating or offensive environment. The approach is not worthy of respect in a democratic society. ...</p>
        <p>The Claimant could generally avoid the huge offense caused by calling a trans woman a man without having to refer to her as a woman, as it is often not necessary to refer to a person sex at all. However, where it is, I consider requiring the Claimant to refer to a trans woman as a woman is justified to avoid harassment of that person.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Kathleen Stock, a professor of philosophy, defends Maya in <a href="https://medium.com/@kathleenstock/i-am-a-professor-of-philosophy-employed-at-a-british-university-in-a-philosophy-department-a038ac89aad0?">the Medium post linked above</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I share Maya's belief. I think it is perfectly true. </p>
        <p>...Women are losing not just their legal and social protections, but we are approaching a situation where women (and men) cannot even legally speak about this loss.</p>
        <p>I therefore call upon the British Philosophical Association, all learned Philosophical societies in the UK, and all British academic philosophers working in UK departments, to stand up and say out loud — or better, write it down where members of the public can read it: people should be legally permitted to believe that biological sex is immutable and cannot be changed, without fear of losing their jobs. You are philosophers. This is your moment. If not now, then when?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>J.K. Rowling is currently trending at number 1 on Twitter (along with "TERF" and "JK Rowling is a TERF") for <a href="https://twitter.com/jk_rowling/status/1207646162813100033?s=20">this tweet</a>: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Dress however you please.</p>
        <p>Call yourself whatever you like.</p>
        <p>Sleep with any consenting adult who’ll have you. </p>
        <p>Live your best life in peace and security. </p>
        <p>But force women out of their jobs for stating that sex is real? </p>
        <p>#IStandWithMaya #ThisIsNotADrill</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Defenders of the tribunal counter with <a href="https://twitter.com/AyoCaesar/status/1207665791639920640">the following</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Maya Forstater did not lose her job because she campaigned against the GRA. She did not lose her job because she believed in biological sex.</p>
        <p>She lost her job because of her refusal to recognise the legal rights of people who had transitioned. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You can also peruse reactions in general <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=maya&amp;src=typed_query">on Twitter</a> and elsewhere.</p>
      <p>edit: the tweet is less bold now</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>