<post>
  <author>TracingWoodgrains</author>
  <date>2019-12-19T17:04:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ebaopf/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_16/fbdzv01/</link>
  <title>Part 2: No True Feminist</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's not a perfect analogy and I want to be cautious in putting it forward, but I can explain my feelings about this best by examining the "Are Mormons Christian?" debate. One reason to do so is that this, as a topic almost entirely irrelevant to all non-Christians, is likely to be a much less heated battleground for most people invested in the trans/GC debate. For Mormons, the answer is an unequivocal, passionate <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/manual/gospel-topics-essays/christians?lang=eng">"Yes"</a>. It's a serious matter for them, and they've devoted quite a bit of time and energy recently to emphasizing it. Telling a Mormon they're not Christian is usually taken as pretty offensive, since they take it as a question of their commitment to the divinity and teachings of Christ.</p>
      <p>So what do other Christians say? It varies, but particularly among most Protestant branches, the answer is an unequivocal "No." Some examples from <a href="/r/christianity">/r/christianity</a> of the many, many times the question has been asked: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Christianity/comments/dju7ek/are_mormons_christians_why_and_why_not/">1</a><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Christianity/comments/bqipg6/are_mormons_christian/">2</a><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Christianity/comments/5qa9cw/are_mormons_christians/">3</a><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Christianity/comments/4qu7kd/are_mormons_christian/">4</a><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Christianity/comments/cedz2v/are_mormons_christians/">5</a> Note that, for many Evangelical branches, this is <em>also</em> a core issue: Christians are saved. If Mormons were Christians, they would be saved. Mormons have heretical beliefs and are clearly not already in the truth. Mormons are not saved. Therefore, Mormons are not Christian. This is a bit of an uncharitable summary, but gets to the seriousness of the disagreement. For them, the question of whether Mormons are Christian is literally a matter of heaven or Hell.</p>
      <p>When I was a Mormon, it was <em>really, really irritating</em> when people told me I wasn't Christian. Being Mormon was the single most core part of my identity, and it seemed self-evident to me that I was Christian. Ultimately, it wasn't as big a deal as gender identity is to trans people, because there was always the undertone in my mind that mine was the one true faith and ultimately "I am Christian" wasn't the core identifier for me the way "I am a man/woman" is for trans people, but it was still a big deal. </p>
      <p>Anyone who's been online also knows how unpopular Mormonism is online (<a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/atheism/comments/aryxyl/mormon_missionaries_now_permitted_to_phone_home/">example</a>). You'll note that this account of mine dates back to precisely when I left Mormonism. That's not a coincidence. Before leaving, I felt massively more constrained in what I could and could not say about sensitive issues online, because I knew that without much urging, both religious and nonreligious people would be happy to tell me that I was a delusional, evil cult member who hated minorities and ignored science and logic. Coming into that environment as a young teenager was honestly pretty traumatic for me and led to a lot of social withdrawal.</p>
      <p>What does all that have to do with this? I'm absolutely certain that people would not lose their jobs for going online and a) stating that Mormons aren't Christian or b) mocking, criticizing, or interrogating individual Mormons who show themselves. I'm also convinced that this is a good and critically important thing to preserve. Well, I won't defend the mockery—that part genuinely did suck—but we need the freedom to call into question even fundamental aspects of someone's self-identity that don't accord with the world as we understand it. My feelings about perceived attacks on my identity and worldview were genuine—or, sure, valid—but it never occurred to me to think that people shouldn't be able to make those attacks. "Wrong" and "impermissible" are very different boundaries. Fundamentally, this ruling seems on its face to make a set of beliefs impermissible.</p>
      <p>My position, then, is that regardless of what someone thinks of radical feminism, this should be seen as a bridge too far. At this point, we're quite used to handling religious disagreements where people have fundamentally incompatible views of the function of the world and their core identities. These disputes can get heated, they can lead to harm and bad feelings and <em>have</em> led to outright wars. But we've proven able to build a society where two people who think the other is headed down an inevitable path towards eternal damnation can still function together, even while each actively promotes their own views. Growing up, I understood that that sort of tension was the price I paid to move among a diverse group of people, and so I accepted it as a sort of truce. </p>
      <p>Rulings like this break that truce.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>