<post>
  <author>UncleWeyland</author>
  <date>2019-12-20T01:49:55Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ecn2l7/aging_is_reversible_in_mice_and_human_cells/fbfbnio/</link>
  <title>Life Pro Tips For Fighting Aging</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Regarding longevity research: I like it, but I might be just a <em>teensy bit</em> biased since that's what I've been interested in for 11 years. I strongly recommend reading <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3836174/">The Hallmarks of Aging</a> if you haven't already done so. Some researchers are a bit too adamant about the implications of their work, but competition for funding is fierce in this field (the NIH's NIA has a pretty bad grant payline, unless you're working on neurodegeneration... specifically Alzheimer's) so I understand why some of them might make very strong claims that are understudied in humans.</p>
      <p>I don't frequent the subreddit, I read the literature. Want my unsolicited advice for maximizing the chances of reaching escape velocity?</p>
      <p>Virtual certainty (&gt;95% chance of helping):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Do not smoke.</li>
        <li>Do not get too fat.</li>
        <li>Do not get addicted to opioids. (Shocking, I know)</li>
        <li>Don't have unnecessary surgery.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>High confidence (76-95% chance of helping):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Routinely eat a variety of food to minimize risks of unknown unknowns.</li>
        <li>Minimize highly processed foods, bias diet towards vegetables and lean proteins.</li>
        <li>Maintain muscle tone and strength.</li>
        <li>Figure out a sleep cycle that works for you and makes you feel rested. Eight hours is not necessary for most people.</li>
        <li>Strengthen social bonds. (Even if that research is bunk, having people around to help you if you get in trouble is good.)</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Moderate confidence (66-75 chance of helping):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Coffee and tea are good. (Bias warning- I like them, so there's inherent incentive for me to want to believe it is good.)</li>
        <li>Very occasional intermittent fasting may have benefits and has low risk of harm.</li>
        <li>Hormesis: occasionally expose your body to moderate stresses it can handle- hard aerobic activity, heatshock (sauna or thermal spring bath), sun exposure (avoid sunburn though) etc.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Low confidence (51-65 chance of helping):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Metformin</li>
        <li>NMN</li>
        <li>Rapamycin (note: this is an immunosuppressant, <strong>do not</strong> just start supplementing your diet with this)</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Zero Confidence (50/50 these may or may not work):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Resveratrol</li>
        <li>Caloric restriction below maintenance (note: the more complex the organism studied, the less effective this seems to be)</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Mild Negative Confidence (opposed to consensus, &gt;50% chance this is ineffective or even bad):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Vegetarian/vegan diet (bias warning- I like eating meat, my opinion is based on evolutionary logic not empirical research)</li>
        <li>Antioxidant supplementation</li>
      </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>