<post>
  <author>alphanumericsprawl</author>
  <date>2020-10-17T22:26:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g95dn98/</link>
  <title>The Decline and Fall of the Western Empire</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Better position vs Islam than were 100 years ago</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>That was the height of the British empire! The French ruled in Algiers and West Africa generally. Only 3 years ago, the Allies had marched into Jerusalem. The last time the Holy City was under Christian rule was 1244. </p>
      <p>If what we have now are satellite states, consider what they used to be! Egypt was under military occupation. BP owned all the oil in Iran: they had to pay 16% of any profit made (and they did all the accounting). When they tried to nationalize the oil in 1951, Britain organized a coup and put the Shah in instead. But even that isn't true dominance. True mastery is when everyone else knows they're too weak to even try to resist. That's what the West had in the 1920s. There were treaty ports on the coast of China. The British Raj. Vast African empires controlled by only a handful of administrators because everyone knew that any revolt was futile.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Growth_of_religion#Historical_growth">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Growth_of_religion#Historical_growth</a>
      </p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_continents_by_population">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_continents_by_population</a>
      </p>
      <p>Just look at the numbers for comparative change. Islam is on a massive upswing proportionately and Christianity is in relative decline. And even that decline is obscured by the upswing in Christianity outside the West. Did you know that in 1950, Europe alone had more than twice the population of Africa? Today it's a little over half.</p>
      <p>I'm not saying this is good or bad but the West has been in undeniable decline over the last 100 years and probably even longer than that. Demographics, resources, control, proportion of world GDP held, it's all going downhill. Even the notion that the great power struggle might be between a Western and non-Western power (China) is incredibly novel. Yes, Japan was a great power since 1905 but they were never number 2.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>