<post>
  <author>anatoly</author>
  <date>2020-10-17T23:24:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g95kpa5/</link>
  <title>More Culture War Discussions and Less Culture-Warring, Please</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So, I keep thinking about the story of the suddenly offensive phrase "sexual preference", the Merriam-Webster dictionary update, and how these played out here 3 days ago. </p>
      <p>I think the culture war in this case is above average triggering for me, perhaps because I grew up in the USSR, where rewriting reference books was actually a thing (not in my time, but back in the 1950s owners of the Great Soviet Encyclopedia were instructed <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Soviet_Encyclopedia#Damnatio_memoriae">to cut out some pages and replace with new ones</a>). </p>
      <p>Yet, as I'm rereading <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8sc0dc/">the</a><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8sbnuu/">two</a> threads I noticed here that dealt with it, I'm struck again by how almost all of the comments take it for granted that the controversy was insta-manufactured for culture war purposes, and Merriam-Webster insta-obeyed the new Orwellian dictate, etc. There are very few attempts - just <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8t62k9/">one subthread</a> and two comments in it, I think - that are bringing in new information, new links about it. And these two comments, which to my mind are the ones most worth engaging with, are almost ignored; by far the majority of the thread, and the most upvoted comments, are data-free narrative-pushing. "THEY LITERALLY EDITED THE DICTIONARY ON THE FLY TO MAKE THEMSELVES RIGHT", stuff like that. "the people around me in life revealed themselves to be unthinking pod people", stuff like that (this one is the most heavily upvoted comment in both threads, I think, ugh).</p>
      <p>But when I first read about it, three days ago - and when it really rubbed me the wrong way, perhaps because of see above - I went and tried to find out whether in fact the controversy was just invented on the spot. And literally my first Google search - for "sexual preference offensive", without quotation marks - led me to <a href="https://www.glaad.org/reference/offensive">a GLAAD page</a> as the third result (it's the second result for me right now). And I learned there that they claim 'sexual preference' to be offensive. Next thing to check was the Internet Archive, which told me they had considered it offensive since at least 2011. And a link on the same page also told me that the New-York Times style guide dictates "sexual orientation", claiming "sexual preference" is offensive for the usual reason, since at least 2013. Then I looked for some response from Merriam-Webster about the whole dictionary updating, and found it with another search. As <a href="/u/ymeskhout">/u/ymeskhout</a> noted in one of the only two information-gathering comments on the original threads (it wasn't there yet when I first read them), they're claiming they had this update ready for a while time, and only hurried to update it because of it being in the news, as they sometimes do (parenthetically, I learned the word "celerity" from their learned response).</p>
      <p>Now GLAAD is not obscure. And the NYTimes style guide is not obscure. And I find it prima facie reasonable that M-W are telling the truth (if they were trying to be super-woke, why not just say "we heard about it, checked with LGBTQ experts, realized it was indeed offensive and are proud of how quickly we fixed our mistake"?).</p>
      <p>The funny thing is, on the object level I still think the whole thing was both ridiculous and a little ominous. The explanation as to why "sexual preference" should be offensive doesn't make much sense to me. What I <em>think</em> is going on is, "preferences" sort of sound not "core" enough to our inner beings. It's less about being able to deliberately change one's preferences and more about them being naturally malleable. If I strongly prefer beef to chicken, it may well be that in 5 years this'll change and I'll strongly prefer chicken to beef. I think activists feel that having sexual orientation in the same category of things is both off-putting and a source of dog-whistles to people who are into "correcting" sexual orientations. At the same time, it's likely that most people <em>and</em> most gay people never heard of this offensiveness and never cared about it, even if "sexual orientation" seems more common now. "Widely considered offensive" is something between a stretch and an untruth.
It wouldn't be the first or the 100th time that activists are trying to treat as settled language controversies the population at whole doesn't really care about. Remember how <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/hispanic/2020/08/11/about-one-in-four-u-s-hispanics-have-heard-of-latinx-but-just-3-use-it/">most Hispanics never even heard of "Latinx" and barely any use it</a>?</p>
      <p>Still. GLAAD is not obscure. The NYTimes is not obscure. It bothers me that the two topic-starters of the original subthreads never bothered to look for any negative evidence to their narrative. It bothers me that almost none of other commenters did (and the two that did were latecomers to the thread, and I only found them when rereading now, a few days later). </p>
      <p>I used to think that one of the best things about the Motte was that I was sure to learn new interesting information, when I come here and read about the culture war issues du jour. Nowadays, when I dive in, I catch myself at mentally preparing for a screen after screen of rah-rah culture-warring, interspersed with occasional thoughtful and interesting arguments and data. The thoughtful stuff comes from both the right and the left, but the rah-rah stuff is incredibly heavily biased to the right. And I guess the problem isn't even the bias itself, it's more that this stuff dominates the subthreads so much and so often, it begins to look like the default stance. I'm not even talking about deliberate consensus-building (those aren't that common). It's more just - pushing narratives. Finding validation of your culture war stance in the latest subthread, basking in it a bit, and pushing the narrative a bit more to validate a little more others that think like you. Push push push. Bask bask bask.</p>
      <p>Maybe that's what many people think about when they talk about the right-wing bias of the sub; I know that's true for me. Not so much the HBD stuff coming up again and again. Not so much the heavy emphasis on social justice in the news. It's the devolvement to narrative-pushing. I think if it were the case that almost all narrative-pushing was coming from the left, I'd hate it just as much and call it a left-wing bias (that certainly happens in some other spaces I visit). But that's not what we have here. And in this place, this devolvement seems particularly unfair because it just goes against the spirit of the place so much. Why do it? I don't really understand it. I don't post here much, but when I do, adding my voice to an already locally dominant (at least on the given news item) narrative seems such a turn-off. Almost every political forum on the net is already all about that, and this one is one of the rare exceptions. What's the attraction then?</p>
      <p>I don't really know what to do about it, or whether anything can be done. It seems like there's a critical mass of commenters for whom this <em>is</em> the "neutral discussion" as they see it (not maliciously so), and then a critical mass of lurkers beyond them that like and upvote this sort of stuff more (maybe not always? maybe I'm too pessimistic?) than other users like and upvote the kinds of comments I like. I don't know. Feels good to find some words for this and get them off my chest maybe.</p>
      <p>Can we please, please do more discussions of the culture war, and less culture warring?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>