<post>
  <author>baazaa</author>
  <date>2020-10-19T11:46:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9bc1yg/</link>
  <title>The Errors of Neoclassical Economists</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Well the main reason I was alienated from the left was because they seem to be allergic to good economic policy, so it's hard to think of any non-terrible leftist economic policy. </p>
      <p>But to give some examples of where the neoclassical economists are wrong and the left could have taken advantage of that... starting topically with the sorts of things Ha-Joon Chang talks about... </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>The aversion to industrial policy as just something which distorts markets has been a massive neoclassical failure. Countries which have nurtured their infant industries, like those in East Asia, have generally showed it pays off. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Being content to let capital-intensive manufacturing jobs and their middle-class jobs get outsourced overseas on the grounds that better jobs will spring up in their place. In particular watching neoclassical economists say with a straight face that as the US runs a capital surplus, foreigners must be building factories in the US and we don't have to worry about factor price equalisation irritates me greatly. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Another thing the East-Asian tigers did was try to increase domestic investment in productive industries, including using tools like window guidance. Meanwhile the neoclassical economists have presided over a massive decade-on-decade fall in investment in the US as a percentage of GDP. Even the left has cottoned on to 'if everyone is buying back shares and no-one investing in R&amp;D, won't that hurt the economy?' to which the neoclassical economists have responded that it doesn't matter if every business in the country doesn't want to invest because I=S and if you just pump up rich people incomes up they'll save it and thus investment will be higher. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Turning a blind eye to catastrophic market failures. The labour market in my country is irreparably broken, employers don't want to hire young people under any circumstances, graduate employment outcomes are dismal even as there are skill shortages in the same areas. Neoclassical economists alas live in some Mincerian fantasy-land and continue to insist that every graduate magically begets a graduate job, rather than facing up to the fact the market isn't clearing, human capital is not being rewarded due to information asymmetries etc. </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>The last one is a case where neoclassical economists will acknowledge issues like informational assymetries in principle while seemingly always ignoring it in practice. Similarly, the principal-agent problems which has led to incredibly overpaid incompetent managers is not, in theory, a counterpoint to neoclassical economics, but does seem to get swept under the rug by them all the time (and the left could campaign on that, except they seem more concerned about billionaires who create great companies than parasitical MBAs who are effectively stealing from shareholders).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>