<post>
  <author>bsbbtnh</author>
  <date>2020-10-17T15:48:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g9425l0/</link>
  <title>Every Country Is Not Vietnam</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Apparently we're not quite as capable as... Vietnam.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This essentially presumes that every variable is the same as Vietnam, which is not the case.</p>
      <p>First, like other respiratory viruses, COVID-19 is going to spread differently based on the weather. It's why we have cold &amp; flu season. Some places have mild cold &amp; flu seasons, because they don't reach the ideal temperature and humidity to support a higher transmission rate. Much of SEA, island nations, and the Southern hemisphere is in this boat. It's also why parts of the US haven't seen the virus spread like it had in NY. The climate is completely different.</p>
      <p>Second, most people who die from this are old or have specific pre-existing conditions. In many 'poorer' countries, those people don't survive as it is. Or conditions don't allow for those conditions to occur at high rates. You're not going to find as much obesity, diabetes, and heart disease in poorer countries, because their diets don't allow for it. Their culture is also different. They are less sedentary, they are more likely to medicate through diets and home remedies that target specific deficiencies, rather than pharmaceuticals. They are probably more likely to 'cure' their underlying condition/deficiency, rather than simply dealing with the symptoms.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, in the first world, we have a lot of old people who have one foot in the grave. Most are in hospice or care homes, the places that were hit the hardest. Countries that did a good job keeping the virus out of those places seemed to do extremely well. In places like NY, where they were sending COVID patients, young &amp; old IIRC, into these care homes, we saw the virus completely destroy.</p>
      <p>Third is testing. 'Poorer' countries aren't going to have the testing ability we have, so they won't see as many cases. And like we never tested young people, asymptomatic or mild cases, neither do they. So most of their cases will go unreported. Plus there's a 'chilling effect' when a country takes strong, authoritarian action. If you have a cough, you're going to stay inside and avoid everyone, because you don't want to get tossed in a camp (like in China). For everyone involved, it's better to pretend nothing is happening. The media there won't report on every case, it isn't wall-to-wall pandemic coverage, their doctors don't want to be the ones reporting cases so literally toss people out of the hospital, the politicians hide the numbers, and people hide themselves. </p>
      <p>Meanwhile we're so focused on testing, yet don't put it into context. At the beginning of the pandemic, the old, the very sick and hospitalized, and travelers were the ones being tested. If you were asymptomatic or a mild case, but don't fall into any of those categories, you wouldn't get a test. At best you were told to stay home. So we weren't seeing the whole iceberg. Now we've been testing young people, at far, far higher rates, because they returned to school. And suddenly we are picking up on the true depths of this disease. But without the proper framing, this looks like a much worse scenario than we were originally in. </p>
      <p>Fourth is the idea of 'dry tinder', which sort of fits into point #2. Most cold &amp; flu seasons the majority of deaths are the old sick people who have one foot in the grave. We usually view higher deaths as being a bad flu season, while lower deaths represents a good one. But a bad flu season in the US doesn't necessarily mean a bad flu season in Europe, despite the same strain. Hell, a bad flu season in Norway doesn't mean a bad flu season in Sweden. And this goes to how many individuals there are for a flu to kill off, the 'dry tinder'. </p>
      <p>Most of the places that have been hard hit have had a year or two of 'good' flu seasons. Few old people died off, building up the amount who are on the verge of death, but just waiting for a bad cough to push them over the edge. So when COVID-19 hit, it wiped those people out fairly easily, and racked up a lot of kills. In places that have had 'bad' flu seasons for a year or two, this wasn't so pronounced. C19 had fewer easy targets.</p>
      <p>Fifth is the sensitivity of the tests. With PCR testing, you do a number of cycles to amplify the result. Typically you wouldn't go past ~34 test cycles to get a positive. But with COVID-19, some places have been doing upward of 36 cycles. And not only are they going to be picking up on individuals who are no long infectious, they will be detecting dead virus, at very low amounts. I've read a few articles about nurses who required two negative tests to return to work, and cannot, because the tests are picking up (likely) dead virus, and they have to sit at home for weeks or months until they clear it all. </p>
      <p>So now take that into consideration when you go from not testing young and asymptomatic individuals, to suddenly doing widespread testing on that population (return to school). You have one kid with a cough get tested, comes back positive, and they start testing everyone (whether it is the district or concerned parents taking their kid with no symptoms to get tested). If your tests are too sensitive, if you're running too many cycles, you could be picking up old infections. But they are going to be all reported as new infections. Imagine have 4+ weeks of undiscovered infections posted all at once. It would look like a dramatic spike and be extremely concerning to public health officials, as well as the media and the populace. But we really need to focus on demographics, hospitalizations, ICU, and deaths.</p>
      <p>And lastly, deaths. Every country is reporting these by different standards. Some will report it as COVID-19 whether the death was from that or not. Motorcycle accident, but tested positive for COVID-19? It's ruled a C19 death. While other places won't rule it C19 unless that's the actual cause of death (due to it causing pneumonia or w/e). And I'm pretty sure I've read about some controversies in which some countries basically not even doing that. If you have C19 and die of pneumonia, they mark it pneumonia with no reference to C19. </p>
      <p>Some countries just aren't reliable, either. I don't trust China's numbers. And even if we try to look at excess deaths or similar stats, China has had some rough flooding this year, and that will likely boost their excess deaths (assuming, again, that the reliably report those).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>