<post>
  <author>ChevalMalFet</author>
  <date>2020-10-18T14:22:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g981zuw/</link>
  <title>Comparing the Character of Islam and Christianity</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Islam <em>is</em> of a different character than Christianity. They're vastly different faiths, despite both swearing allegiance to the God of Abraham. They have different origin stories, different founders, different historical circumstances around birth, etc. They're not simply two different flavors of generic "religion" (the way modern strategy games like Total War or Civilization represent this has always driven me nuts), but extremely different belief systems.</p>
      <p>For example, founding:</p>
      <p>Christianity arose more or less organically from the sermons and life of Jesus of Nazareth. The canon comprises dozens of independently written biographies of Jesus, a history of the deeds of the early members of the church, and letters of instruction written and exchanged among the communities of the early, underground church. Some Christians hold that every word of these biographies, histories, and letters are the inerrant exact words of God, but this is a minority belief within the faith. </p>
      <p>Islam, on the other hand, teaches that the sacred text is the direct word of God, via Muhammed, via Gabriel. This has <em>consequences.</em> No one thinks that the King James Sermon on the Mount is the exact words of Jesus, because we know Jesus spoke Aramaic. But the Koran? Those are the literal Words of God. He <em>chose</em> to appear to Muhammed and speak Arabic - and so any version of the Koran that is not in Arabic, that is not those exact words, is necessarily not the actual Koran. Thus you don't see the flood of translations of the Koran that you do of the Christian Bible, because the texts have two different characters. And in turn, the way the faiths have developed over the last 1500 years has been different. </p>
      <p>Historical founders - Jesus is, famously, a martyr. He was known for his miracles and for his sermons, and in the end was given the common death of a criminal. Muhammed, on the other hand, is <em>not</em> a martyr. While he was persecuted for his faith, he survived, and had revenge on his enemies by defeating them in battle. He's very much a warlord, in a way impossible to imagine Jesus. </p>
      <p>Historical circumstnaces - Christianity arose slowly, but virally, spreading underground among the slaves and poor of the Roman Empire, because it was a faith that uniquely gave meaning and value to slaves in a way that the pagan pantheon did not. Early Christian persecution takes the form of pacifistic martyrs being put to death by the authorities. Christians, by and large, do not conquer, and rarely even wage war (the faith doesn't get muscular until 4 centuries after its founding, when the barbarian kingdoms and the Roman authorities adopt various versions). Instead they learn to accommodate and live within society.</p>
      <p>Islam is a conquering faith from the beginning. Islamic martyrs are men who <em>died in battle defending the faith.</em> Men like Ali, the Prophet's cousin, who fell before the walls of Constantinople. Islam is born when Muslims conquer Medina - this is significant. There is no Islam without an independent Islamic state. From its inception, the religion has also been the state, because how could the Faithful live in a kingdom not ultimately ruled by God? And then Islam is a wildly successful <em>conquering</em> faith, sweeping up Mecca, then all of Arabia, then Syria, Palestine, Egypt, Babylonia, and on into Persia &amp; and India, and North Africa, all the way to southern France and Greece. Accordingly, there is no period of Islamic history of adaption with the secular authorities and accommodation - there ARE no secular authorities in the Daar al Islam. </p>
      <p>Those are just a few of hte ways that Islam is not of the same character as Christianity. I would also argue that Buddhism, Hinduism, et. al. are also not of the same character as Christianity, or of each other. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Christianity did. Not 1300 years after its founding, mind you, back then I'm sure most Christians would have been in favor of beheading blasphemers (assuming anyone even asked rather than just having the Church do so).</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>1300 Christianity was fairly lenient with individual sinners. Things like the Cathar war are remembered because they're so unusual. It's not until the rise of the Reformation and an actual challenge to the authority of the Church that it starts to get harsh with its punishments, and that only lasts about a century or so before compromises and secularism start to win out. Imprisonment or exile were both more common punishments than execution.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>