<post>
  <author>HavelsOnly</author>
  <date>2020-10-19T19:04:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9ctjz5/</link>
  <title>Red Flags From a Parenting Study</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Please disregard as a total trollpost, but here's some red flags from a 30 minute reading of the study. </p>
      <p>They don't report effect sizes in the abstract. Instead they use qualitative language. "Perform better". Okay. Is there any reason not to include a couple of numbers here for your main finding? You included other much less important numbers in the abstract. Is the effect size not actually that large?</p>
      <p>Jumping around to the Data section, their data set has a tiny sample size of male same-sex couples. So all the statistically significant results in the study ought to be more accurately reported as conclusions about lesbian couples, rather than all same-sex couples. In fact, and this is totally buried, the vast majority of these are actual biological children of one of the female parents. Only 50 of their 2971 SS couples have adopted or foster children. Also note that about half of the SS couple children come from a previous heterosexual relationship, so, this might be a little more complicated than the word "family". </p>
      <p>In a rare fit of numeracy, the authors helpfully write: " In summary, the group of 2,971 children with same-sex parents can be divided into 1,390 birth children (46.79 percent), 50 adopted children (1.68 percent), and 1,531 children from a previous different-sex relationship (51.53 percent)."</p>
      <p>Jumping back to the abstract - another sin, much more difficult to notice. " The results indicate that children raised by same-sex parents from birth perform better than children raised by different-sex parents in both primary and secondary education." So we need to add this other stipulation - "raised from birth" to get our effect size.</p>
      <p>And let's not be coy here - people are going to read this study expecting to know whether SS couples are "as good as" heterosexual couples. You should at least report the unconditioned effect differences between groups. Then, if you want to adjust for confounders, do so using the stock statistical methods. What the authors have done is handcrafted a cohort to compare against generic controls and then presented it as their primary finding in a way that is sure to be misinterpreted as answering whether SS couples are "as good as" heterosexual ones.</p>
      <p>NB Single parent households are excluded from the analysis. This is not in the abstract, but obviously known to exert a large effect size on child rearing outcomes. Given stereotypes about relationship instability in gay communities, this seems like it would be a big deal. Now it's not really the authors' fault, since sexual orientation is missing from their data, but I would write in BIG CAPITAL LETTERS - "results hold for couples that stayed together over the time period".</p>
      <p>The first paragraph to mention effect sizes quantitatively reads like random bullshit. " on standardized test scores at the end of primary education by about .14 standard deviations". Is that a lot? Is that 1 point on a 100 point scale test? Is that a full letter grade? We have no idea. And while their positive finding warrants quantitative discussion, their negative finding does not, leaving us only with "not significantly". </p>
      <p>Their secondary school outcomes, for some reason are reported in terms of graduation rate percentage point gain. What happened to test scores? What happened to sTanDaRd DeViAtIonS? (yes I'm aware stdev on a binary outcome makes little sense). In the Data section, they mention not using secondary school testing data because it's subjective, even though graduating secondary school is presumably tied to grades and also subjective. Making the leap from grades to completion seems innocent enough, but it makes you wonder if the effect size in the grades was too small and they decided to report on graduation rates (which, you might not graduate for reasons unrelated to grades). </p>
      <p>One thing they seem totally unbothered by is missing completion data for 2/3rds of their cohort. Missing data is never random guys. F.</p>
      <p>Authors note: "We do not find any heterogeneity by child’s sex, ethnicity, or parental marital status." which is pretty sus, ngl. Differences in outcomes due to these factors are strong and well-documented. Maybe this is evidence we have an extremely unrepresentative data set? Who knows. We only get a sentence. Given that this is the Netherlands (relatively ethnically homogeneous) and they have controlled partially (mostly) for parental marital status, it's probably way more accurate to say your data set is unsuited to answer these questions than to claim no effect.</p>
      <p>***</p>
      <p>I pretty much stopped reading after "Control Variables" because it's obvious the problems will go on forever. The most accurate re-wording of their findings is probably that women raising their own biological children from previous heterosexual partnerships now in a lesbian partnership have approximately as good graduation and standardized test scoring as biological children raised in heterosexual partnerships. So if you want to use this study to figure out if gays should be able to adopt, you probably can't.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>