<post>
  <author>JTarrou</author>
  <date>2020-10-15T10:57:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8vyjrg/</link>
  <title>Why Lean On Cultural Expectations for Violence?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>On reflection, I was too dismissive in my first response. Let's dig a bit here. You seem to place a lot of weight on whether violent behavior on a scale from minor classroom disruption to murder is genetically linked or culturally linked. The reason I said this was irrelevant is that at the level we encounter this problem and the tools we have to address them, it doesn't matter. But even beyond that, the answer to the whole nature/nurture thing is always "some of both" for any phenomenon, and there's no reason to think this is any different. There is no need for different moral valences. I think the underlying assumption, that if it were genetic we could not condemn bad behavior, is, in itself wrong. It might make a difference in explanatory terms, but in prescriptive terms, violence itself has a moral valence which is mostly negative (unlike, say intelligence, which is neutral). We are not talking about ability or inclination here, we're talking about behavior that harms other human beings. Even if there is a genetic link to violent behavior, we'd still have to sanction it.</p>
      <p>All that said, my personal inclination is to lean hard on cultural explanations, not because a sort of soft-HBD isn't true (it is both true and blindingly obvious), but because it's a dead end in terms of policy. Cultural explanations, OTOH, give us something to work with, and even (on a long enough timeline) give us some lever to move genetics. Culture can change genetics through sexual selection. This is how HBD (or population differences, or whatever you want to call it) mostly happens in the first place. The Spanish do not have disparate outcomes from the Belgians because they evolved separately. The simping Scandinavians are the direct descendants of some of the most terrifying people on the planet, less than a thousand years ago. Their genetics with regard to violence haven't changed much, but their culture sure as hell did. For all these reasons, I think that the very soft HBD position (different populations have distinct genetic markers which sometimes affect behavior) is true, but mostly interesting academically rather than a blueprint for societal action. Culture gives us just as much if not more explanatory power, and the ability to do something with that knowledge, and the ability, if we get it right for long enough, to affect the genetic side of things.</p>
      <p>As to the appropriateness of my analogy, it's not an analogy at all, it's a <em>direct comparison of the same behavior.</em> This is about scale, and the scale is that the gap in violence (proxied by murder rates) between blacks and non-blacks is larger than the gap between men and women (including blacks). That is a fact. My point there was that we have no problem with disparate punishment rates for men and women, but we do with blacks/nonblacks. And yet the second disparity should by rights be even larger than the first. We have no trouble holding men accountable for their violence (nor should we), but we're having a lot of trouble when those men are one particular race. Occam points the way to a racial (or racist) explanation.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>