<post>
  <author>WestphalianPeace</author>
  <date>2020-10-15T11:12:58Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j9kxab/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_12/g8vzh9f/</link>
  <title>A Rebuke of Drive-By Snark from the Watching Lurkers</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>What do you even get out of this place that you are so, self-admittedly, flippant about the possibility of being banned? I think that if you are avoiding commenting and going back to lurking that you should really ask yourself whether or not you are a better person after spending time here and whether or not you think your comments here better others. </p>
      <p>Do you realize that for so many of us here that there literally no where else to go where we can be free of 'drive by snark'? That there is literally the entire rest of the internet for you to not only do just that that but also to be openly encouraged for it! And that there is literally, in the traditional sense of the term, just this one place for us who want honest engagement and at least an aspiration to effort-post? </p>
      <p>If you are posting here then there is something that is drawing you here. It's something I think you realize you can't get elsewhere. And yet you describe a craving to be "drive-by snarky". This isn't necessarily even a bad thing. An impulse to criticize people here is a wonderful thing! I see so many posts of 'we need more people who sincerely disagree with us here to stop us from becoming a hivemind'. Maybe you are exactly that person The Motte needs! But if your mixture of attraction to this place and desire to engage can only be expressed as dismissive snark then I implore you once again to seriously consider whether or not posting here makes you a better person or makes this forum a better place. </p>
      <p>Because I want you to understand that your ability to switch between posting and lurking is something that puts you in an extremely small group. In any given group the vast majority of people are just lurking and they are lurking because there is something in a given community that they are craving. And that in this one place in particular, where effort-posting is encouraged, that a culture of respect and sincere appeals to one's ideas is an important element that keeps those lurkers here. </p>
      <p>Do you think others can transition from lurking to posting and back to lurking so easily? Because most can't. The vast silent lurking crowd here has no voice. We rely on those rare few who do post to keep the little flame we value here alive. </p>
      <p>Do you have any idea how intimidating it is to post here if you aren't already established? It's completely nerve wracking. It is pace the room editing your first post over and over again for 2 hours nerve wracking. For most lurkers posting in Not The Motte is intimidating enough. 'will my effort be worthwhile?' 'will someone get angry with my idea?' 'will i get stuck wasting my night after spending 10 hours on my feet working only to be flippantly told off by someone who won't even bother engaging with my ideas?'</p>
      <p>But to get over that hurdle of pure-lurker and post here it's even more intimidating. Because for many of us lurkers this is a place we genuinely care about. Because there are people here who are absolutely without a doubt are better formally educated and outright smarter than us 'mere lurkers'. Which is half of why us lurkers are here! We want to read the conversations of people better than ourselves! But we don't want to embarrass ourselves in front of them. We are completely terrified of fucking it up. </p>
      <p>But the effort-posting makes us want to try.</p>
      <p>The effort posting tells the first-time poster that if you try in good faith that you will be granted leniency for your first time posting. The effort posting tells all us lurkers that "forget the rest of the internet. even if you are wrong here people will try to at least engage with your ideas sincerely. You won't work up the courage to finally write something heartfelt only to be dismissed out of hand and told to go fuck off via slogan".</p>
      <p>And the effort posting makes a first timer poster like I was just a few days ago, want to write something worthy of this little garden. And that in turn keeps this garden alive and keeps those lurking engaged. </p>
      <p>And I really hope it stays that way because this is the only place left on the internet where I can find it. There are elements of respect and conversation that are found only here that keep thousands of lurkers coming back week after week. </p>
      <p>So again I implore you. You express a disdain for effort and valuation of snark. Is this place really making you a better person? Would your snarky comments really enhance the minds of those who lurk here?</p>
      <p>Because as someone who was lurk-only until just recently I can say that your self-described 'drive-by snark' desires are completely antithetical to why I bothered to cross that hurdle to my first post. And I hope you sincerely consider just what the value of 'drive-by snark' is to yourself and this forum vs the real possibility that you are making future effort-posters think 'well......why-bother?'</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>