<post>
  <author>BurdensomeCount</author>
  <date>2021-01-17T04:08:58Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/gjjjfgl/</link>
  <title>A dive into the numbers on Harvard admission without "modifiers."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Given our recent ethnicity form discussion I was thinking about the college admissions at Harvard and how hard it is to get into there without any special "modifiers" so to say. As such I was interested in computing the admit rate for a non athlete, non legacy, gentile white person. I added in the gentile since many people here complain that a big portion of the white people admitted to Harvard are Jewish so shouldn't count as white. I disagree but let's entertain their notion for a bit. </p>
      <p>Before beginning I must say that a lot of what I am doing is an estimation and some of the number I am combining are not for the same year, so there is some fuzziness, however given that  the profile of admissions does not change too much I don't believe it is going to make too much of a difference.</p>
      <p>Firstly we can look at Harvard's own press release here: <a href="https://college.harvard.edu/admissions/admissions-statistics">https://college.harvard.edu/admissions/admissions-statistics</a> We see that there were 40248 applications with 2015 acceptances for the class of 2024, which we will be focusing on.</p>
      <p>We also have diversity data on that page. Firstly we remove the percentage of international students. While Harvard does not disclose the how many international student applications there were we can estimate it. International students at MIT have a 3% admit rate, and there is no reason to believe that Harvard is any different. There are quite a few blog posts saying that Harvard also has a similar rate but they don't seem to be official, but it's still weak evidence so lets go with 3%. </p>
      <p>The geographic breakdown section shows that 11.8% of admitted students were international, which makes 0.118*2015 = 238 students accepted. Our 3% rate translates to 238/0.03 = 7933 international applications. Thus we had 1777 US based admits from 32315 applications. </p>
      <p>Now we separate ethnicity data. Their admissions profile shows that 14.7+24.4+12.7+1.8+0.3 = 53.9 percent of their class is not white, leaving 46.1% white admits. Next we need to work out how many of these are Jewish. Unfortunately Harvard does not itself release this info but there are Jewish groups who estimate this itself. Here: <a href="http://www.reformjudaism.org/sites/default/files/Col_TopCharts_f14_F_spreads.pdf">http://www.reformjudaism.org/sites/default/files/Col_TopCharts_f14_F_spreads.pdf</a> we can see that it says Harvard undergrads are approximately 25% Jewish. However there have been articles in recent years saying the numbers are falling so conservatively I am going to go with 15%. This leaves 31.1% non-Jewish whites.</p>
      <p>Furthermore data (from the class of 2022) discussed here: <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/study-harvard-finds-43-percent-white-students-are-legacy-athletes-n1060361">https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/study-harvard-finds-43-percent-white-students-are-legacy-athletes-n1060361</a> shows that 43 percent of these white students were either legacy or athletes or relatives of people at Harvard. This means we have 17.72 percent of all domestic acceptances at Harvard being White non-Legacy. This translates to 0.1772*1777 = 315 non-Legacy whites. </p>
      <p>How many applications were filed by these non-legacy whites? There were 32315 non-international applications overall. Again Harvard does not disclose the full data itself. The US is approximately 60% white, and while college applications are not going to track demographics completely I think it is a good estimator for the number of non-legacy white applications since I would suspect whites as a whole are more likely to apply to Harvard than the median person but after adjusting for age (since younger people are less likely to be white) and removing the applications from legacies and athletes which are not a significant amount we should end back at 60%. However to be conservative we go with 50%. </p>
      <p>Thus there were an estimated 16158 white no-modifier applications in the year 2020 of which 315 were accepted. This is an acceptance rate of merely 1.95%, which is tiny, even relative to the 5% headline all applicant acceptance rate. Basically if you are a generic white (generic in terms of no special modifier we discussed, these are still people with excellent academics and many many extracurriculars) you have less than a 1 in 50 chance of getting accepted to Harvard. And this is with the conservative number I am using which should push up the calculated probability from the actual probability. Indeed a generic international student is more likely to get accepted than a generic white.</p>
      <p>Other Ivy League universities do exist but since they all tend to have similar acceptance criteria acceptances are very correlated in who they will admit. Basically I think this shows that nobody should these days treat an Ivy league education as something they can achieve any more than a potential long shot if they don't want to set themselves up for what is likely to be extreme disappointment. </p>
      <p>Furthermore this data analysis was done for 2020, a class for which admissions decisions were taken before the time that COVID properly struck. 2021 seems to be a bloodbath, see: <a href="https://www.thecrimson.com/article/2020/12/18/harvard-early-admits-2025/#:%7E:text=Harvard%20College's%20early%20action%20acceptance,admissions%20cycle%20in%20Harvard%20history">https://www.thecrimson.com/article/2020/12/18/harvard-early-admits-2025/#:~:text=Harvard%20College's%20early%20action%20acceptance,admissions%20cycle%20in%20Harvard%20history</a></p>
      <p>Basically this year the early admit rate dropped to 7.4% from 13.9%, almost halving due to increased applications. They admitted 1100 people via this method, leaving 900 spots left for the easily over 40000 applications they will get this year (no reason to not expect the massive increase in restrictive early applications to not translate into ordinary applications). Remember this is before any of the corrections I applied in my post. Honestly I think that if you are a generic white applying this year you have less than a 1% chance of getting in. This is around the chance of calling heads/tails correctly 7 times in a row on an unbiased coin. Not good odds in any sense of the word.</p>
      <p>In fact one of the worst bits about it is the fact that selection is almost, but not quite random. If it were truly random then you could handwave away a rejection as being the luck of the draw and not a personal judgement of you in any way. Conversely if there was a definite criteria then when applying you could easily check whether you had a good shot of getting in. For example in India if you wish to go to an Indian Institute of Technology (best colleges in the country) you need to rank near the top on the entrance exam and this is the only criteria. The admit rate is around 1%, so even less than Harvard but cohorts are similar year to year so you can take plenty of practice exams before applying and look at your performance on them as an indicator of whether you have a good (&gt;50%, say) shot at getting in. No such thing exists at Harvard, which just accentuates the capriciousness of it all.</p>
      <p>EDIT: An upper bound for the number of legacy/athlete/staff applications can be calculated as follows: Here: <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/10/harvard-university-and-scandal-sports-recruitment/599248/">https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/10/harvard-university-and-scandal-sports-recruitment/599248/</a> it says that over 90% of athletes who apply get admitted while here: <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/10/harvard-university-and-scandal-sports-recruitment/599248/">https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/10/harvard-university-and-scandal-sports-recruitment/599248/</a> it says 33% of legacies get accepted and here: <a href="https://talk.collegeconfidential.com/t/harvard-chance-for-children-of-faculty/2078131/6">https://talk.collegeconfidential.com/t/harvard-chance-for-children-of-faculty/2078131/6</a> it says children of faculty and staff have a 46.7% acceptance rate. </p>
      <p>Since 43% of white acceptances are one of these that comes out to 0.43* 0.461* 1777 = 352 such acceptances. Then since the lowest acceptance rate for our group is 33% these 352 acceptances imply there can't have been more than 3*352 = 1056 applications that are white legacy/athlete/staff. Even removing them from all from the 16158 still leaves us with 15102 application which moves the admit percentage to 2.08%, hardly anything special. And remember this is an upper bound. </p>
      <p>Similarly if we don't remove Jews at all and treat them as part of whites we have 0.57* 0.461* 1777 = 467 white non-legacy/athlete/staff acceptances. Then the admit rate becomes 467/15102 = 3.1%, still no more than a random international student. If you think the Jewish analysis was a bit non-rigorous you can compute the total rate like this and use the far more grounded fact that gentiles are less likely to get accepted than Jews to get that the acceptance rate for them is likely significantly less than this 3.1% And remember even this number is an upperbound with lots of conservative assumptions serving to make it bigger.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>