<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2021-01-17T17:08:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/gjm8rdv/</link>
  <title>The extent to which the climate emission targets were or were not the point of the Paris Accords</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The climate emission targets were never the point of the Paris Accords, and this was known at the time. Even it's advocates acknowledged that legally enforceable emission standards against other countries were impossible.</p>
      <p>But that wasn't the point, or the reason why Western industrialists were a huge proponent of the accords (beyond just social posturing). The point of the accords was to enable emission standards- regulatory and commercial- <strong><em>internally</em></strong>, which has both regulatory centralization AND mercantile implications.</p>
      <p>Americans got a peek at the regulatory aspect in how the Obama administration began to aggressively cite the the Paris Climate accords in court to justify expanding the powers of the EPA in ways that Congressional legislation alone didn't. By treating it as a de-facto treaty (despite not going through the treaty validation processes), the American Executive branch was able to increase it's regulatory leverage by citing standards/goals that it itself declared, and then requiring compliance by private actors to those goals on the basis of pointing at the accords. This fit American progressive environmentalist interests, but the broader principle of power centralization applies more broadly. The Paris Accords calls on states to create and meet standards, but doesn't dictate <em>how</em> those standards are met (or allow for outside enforcement), which provides an end-run around the usual democratic systems for creating socially acceptable compromises. </p>
      <p>For what Americans may think of as 'Big Government' fans, the Paris Climate Accords were a boon for any ruling party/coalition with distinct interest in increasing the power and the reach of the state. This is true for the American progressive left, but also for Eurofederalists in the EU (where the EU bureaucracy regularly seeks to expand its remit and permanent establishment power base). This is also completely compatible with authoritarian governments, as it gives them a internally legitimiate lever through which to exercise power for political self-interest. It's also especially compatible with high-corruption/crony-capitalist governments double plus especially, as the lack of external oversight/enforcement means that the rules can be freely ignorred or arbitrarily applied to affect internal corporate politics and coalitions.</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>But the reason why so many Western industrial interests were behind it, beyond social posturing or crony capitalist, is that the Paris accords offer a cover for protectionism in the name of emission standards. By having everyone acknowledge everyone else's right to set  and follow their own emission plans without external interference, the Paris Accords introduced new legal ambiguous space for countries to make laws that might previously have been in violation of previous understandings of trade agreement practices. </p>
      <p>To take a broad hypothetical: under your previous trade agreements, your import of foreign cars might have been limited by their adherence to national safety standards. Dirty-but-safe vehicles could still be imported (and undercut your own domestic industry). But with the Paris Climate accords, you could claim that car emissions are part of your national climate plan, and thus international-law-compliant restrictions on those safe-but-dirty (cheap, foreign) vehicle sales. Everyone agreed to it, so it's legal, right? (Legal enough for lawyers to defend, anyway.)</p>
      <p>
        <em>This</em> matters because it offers a way for the people/states/blocks with the most advanced green tech to shut out cheaper-but-dirtier competitors (usually second/third world countries where labor savings are paramount), and then pull up the ladder after them. First-world-countries who can afford to develop/buy Paris Standard (or standards justified by Paris) no longer have to compete with third world 'dirty' competition, who in turn lose access to the Western economic markets unless they make further concessions to the Western countries and their green-tech interests. (Either in selling their dirty-competitive industries to the green tech equivalents for investment/up-tooling, or in trade agreement negotiations that start from a position of green-country advantage.)</p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>So, again, the Paris Climate Accords were never about the country plans- that was just the selling point to get public buy-in and acceptance. At the government level, the Paris Climate Accords were a Green/ecological interest group initiative AND an international normalization/legitimization of state influence in the economy (that would allow crony capitalism or authoritarianism) AND a way for First World economies to reduce second/third world economic competition while also building-in structural negotiating advantage against poorer/less teched states. All smoothed over by the promise of western aid/money transfers to those poorer states, the usage of which was obviously never going to be closely watched or cared about.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>