<post>
  <author>is_not_strained</author>
  <date>2021-01-12T17:55:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/gj0so7t/</link>
  <title>Political hypocrisy over dubious claims of election rigging</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I would have much preferred if Google, Apple, or Amazon gave Parler an API that filtered comments for violence, and gave them the option of using the API or taking down the service.  As it stands, I can't see what options Parler had as it is completely unclear what comments to moderate.  If saying you are not attending the inauguration is inciting violence, what isn't?</p>
      <p>I don't know what is being said on Parler, and I can imagine that much of it is straight-up advocating imminent violence.  There are (weak)  arguments for banning this, though I have to say these arguments were never applied to color revolutions in other countries.  My real objection is that it is completely unclear where the line is drawn.  Clarity on what is and is not acceptable speech would at least allow people to argue about the actual issue.  </p>
      <p>I can't see a system where false claims are banned as being tenable, even if this is limited to false claims that might encourage violence.  Most of the Gospel is false claims that might lead (and in particular, have led) to violence.  The same can be said for more religious texts, which are mostly false claims unless they are normative claims and most of which have a long track record of leading to violence.  </p>
      <p>Even non-religious texts are full of untruths that lead to violence.  The Marxist theory of value is considered to be untrue by many, and clearly has led to millions be killed.  I think it would be bizarre to ban it.  </p>
      <p>As a Steelman perhaps we could draw the line at statements that are false and would lead to imminent violence in the next few weeks. A clear example of this would be many posts about Jacob Blake.  They claimed he was unarmed, etc. and this led to violence.  I don't think a ban like this would be acceptable.  Note that these are false statements about the conduct of government, in particular the police, so very comparable to claims about elections.</p>
      <p>Even if we limit the ban to false statements implicating the election, then we have to decide whether Stacy Abram's claims are allowed.  She had no conceded her election.  If we limit it to the Presidential election, then presumably we should ban <a href="https://www.csmonitor.com/USA/Politics/2021/0104/Why-Georgia-Senate-runoffs-may-hinge-on-Black-voting-rights">this article</a> claiming (by Warnock) that there was voter suppression in Georgia.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“There’s no question,” Mr. Warnock tells the Monitor after a drive-up rally outside a church in Augusta. “[Voting rights] are being imperiled right now by those politicians who somehow feel that rather than the people picking their politicians, the politicians ought to be able to pick their people. And so they engage in all kinds of tricks, the machinations of voter suppression.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Of course, this is a claim that there was election interference in the other direction.  Why can Warnock claim the election result was tainted, but not Trump?  I find myself ending up with a rule that says you cannot make statements that call the current result in question, which is dangerously close to banning all dissent.  I can't find a reasonable line here.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>