<post>
  <author>Lykurg480</author>
  <date>2021-01-17T15:15:33Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/gjlj2lv/</link>
  <title>Yesterday's modus ponens is tomorrow's modus tollens</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Are you familar with the idea that no-fault divorce would lead to gay marriage? This was a very un-PC thing to believe for a while. Suggesting that these things have similar moral status means that we need to adjust our evaluation of one, if they were different. While divorce was controversial and homosexuality condemned, this mostly worked out as discrediting divorce. As such, the comparison was evil and reactionary. As divorce became more established and homosexuality controversial, progressives themselves adopted the comparison, if in a different wording reflecting the fait accompli: "What, do you think marriage is only for having children???". This wasnt purely cynical; as supporting an ideology doesnt mean understanding it, many of those condemning the comparison really did think that gay marriage was abhorrent, and wanted to protect sexual freedom against such slander.</p>
      <p>I suggest it is a similar situation here. By liberal ethics, biological plausibility or body dysphoria ought not be relevant to the treatment of trans-whatevers. But as is transgender is controversial and transracial is rejected, and it leads to similar reactions. This explains the reactions but not why transracial is a harder nut to liberalise. This is I think because people see sex as different positions within a society, and race as positions in different societies, to the extent that theyre considered relevant. In the Great Organicist Order of the World, that is a smaller jump. Compare for example with our smaller yet recognition of transoccupational people back in the early modern period, which has been so thorough that we wouldnt ususally think of it that way. So I think the biological plausibility argument gets closest to expressing the truth among the common ones, though the plausibility in question is not at heart a biological but an essential one.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>