<post>
  <author>nicolordofchaos99999</author>
  <date>2021-01-13T02:35:10Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/gj2kwld/</link>
  <title>Censorship, social shaming, and no-platforming *works*. That's why we shouldn't do it</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Or, to put it more explicitly, your hypothesis in this post is that in response to perceived “liberal excess”, “the most moderate 50% of Americans shifted towards the Red Tribe a bit, though they did so quietly.” Why <em>quietly</em>? Why not <em>loudly</em>? Because, well, you and I both know that expressing any sort of dissent from the critical race theory party line in <em>public</em> would be … let’s say, hazardous to your future job prospects. </p>
      <p>So now we have, as you claim, a large mass of people who take one stance in public, but take another stance in private, once you’ve gotten them a little tipsy and they can be sure no one else is recording. These stances might not be all that different — you’re not going to see a full-on Marxist turn into a paleocon once the cognac is out — but they are a <em>little</em> different; people’s private views are more rightist than their public views. This is essentially the “silent majority” thesis, reskinned. It’s why Reddit is more right-wing than Twitter is.</p>
      <p>Here’s the problem; people are actually terrible liars. It takes a lot of cognitive effort to parrot beliefs you don’t believe; a lot of people in the Motte seem to be good at this, but I suspect among the “average person” it’s a lot more difficult. Furthermore, lying about your beliefs inherently makes you feel like you’re a coward, because if you were more brave or more high-status you could get away with telling the truth. There’s an easy solution to this, of course; all you have to do is truly believe what you’re saying! Thus, over time people’s brains will rationalize their beliefs to minimize cognitive dissonance, just like in Roger Sperry’s famous split-brain experiments. If you have to mouth left-wing platitudes in public, you will often eventually come to believe them.</p>
      <p>This is why censorship, social shaming and no-platforming <em>works</em>, and this is what humans have been doing for thousands of years, Catholics against Protestants, Christians against Muslisms, Fascists against Communists. The reason that we have (or at least used to have) this truce we call liberal democracy is not that illiberal methods and tactics (the “Dark Arts”) don’t <em>work</em>, but because both sides used to be afraid of retaliation from the other side. That’s not the case anymore, unfortunately. And although I’m sympathetic to the project of getting both sides to put down their illiberal “weapons”, you first have to acknowledge that they are weapons.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>