<post>
  <author>Niebelfader</author>
  <date>2021-01-13T05:20:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/gj31t47/</link>
  <title>Are makeup companies to blame for unwanted sexual attention?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>A little prosaic compared to most of the fare recently, but I'll give it a go anyway:</p>
      <p>
        <em>China: Make-up wipes ad pulled over victim-blaming claims</em>
      </p>
      <p>From the Beeb: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-china-55628587">https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-china-55628587</a></p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>A Chinese company has apologised and pulled an advertisement for make-up remover wipes after it sparked outrage for allegedly victim-blaming women.</p>
        <p>The ad by Purcotton, which has gone viral, shows a woman wiping away her make-up to scare off a male stalker.</p>
        <p>Social media users condemned it as it insinuated women were to blame for unwanted sexual attention.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The ad in question: <a href="https://youtu.be/kSzFOaRVuwQ">https://youtu.be/kSzFOaRVuwQ</a></p>
      <p>A few fun things to unpack here.</p>
      <p>Firstly, I concur with the commentators at least that the ad indeed <em>intends</em> to portray what they claim it to portray: woman gets stalked and wipes off her makeup to comedically disincentivise the imminent molestation. I wouldn't think it especially wise marketing to hinge your publicity on "Lol rape", but then again I'm not a Chinese woman; maybe this <em>will</em> gin up sales in the PRC market. I'm going to file the question of the business case under "I don't have enough cultural context to judge".</p>
      <p>For my second point, an experiment: mute the sound, then watch the ad again. Absent the artificial sinister music hacking our lizard-brains, what's <em>actually shown</em> here? Man is walking behind woman at night... and she, the character, plus we, the audience, infer that this is stalking? He taps her on the shoulder. Rape time? Or asking her the time? I note also that he's being more prosocial than she is by wearing his coof mask; perhaps he's just going to ask her to not be a covidiot and cover up, please don't kill my grandma. That everyone's brain went to imminent molestation seems kinda like paranoid misandry when we actually analyse the video without the musical score.</p>
      <p>The third point I want to make is the one I think is the most interesting: the "women were to blame for unwanted sexual attention" bit.</p>
      <p>I think <em>unwanted sexual attention</em> is one of those superweapon phrases. Like Vauban's star fort, it is configured such that all angles of attack are perilous; the very linguistic terrain conspires against the interrogator. It's biggest bulwark is probably the "unwanted" part, as it's unfalsifiable. It is fulfilled or not by the internal brain-state of the accuser <em>and</em> it cannot be verified by anyone other than the accuser. This gives her complete control over both whether the characterisation is true as a matter of fact <em>and</em> precludes anyone else of investigating it as a matter of fact; in terms of a complete defense it's overkill, almost.</p>
      <p>Then there's the "sexual attention" bit, which is so vague as to give the rhetorical weapon nigh-unlimited range. In the ad we see (what is supposed to be interpreted as) stalking. Now, criminal stalking itself is a slippery enough concept placed against freedom of movement, but let's leave that for another day and provisionally accept for the purpose of discussion that there is a point at which unwanted sexual attention legitimately becomes <em>your action is bad and you should feel bad</em>, e.g. persistent stalking harrassment. However, as I'm sure Motte and Bailey afficionados are aware, the term has been applied in cases to which reasonable people may disagree as to whether the action is bad and you should feel bad: </p>
      <p>• Conversation-starters from unattractive men</p>
      <p>• Physical contact (pats on the shoulder, hugs) that are plausible-deniability platonic but she's not be 100% on board with it, and she thinks he enjoyed it <em>wrong</em></p>
      <p>• Fapping over leaked nudes, or pirated porn</p>
      <p>• Construction-workers wolf-whistling</p>
      <p>• Construction-workers <em>following you with their eyes</em></p>
      <p>• Construction-workers not doing anything you notice but they're undressing you in their mind</p>
      <p>Where we draw the line here is interesting on its own, but the reason the article drew my eye specifically was the insistence that women <em>aren't</em> to blame for unwanted sexual attention. It's like... well, what did you think all that nice make-up was going to do? Make you <em>less</em> attractive to men? Or only make you attractive to men you want attention from, magically excluding low-status males from its thrall? A feminist ex of mine once insisted to me that she really did wear make-up with no consideration for men: its purpose was to satiate her own vanity and make other women jelly. This is at least logically coherent (if, to me, wildly implausible), but even if you're invoking the Doctrine of Double Effect, typically one still accepts <em>responsibility</em> for the undesired side-effects.</p>
      <p>Example: one might perform an ethical calculus which says that invading Afghanistan is worth it to stop the Taliban, even when you accept that you will generate grievances amongst the Afghani populace for the inevitable nonzero number of weddings you'll mis-target and cluster-bomb. One does not then say "I'm not responsible for that wedding bombing"; rather, one says "Yes this bad thing happened and yes I'm responsible and yes I accept that this is a legitimate black mark against me... BUT when taken together with all the successfully neutralised terrorist training camps nearby, it was worth it on balance and I'm ethically in the white on a net measure".</p>
      <p>Analogously, you might think that putting on all the make-up you want is worth it as an exercise in vanity and freedom... but you know full well (or at least you should know full well) that in doing so you're gonna (advertently or not) cluster-bomb non-Chad men's penises with your smokin' hot lashes and DSL. Saying "<em>I'm</em> the victim when heads turn to follow me", rather than the perpetrator, seems to me an unprincipled exception to the general rule of how "responsibility" works.</p>
      <p>If we were just talking about rape and stalking, sure: reactions must be proportionate and stalking a chick because her eyeshadow turned you on is not proportionate. But "unwanted sexual attention" is used to cover much more than that. I mean, trying to strike up a conversation because her eyeshadow turned you on may absolutely be unwanted sexual attention (as mentioned above, it's unfalsifiable, and to claim that it happened constitutes a self-fulfilling prophecy), but under what possible reasoning can you blame the <em>man</em>? And if you can't blame the man, there's only one other actor left in this play, so by process of elimination...</p>
      <p>
        <em>EDIT, my browser ate this final paragraph on my initial posting:</em>
      </p>
      <p>HOWEVER, then try the following on for size. Say there's no make-up involved at all. You just happen to have rolled a natural 20 on CHA and were born in the body of Venus herself. Men's heads turn after you and their codpieces get claustrophobia even if you go out with bed-hair and the frumpiest sweater in your wardrobe. Now the woman didn't <em>do</em> anything - perhaps she even down-dressed intentionally. Where does culpability lie for her exasperation at being hit on 10 times every subway commute now? Having not acted to increase her attention draw at all, now it <em>can't</em> be her responsibility that she... attracts attraction. But the men's acts haven't changed, and in the previous paragraph I absolved them for said act, so...?</p>
      <p>I notice I am confused.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>