<post>
  <author>PM_ME_UR_OBSIDIAN</author>
  <date>2021-01-12T01:07:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/giy6vx5/</link>
  <title>Who is to blame for Ashli Babbitt's death?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2021/01/who-dies-for-trump-the-case-of-capitol-riots-ashli-babbitt.html?utm_campaign=nym&amp;utm_medium=s1&amp;utm_source=tw">Who Dies for Donald Trump?</a>
      </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“I actually saw it first on video when I was on the phone with multiple hospitals trying to find her,” said Kayla Joyce, 29, who said she is the mutual live-in girlfriend of Babbitt and her husband, Aaron. “We found out through the news. Through live television.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Ashli Babbitt was polyamorous? Horseshoe theory strikes again.</p>
      <p>Ever since I saw the video of her being shot, her expression's stuck with me. She had "this was not supposed to happen" written across her face. A different person could have predicted this outcome considering how apparently insistent the people behind the door were that they would shoot anyone who'd try to come through, but not her.</p>
      <p>Between student protests and especially psytrance festivals I've met a fair few people who think their history is already written, that they're not going to win stupid prizes regardless of how many stupid games they play. I'm thinking of a specific archetype, mostly women in their twenties and thirties, bubbly and agreeable, way into astrology, often naive or reckless. Often polyamorous. Rarely career-oriented though.</p>
      <p>I can't say that Ashli Babbitt embodied this archetype, I'm writing this off not much more than a hunch. But if she's anything like the people I know, then society failed her. Capitol police failed her when they didn't stop her anywhere between the steps of the Capitol and the one door that Could Not Be Passed. Right-wingers failed her every time they didn't denounce QAnon as the cult that it is. Progressives failed her when they overplayed their hand to such an extent that Trump the presidential candidate became palatable to so many. Her educators failed her when they didn't impress upon her how seriously the State takes potential threats to its legitimacy. There's an infinite regress of blame coming out of her death.</p>
      <p>In 2012, a friend of mine went to the <a href="https://montreal.ctvnews.ca/multiple-injuries-106-arrests-at-victoriaville-tuition-riot-1.805433">Victoriaville student protest turned riot</a>, crossed police lines, and attempted to break into the ruling provincial party's Congress. Somehow he didn't get shot. Guns somehow didn't seem to appear on either side of the 2012 student protests. At the worst there were baton rounds, which cost a friend of a friend his eye, and another all of her front teeth. </p>
      <p>Obviously Québec politics are small poutine compared to the US federal politics, so perhaps the stakes were lower. I'm just glad my friend came of age in 2012 Québec rather than 2020 U.S.A.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>