<post>
  <author>sp8der</author>
  <date>2021-01-16T19:18:05Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kuxp17/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_11/gjhs727/</link>
  <title>Wokeness as luxury belief system, status signaling framework, and/or religion in the US versus UK</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Maybe this is one of those stark differences between the UK and America.</p>
      <p>I forget where I first read it, it might well have been an SSC post that I can't recall the name of, or an article about Luxury Beliefs, but I do remember reading a statement about how it was usually the well to-do that engaged the most in piety rituals, having, as they did, no need to worry about the material matters of money, food, etc. "Spiritual welfare", then, comes after material welfare is taken care of. Then you have the time and the spare money to waste on grand displays of virtue. Ordinary people have too much to worry about to be able to afford to worry about their spiritual health too.</p>
      <p>And this seemed to ring true for me. Religious belief seems mostly confined to people like Jacob Rees-Mogg here, odd relics of a bygone era, secure in their old ways because they're secure in their old money and haven't been forced to change. In working class northern England, I don't think I knew a single religious person throughout my time at school, except for the kindly old lady next door, even if we did all have to sing trite hymns in assembly most days (my mother got called up to the school when I was aged 6 to ask if there was some family objection to religion since I steadfastly refused to sing. When questioned, apparently my answer was "the songs are just rubbish.").</p>
      <p>Difference aside, I have another hypothesis reconcile this, and to explain America:</p>
      <p>They're not less religious, they just have a different religion. Specifically, the woke religion. This provides them their spiritual need to feel like good, moral people, and an outlet for them to display performative piety.</p>
      <p>Fashion, if you've ever seen <em>The Devil Wears Prada</em>, works like a treadmill. Here, I'll let Miranda Priestly explain: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In 2002, Oscar de la Renta did a collection of cerulean gowns. And then I think it was Yves Saint Laurent… wasn’t it who showed cerulean military jackets? [...] And then cerulean quickly showed up in the collections of eight different designers. And then it, uh, filtered down through the department stores and then trickled on down into some tragic Casual Corner where you, no doubt, fished it out of some clearance bin.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>People will always want to emulate class and opulence, even if they have none themselves. Here in the UK, for a real life example, Burberry suffered a massive reputation hit as counterfeits of its signature patterns were adopted by lower-class, often violent criminal types in an attempted display of class. Burberry became "chav shite", nobody would dare wear it for fear of being associated with the council housed and violent. But this shows that what the upper classes adopt, eventually so too will the lower classes, in an attempt to display trappings above their station and take some of the reflected status for themselves.</p>
      <p>So too, I suspect, does this work for beliefs. The upper middle class adopts some Luxury Belief and, wishing to appear upper middle class themselves, eventually this filters on down to the lower classes, who pick it up. And then the upper middle class moves on, their Luxury no longer luxurious, they need some new source of ostentation to display how much better than everyone else they are.</p>
      <p>And, just like fashion, it all eventually comes around again! Yesterday's high fashion is today's outdated garbage, but tomorrow it will be retro and cool again! Once it slips out of the lower class's repertoire, it becomes "safe" to revisit again.</p>
      <p>And this, I expect, governs the difference between the UK and the USA: The UK has already completed this cycle, the religious-ness has filtered out of the lower classes as uncool, and JRM et al can now lean on it safely once more, with no fear of being confused for a lower class individual "pretending". In the USA, you're still on the downstroke. It's still on its way out. I think, if we look at reported religiosity over time, the numbers would bear this out? That the UK's decline started earlier and has progressed further than the US' fall?</p>
      <p>So that's my hypothesis: The upper classes in America have migrated to a new religion, a new Luxury Belief system, the woke religion, because their old one was adopted by too many of the lower class scum for it to serve as a signal of their better-ness anymore. And it just hasn't filtered out of the lower classes yet.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>