<post>
  <note>Goes along with 109\TheEgosLastStand-20210405123609 and 106\TheEgosLastStand-20210315125130 are all part of the Chauvin Trial.  Parts 2, 5, and 6 were not converted into block content, linked from (r/thethread/comments/q2u01n/quality_contributions_report_for_march_2021/).  May make more sense to add together into a single mega-entry than have as standalones.</note>
  <author>TheEgosLastStand</author>
  <date>2021-03-29T13:00:54Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mfj47c/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_29_2021/gsole3w/</link>
  <title>Derek Chauvin Trial Week 3</title>
  <category>
    <li>civilization</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Chauvin Trial Week 3: Defining Crimes Is Hard</strong>
      </p>
      <p>Voir dire is complete! We had the 14th and final juror on Monday and the 15th, just-in-case-shit-happens juror on Tuesday. With such a short week, there’s not much to report on but I managed to think of a couple things:</p>
      <p>First, 9 women and 5 men will likely serve on this jury (this may change to 8 women and 6 men if some fuckery happens b/c the 15th, just-in-case juror was a man). I wish I had stated this beforehand but I predicted ahead of time more women would serve on this jury because, in general, I find more women get picked for jury service than men. I have a hunch this is because women are more likely to say what the questioning attorneys and judge want to hear, and men are more likely than the average woman to say something that upsets the status quo like ‘fuck the police your Honor!’ during jury selection, thus weeding them out. This is just a hunch based on experience, though. However, originally it had looked like I was wrong because 6 of the first 9 selected were men, but then 2 of those men were sent home <em>after</em> being selected when the judge discovered that the settlement news had interfered with their ability to be fair and impartial. After that it was basically all women selected to serve.</p>
      <p>Second, the judge announced either this week or last that he will not release the juror’s names “until it is safe to do so.” Personally, I think this is incredibly irresponsible and the judge should <em>never</em> release the jurors’ names (though they should be free to reveal themselves, obviously). Story time: the very first murder trial I witnessed in the jurisdiction I practice in occurred after a man was shot to death on his own lawn. Why was he shot you ask? Well, he had been picked up by robbers to work on a car for them very shortly after they had committed the robbery. The money, the items they stole, the masks and guns, etc., were all still in the car when they picked up the victim. The victim then snitched, anonymously, that it was them who committed the robbery. Sometime thereafter, the courthouse <em>accidentally released the victim’s name publicly as a witness in the robbery case, and the defendants found out he was a snitch and they had members of their squad fucking murder him</em>. Granted, this was a witness who snitched and not a juror, but I think this story is analogous enough and the message is clear: do not release their names <em>just in fucking case</em>. You don’t know how crazy and vengeful people are and how they will react. I have never heard of juror’s names being released like this and I don't think they should <em>ever</em> be released under any circumstances.</p>
      <p>But, since I didn’t have a ton to write about in the ~1.5 days of voir dire, I figured I’d do some digging on the charges Chauvin faces and some definitions/caselaw, etc.</p>
      <p>The first charge Chauvin faces is second-degree unintentional murder (Minnesota Statute 609.19.2(1)), which means “caus[ing] the death of a human being, without intent to effect the death of any person, while committing or attempting to commit a felony offense other than criminal sexual conduct in the first or second degree with force or violence or a drive-by shooting,” aka felony murder. Interestingly, though, the charged underlying felony in this case is third-degree assault (helpfully defined as “[w]hoever assaults another and inflicts substantial bodily harm”...yeah I love when the definition of assault includes the word assault, but this is law we’re talking about, not sense-making. I think the definition of assault is <a href="https://www.revisor.mn.gov/statutes/cite/609.02">here at subsection 10 if you’re interested</a>). It’s pretty rare, from my experience, for jurisdictions to allow third-degree assault as the predicate felony for felony murder. Usually, felony assault and felony murder <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felony_murder_rule#Elements">merge</a> but <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/minnesota/supreme-court/1984/c5-83-87-2.html">Minnesota rejects applying the merger doctrine to this scenario</a>. If Minnesota applied the merger doctrine like many jurisdictions do, this charge would not be possible with assault as the underlying felony.</p>
      <p>Skipping past issues with third-degree assault, let’s talk about “cause,” which is probably the ultimate issue in this case. The definition of “cause” for purposes of this statute means that, in Derek Chauvin’s case, his actions are a <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/minnesota/supreme-court/1989/c8-88-1771-2.html">“substantial causal factor”</a> in Floyd’s death. Or, it must be shown that Chauvin’s acts injured Floyd, and those injuries led to his death. Honestly, these definitions did not help me very much--I found Minnesota’s caselaw lacking in this area and, unfortunately, I do not have access to their jury instructions because MN charges money for them (bastards...those jury instructions might have helped my research a great deal). </p>
      <p>The defense can attempt to show that the drugs and Floyd’s underlying health conditions were a superseding cause (which Minnesota confusingly calls a ‘superseding intervening’ cause, which <em>I</em> was always taught are distinct concepts), thus preventing Chauvin’s conviction of this charge, but to show that they must establish (as far as I can tell) that <a href="https://caselaw.findlaw.com/mn-supreme-court/1576335.html">the drugs/conditions, by themselves, caused Floyd’s death</a>.</p>
      <p>The second charge is third-degree murder (Minnesota Statute 609.195(a)), meaning “[w]hoever, without intent to effect the death of any person, causes the death of another by perpetrating an act eminently dangerous to others and evincing a depraved mind, without regard for human life, is guilty of murder in the third degree,” aka depraved-heart murder.</p>
      <p>Slightly elaborated, a depraved mind is engaging in conduct that <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/minnesota/court-of-appeals/2020/a19-0708.html">the actor is aware creates a substantial and unjustifiable risk to human life and consciously disregards that risk</a>. But it’s defined elsewhere as “ordinary symptoms of a wicked or depraved spirit, regardless of social duty and fatally bent on mischief” and “[a] mind which has become inflamed by emotions, disappointments, and hurt to such degree that it ceases to care for human life and safety,” so I’m not sure I can say what a depraved mind really is. But I can say that researching this led me to one of the most confusing, hair-splitting sentences in the history of caselaw:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.courthousenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/mn-noor.pdf">“In sum, we are mindful of the statements in jury-instruction caselaw stating that a conviction of third-degree murder is not possible if the death-causing act was directed at a <em>particular person</em>. But other supreme court caselaw indicates that a third-degree murder conviction may be based on conduct directed at a <em>single person, and even a targeted person</em>.”</a> ...dafuq?</p>
      <p>That quote nearly broke my brain; what the fuck is the difference between a particular person and a targeted person? Fortunately, elsewhere this opinion <em>sorta</em> clarifies that if the depraved-mind conduct is directed at a person with <em>intent to kill that person</em>, third-degree murder is not possible, but if the depraved-mind conduct is directed at a person <em>with no intent to kill any particular person</em>, third-degree murder is possible. But still, fucking fix your shit Minnesota Court of Appeals.</p>
      <p>The final charge is second-degree manslaughter (Minnesota Statute 609.205(1)), i.e. you are guilty if you  “cause[] the death of another . . . by [your] <em>culpable negligence</em> whereby [you] create[] an unreasonable risk, and consciously take[ the] chance[] of causing death or great bodily harm to another.” Culpable negligence seems to be the money language here, so that’s where I’ll focus.</p>
      <p>Culpable negligence borrows a lot from the tort definition of negligence. Further defined, <a href="https://caselaw.findlaw.com/mn-supreme-court/1501101.html">culpable negligence means gross negligence + recklessness. Gross negligence = a gross deviation from the standard of care a reasonable person would observe in the actor’s circumstance (objective standard), and recklessness = an actual, conscious disregard for the risk created by the conduct (subjective standard). Further, for criminal liability to attach, the defendant's breach of duty (i.e., the lack of adherence to the appropriate standard of care) must be the proximate cause of the victim's death</a>. So, did Chauvin “grossly” and consciously deviate from an applicable standard of care towards Floyd, thereby proximately causing Floyd’s death? If so, he should be found guilty of second-degree manslaughter. </p>
      <p>I hope this post has made some sense--I wrote it without tons of preparation and with some booze in my system, and it definitely falls short of my official legal-writing standards, but I want to make these posts engaging and understandable. And I am not gonna go too much into predictions because juries are notoriously hard to predict and I haven’t seen all the evidence. But the TL;DR is, this trial is largely going to be about what caused Floyd’s death. Was it the drugs and/or his underlying health conditions? Was it Chauvin? Was it both, and if so, what level of blame can be assigned to each? The more the blame the jury assigns to Chauvin, the more likely he is convicted of at least one of the above charges. I cannot predict what the jury will do, but I do predict the big fight will be defense and prosecution experts fighting over Floyd’s autopsy and the likely cause of his death. And that will probably be slightly on the boring side, but dammit I’m going to watch anyway.</p>
      <p>Opening statements start this morning, let’s fucking go!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>