<post>
  <note>Along with 109\TheEgosLastStand-20210405123609 and 108\TheEgosLastStand-20210329130054, all part of the Chauvin Trial.  Parts 2, 5, and 6 were not converted into block content, linked from (r/thethread/comments/q2u01n/quality_contributions_report_for_march_2021/).  May make more sense to add together into a single mega-entry than have as standalones.</note>
  <author>TheEgosLastStand</author>
  <date>2021-03-15T12:51:30Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/m5eawi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_15_2021/gr09pv7/</link>
  <title>Derek Chauvin Trial Week 1</title>
  <category>
    <li>civilization</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Derek Chauvin’s trial began this past week and I’ve been watching basically every minute of the coverage. I skip all the expert analysis stuff because that’s a bit much imo, but I have watched the questioning of every juror so far. </p>
      <p>As a quick aside, I genuinely suggest you watch part of jury selection if you haven’t and are basically unfamiliar with it. You really do get a strange hodgepodge of nearly every type of person imaginable in jury selection and the attorneys regularly ask questions normally reserved for places like the culture war thread. Hearing everyday people wrestle with these questions can be both interesting and, at times, hilarious or cringeworthy.</p>
      <p>Quick update and some notes on the current situation:</p>
      <p>-We have 7 jurors in week 1! Recently, there was a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/lv2rb7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_march_01_2021/gpd63ok/">post in the culture war thread</a> wondering how they would even get jurors. A reasonable question, but about 1 in 7 jurors that were given the questionnaire (i.e., the original jury pool) were selected to serve, and about 1 in 4 jurors that made it past the first round of for-cause excusals were selected to serve. Juror selection has gone relatively smoothly, imo, and it really hasn’t been <em>that</em> much harder to find jurors for this trial than any other trial in my experience. We’re already halfway done with picking jurors and the trial proper isn’t scheduled to begin for two more weeks.</p>
      <p>-The 3rd degree murder charge was reinstated on Wednesday (i think), giving the prosecution one more avenue for a guilty verdict. 3rd degree murder in Minnesota is essentially depraved-heart murder. The charge had been previously dismissed by the trial court because he did not believe the alleged conduct could fit the definition of 3rd degree murder, but the Minnesota court of appeals reversed that decision.</p>
      <p>-The Defense was granted an astounding 15 peremptory challenges (i.e., they can get rid of 15 prospective jurors for basically any reason). Also, the prosecution only got 9 peremptories. I’ve seen quite a few trials, but I have never seen one side get that many peremptories, nor have I seen one side get more than the other. Going into week 2, the defense still has 7 peremptories left and the prosecution still has 5.</p>
      <p>-Probably stating the obvious a bit, this case has a really weird dynamic where the prosecution, normally attempting to find jurors who are trustworthy of police, are now trying to find jurors who are more skeptical of police. The defense, on the flip side, are trying to seat jurors more likely to see police in a positive light. Not a big deal or anything, but this is really odd relative to a run-of-the-mill trial so I wanted to mention it.</p>
      <p>-I wanted to gripe for a minute about Batson challenges. Batson challenges are a suggestion, usually by the defense, that the other party has used a peremptory challenge for an unlawful reason. The unlawful reason could be race, sex, ethnicity, or religion, but they are almost always raised in the context of race. And even though you cannot challenge a juror for their race no matter what their race is, these challenges almost exclusively are used when a nonwhite juror is excused, <em>no matter how reasonable the challenge is</em>. </p>
      <p>The prosecution raised two of them so far, and in line with my unfortunate experiences with Batson challenges, they were both about race and both raised after the juror in question was properly struck by the defense.</p>
      <p>I find these challenges incredibly annoying. First, they are almost never raised in good faith. From the pattern of practice in which it is used, it is clear to me Batson challenges are raised <em>automatically</em> by parties when the other side strikes someone who looks even vaguely ethnic. Oftentimes, when a Batson challenge is raised I cannot even tell what race the stricken juror <em>even is</em> and I doubt the challenging party can either, but hey, they were struck and are not white, right? Might as well raise the challenge. </p>
      <p>Second, it really slows things down. Usually by the time attorneys are using their peremptories, it’s been a long fucking day. The jurors are brought in first thing in the morning, and by about 2-3 p.m., after lots of administrative crap is taken care of, they are finally being officially chosen. When one party raises a challenge, the proceedings stop. The court then has a side bar, where one side explains their challenge, then the other side responds, then the judge makes a decision and a record about their decision. All in all, it adds probably 10 or so minutes to a trial per challenge (plus, the juror, excited because they were just told they were being sent home, now is asked to stay so the parties can argue about them, which is both awkward and unfortunate for the juror). Not a big deal, but when you’re already several hours into this thing and you’re both tired and pretty close to having a jury selected so you can move on, <em>and</em> you’re pretty sure there’s no good reason for the challenge in the first instance, it can really get on your nerves.</p>
      <p>I plan on keeping up with this trial so I will probably post more going forward.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>