<post>
  <author>2cimarafa</author>
  <date>2021-06-23T21:56:41Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/o4ooc7/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_21_2021/h2tg1un/</link>
  <title>"The ever-growing waves of violent crime, property theft, muggings, rapes, occasional civic unrest and so on, the endless tent cities, the entire corners of Paris, Lyon, Marseilles and other great cities that are dirty and disgusting and crime-ridden, handed over to the underclass aren't the consequence of 'Islam.'"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Conservative Anglos bear a strange misunderstanding about what the challenge in France actually is. Macron's actions, designed to shore up support because he knows he will face either a rightist LR candidate or Le Pen in the election are transparent, but ultimately impactless. </p>
      <p>It is hard to say this so repeatedly, but here it is again - <strong>the issue in France isn't "radicalization".</strong> Or indeed 'Islam'. Forcing mosques attended largely by middle-aged Algerian men who immigrated in 1975 to agree that they support "French values" (much like I check the user rights agreement on a piece of software) isn't going to deal with the fundamental cause of France's deep social malaise and the rise of the radical right. </p>
      <p>The real issue is - as Houellebecq describes - the fact that the (largely second and third generation) maghrebi underclass, particularly young men, exist entirely outside of French society. The ever-growing waves of violent crime, property theft, muggings, rapes, occasional civic unrest and so on, the endless tent cities, the entire corners of Paris, Lyon, Marseilles and other great cities that are dirty and disgusting and crime-ridden, handed over to the underclass aren't the consequence of "Islam". Plenty of Muslim countries, including conservative ones, don't have them. Most of these young men are not religious in any significant way; they will not weep and gnash if Macron makes a Mosque they never visit agree to a policy they don't understand or care about. As 'Submission' jokes, a dose of conservative Islam well implemented might well be a positive for many of these listless people. </p>
      <p>Macron could forcibly convert every young male in the banlieues to Roman Catholicism tomorrow and, except for perhaps preventing a few terrorist attacks, France's trajectory would remain unchanged. I sympathize with those honorable Muslims whose following of a tradition a thousand years in the making may suffer because the land they inhabit is unwilling to confront the toxic effects of the labor, immigration and housing policy that produced the banlieues and their inhabitants.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>