<post>
  <author>Rov_Scam</author>
  <date>2021-06-18T20:27:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/o2hcop/friday_fun_thread_for_june_18_2021/h290syi/</link>
  <title>As another user put it--"probably the best takes on the demise of counterculture and the failure of the New Left I’ve seen in a long time."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <strong>Moronically Long Response, Part I</strong>
      </p>
      <p>I think this song works best as an examination of the state of leftist revolutionary movements in the late '60s. First, a little history. Marx famously declared in the Communist Manifesto that the inherent contradictions of capitalism would inevitably lead to the proletariat rising up and seizing the means of production, ushering in a true communist state (to state it simply). 50 years after he wrote this, the revolution still hadn't come, and people began to wonder why. Lenin and the Bolsheviks suggested that the masses were too ignorant to go it alone, and needed to be shepherded by an elite revolutionary vanguard. This produced a communist revolution in Russia, but it failed to ignite the kind of worldwide movement that Marx had predicted. In fact, it sort of ran contrary to Marx, as Russia was at the time one of the least industrialized countries in Europe, and Marx had suggested that a large industrial proletarian class was a prerequisite to revolution. Meanwhile, capitalism continued apace in the industrialized world. </p>
      <p>By the 1920s it was clear that the kind of organic revolution that Marx had predicted was not going to take place, and a number of thinkers sought explanations. Gramsci posited that capitalism had been successful at imbuing the masses with a false consciousness that he termed as Hegemony. the general idea was that capitalism so fully dominates those subjected to it that the exploited begin to believe that the system is operating within their best interests. It thus becomes all the more imperative that the proletariat be educated by an elite vanguard so that they can see where their true interests lie. Underlying this whole disconnect was the fact that conditions for industrial workers had improved greatly between Marx's time and Gramsci's. Marx thought that the only way workers could end the horrid conditions they were being subjected to was by overthrowing the system entirely. Instead, they had merely moderated capitalism's impact by winning gradual reforms—higher pay, limited hours, improved safety conditions, etc. To the leftists, however, these reforms were merely institutional; instead of ending a system that was inherently exploitative, the capitalists had instead thrown a few crumbs the workers' way so that they could just barely stave off revolution. But if only the workers understood that they were being hoodwinked, etc., etc.</p>
      <p>By the 1960s, most leftists had given up on the idea that the communist revolution would ever be led by the working class. The postwar economic boom and strength of unions meant that most industrial workers had entirely too much invested in the current system to upend it entirely; average folks with refrigerators and two cars who always have enough to eat are disinclined to jeopardize their situation. The idea that these people were being exploited, however, didn't go away. This was also the beginning of the age of consumerism, so the narrative changed such that now the proletariat was being bribed by the availability of cheap consumer goods. That capitalism was against the best interests of the working class was accepted as axiomatic by academic leftists—they never took seriously the idea that most of the working class actually liked capitalism and genuinely thought it was in their best interests. They were merely unenlightened sheep. </p>
      <p>Operating in this milieu were European émigré philosophers who had brought leftist ideas to American universities after the Nazis took power in Europe. These philosophers, among them the critical theorists Adorno and Horkheimer, came to the conclusion that students should be the new revolutionary vanguard. And so began the New Left. No longer would socialist operatives spend their time in factories organizing labor unions, they would spend time at universities organizing students. The New Left completely untethered leftism from its traditional concern with the industrial proletariat. At the same time, it embraced critical theory's ideas about power structures to expand Marx's ideas to anyone who presumably lacked power. This resolved the inherent contradiction of needing an elite vanguard to effect revolution—if the oppressed are defined as anyone outside of the existing power structure, then anyone who claims to be oppressed certainly qualifies. It doesn't matter if you're the upper-middle-class son of a lawyer attending a prestigious university; if you lack any real political power you're oppressed. And the young almost without exception lack political power. And even if it did seem a bit rich to claim you're oppressed yourself, there were still plenty of marginalized people out there for you to advocate on behalf of. This is the whole SDS-style counterculture the 1960s is famous for.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>