<post>
  <author>dedicating_ruckus</author>
  <date>2020-01-15T22:26:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/fehzrlr/</link>
  <title>Trump Supporters - Defending the Ingroup</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Rather than "making Outgroup eat shit", think of it as "defending Ingroup from Outgroup's nefarious plans".</p>
      <p>The general worldview underlying Trump support (as I see it) goes something like:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>the Left has an active agenda for subjugating the Right in politics and destroying its way of life, and is currently engaged in implementing that agenda</li>
        <li>despite winning many elections, the Right has not succeeded in rolling back or permanently damaging that agenda; the best result has been a clearly-temporary stalemate</li>
        <li>this is because the Right's standard-bearers have been systematically unwilling to vigorously oppose that agenda, even when given the power to do so</li>
        <li>they're unwilling to do that because the Left uses control of information outlets to smear any opposition to the Left's aggressive agenda as being immoral</li>
        <li>thus, an effective standard-bearer for the Right must be willing to ignore the Left's claims of immorality, no matter how persistent or universal</li>
        <li>Trump is the only significant Rightist politician in (a while) to show willingness to do this</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Rightists are willing to support Trump, despite all his flaws, because he's seen as an effective fighter against the Left. And <em>the reason they're so desperate for an effective fighter</em> is because they see the Left as holding a commanding position, actively plotting to use it to harm the Right, and the existing Right as being devoid of any strong defenders.</p>
      <p>You can quibble with the real-world correctness of this worldview -- it certainly is wrong in at least some details -- but I hope this helps you understand something about what Trump supporters are thinking.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>