<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-01-11T20:00:26Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/ekpcmb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_06/fdxtqsn/</link>
  <title>Examples of Conceptual Transformations</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>(Apologies for length - I wrote this in a hurry so didn't have time to make it shorter)</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Got any examples?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Certainly, though in terms of bringing out the idea, it might be more helpful for me to give a rough recipe for conceptually interesting/transformational ideas and artworks, so you can identify cases that are most obvious and particularly meaningful to you. With that in mind, here are a few general points I'd flag, with a selection of examples mixed in.</p>
      <p>(1) The most important thing to note is that typically we're only <em>really</em> aware of conceptual transformations that we live through ourselves (hence why so many of my examples below come from videogames - I've been an active participant in more than half the history of videogames, so the transformational moments are vivid to me). Most of us have probably had the experience of introducing to someone younger than ourselves  a pioneering piece of music, movie, TV show, or videogame that blew our minds and finding ourselves disappointed when they're underwhelmed by it. You may have had this experience with, e.g., Mario 64, or Seinfeld, or NWA, or even Toy Story. "It's okay I guess," says your friend, "but I feel like X did this kind of thing better." Ah, but you emphasise, no, this work <em>came before</em> X and <em>made X possible.</em> "Oh, I get it. So it's like, historically significant." No! you want to say. There's more to it than that! It's not just a point on a timeline - it created the culture you live in today: you are now living in the Mario 64/Seinfeld/NWA/Toy Story universe! I feel this way talking to my dad about the Beatles. To me, I can hear that the Beatles are <em>good</em>, and <em>eclectic</em>, and I <em>know</em> that they're historically important, but I can't grok how transformational it was for my dad to hear them. There's a whole entry about this kind of thing on TVtropes called <a href="https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/SeinfeldIsUnfunny">Seinfeld is Unfunny</a>, but I think the point is more profound than that entry really brings out, and it's essentially the same principle as Thomas Kuhn's notion of a paradigm shift in science (see's Scott's review of his book <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/01/08/book-review-the-structure-of-scientific-revolutions/">here</a>). The point is that if we grow up in a world defined by a transformational creative breakthrough, it's difficult and perhaps impossible for us to fully get our head around what the world must have been like for people beforehand. We hear how about how Copernicus replaced the geocentric model of the solar system with a heliocentric model, for example, and it's easy to write this up as an impressive bit of astronomy and feel puzzled about why it was so strongly resisted at the time. But it's worth trying to project yourself into the head of a smart person pre-Copernican revolution and think about how the idea of a geocentric universe would shape your views about God, cosmology, the meaning of humanity, the status of humans among other animals, and so on.</p>
      <p>(2) On this note, a common marker for a transformational work of art or idea is that once you've gotten over your initial feeling of awe, panic, wonder, fear, or disgust, suddenly a whole new set of possibilities open up <em>all at once</em>. This is one of the main ways in which we can distinguish transformational creativity from "exploratory creativity", which involves filling out or populating an already established space. Returning to pop culture, you might think something like Skyrim or Far Cry 3 or Game of Thrones are examples of this latter category (though I realise any given example is contestable). "Hey, let's make an X that's like A but contains elements of B." When we encounter works like this, it's like uncovering fog of war in a map we'd already established. By contrast, transformational works are more like those rarer moments in videogames where the boundaries of the map suddenly get expanded in a way we didn't realise was possible and our sense of the gameworld and our possibilities for action within it are dramatically changed. I had something like this experience playing Mario 64 for the first time, but also GTA 3 and Half-Life 2 (that first moment with the gravity gun...) - in all these cases, I immediately though "holy shit, they're going to be able to do so much with this!" My dad says something similar about hearing the Beatles: he immediately knew that pop music would never be the same again. I think emotionally at least there's an analogy with how some people felt when they first stepped out of the vault in Fallout 3, or out of the prison sewer in Oblivion. Very often these transformations rapidly give birth to a new genre (as in the case of HG Wells' work, or Tolkein's, perhaps), as a lot of people suddenly become aware of a <em>new</em> orchard of low-hanging aesthetic fruit all at once and there's a creative goldrush. Turning from art to science again, imagine what you'd feel if you were a geocentric astronomer and you'd just read <em>De revolutionibus orbium coelestium</em>. If it's the sun rather than the earth that's at the centre of the universe, do we still need the idea of the fixed stars? What if the stars were in fact suns like our sun? And if there are other suns other there, could there be other planets? Could some of them contain living things? Perhaps even intelligent beings like ourselves? (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giordano_Bruno">RIP Giordano Bruno</a>)</p>
      <p>(3) You might be wondering whether I can really be seriously comparing Copernicus to the Beatles, let alone Mario 64. Certainly, there's a dramatic difference in cultural significance between these cases, and a quantitative difference in effect; not all instances of transformational creativity tangibly change <em>everything, all once</em>. But I'd still claim there's a qualitative commonality among all these cases: they all involved the emergence of new conceptual frameworks, a change to the map itself rather than a case of filling it out. That's not to deny that cases of 'mere' exploratory creativity can be significant. This is especially true in the case of technology, where things like economies of scale and advertising can mean that a device that wasn't especially creative can have <em>transformational consequences.</em> Arguably the iPhone as a piece of consumer electronics is a case of this - as a device, it didn't do anything strictly new, nor was it the first time most of its features had been packaged together, but thanks to its success, a whole new technological ecosystem was created (there's a case to be made that the Appstore, by contrast, was genuinely a case of transformational creativity). Facebook is another nice case: MySpace had already done the hard work, but by tweaking certain elements, Zuckerberg was able to unleash a merely exploratory-creative product that had transformational effects.</p>
      <p>(4) Related to this, note it can be very hard to tell <em>which</em> ideas and works of art were the original transformational ones. Normally, the great conceptual leaps happen at the frontiers and among the avant garde, and the people who discover the frontier aren't the ones who exploit it. Figuring out when and where the <em>real</em> leaps are made can be challenging in retrospect, as very often the works that usher in the conceptual revolutions in our own minds aren't the ones that deserve the ultimate credit. You can see this when snobs and aficionados get together. "Punk started with the Sex Pistols." "No, it started with the Ramones." "No, it started with New York Dolls." "No, it started with the Velvet Underground and Iggy Pop." How many people who listen to contemporary electronic music know about its origins in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musique_concr%C3%A8te">Musique Concrète</a>? Another example: my dad stopped keeping track of pop music some time in the late 70s (he didn't care for prog rock or punk), and then suddenly discovered Oasis in the mid 90s. For him, they were revolutionary: the harmonies and inventive chord structures of the Beatles fused with the raucous sneer of the Rolling Stones. They spurred him to get interested in pop music all over again, and he fell in love with Britpop and its antecedents like Madchester. But for people who'd been tuning in since the 80s, Oasis were clearly building on the music of people like The Stone Roses and The Smiths, and were more exploratory than creative. Moreover, any complex transformational work will of course have exploratory elements as well as wholly derivative elements. Even though Picasso revolutionised our understanding of the representation of form in <em>Les Demoiselles d'Avignon</em>, he didn't revolutionise our understanding of colour, and in this regard was relying on centuries of prior experimental work with the development of pigments and colour theory. So establishing where transformation ends and where the exploration begins can be hard. But I don't think it's impossible, or that it's <em>just</em> subjective. There really are transformational works of art and ideas and breakthroughs out there, even if their contours can be hard to map.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>