<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-01-16T17:50:50Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/fekcada/</link>
  <title>Analyizing Transinclusive Views of Gender</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This could be beyond my paygrade, but I want to try to flesh out some thoughts I've been having about the concept of gender and how it relates to trans identity. This is not my wheelhouse exactly, but I've seen quite a few good talks about the philosophy and psychology of gender lately and it seems to me that the two most popular transinclusive views of gender these days are as follows.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(1) Self-identification:</strong> someone is a man/woman iff they sincerely claim to identify as a man/woman.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(2) Cluster concept:</strong> someone is a man/woman iff/to the extent that they satisfy a certain number of properties associated with being a man/woman. These include both biological attributes (hairy chest, breasts, penis, etc.) and cultural ones (dressing in 'masculine' ways, adopting gender-specific norms of speech, etc.). We can also add self-identification as a further attribute in the cluster.</p>
      <p>There are straightforward objections to both views. One big objection to the cluster concept view is that it doesn't necessarily respect self-identification. Someone might identify as a man yet fail to satisfy any of the other properties in the 'man' cluster, hence failing to qualify as a man. Another is the fact that it seems uncomfortably close to enshrining gender stereotypes that we take to be oppressive and/or restrictive (e.g., that women wear make up). If someone fails to cleave to a certain part of the gender stereotype, in other words, that might make them <em>less</em> of a man or a woman.</p>
      <p>The main problem with the self-identification view by contrast is that it's a bit mysterious and empty. What does it mean to identify as a man or woman if this doesn't entail identifying oneself as exhibiting or intending to exhibit certain canonical masculine or feminine traits or behaviours?</p>
      <p>What follows is my attempt to answer this question and provide a slightly thicker formulation of the self-identification view. Like I said, this may be beyond my paygrade - I'm '<a href="https://thingofthings.wordpress.com/2015/01/28/cis-by-default/">cis by default</a>' in Ozy's sense of the term, so I welcome correction from  any trans-identifying or trans-adjacent commenters.</p>
      <p>In short, then, I think our sense of gender identity may be <a href="https://www.alleydog.com/glossary/definition.php?term=Experience-Expectant+Plasticity">an experience expectant concept</a> (EEC). An EEC is a concept that is 'innate' in the sense that <em>ceteris paribus</em> the concept emerges universally in the course of childhood development, but does so in a way that relies on the environment to fill in details. Some of the most obvious examples of EECs are things like taboos and profanities. As far as I'm aware, every culture has various local cultural taboos and words or actions that are recognised to be profane or obscene. However, these vary considerably from one culture to the next. There's a bit more to EECs than this, though, insofar as they're usually marked by a particular <em>window of development</em>: the particular content that fills out your EEC is acquired at some stage of childhood and proves surprisingly sticky in later life. Here's<a href="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/4f61/5dbb532f3ce5ab7f2a24f53c5a2ccf53b9f0.pdf">a nice passage from Jonathan Haidt</a> illustrating the point in regard to Japanese children living in the US and their experiences learning about American norms about communication and self-promotion -</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Minoura found that there was a sensitive period for culture learning between the ages of 9 and 15. When children spent a few years in the United States during this period, they developed American ways of interacting with friends and American ways of feeling about problems in interactions. A few years spent in America before that period led to shallower, nonemotional learning about norms and left no lasting effects. A few years spent in America after the age of 15 led to puzzlement and culture shock but to little change in the self.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The picture I'm building up to is roughly this. We're all born with an EEC of our gender identity that tells us whether we're a man or a woman. This doesn't automatically specify norms of masculinity or femininity, but 'soaks them up' from the environment. This concept manifests itself phenomenologically as a strong feeling that one should do as the other boys are doing or do as the other girls are doing. Whether you have a 'man EEC' or a 'woman EEC' could easily be determined in utero or in early development according to this view, even though the specific details aren't filled in until later. This allows us to avoid the dilemma pointed out in <a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=i&amp;source=imgres&amp;cd=&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjt763X1YjnAhXN8uAKHahwBfAQjRx6BAgBEAQ&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fknowyourmeme.com%2Fphotos%2F1066087-daily-struggle&amp;psig=AOvVaw3bc5_YEla4VmpD8lJsocHR&amp;ust=1579281852754978">memes like this</a>. You can absolutely be born with a man EEC or a woman EEC that's at odds with the gender you were assigned at birth, <em>even though gender is socially constructed</em>.</p>
      <p>As an addon to the theory, I'd suggest that perhaps the salience of one's EEC is driven by some kind of internal 'prediction error amplification mechanism'. If your brain is telling you that you're a boy and society is pushing you towards normatively feminine activities and modes of behaviour, damn right the error signal is going to get amplified and become more phenomenologically salient. By contrast, if you're acting in ways that accord with your gender EEC, the error signal will shut up and be quiet. This is the best way I can make sense of the fact that folks who are cis by default aren't particularly aware of 'feeling masculine' or 'feeling feminine'. I can even imagine how the feelings of shame and discomfort that would follow from violating this error signal could explain fetishes some cis men have towards things like sissification.</p>
      <p>This allows us to give a self-identification view that's a bit richer and more interesting than the simple stripped down version sketched above. You're a man if you have a 'man EEC' and a woman if you have a 'woman EEC'. This will involve a distinctive kind of phenomenology that will latch on to normatively masculine or feminine behaviours, but it won't be <em>defined</em> by them. Rather, we all have a distinctive innate kind of thought or feeling about our gender identity that gets coupled to but is not constituted by our society's gender norms. Given that EECs can shift <em>slightly</em> and <em>slowly</em> over the course of one's life, one can also accommodate cases of trans people who decide over time to dress and act in ways that don't necessarily conform with their self-identified gender - they're slowly and painstakingly deconstructing the attitudes that got hoovered up by their EEC in early childhood.</p>
      <p>One downside to this view - like other self-identification views - is that of course is that it's very hard to tell whether someone is being sincere when they claim to identify as a man or a woman. I don't think malicious self-identification is currently a huge problem, but I recognise many people worry about it. But the EEC view has at least one thing going for it in this regard, which is that EECs tend to be very deeply rooted in our minds and very hard to fake. Moreover, as suggested by the Haidt passage above, they often involve a strong affective component. For example, most people exhibit <a href="https://www.sciencefocus.com/the-human-body/why-its-good-to-swear-like-a-champ/">characteristic involuntary physiological responses</a> to slurs in their native language, but I presume they wouldn't have the same response to slurs in other languages or that they've not been suitably exposed to. This raises the possibility that we could develop physiological measures to test whether someone has one gender EEC or another. I realise this may sound dystopian, and I don't like the idea of 'trans tests' any more than sexuality tests, but the very possibility of such tests might placate those who worry that self-identification views are an epistemological black hole.</p>
      <p>I don't know if this view is out there already in the psychological literature or in the metaphysics of sex and gender, but it seems to me to give us everything we want from a theory of gender while respecting self-identification. As I say, I'd love to hear what others think, especially (though not only) from trans-identified people here.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>