<post>
  <author>edalis</author>
  <date>2020-01-14T11:07:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/fed5lvu/</link>
  <title>The Rise of Skywalker was a Romance</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>--The Rise of Skywalker spoilers--</p>
      <p>I think the main issue is that the Star Wars Sequel Trilogy wasn't written as a sci-fi drama. At its core, it was written as a <em>romance.</em> The Rey/Kylo romance is the A-plot, and everything else - the Resistance, the Jedi, Finn, Poe, Luke, Leia, etc is the B-plot. (Note: I'm not saying that it was a <em>well-written</em> romance, merely that many of the plot developments and writing choices make more sense when you see that the Sequel Trilogy was plotted out, first and foremost, as a romance.) </p>
      <p>You can tell by how Adam Driver and Daisy Ridley knew their entire character arcs from early on (<a href="https://screenrant.com/star-wars-9-kylo-ren-adam-driver-story-arc/">https://screenrant.com/star-wars-9-kylo-ren-adam-driver-story-arc/</a>), while everyone else's plot arcs seem to be written on the fly, not set in stone (e.g. Poe's character was meant to die in the early drafts of TFA, the sudden unforeshadowed introduction of Palpatine in TROS, etc). There are multiple plot holes and random inexplicable developments in the B-plot, but Rey and Kylo are the only ones with a solid, coherent storyline - a romance which fulfills standard romance genre conventions - across all three movies. </p>
      <p>Full disclosure now: I'm a huge fan of romance. The romance genre trappings of the Sequel Trilogy was quite apparent to me ever since I watched TFA, but I'll lay it out here:</p>
      <p>In Act 1, TFA, we have Rey (the subject), a plucky, lonely peasant scavenger living in the desert. She gets swept up in a war and meets Kylo (the object). Kylo takes off his helmet and… Kylo is tall, dark and handsome. Kylo is angsty and emotionally tortured. Kylo has long, wavy dark hair. Kylo is royalty, the son of a princess and a dashing rogue. Kylo has a cool "sword" and a swishy flowing cape and wears all black. Presumably, he's rich as well (the First Order sure doesn't seem to be short on cash.) Basically, Kylo fits every romance genre bad boy stereotype. And Kylo is evil and would happily murder everyone else… <em>except for Rey</em>. We see that when he stabs Finn without batting an eye, but instead asks Rey to join him so he can teach her the ways of the Force. (Of course, Rey refuses. He's still evil.) </p>
      <p>In Act 2, they find out that they have a mysterious, "magical" bond. Rey talks to Kylo through their shared bond and gradually becomes close to Kylo. There's a gratuitous shirtless scene. They reach out. They touch hands. Clearly, they could have gone further than that if they hadn't been interrupted by Luke, who is aghast that Rey is consorting with the ~bad boy~. Rey learns that Kylo was actually misunderstood all along - Luke tried to kill him in his sleep. She goes off, into great danger, to reach out to Kylo and turn him good. Kylo kills his master when he tries to make Kylo hurt her. Rey and Kylo fight together, and when united they destroy everything in their path - but it turns out he still wants power, still wants to rule the galaxy. "Join me, <em>please,</em>" Kylo says, hand outstretched, as sparks literally fly around them. Rey, in tears, rejects him again. </p>
      <p>In Act 3, Kylo discovers their most powerful foe yet, who again offers him unlimited power if only he would kill Rey. He reaches out to Rey and tries to get her to join forces with him, but Rey rejects him. Rey fights him again on the ruins of the Death Star, and although he wins and brings her to her knees, he can't bring himself to land the killing blow. Rey, on the other hand, seizes the chance to stab him. She's immediately horrified with herself and heals his wound, while tearfully confessing that she would have taken his hand - Ben's hand. </p>
      <p>After that confession, well, Kylo has all the motivation he needs to turn. They unite to fight Palpatine, she is killed in the battle, and Kylo gives his life to bring her back. They kiss - at the climax of the final act, the subject finally gets the object of her desires - but then Kylo dies, sacrificing his life for hers. </p>
      <p>This trilogy was written primarily as an epic tragic romance, in which Jedi Killer Kylo Ren, Ben Organa Skywalker Solo, galactic royalty, a literal dark Knight, falls in love with the Last Jedi, Rey Nobody, a beautiful peasant girl who collects trash in the desert. The Reylo arc is the only story arc which is largely coherent from beginning to end. The B-plot exists to drive forward the romance A-plot, which is why Rey conveniently develops Force powers as the B-plot demands, why the Resistance is at times horribly outnumbered (down to about ten people at the end of TLJ) and at the end of TROS somehow has enough ships to fill the sky because the B-plot calls for it. The Resistance vs First Order B-plot is only important insofar as it provides a dramatic backdrop to the Reylo A-plot, and when that is resolved, the Resistance handily beats the Final Order <em>offscreen</em>. Finally, Finn is there to fill the part of the romantic rival, the comedic best friend, the good boy to Kylo's bad boy whom Rey firmly rejects in favour of Kylo.</p>
      <p>Viewed as a sci-fi drama, the sequel trilogy is an incoherent mess. But viewed as a romance, it's quite straightforward and fits neatly into the conventional romance genre norms, even if they aren't particularly well-executed.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>