<post>
  <author>marinuso</author>
  <date>2020-01-12T23:07:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enjdoz/smallscale_question_sunday_for_the_week_of/fe5kbnh/</link>
  <title>A Time Traveler Stops Climate Change</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Given a ray-gun and a time machine, how would you stop climate change?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>If you're serious about it, you'd have to stop the Industrial Revolution from happening. Any industrial society is going to use fossil fuels at scale, and if they don't then their rivals will do so and conquer them. It is cheap and easy to develop and use, much more so than any alternatives, certainly in the beginning.</p>
      <p>So at first I thought: go kill the guy who invented the steam engine. But that wouldn't work. Someone else would invent a steam engine. There have been plenty of aborted attempts before.</p>
      <p>But here's the thing: the people like Newcomen and Watt, who developed it enough to be useful, lived in a society that had a use for a steam engine. 
In fact, they lived in a society that was already using wind- and water-powered machinery at scale. The advantage of a steam engine was that you could build your mill wherever you wanted, without having to rely on wind and without having to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flatrod_system">build power transmission infrastructure</a>. That society will inevitably build a steam engine good enough to replace a water wheel, and once that's done they will then inevitably refine it enough to be much more powerful, and then they will go through an industrial revolution. You can go and kill their geniuses, and you may delay it, but you will not prevent it. Unless you keep coming back every couple of years to shoot everyone involved with combustion engine projects, they will get there eventually. The society of Thomas Newcomen was almost industrial already; they were limited by their power sources, not by their mindset.</p>
      <p>Early modern England certainly wasn't the only or even first society where someone came up with the idea of steam power. It is just that in the other societies, steam-powered contraptions were mere curiosities. </p>
      <p>For example, in the Ottoman Empire in the 16th century, there lived a man named Taqi ad-Din, who would've made a fine Renaissance man if he had been born in a different society. He wrote a bunch of books. But as it was, his talents went mainly to build the Sultan fancy clocks. (And even then, he was lucky he wasn't just working the land somewhere in obscurity.) He also made an automatic spit roaster. This was powered by what is to modern eyes obviously a little steam turbine, using steam generated by the fire that's also cooking the meat. But neither he nor anybody else in his society saw any use for a steam turbine. (He in fact drew up designs for a bunch of animal-powered water pumps in the same book in which he wrote about the spit roaster.)</p>
      <p>In the Ottoman Empire, the work was done by hand, by slaves or maybe serfs. Unlike Western Europe at the time, they didn't have large mills or factories. There was very little useful machinery. Nobody ever bothered to build any, even though they clearly did have people like Taqi ad-Din who were capable of designing them. Even the automatic spit roaster was never widely adopted. Much like the clocks, it was a curiosity for the upper class, who might've said: "look at that, it turns by itself", but none of whom said: if we make a bigger one we could run our X with it. They just did not have the right mindset (and they had an abundance of bonded labour). </p>
      <p>The same thing was true of the Roman Empire before that (though their Aeolipile would never have powered even a spit roaster, so perhaps they are forgiven for not seeing the potential), as well as the ancient Greeks, who were clearly capable of making complicated machinery (like the Antikythera mechanism), but who just generally didn't, because why would they? It was something the rich did as a hobby. And it was even true of the antebellum American South, which was also a slave society. They didn't industrialize even though everybody else was, and that's a big reason they lost the war. They are perhaps the worst example: the technology was already widespread, and they <em>still</em> just didn't bother.</p>
      <p>So, to prevent climate change from happening, what you basically also need to prevent from happening is <em>modernity</em>. No society based on slavery or serfdom will industrialize on its own - the upper class will never see the use for machinery, and the lower class will be prevented from developing it even if they could. And no middle class really exists - that is perhaps what defines such societies even more than the use of forced labour, which still happens to some extent even in the modern day. </p>
      <p>You need a society where slavery is not a big thing, and most labour is free, for <em>automatization</em> - and thus machinery - to make sense.  When you are working for yourself (which is widespread in such a society), you want machines to lighten your burden. And when you are employing others, you want machines to lighten theirs, so you don't have to employ as many people and you can save on wages. And once that's going on, you want better machines than your competitors (also a thing in a free society), so you can outcompete them. The Industrial Revolution is now inevitable. </p>
      <p>But if you still want to prevent climate change, you're in luck. This type of society was invented only once in history: in early modern England and the Netherlands (which were in close contact and basically did it together). After that, East Asia took to it with vigour, but they didn't invent it, and even then, only Europe (plus US and Canada) and East Asia seem to want to have such societies despite the clear advantages. </p>
      <p>So here's how you prevent climate change: take your raygun and your time machine, and go to England in the 1500s.  Kill everyone. (You can leave the outer regions of what is now the UK alone. They don't matter. In fact, in the 1500s they may help you.) Go to Holland and kill everyone there (again, the outer regions of what is now the Netherlands can probably be left alone). If you want to be extra sure, go to Japan and kill everyone there as well; and then visit the main Hansa cities and wipe them out. </p>
      <p>Once you arrive back in the current day, you will very likely find that humanity has not industrialized and you have saved the climate. Congratulations!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>