<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2020-01-15T18:24:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/fehapmi/</link>
  <title>Trying to Understand Marx</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So I’ve been trying to read up on Marxist theory, and it turns out I’m not very good at reading up on Marxist theory. Reading <em>Das Kapital</em> is rough work, and the frequent necessity of researching the contemporaneous jargon to figure out what the fuck Marx is trying to say is a constant niggle. I find myself reading other people’s explanations and interpretations of it, and it’s foggy because they all seem to disagree with each other. Plus, I have a strong streak of stupidity about me, which always complicates things.</p>
      <p>But I <em>think</em> I can see the general shape of Marxism as an ideology. I’m going to take an honest shot at regurgitating it, both in the hope that a knowledgeable somebody will jump in and elucidate stuff and to entertain people with my inelegant floundering.</p>
      <p>In the beginning was the Economy, and from it all things sprang. All ideas and culture and art and politics were a follow-on effect of people sitting down and applying some elbow grease to produce some good that people need. The “sit down w/ elbow grease“ thing can be divvied up and catalogued into subsections. To wit-</p>
      <p>You got the tools of production, which are all of the physical things we need to pump out a product- fertile soil to plant in, hammers and nails, buildings, needles, shovels, etc, etc. Then you have the subjects of production, the raw material you actually transform into something useful- seed, wood, cotton, iron ore, etc.</p>
      <p>The tools and the subjects are lumped together into the blanket term “the means of production,” and they are inherently absolutely worthless. If I take a sewing a machine and twenty pounds of thread and leave them in the room together, nothing happens. If I want warm socks, I need a laborer in there using the tools on the subject to produce anything of value. Even if you bring in alternate energy source to provide the oomph- wind mills, water mills, solar power, oxen or horses- you’d still ultimately need a human doing upkeep or supervision, so you can just simplify the fuzzy bits of the animate energy that use the means of product to create nifty stuff as just being laborers. That animate energy, or worker, is the <em>force</em> of production.</p>
      <p>So. Tools + raw materials + energy (a worker) = valuable stuff. So far, so simple.</p>
      <p>As was stated, this economic and material process predates all ideas and immaterial culture, and is in fact the source of it (I <em>think</em> that this is what Marx means by historical materialism). All religions and politics and art and values are there to reinforce this economic process. So for instance, a hunter gatherer tribe might worship a Wolf God if it helps culturally transmit pack hunting techniques to the next generation; a cultural value of revering the ancestors makes sense if only the fifty year olds remember where the good foraging grounds were from last generation. I’m spitballing these examples, so no guarantees that I’m hitting the mark.</p>
      <p>This culture that supports the economic model is the <em>mode</em> of production. It’s all the memes and stories and beliefs and everything that keeps humanity at work to reliably produce the food and the tools they need to survive.</p>
      <p>The mode of production glues the force of production to the means of production to produce the vital goods.</p>
      <p>The thing is, the technology and knowledge base that constitute the tools of production is shifty. They mutate over time to change up what we are capable of; technology evolved, better tools and techniques are available, and sooner or later there’s a new way to do things that outcompetes the old way of doing things, because the new way can reliably produce more and better stuff.</p>
      <p>This clash between old and new is expressed by <em>dialectics</em>, which is some kind of thing that I don’t know if I comprehend yet. You start of with a thing (<em>thesis</em>), but that thing has a thing inside of it that makes it stupid and wrong (<em>antithesis</em>). Then you figure how to brute force it and make the stupid goddamn thing work anyway (<em>synthesis</em>). The thesis is the old way, the tension between obsolete tradition and efficient innovation is the antithesis, and when the new way crushes the old way and leads humanity into a better future, it all works out in synthesis.</p>
      <p>The hunter gatherer mode couldn’t produce as much food as the agrarian farmer mode, so the farmers blasted the hunters away. The small farmers couldn’t produce the surplus of the large latifundias, so the feudal mode wrecked the agrarian mode. Etc, etc.</p>
      <p>Ever since we moved away from the hunter gatherer clan, society has been marked by tons of surplus resources. We work for four hours a day to produce the food and clothes and stuff we need, then the next four hours of work produces extra stuff that is up for grabs. When we were hunters, the surpluses were tiny and shared equally. The second civilization started, a small cabal on top of the food chain laid claim to all the excess to use as they see fit.</p>
      <p>This is the start of class- the laborers producing excess value, and the elites living easy off of the surplus. Lords and serfs, owners and slaves, conquerer and conquered. The tension between the guy working 14 hour days and the guy sipping wine in his manor is the defining fault line in every society that produces massive surpluses.</p>
      <p>By definition, the mode of production always favors the elites- if the economy depends on laborers laboring to produce excess, the culture tells them to keep doing it.</p>
      <p>This pattern is inevitable and repeats every time there is a shift from the old mode to the new mode. The central contention of Marxism (again, <em>I think</em>, I am still groping in the darkness here) is that the current mode is outdated and fighting a new mode. The prosperous peasants of the Middle Ages, who owned the massively productive industries in the urban areas, managed to outcompete and destroy the landed aristocracy; these burghers (bourgeoisie) are now the dominant class living large off of the surplus by exploiting the animate force of the working class. It is inevitable that the intolerable conditions of the current mode of production- all the horrors of poverty, inhumane working hours, low pay, filthy living spaces, etc- will combine with the massive surpluses available to whoever captures them, and induce its own destruction. Thesis- the capitalist factory owner has a small empire all to himself and exploits the labor of others for personal gain. Antithesis- the workers hate working long hours for low pay and an early grave when they get their arms mangled in the machinery. Synthesis- the workers shall, sooner or later, leverage their superiority in numbers to revolt and grab the factories for themselves and share the surplus equally instead letting those rich fuckers rip them off like this.</p>
      <p>The question of what exactly this new mode of production is going to look like, well, that’s the kind of thing you need to murder your fellow revolutionaries over.</p>
      <p>Again- I cannot tell you how unsure I am of how accurate I am phrasing this. I’m trying my best, but that doesn’t mean much. But if I’m near the mark, this kind of contextualizes all that cultural Marxism I hear getting thrown around. The class struggle is not merely rich people and poor people whupping on each other, it is a confrontation of incompatible cultural modes that support incompatible economies. “Arguments as soldiers” has never been so accurate a diagnosis- every cultural impulse and value and quirk is either supporting the revolution or it’s an enemy soldier holding the line against your onslaught. “Correct” and “incorrect” matter little compared to “a reason to hang the foreman from the lamp post” and “a reason not to”.</p>
      <p>I also kinda dig why this appeal hits some countries harder than others. If you are a serf in Russia in 1917, your life is kind of horrible and it’s quite clear that the new mode would be better for you than the old mode. But a factory worker in America in 1890 is freer and wealthier and can move out west to seek his fortune if he saves up enough- the old mode, uncomfortable and miserable and heartbreaking though it is at times, works as advertised. Mao-Zedong had a quote somewhere where he claims that no matter how many socialists we produce, America will never be truly left wing because we haven’t suffered enough. When I heard it, I took it as basic Nationalism showing a grudge- “I grew up on the wrong side of the tracks, you’re just a rich kid in over his head”- but now I’m thinking it is literal truth. Maybe we need about a hundred years of violent oppression and economic exploitation before we could even conceive of an American Communist Party that isn’t a punchline to a lame joke.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>