<post>
  <author>NikoAlano</author>
  <date>2020-01-15T23:03:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/fei3gie/</link>
  <title>Clarifying Marx for mcjunker</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I will start off by saying that I am glad you are trying to struggle through an understanding of Marxism. Even things you think are unlikely to be true can help you to elucidate your thoughts on other topics and can give you a better understanding of why people who are wrong act or think the way they do. The Motte could stand to take more deep dives into the positions of people they think are wrong.</p>
      <p>Moving on from that, I think you are getting some parts of Marx quite wrong (though in ways that other Marxists through history have probably thought right).</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>In the beginning was the Economy, and from it all things sprang.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is wrong because for Marx the economy as such only begins to exist under capitalism. It's not that people throughout history haven't labored to some purpose, but that the economy as a separate sphere of society only came to exist under capitalism. Here we can look to Marx's view in <a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1844/jewish-question/">On <em>The Jewish Question</em></a> to understand that it is only with the breakdown of feudalism that society begins to have distinct civil (that is, economic) and political spheres. Under feudalism, there was no distinct economy as most goods were not commodities and most laborers were not wage laborers.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>If I want warm socks, I need a laborer in there [sic] using the tools on the subject to produce anything of value.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You have to be very careful using the word "value" with Marx, because he uses it precisely to describe a concept which is only manifest in capitalism. Of course your meaning is totally fine in plain English, but if you want this to be the trans-historical sense in which Marx talks about something being valuable you should be talking about use-values (that is, something that you can use to some purpose, which is obviously something humans through all societies have been interested in).</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>All religions and politics and art and values are there to reinforce this economic process. So for instance, a hunter gatherer tribe might worship a Wolf God if it helps culturally transmit pack hunting techniques to the next generation; a cultural value of revering the ancestors makes sense if only the fifty year olds remember where the good foraging grounds were from last generation.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I'd be a little more circumspect about reading too much intentionality into this kind of stuff for Marx. Marx isn't a conspiracy theorist who thinks everything that isn't the system of labor production is just a means of justifying labor production. He's generally going to want to explain the prevailing beliefs and behaviors of society somehow, but not always in a means that stabilizes society. More on this in a second.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>This culture that supports the economic model is the mode of production. It’s all the memes and stories and beliefs and everything that keeps humanity at work to reliably produce the food and the tools they need to survive.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The mode of production is better understood as being defined by its dominant relations of production (how does society structure labor processes; who makes what for whom?). Do peasants grow food, some of which is taken and consumed by their lord? Are slaves mining ore for their masters? Are proletarians selling their labor power for a wage? All of the memes and stories and beliefs are peripheral to the relations of production determining the mode of production in society. Though some people have taken the culturalist turn in left-wing circles, Marxists themselves are generally not favorable to this, even if (in a figure like Antonio Gramsci) some are willing to give culture a pretty decisive role in explaining revolutionary politics.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The thing is, the technology and knowledge base that constitute the tools of production is shifty. They mutate over time to change up what we are capable of; technology evolved, better tools and techniques are available, and sooner or later there’s a new way to do things that outcompetes the old way of doing things, because the new way can reliably produce more and better stuff.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>This is either too abstract/vacuous to explain much or it reverses the order of historical explanation for Marxists (who don't think that technological changes often directly explain changes in the mode of production). Technology and society's knowledge base as such don't have much to do with the relations of production. The water mill was invented in antiquity but only became prevalent in Europe after the fall of the Roman Empire and Rome didn't fall because they lacked enough water mills. What happened was that a technology which wasn't as useful under the slave societies of Rome (because slave societies aren't particularly interested in labor-saving devices) became useful under feudalism in part because peasants needed their master's water mill to more effectively grind grain and the master needed a way to "tax" their vassals.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>This clash between old and new is expressed by dialectics, which is some kind of thing that I don’t know if I comprehend yet. You start of[sic] with a thing (thesis), but that thing has a thing inside of it that makes it stupid and wrong (antithesis). Then you figure how to brute force it and make the stupid goddamn thing work anyway (synthesis). The thesis is the old way, the tension between obsolete tradition and efficient innovation is the antithesis, and when the new way crushes the old way and leads humanity into a better future, it all works out in synthesis.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>No. This is all very wrong and it is good you don't really comprehend the dialectic because you shouldn't comprehend the significance of nonsense. The first thing to say is that the notion of dialectics you are putting forward is based on Fichte (not Hegel, let alone Marx). The second you hear someone talking about some kind of abstract schema of dialectics you should be very concerned that you are talking with a snake-oil salesman. With Hegel and Marx the dialectic is basically just the process by which problems in the broad sense (internal tensions, epistemological gaps, social uncertainty, etc.) in a system are dealt with.</p>
      <p>For example, in the Phenomenology of Spirit Hegel starts off with people in a state of sense-certainty. That is, someone who can only speak of things in terms of immediate indexicals "I am here now", "this is this", "I am me", and so on. This seems fine as well as it goes but such a being is incredibly limited if it can't make further distinctions or articulate any kind of knowledge beyond immediate indexicals. So such a kind of person must advance beyond this state into a more variegated kind of experience in which allows for knowledge of truths that aren't so vacuously true. This kind of movement is perfectly dialectical but doesn't require a mechanical adherence to the Fichtean dialectical schema. In an ironic sense I suppose you could say that to the degree to which the Fichtean schema is true it is because of it's being vacuous in the same way the the sense-certainty person's proclamations are true.</p>
      <p>Beyond that, there are different arguments about the degree to which Marx's dialectical understanding is supposed to be understood as transhistorically true. That is, there are some people (the late Moishe Postone, for example) who think that dialectical explanation only becomes useful under modernity and capitalism. Das Capital is obviously about the dialectical unfolding of the system of capital and Marx thinks in <em>The German Ideology</em> that capitalism is in some sense the final stage of the process of alienation in class society (hence why he thinks capitalism can lead only to socialism, if it does to anything else at all), but there are some people who worry that other modes of production might not be as comprehensible as a totality (that is, as a completely structured unity) in the way capitalism is. Maybe feudalism was irrational in a way that capitalism isn't for instance. In any case, notions of efficiency aren't generally how Marx understands historical development (though he probably wouldn't doubt that "more efficient" societies could, in a certain sense, dominate their neighbors in a way that could allow for snowballing effects), though there are Marxists like Gerald Allan Cohen, who do believe that (I think wrongly).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>