<post>
  <author>paanther</author>
  <date>2020-01-14T22:23:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/feet3bg/</link>
  <title>Laws vs Programs</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>it often amazes me that when I read the actual text of a bill, how often I find apparent loopholes big enough to fly a jumbo jet through</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think it’s more likely that you’re thinking about the law as a programmer and not like a lawyer would. Laws are always filled with vagaries and the vagaries are always plugged according to the restraint of individual judges and reasonable guesses about intent. This is how the system has always been. I think a lot of more mathematically-minded people have a system in mind where they would write a more precise version of the laws and people would obey it, but that’s just <em>fantastically</em> optimistic not just about your own legal abilities but about the reading comprehension of the average person. For fuck’s sake many judges in the US are <em>elected</em> and have comparatively few formal qualifications at all. Imagine what a country would be like if where the laws were written by people who graduated from MIT <em>for</em> other MIT grads, but actually implemented by frat boys with business degrees (barely) and political aspirations; it would make no sense, it would be chaos. It certainly wouldn’t be better than our current system, which has some eye towards comprehensibility.</p>
      <p>I think that instead of thinking “I see giant holes that can be driven through this”, you should recognize that the law only exists insofar as you can <em>convince people</em> that those holes exist and they should allow you to drive through them, and that this is precisely the point.</p>
      <p>If the dictionary definition of a word would imply that some insane legal exploit exists that no one’s using, consider that there’s so much discretion intentionally baked into the system that no one could actually use that exploit because everyone at every stage of the process would recognize that A) it’s ludicrous, B) it would make the law ineffective if they allowed you to use it, and C) it clearly wasn’t the intent. More to the point, this discretion in practice <em>is</em> the law, not some Platonic ideal of how you think the words in question should or could be read.</p>
      <p>I’m a relatively progressive person so I’m not predisposed to jerk off over the Constitution as if it’s a unique document the likes of which no man will ever produce again, but... well, if you tried to make a government from the mindset of a programmer, ie perfectly literally, you’d end up with 150,000 pages beginning with 100,000 pages of definitions of every single damn word, no one would ever use it, and it would be filled with a huge number of exploits because designing it would be a problem beyond human ingenuity. Whereas documents like the Constitution work because they build on intuition and shared context and guesses about intent; if they didn’t, you’d have to solve human cognition and economics and physics just as a prerequisite to designing a government.</p>
      <p>The last paragraph’s a bit of an exaggeration, but I stand by the general point: thinking of this problem from a purely mathematical or programming lens cuts out the human factors that actually are most of the law.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>