<post>
  <author>Shakesneer</author>
  <date>2020-01-16T04:20:15Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/feivlkm/</link>
  <title>Ford vs Ferrari - A male confict</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Ford v. Ferrari was the best movie of the year, easy. The story is essentially a male conflict -- not just because the major characters are almost all male. They dream big, they fight, somebody wins somebody loses, then they almost dust themselves off and get back to being friendly. It's not just reckless "for no actual reason" -- it's the essence of manhood, it's the spirit, the glory, the thrill of what it means to be a man and go out into the world and fight for some unrealized perfection.</p>
      <p>I know that women don't always understand this thrill, and often think it ridiculous, and are sometimes even justified in thinking it so. But I guess I'm surprised you're surprised. It's not a <em>new</em> theme in fiction. Achilles chose immortal glory and death over a comfortable life at home; Captain Ahab chased that whale for revenge to no good end; The Count of Monte Cristo likewise chose vengeance and justice over settling down to a comfortable and sumptuous life. And it's not just constrained to fiction. The desire to go out and conquer new domains and explore the frontier is how history is made. Without that impulse you have no Columbus or Magellan or Cook, no Edison or Tesla or Bell, no Michelangelo or Titian, no Napoleon, no Alexander, no Caesar, no Spartacus, no Armstrong, no Mohammed, no Luther, no Calvin, no Christ. The desire to <em>go out</em> and <em>achieve</em> is the great noble spirit of mankind, it's what lifts us up out of the dirt and makes possible all the greatness of the human experience.</p>
      <p>Granted we could sit here and parcel things out, "Ford was inventing to escape farm life, very rational," "Achilles could have lived a comfortable life instead, very irrational." This is a very feminine way of looking at the world. I don't mean that as an insult -- the feminine capacity to stand back from man and criticize him, to bring him down to earth and focus on the practical is a very important quality. But it misses something of the grandeur and <em>glory</em> of truly doing something great. It isn't rational, it isn't explicable, and no man truly becomes great because he merely wanted to balance his checkbook or build a better mouse trap. It's something in the <em>soul</em>, it's something that pushes us to conquer in whatever frontiers are available to us, whether that be the manifest destiny to overtake a continent or the <em>mere</em> thrill of winning a race.</p>
      <p>After all <em>Ford v. Ferrari</em> isn't just about the thrill of a race. This male struggle to express, this will to power, this desire to master space, is the core conflict of the movie. It really isn't about Ford vs. Ferrari at all. Sure, the arc of the story is about a competition to beat Ferrari at a race and this is where the story reaches its nominal climax. But the real conflict of the movie is about Ken Miles and Carroll Shelby and all the true racing men -- and the corporate suits at Ford who don't <em>get it</em>. Ostensibly, Miles and Shelby and Ford are all on the same team. But in reality, Miles and Shelby represent the drive to be great, to achieve excellence, and Ford is full of managers and corporate paper shufflers who really only care about appearances and procedures. And so they fight, constantly, over how the car is going to be built, who's going to drive it, which rules can and can't be broken, what is and isn't polite to say. Shelby American is trying to build the best damn racing car in the world, Ford is trying to look good while doing it, and so they clash over and over again. This is why, at the climax of the movie, as the race of the <em>24 Hours at Le Mans</em> is reaching its end, the true struggle is not between the drivers of Ford and the drivers of Ferrari, but between Ken Miles and the outrageous request Ford makes to -- but I'll say no more.</p>
      <p>Ken Miles, of course, fully embodies this striving-for-greatness in all his buffs and flaws. He's a coarse man with a bad temper, he loves his wife and children, he's argumentative and particular, he can't really swallow his pride to serve other men even if he is a good man after all. But this isn't a story about how Ken Miles learns to humble himself and accept that life, after all, is boring, quotidian existence is something to be tolerated, let's all watch TV and eat ice cream on the couch and make ourselves comfortable and bored. Ken Miles strives for excellence, he pursues greatness, he aspires to true mastery over his craft. His craft is driving cars recklessly fast around a race track, and in the strictest sense it's irrational and more than a little dumb. But it doesn't really matter what the field of combat is as long as there <em>is</em> combat, and that's what pushes Ken Miles to win at Le Mans, that's what pushes him in his obsession with racing the perfect lap, that's what makes his final death and sacrifice so ridiculously glorious.</p>
      <p>Sure, Peter Miles may have been happier if his dad had never gone racing and lived to cherish and father him for the rest of his life. But that's not a story that would inspire any of us today, that has no greatness of soul. And as tragic as it can be, that's the spirit that moves and animates us, that's what it means to feel alive. I would never call it toxic, I would never call it denigrate or criticize it, because to do so would be to insult the spirit of the men who gave us the world in which we live. It cannot be understood in the clinical terms of a sociologist studying male disposability or ritual worship. It's a great soul, in the blood, felt deeply in the spirit. I think the world would become an infinitely better place if men today felt that spirit, if instead of meeting quarterly sales targets and filing reports we felt a great calling to go out and conquer, even the irrational, even in when it seems silly for only a trophy at the end of it, even at the risk of death. </p>
      <p>If I could find such a frontier I would not be posting here. I would be at the pushing edge of mankind on Mars, I would chart the deep recesses of the genome, deepwater trenches in the Atlantic would bear my name, a temple in Constantinople would stand glory to my conquests, the Earth would thrum with the news of my conquests. Alas, all the frontiers are closed, and I return to my office job and twiddle my thumbs for a living. All the frontiers are closed, for now.</p>
      <p>This is the spirit of <em>Ford v. Ferrari</em>, and what amazes me is that such a movie could really be made today. It is so far from anything political, anything we talk about as "Culture War". I am surprised, in fact, that Hollywood could make this movie, because it seems to capture a spirit out of step with the world in which we now live. I am not sure if it is truly a <em>great movie</em>, and it is time to let time gather dust so we can get a little perspective on it. But it is a <em>great story</em>, and that moves me to speak the earnest thrill of my heart, that the age of heroes will return and inspire mankind anew with the glory of a new frontier, new space to conquer, something over which to achieve mastery. More than a platform or a policy, I want a Caesar!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>