<post>
  <author>UltraRedSpectrum</author>
  <date>2020-01-13T21:13:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/enzofb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_13/feakzo6/</link>
  <title>Thoughts on Gender: Subjects and Objects in Literature</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This was (and is) a reply to another comment, but someone suggested I make it a top-level post, so here goes. The post this is a response to was about the OP's theory of drama as it relates to women in leadership. Specifically relating to drama, this is an explanation of my theory that gender doesn't matter <em>at all</em>, but the author's <em>preconceptions about gender</em> do matter a lot, and cause all of the effects that we see wrt women in fiction (e.g. people being unimpressed with female protagonists).</p>
      <p>I believe that writers subconsciously write male and female characters in accordance with ultra-traditional gender roles, <em>especially</em> writers who have strong ideological opinions about gender (and totally regardless of <em>what those opinions happen to be</em>).</p>
      <p>To summarize, the vast majority of writers write male characters as subjects and female characters as objects. When female characters are written as objects while also being placed in the protagonist role, the result is a pointless mess, because the protagonist role only works for subjects.</p>
      <p>What do I mean by subject and object? A full sentence needs both a subject to act and an object to be acted upon. Likewise, a full story requires at minimum a subject whose motivations drive the plot and an object whose qualities drive the plot. The simplest example of this in terms of gender is the woman-as-prize plot. The questing knight desires (subject) the beautiful princess (object). The knight is defined by his motivation, the princess is <em>also</em> defined by the knight's motivation; specifically, he wants her because she is beautiful. Her qualities only matter insofar as they matter to the knight.</p>
      <p>Another way to look at this is that the subject acquires the object of its desires. In order for this to be the case, the subject <em>must not already have the object of its desires</em>. This seems so obvious as to be tautological, but it's a hell of a stumbling block.</p>
      <p>Now I'm going to get to the point. Let's examine a simple story: A teenage boy desires a teenage girl. He's an awkward horny average-looking everyman, she's the hottest girl in school. He asks her out but makes a fool of himself, and in the process triggers the B-plot (superheroes, saving the animal shelter, winning the Big Game, whatever). He spends the next two acts resolving the B-plot, proves himself worthy, and wins the girl. Woman-as-prize.</p>
      <p>Let's imagine we're rewriting this with a female protagonist. A teenage girl is mostly indifferent to a teenage boy. She's the hottest girl in school, he's an awkward horny average-looking everyman. She something something B-plot something. In the process of resolving the B-plot, something. He doesn't prove himself worthy of her something something and they all lived happily ever after.</p>
      <p>In our attempt to lazily copy-and-paste a stock plot without changing the characters, we've hit a snag. The core of the plot was the male protagonist's desire to prove himself worthy of the female love interest. But in trying to rewrite it with a female protagonist, our imaginary writer fails to fully swap the roles. The writer can't imagine the story being about her proving herself worthy of a male love interest. In the mind of the writer, she's still the beautiful princess whose qualities make her desirable - even though now she's the one who's supposed to do the desiring. The princess can't desire, that would be weird. It makes it too easy for the knight. Except <em>she is the knight now.</em> If she doesn't want anything, the story is about a person who doesn't want anything.</p>
      <p>This conflict is at the heart of a lot of lackluster female protagonists. Look at Rey from the new Star Wars movies. Besides being literally the object of desire in a fucked up love triangle (can you imagine Princess Leia and Darth Vader competing for Luke Skywalker's affections?), her motivations are so weak as to be meaningless. She wants to find her parents, fails, fails again, her parents don't matter, never meets them, never going to meet them, forget that noise look at the explosions! She has qualities, like being able to lift millions of tons of rock or mind control Stormtroopers, but she doesn't have a throughline that motivates her passage through the story before finally being resolved at the end (compare Luke Skywalker and <em>his</em> father, who he actually does find, and how Luke's conflict with his father ties in with other aspects of the movies like the Force).</p>
      <p>Rey just does what is required of her by the plot, like a really boring genie. She was trapped, so she had to lift lots of rocks to escape. She was captured, so she had to mind control a Stormtrooper to escape. Something something Force Jedi Sith the end. She doesn't self-motivate, she's blown along like a leaf in the wind, or a princess. In fact she's very much like Princess Zelda, who at the end of the game uses her godlike magical powers to fix everything in the world, but who spends almost the entire runtime of the game up to that point as a plot device and occasionally a literal inanimate object. The character who can never be weak also can't be present when all is darkest and a child with nothing but a magic sword must oppose an evil sorcerer with the powers of a god. The writers, despite their feminist credentials, are simply unwilling to do the work of imagining a female Jedi <em>Knight,</em> as in knight errant, as in cowboy, as in samurai, as in dirty and travel-stained, as in following a quest. Not a princess, not beautiful, not desired.</p>
      <p>A hypothetical woman-with-no-name, who starts at the bottom and works her way to the top, who no one thinks anything of until she proves herself worthy, <em>she</em> could be a Jedi Knight. She could be a cultural icon every bit as relevant as Luke Skywalker. But that would require mental flexibility that most writers (most people) are incapable of.</p>
      <p>It's nothing to do with gender and everything to do with attitude.</p>
      <p>To return to your point (EDIT: This part refers to the post this was originally a reply to) I think it's harder to see oneself in a person with no motivations. We can all see ourselves in Luke as he fights to rescue his best friend Han Solo from Jabba the Hutt, the same best friend who overcame his defining flaw of selfishness to save Luke's life during the death-defying attack on the Death Star. It's a universal motivation that anyone can relate to, Luke as a knight rather than Luke as a man per se. On the other hand, only someone who liked Luke a lot but now wants to see a female Jedi in action can see herself in Rey lifting lots of rocks to escape through the convenient secret exit they discover just when they need one, thereby putting everyone back in more or less the same position they were in at the start of the movie.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>