<post>
  <author>4bpp</author>
  <date>2020-12-13T09:33:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/k8bxy1/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_07/gfo7016/</link>
  <title>/u/4bpp on the tacit collusion between pro- and anti-abortion crusaders to never, ever seek principled consistency</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I can't square the third argument - anti-DP but pro-abortion.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>As someone in that camp: As far as I am concerned, fetuses are not meaningfully human. Whatever features make a human life "sacred" or worthy of consideration are not present in them. If not for cultural familiarity, the position that a fetus deserves protection would be as weird to me as the religions that proscribe cutting your hair (and the more widespread superstitions that hair cuttings must be disposed of in special ways), elaborate burial ceremonies for amputated limbs or a blanket ban on "spilling your seed".</p>
      <p>The problem is that talking about "sanctity of life" actively obscures the actual disagreement: the typical blue-tribe position, if anything, is <em>more</em> attached to sanctity of life (does not believe it can be forfeited by bad decisions, peer consensus or evil actions), but extends the definition of life to fewer things. My reading of why nobody makes this clear is that</p>
      <p>(1) for the red tribe, "sanctity of life" makes for much better slogans than "expand the definition of life" or something (to begin with, if you are big on normative morality, you don't really want to implicitly concede that the underlying category definitions are up to debate). Maybe "baby lives matter" would have been a better slogan, but the other side was first to take the pattern to market.</p>
      <p>(2) the blue tribe does not actually want to get into a debate to narrow down the definition of life because "this life is unworthy" triggers their Nazi pattern matchers, so they are willing to concede the "sanctity of life" framing to their opponents and are happy to instead fight the battle by pointing out hypocrisies and implying that "sanctity of life" might be a fig leaf (for something else than what it actually replaces, though: disincentivising casual sex by punishing women for it);</p>
      <p>(3) neither side is interested in an argument about the circle of care that might balloon to the point where vegans and animal rights activists, palliative care extenders and other weird groups that split coalitions in the middle might come out of the woodwork.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>