<post>
  <author>HuskyCriminologist</author>
  <date>2020-12-14T23:15:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kcsx2u/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_14/gfv3bm5/</link>
  <title>/u/HuskyCriminologist puts a bunch of former (?) radicals on a list</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Is there something self-serving about radical action? Is there something self-serving about martyrdom?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Well, let's take a look at where the SDS Weathermen are today. I'll be going from the list of members from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weather_Underground#Legacy">this</a> wikipedia page, as I haven't read <em>Days of Rage</em> in a while.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>Bill Ayers. Co-founder. All weapons and bombing charges dropped due to illegal evidence-gathering techniques of COINTELPRO. Retired professor in the College of Education at the University of Illinois at Chicago, formerly holding the titles of Distinguished Professor of Education and Senior University Scholar. Was a confidant of President Obama.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Bernardine Dohrn. Co-founder. At one point on the FBI Most Wanted list. Pled guilty to misdemeanors in 1980. From 1991 to 2013, Dohrn was a Clinical Associate Professor of Law at the Children and Family Justice Center at Northwestern University School of Law.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Kathy Boudin. Convicted of felony murder in the 1981 Brinks Armored Car Robbery in which two police officers and one Brinks guard died. Released from prison on parole in 2003 and became an adjunct professor at Columbia University.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Linda Evans. Convicted of straw purchasing firearms and harboring a fugitive in relation to the 1981 Brinks robbery. Sentence commuted by President Clinton in 2001. Currently an active lobbyist for leftist causes.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Brian Flanagan. Admitted to multiple counts of bombings (no injuries or deaths resulted from these actions). Never went to trial due to illegal evidence-gathering of COINTELPRO. Lived a relatively quiet and boring life post-WU.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>David Gilbert. Convicted of felony murder in 1981 Brinks robbery. Currently serving 75-to-life.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Diana Oughton. Died in 1970 while making a nail-bomb intended for a Fort Dix military dance event</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Terry Robbins. Died in the 1970 bomb-making accident.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Ted Gold. Died in the 1970 bomb-making accident.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Naomi Jaffe. Likely bomb-maker. Currently a lobbyist for leftist causes. Most recently the Executive Director of Holding Our Own, a multiracial foundation for women.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Jeff Jones. Likely co-conspirator on 1981 Brinks robbery. Sentenced to probation and community service. He now heads up his own consulting firm called Jeff Jones Strategies that specializes in media expertise, writing, and campaign strategies that help grassroots and progressive groups achieve their goals.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Eleanor Raskin. Likely bomb-maker. All charges dismissed. She is currently an administrative law judge with the NYS Public Service Commission. Stein was previously a visiting associate professor at Albany Law School and taught transnational environmental law. For ten years she served as an Administrative Law Judge at the New York State Public Service Commission in Albany, New York.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Mark Rudd. Known bomb-maker. Received a small fine and ultimately spent less than one year in jail. After serving as a mathematics instructor at Central New Mexico Community College, he is now retired in Albuquerque, New Mexico.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Matthew Steen. Convicted of federal conspiracy and bank robbery charges. Served 3 years of a 10-year sentence. Became the director of a Community Action Agency for Santa Barbara County and was elected to the board of trustees of the local Community College District in Santa Barbara. Former member of several San Francisco city committees.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Susan Stern. Member of the Seattle Seven. Charged with conspiracy to incite a riot. Caused sufficient disruptive behavior in the courtroom to get a mistrial. Served 3 months of a 6 month sentence for contempt of court. Died of a drug overdose in 1976.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Laura Whitehorn. Also a member of the The May 19 Communist Organization. Sentenced to 20 years for the 1983 Senate bombing. Served 14. Previously a Senior Editor with POZ Magazine in New York City. Currently a lobbyist for leftist causes, and leader of a group dedicated to supporting New York State "political prisoners" from the black liberation movement and anti-imperialist solidarity movement.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Eric Mann. Sentenced to two years in prison on charges of conspiracy to commit murder. Served 1.5. Became a very active member of the labor rights movement. Worked as a full-time journalist for the Boston Globe. Founder and current director of the Labor/Community Strategy Center in Los Angeles, California. Wrote the Playbook for Progressives.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Cathlyn Platt Wilkerson. One of two (the other being Kathy Boudin) survivors of the 1970 nail-bomb explosion. In 1980 was convicted of illegal possession of dynamite and sentenced to 3 years in prison. She was released after serving 11 months. Spent 20 years teaching mathematics in high schools and adult education programs.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>It seems as though being a white leftist radical in your youth, committing crimes up to and including murder, can really pay off in your later years with things like working at a prestigious law school, lobbying the government, even advising the President of the United States.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>