<post>
  <author>iprayiam3</author>
  <date>2020-12-14T13:41:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kcsx2u/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_14/gft6kkj/</link>
  <title>/u/iprayiam3 is confused about university students being subjected to ideological purity tests</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Im a little confused, why are university students being interviewed on culturewar topics as a prerequisite for entrance?</p>
      <p>And as they are, why are you suprised they are dancing on the head of a needle in order not to say the wrong thing?</p>
      <p>Im sure most of them see this as "getting a girl in bed" more than as "choosing a spouse". There is some transactional value they're trying to extract here. So they're going to say whatever it takes to get that. Obviously this means answering questions with high agreeability and a lot of room to fudge. That is the simplest strategy when you dont yet know what will count as disqualifying.</p>
      <p>A high honesty, firm commitment strategy is far far riskier and offers almost no benefit if you are treating this interview / date transactionally.</p>
      <p>The real problem here, bluntly, is thinking in a situation like this with such unequal insight and unequal rewards, that anyone would answer honestly or that it is a remotely useful way to extract information from the interviewee.</p>
      <p>Its why girls are advised not to sleep with a guy in the first date. Because with that kind of reward on the table, the entire courting process is subverted.</p>
      <p>Here the student knows nothing about your commitments or the beurocracy of the university you represent and as far as they are concerned, they have nothing of great value to offer you. You dont really need anything from them, individually. On the other side, you are asking them to open up with extreme depth, make themselves very vulnerable, all while dangling something of very high value over their head.</p>
      <p>Honestly anyone who <em>doesn't</em> obfuscate with extreme agreeability in that scenario should be seen as a huge red flag.</p>
      <p>
        <em>Anecdote:</em> once in a  job interview the hiring manager asked whether I preferred working in a startup / entrepreneurial environment or a more traditional, stable corporate enviroment.</p>
      <p>I pretended to reflect for a few moments and answered "somewhere in the middle". He loved that answer and explained how this job was a little of both. I got hired.</p>
      <p>During my pretend reflection, i wasnt actually considering my preferences. I was quickly seeing if he had given a preferred answer away, and in absence of that, I chose the answer with the least distance from either possible right answer. I was minimizing the amount I could be wrong, so as not to be disqualified.</p>
      <p>Whether my manager was really interested in my preference, I'll never know. Maybe. Maybe he was actually looking to test agreeability, flexibility.</p>
      <p>Either way, there was no incentive to be honest. Even if I had an extreme preference, my best bet was ro give the in the middle answer, then wait to hear my boss's  reveal about the actual enviroment, and make my own decision about whether it was a good fit for me.</p>
      <p>If you're asking folks about free speech against Christians, they make be giving the most probable "progressive" answer. Then when you double down on a minority, youve given them a clue that they didnt answer right, so they adjust their next answer to bridge back the distance.</p>
      <p>I dont think they're really revealing a muddled belief system, I think you are seeing hedging in action. As an experiment, try asking some a different follow up, after theyve agreed to censor Christians</p>
      <p>Basically restate the question with thr same scenario and players in a slightly different way. Ill bet they will come back and hedge almost as much as they do to your minority religious question.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>