<post>
  <author>iprayiam3</author>
  <date>2020-12-20T02:54:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kcsx2u/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_14/ggfo7dy/</link>
  <title>/u/iprayiam3 on the ad hoccery of practical moral reasoning</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Would you snitch on your best friend if he confessed to murdering someone?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Years and years ago I was in a situation where I found out somebody had done something very bad, but not illegal to somebody I did not know but happened to live in my apartment complex. I struggled deeply about whether I should tell the person and looked for serious moral advice, but found nothing particularly helpful.</p>
      <p>I ultimately decided that the simple principle of, <em>"I'd want to know"</em>, combined with the fear that any justification not to speak up would just be covering for moral cowardice, was enough to speak up.</p>
      <p>Some time later, married, I reflected and realized that the danger of retaliation, no matter how trivially small was enough to make me rethink my conclusion in light of having a family. My moral responsibility to keep my family safe was a new variable.</p>
      <p>A few years after that, I was sent an note from the afflicted party out of the blue that said basically, <em>"Remember that incident? I want you to know how glad I am you spoke up. It saved my life."</em></p>
      <p>Suddenly my calculus swung again, though each time, my position has been less firm than my original resolve.</p>
      <p>I say all this to demonstrate the difficulty of these questions to really communicate what you are looking for. My own situation changed much more over the years than any moral principle about snitching underlying my position. And any answer I give will be as much about me filling in narrative details as communicating principles. </p>
      <p>My details won't be yours, and by the time we finish, we might have constructed two completely different contexts. And we might actually agree with each other's answer based on context, but our yes / no will never show that.</p>
      <p>For example, what if I answer your question 'no' because I think about the possibility that it won't lead to conviction and retaliation against my family. Meanwhile you answer 'yes' because you are actually an unmarried ex-marine, criminal investigator. And Jim answers 'maybe' because he is a Catholic priest, and it completely depends on whether the confession was under the seal of the sacrament of Reconciliation.</p>
      <p>You, me, and Jim could ALL AGREE to a yes, no, or maybe if presented with the respective situation. But we all got the prompt we got, applied our personal experience, and the researcher is left with a simple yes, no, and maybe.</p>
      <p>The researcher has absolutely NO DATA about the differences in our morality, epistemology, or politics and it is foolish to think they do. None of us answered according to those standards, really. We were busy filling in situation detail. In fact, our perspectives are all three the SAME, but the researcher only sees three different answers.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>