<post>
  <author>professorgerm</author>
  <date>2020-12-16T15:00:57Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kcsx2u/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_14/gg1aks9/</link>
  <title>/u/professorgerm on homeless people: "If people don't want to be somewhere, they won't stay."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>As others said, be a little more skeptical of 99PI, they have <em>exactly</em> the biases one would expect from a description like "a podcast based in Oakland, California that talks about architecture and social issues." </p>
      <p>That said, it's in my queue but pretty low on the list, so if they've brought up Salt Lake City most of this will be old news to you. But being Californian, I doubt they've looked that far to one of the most famous, and "failed" (depending on your definition), examples of Housing First. I've written about it <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/bytvw2/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_10_2019/er20s6f/">here</a> and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fyrcczq/">here</a>, but only as an interested amateur- this is far out of my wheelhouse, take my opinions with a grain of salt. </p>
      <p>As someone once quipped, the worst part about being poor is living next to poor people. Don't underestimate that as a major cause of hesitance to assist, and a major cause of why assistance fails. I fully expect the good-hearted utopians at 99PI <em>refuse</em> to even consider that should push come to shove, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/jv161w/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_november_16/gcy4h9n/">they would not be the kind of people they like to think they are</a> (unrelated to housing, but an example of people losing their principles when they need put in action <em>by themselves</em>). Maybe I'm wrong and they're as selfless as they think- but I doubt it.</p>
      <p>From my first comment link:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Serious substance abuse problems are tougher than mental illness for Housing First to address, Tsemberis said. Most of the 15 percent to 20 percent of clients who wash out of his Housing First programs are serious addicts. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>As others said, it's largely a substance abuse problem, and that's much more intractable than even mental illness in the SLC experience. There is very little that can be done for these people short of institutionalization. And short of institutionalizing the utterly hopeless, they will be a poison in every well that attempts to help the merely downtrodden but fixable.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>And here's <a href="https://www.sltrib.com/news/2018/12/16/gehrke-are-utahs-million/">an article from the Salt Lake Tribune</a> stating, in short, that no one really knows how much it's working, in part because there's so many definitions for varieties of homeless and just what "working" is supposed to mean:  </p>
        <p>Auditors found, for example, a Rapid Rehousing program in <a href="https://le.utah.gov/audit/18_12rpt.pdf">Salt Lake County reported 68 percent of those people who had received subsidized housing ended up back on the street</a>. In reality, three-fourths of those clients never actually got any housing subsidies.<br />
But <a href="https://www.sltrib.com/news/politics/2018/08/12/operation-rio-grande-one/">those data points didn’t really add up to providing a useful answer to the broader, more holistic question: Is it working? The answer was more or less a shrug.</a></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>From my second comment link: </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>This was mostly focused on providing low-cost or free rental units rather than actually handing over deeds, though there are many reasons to do it this way instead unless your goal is incrementalism to <a href="https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20181210-can-singapores-social-housing-keep-up-with-changing-times">Singapore-style social housing</a>. The short version is: <strong>the costs skyrocket while motivation to keep it running does not.</strong></p>
        <p>Maintenance is hard (part of the reason for doing it rental-ish style rather than ownership style, I think; there's pre-existing systems to handle that maintenance better); keeping some of the people from destroying the property is hard; keeping them from terrorizing their neighbors is hard (for various degrees of terrorize, of course, an autist with a sensory disorder has a much lower threshold than, say, a Middle Eastern refugee).</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Here's a more academic overview of SLC's <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/10511482.2020.1828988">Rapid Rehousing Program</a>, that describes in more detail one of the voucher systems used. They summarize the problem that the vouchers <em>end</em>, and so the families cannot pay even reduced-rate rents once those vouchers end. A history of eviction is also one of the few things people could be denied rent for, so they would end up concentrated into the buildings with the most lenient landlords (and thus creating a downward spiral for the community and the property).</p>
      <p>At the time I was there new apartment construction was required to include a certain number of reduced rate and voucher units, so even at a fairly nice building there were voucher tenants, and you could pick them out pretty easily. The elderly weren't too bad, but there was a sort of revolving-door for younger (here meaning under-60) voucher tenants, likely as the vouchers ran out and they were still too unstable (or, frankly, uncaring) to afford market or even reduced-rate rents.</p>
      <p>Here's a <a href="https://media4.manhattan-institute.org/sites/default/files/housing-first-and-homelessness-SE.pdf">Manhattan Institute report</a> (free-market think tank; they publish <em>City Journal</em>) that goes into some more analysis, that Housing First works well for what they call "high utilizer" homeless but that it makes a poor core program, and cannot stand on its own (put simply, without LOTS of counseling and employment guidance it's utterly doomed). </p>
      <p>In short, housing initiatives will only work if: A) the state owns the property and will eat the costs without a profit motive and B) the state completely disregards the wants, needs,  and cares of the presumably-productive tax-paying neighbors. </p>
      <p>Some reasonably large number (in numbers, if not in percentages) of homeless will never be able to afford actual housing, at market rates, and hold actual jobs. They will be permanent wards of the state, in effect. </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I do wonder if we could try transplanting an entire homeless community into affordable housing elsewhere, but that would probably never work. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/bvg7ba/instead-of-helping-homeless-people-cities-are-bussing-them-out-of-town">Other cities are pretty notorious</a> for bussing their homeless to California, since Californians will largely suck it up and put up with them (and because they're not likely to freeze to death in coastal California), and <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Hundreds-of-homeless-people-board-a-bus-out-of-SF-14188436.php">San Francisco has its own bussing initiative</a>. </p>
      <p>If people don't want to be somewhere, they won't stay.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>