<post>
  <author>stucchio</author>
  <date>2020-12-21T22:41:36Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/khcdwb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_21/ggms1tn/</link>
  <title>/u/stucchio wonders if President Trump's distaste for bureaucrats made him the MVP in global COVID-19 response</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Lets talk about Trump, COVID and the FDA. Here's Der Spiegel on the topic:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The contrast is unmistakable. On the one hand, there is the supposedly incompetent Trump administration, which will provide vaccines to 20 million Americans in the next two to three weeks alone. By the end of March, the plan is for around 100 million Americans to have received the two vaccine injections they need.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, there is the supposedly well-prepared Europeans, who continue to have to wait for a vaccine that was developed in Germany. And who still don’t know exactly how much of the vaccine they will be getting in the coming months.</p>
        <p>Initially, Germany’s health minister has announced, there will probably only be 400,000 vaccine doses for Germany, with another 11 to 13 million to follow by March -- a fraction of the amount the Americans are getting.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/the-planning-disaster-germany-and-europe-could-fall-short-on-vaccine-supplies-a-3db4702d-ae23-4e85-85b7-20145a898abd">https://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/the-planning-disaster-germany-and-europe-could-fall-short-on-vaccine-supplies-a-3db4702d-ae23-4e85-85b7-20145a898abd</a>
      </p>
      <p>The article goes into great depth about how Europe is failing horribly relative to the US (not to mention East Asia).</p>
      <p>So why is the US doing so well?</p>
      <p>Lets go back to 2016. Trump picked Scott Gottlieb for FDA head, heavily criticized at the time. Gottlieb was a big proponent of FDA deregulation and getting drugs to market faster. In particular, faster approvals of generic drugs was a key policy of Trump to reduce drug prices.</p>
      <p>Needless to say, our elites disapproved.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-health-fda-gottlieb-idUSKBN16H2AM">https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-health-fda-gottlieb-idUSKBN16H2AM</a>
        <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2017/04/04/health/fda-gottlieb-background-qualifications/index.html">https://www.cnn.com/2017/04/04/health/fda-gottlieb-background-qualifications/index.html</a>
        <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/04/15/us/politics/trump-appointees-potential-conflicts.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2017/04/15/us/politics/trump-appointees-potential-conflicts.html</a>
      </p>
      <p>Gottlieb and others did push deregulation, including of <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/food/2020/12/18/deregulate-frozen-cherry-pie/">random silly things</a>. </p>
      <p>Around 2019, Trump got interested in vaccines. He wound up passing an <a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/FR-2019-09-24/pdf/2019-20804.pdf">executive order</a> based on the premise that production and scale matters a lot, efficacy matters less because the goal is herd immunity. The main target of the EO was flu vaccines and pharma companies shipping (as the FDA/CDC requested) small numbers of doses of high efficacy flu vaccines.</p>
      <p>Also from a 2019 report from Trump's Council of Economic Advisers:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>...innovation to increase the speed of vaccine production is key. Improving vaccine efficacy  alone  will  be  of  little  value in  a pandemic if...the  vaccine  only  becomes  available  after  a  large  number  of  infections  have occurred. Improving efficacy only yields value after greater speed has been achieved.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>With this in mind, come 2020. Starting as early as Feb, Trump was talking about the need for a vaccine. </p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefings-statements/remarks-president-trump-press-conference-4/">https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefings-statements/remarks-president-trump-press-conference-4/</a>
      </p>
      <p>In May (about 4 months after the first vaccine was created!) Trump started getting optimistic about it, suggesting it could be available by year end:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/1260919777301798912">https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/1260919777301798912</a>
      </p>
      <p>In May the establishment (FDA officials, the media, etc) was calling Trump a liar for suggesting the vaccine could be ready in 2020:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/coronavirus-live-updates/2020/08/05/899411652/fda-adviser-not-realistic-to-expect-a-covid-19-vaccine-in-2020">https://www.npr.org/sections/coronavirus-live-updates/2020/08/05/899411652/fda-adviser-not-realistic-to-expect-a-covid-19-vaccine-in-2020</a>
        <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/trump-promises-coronavirus-vaccine-end-year-experts-temper/story?id=70712823">https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/trump-promises-coronavirus-vaccine-end-year-experts-temper/story?id=70712823</a>
        <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/congress/coronavirus-whistleblower-bright-issues-stark-vaccine-warning-we-don-t-n1207056">https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/congress/coronavirus-whistleblower-bright-issues-stark-vaccine-warning-we-don-t-n1207056</a>
        <a href="https://thehill.com/policy/healthcare/public-global-health/484702-health-official-says-coronavirus-vaccine-will-take-at">https://thehill.com/policy/healthcare/public-global-health/484702-health-official-says-coronavirus-vaccine-will-take-at</a>
        <a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.ca/entry/trump-coronavirus-promise_n_5eab2740c5b635cbe76d2097">https://www.huffingtonpost.ca/entry/trump-coronavirus-promise_n_5eab2740c5b635cbe76d2097</a>
      </p>
      <p>What happened?</p>
      <p>Casey Mulligan - the leader of Trump's Council of Economic Advisers - has now provided some insight into what happened:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I was in the Oval Office with the president and his economic team in February (when COVID-19 cases were beginning to spread).  His staff was worried that the FDA would not be interested in removing any more approval barriers.  But the President was confident, telling us that “I’ve done it before and will do it again … bring the FDA management in here.”  President Trump initiated his Operation Warp speed, led by HHS, to give many private companies incentives for “speed and scale” of vaccine production and to give all companies the opportunity for streamlined FDA approval.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>
        <a href="http://caseymulligan.blogspot.com/2020/12/how-economics-helped-end-pandemic.html">http://caseymulligan.blogspot.com/2020/12/how-economics-helped-end-pandemic.html</a>
      </p>
      <p>So after all this, it looked like Trump - and no other major politician - was actually the right person to handle COVID. He recognized that the bureaucrats at the FDA were the problem and did what he could to get them out of the way. I suspect that no other US politician would have done the same. From what Der Spiegel writes, it appears that no Euro politicians (besides perhaps Boris Johnson) were willing to either.</p>
      <p>I would love to hear criticisms and thoughts on these claims. It's an idea I'm trying out and find plausible - but certainly not ironclad.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>