<post>
  <author>ZorbaTHut</author>
  <date>2020-12-16T14:57:46Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/kcsx2u/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_december_14/gg1a87t/</link>
  <title>/u/ZorbaTHut uses CCG meta to teach us about the inanity of recommending reforms without identifying tradeoffs</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So there's this guy called Day9.</p>
      <p>(Bear with me, I'm going somewhere with this.)</p>
      <p>Day9 is a game streamer online. I frankly don't know what he's best known for at this point, he's been doing game streaming online since before game streaming online was a thing. One game he plays a bunch of is Hearthstone.</p>
      <p>Hearthstone is a collectible card game similar to Magic. You have a deck of 30 cards and you try to use those cards to kill your opponent. If they pull out something clever and you don't have a card with a response to it, then you probably lose.</p>
      <p>For a long time, whenever he would play Hearthstone, he would be barraged by suggestions. "Add a Dark Iron Dwarf!" "If you'd have Electra Stormsurge, he'd be dead by now!" "You could have survived that with Kronx Dragonhoof!" These suggestions were generally <em>accurate</em>, but also useless.</p>
      <p>Because, remember, you have a deck of 30 cards. You do not have a deck of "30 cards, plus Electra Stormsurge I guess." You can't just <em>add</em> things; every card you put in your deck is also a card you have to take out of your deck.</p>
      <p>So eventually he had a new policy. If you wanted him to add a card, you <em>also</em> had to tell him what card to take out. The barrage immediately stopped; it's much much easier to recognize that magically adding a card is a good idea than it is to recognize which card should be removed in its favor.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>I think you're right. Teaching people Latin and Greek would be nice. If we could do that for free, we should do it.</p>
      <p>But we can't. School days are already far too long, and we already don't have enough money to provide the good schooling you want to introduce.</p>
      <p>So: Okay, that's a proposal. What do we remove in its favor? You want two years of classical civilization education; tell me what two years of existing education you're willing to throw away.</p>
      <p>Then we've got something to talk about.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>