<post>
  <author>CanIHaveASong</author>
  <date>2020-10-22T23:35:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9pcksb/</link>
  <title>Male Privilege in the Gymnasium</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Some time ago, a friend of mine was kind enough to describe her experience of white privilege from her perspective as an African immigrant.  It helped me make firm a concept that had seemed vague and slightly sinister before.  Defining concepts concretely is always helpful for discourse, but I've never seen privilege steelmaned here before.  So, as privilege is absolutely culture war, I thought it was worth pennning something out, based on my own experience.  </p>
      <p>Before Covid hit, I was a regular at my local gym.  Three times a week, I warmed up at the treadmill or  the stairs, then I hit the weightroom.  It was my happy place.  I like getting stronger, and seeing my body become capable of more and more.  However, as my weightlifting routine grew more advanced and more focused on freeweights, I began to notice something:  The weightroom was not built for women like me.  Equipment was too big, the weight increments were too heavy, and the available equipment was designed for male-centric routines.  </p>
      <p>I'll give some specific examples.  The row machine has weight increments of 15 pounds.  This is too high for me.  The gym owners compensate by having 7.5 pound weights you can put on top of the standard weight stack.  However, these are in great demand, so they tend to float around the gym, and are inconvenient to track down.  The dumbbell rack has weights in 5 pound increments.  For most excersizes, this is okay, but small muscles, such as some shoulder muslces and the triceps, need a smaller weight increase for my female body.  The gym stocks 7.5 pound and 12.5 pound dumbbells, but they also have no standard home and float all over the gym.  They are an inconvenience to track down.  There's a squat machine that requires you to push up with your shoulders.  The shoulder pads are too far apart for my shoulders, and they rest on the very outer edges.  It makes the machine very uncomfortable to use, and I end up pushing with my shoulder/arms instead of with my torso.  Similarly, all the pullup stations have grips that are too wide for me.  Some franchises (but not all!) have a squat cage that can double as a pullup station, but it's almost always in use, so I have to wait in line.  I always have to fiddle with the cage, installing the foot rests and taking the bar out, before I can use it to pull up.  The hamstring curl machine is usable, but it's designed for longer legs than I possess, so I can never get it set quite right.  There's a dedicated piece of equipment for doing shrugs.  I only ever see men use it, and then only rarely.  Most men who do shrugs just do them with dumbbells.  They just grab the relevant dumbbells and shrug.  Easy peasy.  Despite this specialty machine being available for men, there is no piece of equipment for the most popular female exercise:  Hip thrusts.  If we want to thrust, we have to wait for a bench with a barbell to open up, put the barbel on the floor, and find the one barbell pad the gym possess, which is never in the same place twice.  Then, when we have assembled everything, we can wriggle under the ensemble, and perform our exercise.  </p>
      <p>But Canihaveasong, it sounds like you use the gym just fine?  I do.  However, compared to a man with a similar routine, I'm inconvenienced a lot more.  I have to search the gym for the relevant equipment, and wait more for the stuff I can use.  A lot of the equipment is designed without realizing someone my size and sex might want to use it.  Most men who lift won't realize a woman is inconvenienced in all these little ways.  After all, the pull up bars work for him.  The weight increments are just fine.  This is is male privilege.  The system was designed for men, and anyone else is going to have an inferior experience.  </p>
      <p>The weight room is not the only place male privilege exists.  Drug trials have historically <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2019/jul/28/medical-bias-against-women-drug-trials-cpr-medicine-gender-inequalities">defaulted to using men</a>, so women are more likely to get dosed incorrectly.  <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2019/feb/23/truth-world-built-for-men-car-crashes">Crash test dummies</a> are designed to represent the average male.  As a result, women are 47% more likely to be seriously injured in a crash.  Having male privilege doesn't mean men are bad.  It just means men are thought of as the default. </p>
      <p>When people talk about dismantling privilege, what they mean (in the steel-man sense), is no longer assuming one kind of person as default, and instead trying to accommodate all users.  </p>
      <p>When my gym renovated just before Covid hit, they changed their hamstring curl machine out to a model with more pivot points.  I could finally set it to my size!  Of course, this is not without consequence to men.  They now have two more pins to fiddle with to the get the machine set up right.  By including women, men are slightly inconvenienced.  For that matter, the change to two sexes of crash test dummies will mean that car safety is not precisely tailored to male bodies anymore.  Male safety may suffer slightly.  Are these acceptable sacrifices to be inclusive?  </p>
      <p>It would probably be unreasonable for my gym to accommodate women to the same degree it accommodates men.  After all, women are only 10% of the weightlifters, if that.  However, there are small things they could do to make our experience better:  More adjustable machines, pull up bars for our size, etc.  A lot of women feel out of place in the weightroom, like it's a place we're not welcome.  (You can go to <a href="/r/xxfitness">/r/xxfitness</a> if you doubt me here).   If the weightroom  had more equipment for women would more of us lift?  Maybe, maybe not.  However, if it were friendlier to my sex, my routine would be a lot quicker.</p>
      <p>edit:  To fix some grammar.</p>
      <p>edit2:  Replied to the most common complaint in a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9rxya7/">top level comment</a> below.</p>
      <p>edit3:  I have gotten many responses, and many of them very similar.  I cannot reply to each one.  If you make a comment that stands out from the crowd, I'll try to find time for it.  However, I want to respond to a few additional common criticisms.  I point out in another comment that the gym could better accommodate women without harming male users with <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9r9lzn/">less than $1000 worth of additional equipment</a>.  Making the gym more friendly to women does not mean making it more hostile to men, and it does not mean making huge, expensive changes.  In addition, I see a lot of people disregarding what I mean to be a "motte" argument, and instead arguing against the "bailey" of reparations, equity in professional jobs, etc.  I will not respond to those posts, as I'm not arguing for any of those things.  </p>
      <p>In addition, regarding my reply to the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9rxya7/">most common complaint</a>, I think to some degree my sparring partners and I are grouping concepts differently or disagreeing on semantics.  I believe I understand where they are coming from, but I disagree that it's a meaningful distinction.  </p>
      <p>Thank you, and have a good evening!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>