<post>
  <author>CPlusPlusDeveloper</author>
  <date>2020-10-19T21:42:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9ddpi5/</link>
  <title>Defending the Rational Addiction Model</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Addiction often (not in every case, but in many cases) represents irrational behavior</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I think this is too quick to discount the rational addiction model. Yes, most addicts profess a supposedly sincere desire to kick the habit. But this is exactly what we'd expect them to say, given social desirability bias. </p>
      <p>If I'm an unrepentant drunk, why would I publicly advertise it? Much better to tell everyone that I'm in the swirls of an addiction, that I'm desperately trying to escape. I don't love alcohol, in fact I hate it, but it's got a grip on me. That way I can still get loaded, but most people will feel sorry for me instead of getting angry at my bad behavior.</p>
      <p>People in the United States enjoy an exceptionally high level of material living standards. Much higher than <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_household_final_consumption_expenditure_per_capita">any other large country</a>. Despite public perception, America also has a very progressive tax system and extensive welfare benefits. Even the bottom quintile, despite widespread non-participation in the labor force, <a href="https://pubs.aeaweb.org/doi/pdfplus/10.1257/jep.30.2.3">enjoy a standard of living</a> comparable to middle-class professionals in Europe. </p>
      <p>Like most things, what makes the US exceptional in this regard is its exceptionally high level of aggregate wealth. Given our much higher economic productivity, America is simply further down the road to a post-scarcity society. And the reality is that when humans no longer have to get their ass out of bed to avoid starving, many will simply choose to pass the time by getting high, watching TV, browsing social media, and eating tasty food. Of course most everyone will talk a big game about bigger dreams and ambitions, but without anybody holding their feet to the flame this is mostly just idle chatter.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>