<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-10-20T19:21:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9gouaj/</link>
  <title>Who Enforces Norms of Masculinity? (Quality Thread)</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Yesterday I raised the question of whether - and why - young men seem to be comparatively bad at the kind of low-stakes social media communication that women excel at. The example I gave was from a language exchange app, but the consensus in the comments seemed to be that this was a broader phenomenon also visible in places like Instagram, Facebook, etc..</p>
      <p>What I found particularly interesting was the idea raised by some posters that <em>norms of masculinity</em> make it harder for men to post engaging content on these platforms, since cat pictures, delicious cupcakes, etc. get coded feminine. Whether or not this specific example holds water, I definitely got the impression from some (presumably male) commenters that they felt at least a little constricted by norms of masculine conduct, and that's what I want to discuss a bit more now. Specifically, I want to hear people's views on the following question: <strong>who enforces norms of masculinity, and who do they benefit?</strong></p>
      <p>My agenda here, insofar as I have one, stems from my own life experience, so I hope you'll forgive a bit of navel-gazing.</p>
      <p>To simplify a bit, I spent my early teens in a fairly typical macho young male environment in which lots of stuff was coded as 'gay' or otherwise uncool because it wasn't seen as masculine. Over time, I fell in with the drama crowd and the indie music crowd, both of which were far more lax about these norms, and in short, it was a liberating experience.</p>
      <p>It also resulted in me having a lot more sex than I otherwise would have done. As I leaned into the more flamboyant aspects of my personality, my social status rocketed. The first time I made out with a girl at a party, it was because I was the only guy who'd let her put mascara on me. The first time I slept with a girl it was (in part) because she was impressed at my vegetarianism (something that had been routinely mocked as gay and un-masculine by my friendship group). And on the first occasion when I enjoyed the company of two women at the same time, it was after I'd had a long conversation with both of them about horoscopes, including correctly guessing their star signs (sometimes you get lucky). And in general, in my adult life, I've not given a fig for norms of masculinity, happily posting cat pictures and Frozen pastiches to social media, and as far as I can tell it's worked out very well.</p>
      <p>I mention this not to brag, but just to note that in my own perhaps very partial experience, rejecting some of the conventional norms of masculinity led to more, not less, success in the straight dating marketplace. Which in turn makes me wonder: if it's not women enforcing  norms around masculine behaviour, then is it men? If so, why?</p>
      <p>I have a few thoughts about this. One possibility is that I'm unusually well placed to violate some masculine norms and get away with it. I'm a tall, burly, extremely hairy guy (my nickname for a long time was "wolf boy") whose mannerisms and voice are pretty traditionally masculine. So maybe it's a "only Nixon could go to China" phenomenon - I could violate masculine norms only because my broader presentation was quite masculine, and other men who tried the same thing might not get away with it, at least not without diminishing their dating prospects</p>
      <p>Another possibility is of course that it only works in my own specific bubbles. The crowd I've run with most of my life has been intellectual, artistic, and flamboyant. Perhaps if I'd grown up in small town Idaho I wouldn't have been able to get away with it. I will mention that on the occasions when I've spent time in small town America, my flamboyant eccentric Brit-shtick seemed to go down a charm (but perhaps quod licet Britannicis non licet Americanis?). But in any case, even if there's a bubble effect, it still doesn't answer the question of who's enforcing these norms and why.</p>
      <p>One hypothesis I'm taking increasingly seriously is that most norms of masculinity are basically enforced by men in a kind of prisoner's dilemma situation. To offer a hopelessly crude Pleistocene analogy: if one guy hangs back from the mammoth hunt to go berry picking with the women, maybe he'll end up having a roll in the grass with one of the girls. But if all the men do that, it'll become a zero sum competition, and at the end of the day you still won't have any mammoth meat. So even if violation of masculine gender norms might be a benefit to a defecting individual, it's a harm to men at large.</p>
      <p>That's a very crude bit of evo-psych theorising, but I'd note that it matches what I've heard a lot of women say about the way that (some) norms of femininity and slut-shaming work: that they're enforced by women to basically prevent defection in social game-theoretic contexts. Maybe Pamela can get an edge in her local dating scene by wearing risque outfits, or always hanging out with the boys, but if she does that, it's just going to lead to a race to the bottom (so to speak). So Pamela gets called out for being a slut and a Pickmeisha.</p>
      <p>I should add that I don't endorse the idea that all norms of masculinity should be abandoned - there are a bunch of quite healthy and admirable aspects of masculine identity that are absolutely worth preserving. But there seem to be a bunch of relatively arbitrary and pointless ones (why is liking Disney or horoscopes or cats coded as childish and feminine, but computer games and Warhammer coded as masculine?).</p>
      <p>I guess I should note in closing that I recognise that a lot of the above ideas are already well-trodden in feminist theory via ideas like toxic masculinity. But I deliberately wanted to avoid getting bogged down in debates about these very loaded political terms.</p>
      <p>In any case, I'm curious what other men here think about all this - where gender norms around masculinity come from, how they're enforced, whether they're in general a good thing, and perhaps most importantly, how their enforcement is experienced (who does the shaming?). And of course, I'd also be curious to hear from our female posters about their equivalent experiences with norms of femininity.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>