<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-10-19T19:25:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9cwhec/</link>
  <title>A Hereditarian Left View of State Compensation for Disadvantageous Traits</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>&gt;  Forget genetic disadvantage. People who are rude and insulting have a disadvantage. Should the left then promote special advantages for the rude and insulting, in order to compensate for their disadvantage?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Speaking as someone who skews hereditarian leftist (in economic issues), I think it's fair for the state to compensate individuals for disadvantageous traits that have the following broad profile -</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(1) Relatively immutable.</strong> If a trait is bad for me but I (or society) can do fairly straightforward things to change it, that suggests that there are better approaches than direct compensation. If someone is bad at reading because of lack of education, it's generally going to be better to help them via improving their reading; but if they're bad at reading because of an immutable neurological deficit causing total alexia, then compensation might be a better option.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(2) Not antisocial.</strong> Mutable or not, it sits poorly with our moral intuitions about justice to compensate people for traits that are associated with immoral behaviour, even if those traits are not readily mutable. Compensating someone for having an immutable trait that makes them shy is going to be an easier sell as a policy than compensating someone for a similarly immutable trait that makes them rude and aggressive. Part of this is just bedrock moral intuition about the kind of things society should react positively towards, but there's also the concern that by compensating people for immutable antisocial traits, you risk glamorising those traits and encouraging others (whose possession of the trait may not be a done deal) to acquire them/not outgrow them.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>(3) Relatively legible (both in terms of possession and negative consequences).</strong> Finally, since we're dealing with policy, we have to operate in the realm of things that the state can and can't readily do and aren't particularly open to abuse. These legibility concerns kick in both at the level of initial assessment (does the individual in fact possess the trait?) and at the level of cost calculation (what's the dollar cost of them having this trait?). If a trait is relatively easy to fake (e.g. back pain) then it's harder to implement a fair and generous system for compensating for it without inviting abuse of the system. Likewise, if a trait is associated with relatively abstract and complex social disadvantages (e.g., being unattractive), it's going to be harder to effectively compensate for it than if it's associated with straightforward economic disadvantages (e.g., being unable to work due to chronic pain).</p>
      <p>These are the core ingredients that I think should go into our 'state disadvantage compensation regime'. At one extreme, we might have a disadvantageous trait that is immutable, not antisocial, and highly legible, such as not having the use of one's legs. At the other extreme, we might have a mutable trait that is antisocial and not particularly legible; for the purposes of example, imagine someone who has low social status because they use racial slurs and profanities all the time. These latter traits are going to be better dealt with through other social and political tools than direct compensation.</p>
      <p>I think if you twiddle with these knobs, so to speak, you can shunt around our moral intuitions about whether it's reasonable to compensate someone in a given case. So if our imaginary person who uses profanities all the time has a medical diagnosis of Tourette's and is already on all appropriate treatments for it, then that twists the mutability knob down and the legibility knob upwards (because it's fairly easy to get a clean diagnosis of Tourette's). At that point compensation for disadvantages associated with the trait starts to look more reasonable to me.</p>
      <p>A really tricky case for me and others of a similar mindset is being very physically unattractive. This seems to me to be a trait that's mostly immutable and relatively non-antisocial (sure, it's nice to be around attractive people, but it's a fairly minor effect; as a married guy, I wouldn't take a wage hit to be around more attractive coworkers). On the face of it, this might seem a good target for compensation. But I think the legibility aspect is where things get tricky. While it's relatively easy for us to identify very unattractive people, and there are significant lifetime costs associated with being very unattractive, these are very hard to quantify in an individual case: unless you're trying to be a model, there aren't going to be many jobs you simply can't do by virtue of being ugly. Nonetheless, in a post-scarcity economy with smart AIs to help us figure these things out, I think there would be a solid philosophical case to be made for compensation for very unattractive people.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>