<post>
  <author>is_not_strained</author>
  <date>2020-10-22T17:28:27Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9o0xst/</link>
  <title>Armchair Economics on Immigration</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I got a little pushback on a recent comment on immigration, so I thought I would give a little more detail in my criticism of mainstream analysis. Economists love to tell people that various types of taxation are bad.  For example, corporate profits should not be taxed, not should capital gains.  Everyone happily ignores this, as the models are too simplistic to apply to the real world.  However, when economists use similar models to analyze immigration and find it an unalloyed good, people seize on this as proof that immigration should be increased without bound.</p>
      <p>I see there being 5 types of immigration, 2 of which create clear benefits to the host society, and three of which are generally harmful to the host society.  This does not mean that only the first 2 should be allowed.  Perhaps some society might choose to suffer in order to help others.   The five types are asylum/refugees, poor and untrained, generic professional workers, superstar talent, and direct family (oversea spouses).   </p>
      <p>I'll start with perhaps the easiest, refugees.  It is worth considering the entire refugee issue.  The whole idea really only makes sense for Jewish people in the pre-Israel era.  There was a tendency for hundreds of years, for occasional pogroms.  In these cases, Jewish people could easily move from one sub-society in one country to another, as the other countries also had Jewish communities.  They could not move to a homeland, as they had none.  Consider what would happen if a group of French people was oppressed somewhere - they would move to France.  The same applies to all groups with countries.  Before Jewish people had a country to retreat to, refugee resettlement or asylum made sense.  </p>
      <p>Does it make sense now?  Well, there are three main cases.  The first is when a country descends into civil war, and decides to expel a large group or make things bad enough that a large group flees.  Should the rest of the world have a policy that, in this case, people get to move to whatever first world country they like?  That seems crazy to me.  The first world should stop the civil war, and ensure people are not expelled.  That is what the UN is for.  The Rohingya should not be moved on masse to Ohio.  Instead, Burma should be nicer.  The same applies to the other major sources. Merely because a country is doing badly, should not gift one of the sides with free access to one of the most valuable things in the world, first world citizenship.  If like Ilhan Omar's family, you decide to lead and fight in a civil war, you should not get the consolation prize of living in Minnesota.  This is incentivizing misbehavior.  The same applies to Afghanistan, Ukraine, Libya, etc. </p>
      <p>There is a second kind of refugee, the people who were recruited by local gangs and decided to leave, or women who were victims of domestic violence, or sexual minorities who were threatened, or people who live in areas where the murder rate is high. I'm sorry some people's countries are bad, but realistically, the vast majority of people in the world live somewhere like that, and they can't all fit in the first world.  Under the broad excuses that people give for refugee claims, pretty much everyone, or perhaps 75% of the world would be covered.  This is just too much.</p>
      <p>That brings me to the third refugee/asylee group, people who are involved in politics in the source country and fail afoul of the local government.  There are two sub-cases, one where the government is actually bad, an enemy of the US, and where the US wants to support the insurgency.  I support asylum status for Victor Laszlo, and she should have got on that plane, Bogart notwithstanding.  For countries that are not Nazi Germany 1941-45, I am less impressed.  I don't like the US encouraging governments in exile, and would rather diplomatic pressure to allow better treatment of dissidents.  In the Cold Wat, this made sense.  Right now, save for Iran, and possibly China, I don't see the need for the US to support dissidents, as the problem, countries repressing other political parties, is just not happening, and the risks on the other side, of the UK hosting Mr. Ulyanov, while he plots in exile, are too high.</p>
      <p>So, minimal refugees, save those that really need it.  Onto the poor and uneducated.  Lots of people will talk about the importance of introducing UBI as, soon, there will be no jobs for many people.  From this, I see that we don't need the poor and uneducated, as soon, there will not be jobs even for locals.  I don't understand how people can simultaneously believe that UBI is needed, and support mass immigration of the poor.  </p>
      <p>Suppose the need for UBI is delayed.  Poor immigration is supposed to help in that case by doing jobs more cheaply than local people will work.  The problem for locals is the huge redistribution that the US system assumes.  These imported workers are given all the usual benefits (roads, emergency medical care, emergency services, police, water, all the stuff the Romans did for us), and their children are given all that and more, as the insidious affirmative action of the US kicks in.  Half of the college places in California are dedicated to the children of the recent poor immigrants, and costs like that are never accounted for in economic calculations.  I know this makes the "lump of college" fallacy, as of course the size of colleges will just increase as we allow more immigrants, but, in fact, the "lump of Ivy" fallacy is fairly accurate. The top colleges have not increased in the last 30 years.  However, now 50% of those colleges go to the children of recent immigrants or foreigners.  The usual claim that the pie naturally increases is falsified here. </p>
      <p>If not the poor, nor the oppressed, is educated labor helpful?  There are two main cases that I want to consider.  Take doctors:  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Association_of_Physicians_of_Indian_Origin">25% of US doctors are from India</a>. They do medical school in India and come to the US.  <a href="https://www.irishtimes.com/news/health/ireland-relies-heavily-on-foreign-trained-doctors-report-shows-1.4075535">42%</a> of Irish doctors are foreign.  Is this because American or Irish people don't want to be doctors?  No, the requirements to get into medical school in both places are insanely high, and many, many people who would be great doctors cannot get in.  Why don't these countries let more citizens become doctors? There is no evidence that this would hurt the quality of care, and in fact, due to better familiarity with local customs and norms, would probably make care better (at least in Ireland).  </p>
      <p>Every professional that immigrates to a first-world country is taking a slot from a local.  These are not just good jobs, but great jobs, and so the locals who are displaced are hurt by this.  Is the broader society helped by these immigrant doctors?  There is an argument for allowing immigration when there is a transient shortage.  This argument is much weaker when the immigrants need to do a residency before practicing, and this argument only applies to transient shortages where there really is a need for more doctors.  In the long term, more Americans or Irish should go to medical school.</p>
      <p>The same applies to STEM fields.  The vast bulk of H1-Bs does work that Americans could so just as well, or better in most cases.  <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/116/14/6732">Graduates of American colleges</a> in CS are a standard deviation better than foreign workers.   H1Bs are recruited, in the ain, not because they are better, but because they are cheaper.  </p>
      <p>Not all H1Bs are of mediocre quality.  Some immigrants are superstars. The immigrants who founded <a href="https://fortune.com/2019/01/15/immigrants-founded-half-fortune-500-companies/">Fortune 500</a> companies came from Europe in the main, though 4 did come from China.  None came from India, though this is a little unfair, as the source no longer counts SUN, who did have Vinod Khosla, an Indian immigrant.    There is another Indian, Francisco D'Souza, who is one of the two people born in Africa who have founded Fortune 500 companies, the other is Elon Musk.  (Francisco's father was called Placido, and his sisters are Jacinta, Lucia, and Maria, none of which are traditionally Indian names).</p>
      <p>Jensen Huang founded Nvidia, Bob Huang founded Synnex, both Taiwanese.  David Lam, of Lam Research, is the lone founder from China (Hong Kong).  As Yahoo was acquired, Jerry Yang, also Taiwanese, is not on the list.  All of these attended either top American colleges or Rochester and Temple.  There is a good argument that graduates of top colleges (&lt; 50 in college rankings) provide real value to America that is accretive to overall prosperity.  These superstars should be encouraged to immigrate.</p>
      <p>Finally, we have foreign spouses, people who come to a country and fall in love with the place and want to stay.  I support people being allowed to immigrate for reasons like this, but obviously, this needs to be regulated.  I see no great reason for limiting immigration of foreign spouses in any way, and I would like people to be able to stay if they really want to.  I just recognize that the number of people in the latter category is just too high not to require some limiting factors.  </p>
      <p>A final note on arguing against interest:  I am currently possibly illegally in the US (it is a minor issue, I hope, and it should be fixable, especially under a Biden presidency) so I recognize that I am supporting policies that would hurt me in general.  That said, I probably could count under all five headings, depending on what point in my life you look at, and whether you consider some youthful exuberance to be a threat to the state (not America, another regime that no longer exists, only partially (very, very partially) due to my efforts).</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>