<post>
  <author>LawOfTheGrokodus</author>
  <date>2020-10-20T00:00:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9dszep/</link>
  <title>On Section 230 and Restrictions on Online Speech</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>There is a serious effort to repeal or put onerous and dubiously-constitutional conditions on Section 230 protections. I was a libertarian a while back, but I have come to recognize how oppressive and coordinated a semi-free market can be.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Section 230 probably doesn't do what you think it does. All it says is that entities are only liable for what they themselves say online. This is why, if I were to hypothetically post a true threat or some other not-constitutionally-protected message here, neither Reddit nor poor <a href="/u/ZorbaTHut">u/ZorbaTHut</a> would be in hot water. In the absence of Section 230, the only options are:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>An exhaustive regime of moderation that exclusively allows through messages that have been hand-checked to make sure they don't contain anything that could result in liability.</li>
        <li>A total ban on user-generated content.</li>
        <li>A total ban on moderation except maybe to remove actively illegal material.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>None of these are likely to be satisfactory. I have some desire to at least see option 3, but I'm pretty sure people won't like it. And even if you think our current crop of internet giants are corrupt and won't mourn their passing, repealing Section 230 won't just kill them — it will render any future computer service that allows vaguely free user contributions nonviable. Not just websites: in-game chat systems are kaput, as are communication tools like Discord. The liability is effectively infinite. IRC and email might survive since they are living option 3, but I think spam filters could be in trouble.</p>
      <p>Please correct me if I'm wrongly assuming here, but I'm guessing you want Section 230 constrained or repealed thanks to political bias by companies like Facebook and Twitter? If so, I hope you see that a repeal would accomplish that only in the same way that detonating an EMP over the country would. (I recognize that it's possible that you actually affirmatively think it would be a good thing for the internet itself to be destroyed, setting aside any matters of partisan bias. While I actually find that a more reasonable view than you might expect, you must acknowledge that it's wildly unpopular and it occurring accidentally would invite a backlash for the ages.)</p>
      <p>If you are concerned about partisan bias, putting conditions on Section 230 would be a better way to go. It's a popular idea: at a conference on election integrity I attended, a (Democratic) FEC commissioner passionately pushed for conditioning Section 230 protections on websites making an effort to fight "misinformation," the nature of which I'm sure you can imagine. And that's the problem: both partisan moderation and misinformation/hate speech/disliking AOC are clear-cut instances of first-amendment-protected speech. Both you and that FEC commissioner want the government to violate  protections on free speech, and are using the threat of unlimited liability from withdrawal of Section 230 protections as a cudgel to force websites into compliance. Courts aren't stupid and judges across the ideological spectrum are pretty good on the free speech front; that's not the sort of thing that passes muster.</p>
      <p>But while I'm slapping down your(?) proposal to threaten Section 230 protections to compel behavior in a way not permitted by the first amendment, I would be remiss to note that while Twitter et al aren't acting unconstitutionally (since that only binds the government), they are acting counter to the spirit of free speech, and therefore in my view wrongly. The problem is like the problem with many proposed remedies for hate speech: of all entities in this country, the government is uniquely constrained from fixing a problem where people are using their free speech rights in immoral ways. (Which is a good thing, because I know the government's idea of immoral speech doesn't remotely match mine, and you should know it doesn't match yours either.) You're petitioning the one entity in the whole country legally barred from interfering with Twitter's ability to use its free speech rights in immoral ways. But it might also be the one entity powerful enough to check them.</p>
      <p>Markets aren't doing great at remedying this: Parler... exists, but let's be real, it's not a true competitor to Twitter. I'd say Facebook is a true competitor to Twitter, but of course Democrats and Republicans would agree it has many of the same problems. I'm open to the idea that antitrust laws could help, giving the folks on the left their no-hate-speech utopia, and the folks on the right their garden-free-from-censorship, but I honestly don't think that Facebook and Twitter at least are monopolists, and anyhow our society isn't so pillarized that a theoretically crosspartisan platform like Facebook isn't something people want. The government could make their own social media platform, but it couldn't have any moderation at all, and so would probably not have an especially appealing crowd of people in among the constitutionally protected ads for penis extension supplements (complete with before and after photos!).</p>
      <p>My druthers for government action that would pass constitutional muster, not destroy the internet, bolster competition, and ameliorate issues of internet giants unaccountably using their speech rights in bad ways would be to enact regulation requiring interoperability between social media services. If I make UncensoredBook, I should be able to communicate with my friends on Facebook in the app. If I make a post, my friends on Facebook should be able to see it if it's in compliance with their moderation rules and vice versa.</p>
      <p>This isn't perfect. First of all, there's technical challenges. But as I've seen folks here point out, the censorship from the left can jump one level lower. I think I'd be okay with nationalizing Cloudflare, under the knowledge that it would provide DDOS protections for Nazis and commies and ISIS and pornographers alike. Eventually, we get to "Well just make your own global financial system." That's not great either. I will say that think at that point, such a system is somewhat more resistant to censorship from social pressure, since it's further disconnected from the objectionable content than a social media site that appears in every screenshot of the objectionable material. But if the problem continues even to that level, I would support government-guaranteed backup payment processors and crediting. I don't know the legal issues around this topic nearly as well, so I'm not sure what is allowed there. Maybe this is actually something blockchain can help with?</p>
      <p>EDIT: Incidentally, the Fairness Doctrine was held to be constitutional because of the scarcity of space on the radio spectrum, a rationale that would not apply in the nigh-unlimited space of URLs.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>