<post>
  <author>Mottizen</author>
  <date>2020-10-22T15:57:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9npktq/</link>
  <title>The Wendigo Psychosis Theory of Jordan Peterson</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I stand by the Wendigo psychosis theory. I don't have the original 4chan post saved, but basically, Wendigo psychosis is a historical "culture-specific disorder" for Algonquin peoples that inspires them with irrepressible cannibalistic urges. This was linked in their folklore to the Wendigo, an evil spirit that possesses people after they taste human flesh. You might write it off but Robert Brightman's <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/482140">"The Windigo in the Material World"</a> is an interesting overview of symptoms, with several examples of historical "wendigo psychotics" stretching from the mid 17th to early 20th centuries. Nor was this restricted to the east Canadian tribes, as there's a parallel "wechuge complex" known to the Beaver tribe in western Canada.</p>
      <p>It's not very well-known even among his fans, but in JBP's academic years he was involved with Native American tribes and participated in different kinds of rituals. He's particularly close with the Kwakwakaʼwakw, to the point that he was given the name Alestalegie ("Great Seeker") in a Kwakwakaʼwakw ceremony (as documented <a href="https://www.jordanbpeterson.com/media/kwakwakawakw-controversy/">on his website</a>). There are four main "secret societies" in Kwakwakaʼwakw culture, and the most prestigious is the Hamatsa ("Cannibal") society. Historically, according to Hamatsa members, literal cannibalism was practiced during their secret initiation ceremony. But Wikipedia assures readers that <em>of course</em> this no longer happens.</p>
      <p>Compare JBP's symptoms to those of Wendigo psychosis. In <em>Maps of Meaning</em>, he talks about persistent thoughts of incest and cannibalism. In the year or two before he disappeared into a Russian hospital, he and his daughter became the most prominent advocates of a strict carnivore diet, and in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HLF29w6YqXs">this JRE interview</a> Jordan describes how he experiences extreme emotional distress otherwise. He says the diet helped his health, but it obviously didn't do enough — chalk it up to benzo dependence, but between you and me, I know a lot of people who were able to kick that without needing an eight-day drug-induced coma in Siberia. I love JBP, but he doesn't need a Russian hospital, he needs an exorcist.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>