<post>
  <author>Sizzle50</author>
  <date>2020-10-21T17:27:07Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9k6n7m/</link>
  <title>The Provenance of Certain Hard Drives</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Contra MSNBC types, there is zero evidence whatsoever of Russian involvement. Rather, the provenance of these hard drives likely runs through enigmatic Chinese billionaire dissident Guy Wengui (郭文贵) AKA Guo Haoyun (郭浩云) AKA Miles Guo AKA Miles Kwok. Wengui, a Beijing real estate developer and investor, fled China in 2015 following corruption charges and has been living in exile in a luxury apartment in Manhattan. From there, Guo founded the Chinese Whistleblower Movment, sporadically leaking information and documents reflecting negatively on the CCP - the Chinese government in turn dismisses these documents as forgeries</p>
      <p>Whilst in Manhattan, Guo synced up with ousted former Trump chief strategist Steve Bannon to together form GTV Media Group. On the 31st anniversary of the Tiananmen Square Massacre, Guo, flanked by various Chinese celebrities, declared a New Federal State of China, a government-in-exile with the sole focus of overthrowing the existing Chinese government. <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-china-tiananmen-hao-idUSKBN23B1N5">The group flew banners over majors cities</a>, including NYC, and has distributed leaflets with anti-CCP claims up to and including the notion that COVID-19 is a bioweapon developed by the Chinese government</p>
      <p>In September, weeks before the NYPost's bombshell story, a Chinese dissident streamer working with GTV directly claimed that 3 hard drives containing information destined to change the outcome of the election had been sent to the US DoJ, though the DoJ slow walked the investigation. The hard drives were said to contain sex tapes of Hunter Biden showcasing abuse of underage girls, along with details of shady deals between Hunter Biden and Chinese parties, as well as the Burisma scandal and some compromising scandal in Kazakhstan. One hard drive was also stated to contain information relating to COVID-19 being released from the Wuhan Institute of Virology. A translation of the September 25 stream is <a href="https://www.brighteon.com/f7829f82-261f-471f-9bcb-3ecaaf478de1">here</a> and a contemporaneous tweet by a Guo affiliated twitter account is <a href="https://twitter.com/HimalayaGlobal/status/1310723464341286912">here</a> with a truncated excerpt</p>
      <p>The deal between Hunter Biden and Chinese parties described on the stream involved Hunter Biden being paid $1M upfront 'like a tip' and then $10M after signing for a deal worth billions. Due to <a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/news/hunter-biden-offered-10-million-annually-by-chinese-energy-firm-for-introductions-alone-email-shows/">recent leaks</a>, we now know that Hunter Biden did indeed enter into a consulting contract with China's largest private energy company, CEFC China Energy, in 2017 that earned him $10M annually "for introductions alone". Former CEFC chairman, Ye Jianming, dealt with Hunter Biden directly, <a href="https://www.washingtonexaminer.com/news/analysis-hunter-biden-tied-to-china-firm-with-questionable-dealings">gifting him a 2.8 carat diamond</a> at their first meeting, which Hunter's ex-wife claims was worth $80,000; Hunter claims it was only worth $10,000 and he gave it away to his staff and doesn't know what happened to it. Ye and Hunter discussed creating a holding company to form more a 'more lasting and lucrative arrangement' tying the two financially, including kickbacks for 'the big guy' (asserted by Fox's <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/hunter-biden-china-email-source-verifies">anonymous sources</a> to be Joe himself). Ye, who per National Review was 'connected to Chinese military and intelligence' has been detained by the CCP since 2018 for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ye_Jianming">bribing foreign officials in Hong Kong and Senegal</a>. Ye's deputy Patrick Ho was arrested in NYC on bribery charges re: Chad and Uganda contemporaneously, and his <a href="https://www.theepochtimes.com/head-of-chinese-energy-ngo-sentenced-to-3-years-in-prison-in-us_2854152.html">first phone call upon arrest was to Hunter's uncle James Biden</a></p>
      <p>Further revelations from the NYPost's leaks are <a href="https://nypost.com/2020/10/20/photo-biden-meets-hunters-alleged-partner-from-kazakhstan/">Joe Biden meeting with Hunter's business partner from Kazakhstan</a>, oligarch Kenos Rakishev. Per the recent <a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/HSGAC_Finance_Report_FINAL.pdf">Senate Report</a> on Hunter Biden's alleged corruption, Rakishev sent nearly $150,000 through intermediaries to Hunter's partner Devon Archer - currently in jail for fraud - "for a car" the same day Vice President Joe Biden arrived in Kyiv to discuss the US response to Russia's invasion of Crimea, of which <a href="https://www.rferl.org/a/ukraine-diplomatic-response-over-kazakh-president-denial-of-crimea-annexation/30308855.html">Kazakhstan</a> had been mildly supportive. Joe Biden had previously denied ever discussing Hunter's overseas business dealings at any point</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/video/2020/10/20/giuliani_i_turned_over_hunter_bidens_laptop_with_pictures_of_underage_girls_to_delaware_police.html">Last evening</a>, Giuliani announced he had turned over Hunter Biden's alleged laptop to Delaware police and that it contained photos of 'numerous underage girls' and discussions of Hunter Biden inappropriately exposing himself to a 14 year old - thought by some to be Hunter's niece Natalie based on unredacted transcripts held in Giuliani's hand during the interview</p>
      <p>All of this comes together when we see this <a href="https://i.redd.it/vlfjbitnunn51.png">photo</a> of unknown date - but predating the NYPost story - of Guo and Giuliani standing in embrace with Bannon's unmistakable visage visible in the background, and Guo-affiliated Chinese 'whistleblower' virologist Li-Meng Yan caught in the reflection. Last month, Yan co-authored a pre-print research paper <a href="https://medium.com/microbial-instincts/critical-analysis-of-the-new-preprint-that-prove-sars-cov-2-is-manmade-d9eed3c7c858">claiming that COVID-19 was developed in a Chinese lab</a></p>
      <p>So, there we have it. A billionaire Chinese dissident aligned with Trumpworld svengali Steve Bannon is the likely source of the Hunter Biden data troves as part of his ongoing war with the CCP. This is not to say that the data troves are fake - recall that the 2016 Tony Podesta hacks only involved the illegal leaks of very real and accurate information. But the various and sundry Hunter Biden scandals are just one facet of a broader initiative to push a narrative that COVID-19 was made in a Chinese lab - something <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/04/30/politics/trump-intelligence-community-china-coronavirus-origins/index.html">President Trump himself has claimed to have seen evidence of</a> - and anyone who's mentioning Russia in the context of this story is <em>wildly</em> out of their depth</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>