<post>
  <author>wlxd</author>
  <date>2020-10-20T03:41:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/jdvqk5/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_october_19/g9efhqg/</link>
  <title>Cutting Through Statistical Sophistry on Red State Tax Deficits</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Talk to me about how unfair these are when the red states start paying their fair share in taxes.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>What you link is actually a good example how the narrative is made despite the facts. The trick is to conveniently choose metrics, and name them using such words as "dependency" to imply the meaning that's simply not matching the reality on the ground. It only takes a moment to see that.</p>
      <p>Let's compare states of Florida (28th and 33rd on the lists of most "dependent" residents and state governments respectively) and California (44th and 36th). Florida is more "dependent" by their metrics. Let's look at the numbers (data is from <a href="https://ballotpedia.org/Total_state_government_expenditures">here</a> and other places).</p>
      <p>California pays $11500 per capita in federal income taxes, and its state government spends $2400 per capita from federal funds. That adds up to 21 cents getting back on every dollar sent to the feds.</p>
      <p>Florida, in comparison, pays $9500 per capita in federal income taxes, but its government only spends $1200 per capita from federal funds. That translates to 13 cents getting back on every dollar sent to the feds. "Fair shair in taxes", huh?</p>
      <p>Now, consider that the following hypothetical: imagine that Florida somehow gets the same amount of money per capita that California gets, that is, that Florida gets double of what it gets rights now. Considering that California government spends $6600 per capita in total, while Florida spends only $3700, this would allow Florida to cuts its own state taxes (already, as everyone knows, very low) in half, while keeping the same level of services. However, doing so would make Florida <strong>more</strong> "dependent" on Federal Government by the absurd metrics you linked.</p>
      <p>In fact, the easiest way to become less "dependent" for a state is to create tons of new state spending programs, and increase state taxes to cover them: you keep getting the exact same amount of money from the federal government, but now your state government is less "dependent" on the feds. Conversely, if you cut your services so much that whatever is left can be fully covered from the money you get from the feds, which allows you to cut all your taxes to zero, you score of "dependency" is now <em>infinite</em>, even though you could easily bump your taxes a bit to cover your minimal spend in a scenario where all money from the feds evaporates.</p>
      <p>To sum up, what you link is prime example of statistical sophistry to support the desired narrative.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>