<post>
  <author>CriticalDuty</author>
  <date>2020-07-02T22:28:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hhtwxi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_29_2020/fwqw4jd/</link>
  <title>Charity as A Game Mechanic</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I have resolved to be less charitable to my outgroup in my offline life, or rather I have resolved to return to my natural disposition, which is highly uncharitable to my outgroup. This is not intended to be a flame-out kind of post, but right now I feel that I have been the subject of considerable gaslighting by the sidebar and general culture of this sub. </p>
      <p>I think it is a fair characterization to say that FCfromSSC and qualia_of_mercy were banned because given current events, they did not feel it was possible to continue extending charity to their outgroup. Naraburns made an interesting mod-hat <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/h99lly/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_15_2020/fv57ply/?context=3">comment</a> while banning FC:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>a major prerequisite to constructive participation in this sub is a certain measure of optimism--namely, optimism that it is possible for people of widely differing value functions to coexist and discourse with one another without firing bullets, toppling statues, burning down buildings, and so forth. I understand why a lot of people currently think it's impossible, but that kind of thinking is fundamentally at odds with the ethos of the sub. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>It's unfortunate that SSC is down now, because otherwise I would quote a line Scott wrote in his review of Malcolm Muggeridge's autobigraphy. There's a section where Muggeridge, the perennial pessimist, narrates his memories of the German bombing of London during World War II. Scott remarked that Muggeridge seemed almost exultant as the destruction rained down around him, because, if I remember the line correctly, "<em>his inner conviction that everything was on fire and collapsing was matched by everything really being on fire and collapsing, and no one could pat him on the head condescendingly and tell him it wasn't true</em>". </p>
      <p>That's similar to how I feel at the moment. I have always held an inner conviction that my outgroup are bad people. I begin from the premise that if an action is socially destructive, no reason or motivation justifies that action, and from there I impute backwards the fallen moral character of people who engage in socially destructive actions. This runs contrary to the ethos of TheMotte, where you are supposed to take people's reasons and motivations into consideration by beginning from the premise that they are acting in good faith, probably share many of your terminal values, and have well-considered and understandable reasons for engaging in their actions. That's my understanding of the sidebar's rule requiring charity, and I believe this rule is intended not just as a requirement for inter-tribal debate within this sub, but as a prescription for good practices outside this sub as well. So while posting on this sub, to the extent possible (and not always with success), I try to suppress this inner conviction, and where the gaslighting comes into the picture is that I think the suppressive effect that this sub's culture has had on my inner convictions has blinded me to reality, and that I have only recently had the scales ripped away from my eyes.</p>
      <p>How do I maintain charity in the aftermath of national riots where the rank-and-file of my outgroup looted, burned, killed and plundered their way across the country, while the outgroup's top brass, from prosecutors and mayors to governors and Senators, stood with the mob in lockstep solidarity? How do I pretend I share any terminal values with these people? I defy anyone to look at the scale of the devastation, and the power and authority of the mob's supporters, and tell me I'm "weakmanning" or "cherrypicking" here. There is a grim liberation in coming to the realization that I was right about my outgroup the first time around, since I can see the evidence piling up on national television - every channel! - every day. These are people whose power dwarfs mine, and this realization ultimately changes nothing, but there is at least a little pleasure in knowing that my inner convictions weren't completely baseless. No one can pat me on the head condescendingly and tell me I was wrong.</p>
      <p>I have posted in this and the predecessor sub for years, and I vividly remember all the excuses that were offered for my outgroup's escalating behavior over that time. I'm sure many here remember them too - "that's not representative", "this is confined to college campuses", "this has no real-world impact", "this is being blown out of proportion". Now as the rubble smolders across America, I submit that these have been categorically exposed as, at best, ignorance; at worst, rank lies. How can I ever take these protestations seriously again? How should I judge those who continue to make them - are they ignorant, or are they trying to deceive me? If my inner conviction that my outgroup is an undifferentiated gestalt of terrible people explains reality more convincingly than the charitable explanations on offer, what then is the point of charity? Is it just a pointless thought exercise?</p>
      <p>Charity in this sub is like a gun in a video game; you have to use the gun if you want to make your way through the game, and you can engage in behavior that is unnatural outside the game, such as killing hordes of NPCs. But all of that ends once you leave the strict confines of the game. You no longer need a gun, and indeed if you keep using one the way you use it inside the game, you will suffer severe consequences. Likewise, charity has a clear value within (and only within) the strict confines of this sub, the most obvious example being that you have to employ charity to avoid getting banned. It's not really clear that charity has any value outside this sub, though, since it fails to explain real-world behavior in a convincing way, and continuing to employ charity so liberally will make you an easy target for those who mean you harm. </p>
      <p>I like the video game analogy though, because it implies that just as a video game is a distortion of reality, so too is this sub a distortion of reality. I think there's a very rose-tinted assumption that this sub gathers a cross-section of ideas for dispassionate analysis that can be applied to real-world interpretation and application. Nowadays I think this is just a little pocket universe where reality has been deliberately suspended in favor of fanciful assumptions with no correspondence to truth; within this sub, it may be somewhat interesting to wonder "What if my outgroup weren't aliens with incomprehensible motivations?", but outside this sub, I am at a loss to see how their behavior could be distinguished from said aliens, and so whatever analysis this sub produces sheds little light on the matter. We might as well be discussing how the moon's triangular shape affects the tides - it doesn't matter, since that's not the moon's actual shape.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>