<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-07-02T15:08:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hhtwxi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_29_2020/fwpcjmb/</link>
  <title>Jane Austen Is What 2020 Needs</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Are you frustrated by contemporary politics? Fed up of virtue signalers and cancel culture? Alienated from the media and public discourse?</p>
      <p>In that case, I would suggest that this is an excellent time to acquaint or reacquaint yourself with the second greatest writer in the English language. I speak, of course, of the inimitable Jane Austen, whom I suspect is under-read in this community, especially compared to, e.g., Shakespeare or Dostoevsky. Too many people I know associate Jane Austen with romantic novels about posh ladies in frilly dresses, and put her in the same mental bucket as tawdry romances. In fact, as I'm sure many here know only too well, she is a scathing satirist and profound moralist, who charts the virtues and vices and heroes and villains of everyday life with astonishing insight, wit, and (on occasion) brutality.</p>
      <p>For my part, returning to Austen recently, I was impressed at how relevant a lot of her critiques of character are in the present climate. Austen's value system reminds me a great deal of CS Lewis in its focus on virtues such as modesty, humility, self-knowledge, restraint, and moderation (indeed, quite a few heavyweight philosophers including J.L. Austin and Gilbert Ryle <a href="https://www.logicmatters.net/resources/pdfs/JaneAusten.pdf">have waxed lyrical</a> about the sophistication and cogency of her moral framework). She was also a pragmatist; for all that we may now associate Elizabeth Bennett and Mr Darcy with passion and romance, the fact is that a huge part of what makes Darcy such an impressive match is his ten thousand a year from the Pemberley estate. She was not in denial about the importance of money or station - quite the opposite.  Not that Jane Austen should be considered a thoroughgoing conservative, by any means; in addition to <a href="https://www.globalcitizen.org/en/content/was-jane-austen-a-feminist/">having some proto-feminist credentials</a>, <a href="https://consideringausten.wordpress.com/austen-and-antigua-slavery-in-her-time/">there are strong suggestions in her letters</a>, for example, that she had sympathies for the abolitionist movement.</p>
      <p>But what's especially satisfying for me reading Austen at the moment is that this rich moral landscape is almost wholly devoid of debates about politics and religion. What we instead find is a focus on <em>good manners</em> and <em>conduct</em>. These are concepts that I think contemporary ethics has somewhat neglected, preferring instead a more simplistic and strident moral framework of righteousness and wickedness grounded in one's political beliefs and public performances, rather than, say, how one treats one's grandmother or neighbour. Indeed, it's easy to imagine what Jane Austen would think about the behaviour of many in the present day - while she greatly admired people of <em>principle</em>, she'd deplore the shallow virtue signalling of social media, and the hungry hollow thirst for admiration and validation of those who brag, self-aggrandise, or seek to be envied on Instagram and Facebook. She would also be scandalised by the casual way that people throw  their friends and family under the bus (or should that be the <em>barouche</em>) in the name of online point-scoring.</p>
      <p>She's also, it goes without saying, a spectacularly gifted writer. Her language is deceptively simple, with layers of irony and nuance buried beneath the surface. I'm reminded of one of my favourite quotations by the ordinary language philosopher JL Austin who - in defending the value of careful analysis of language as a source for philosophical understanding - <a href="https://sites.ualberta.ca/%7Efrancisp/NewPhil448/AustinPlea56.pdf">observed as follows</a>:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>[O]ur common stock of words embodies all the distinctions men have found worth drawing, and the connexions they have found worth marking, in the lifetimes of many generations: these surely are likely to be more numerous, more sound, since they have stood up to the long test of the survival of the fittest, and more subtle, at least in all ordinary and reasonably practical matters, than any that you or I are likely to think up in our armchairs of an afternoon-the most favoured alternative method.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>In this respect, I think Jane Austen is an exemplary philosopher, and so often in a little aside in her work I notice little subtleties of meaning that I hadn't previously grasped. Emma observes of Mrs Elton that she was if "not foolish [then] ignorant", while Darcy notes that "Arguments are too much like disputes.” Indeed, one can scarcely read a page or two of Austen attentively without coming away with a better understanding of the nuances of our everyday concepts.</p>
      <p>I would thoroughly recommend, then, that members of this community not hitherto acquainted with Austen's work take this moment to give her a chance. I think <em>Emma</em> in particular may be a good fit for some people here, given its cynicism, irony, and scathing wit. There are also, of course, many excellent adaptation of Austen's work, though they inevitably fail to convey her mastery of the English language. Still, if you can't be persuaded to read Austen at present, then I can recommend the 1995 film <em>Sense &amp; Sensibility</em> as a good starting point, insofar as it strikes me as probably the most authentic adaptation of any of her books, not to mention a wonderful film in its own right. (It's also remarkable to me that a Taiwanese director, Ang Lee, was able to so perfectly understand and express the work of an early 19th century Englishwoman. But I'm sometimes tempted to think there are deep similarities between the middle class English value system and some aspects of Confucian culture).</p>
      <p>Finally, I would note that I can have no doubt that in a community of this size and intellectual calibre, there will be those whose familiarity with Austen's work greatly exceeds my own, and to them I would apologise for any egregious omissions or errors I have made in making the case for her merits and ongoing relevance. I should thus append the admission that I'm not an Austen expert by any means, having read her books merely for pleasure, and I have only engaged superficially with the voluminous scholarship on her life, letters, and principles. But I should be delighted to hear what others think of her work, and how it can usefully inform our outlook and values in the present.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>EDIT:</strong> perhaps I should include a slightly longer sample from the Great Woman herself. I've already mentioned Austen's skills as a philosopher, but here's an extract from <em>Emma</em> that shows off her flair as a psychologist. The context is that the eponymous protagonist has convinced herself that a young man she somewhat admires called Frank Churchill is enamoured with her, and she hypothesizes that she might be in love with him. What follows is a lovely if tongue-in-cheek description of how she wrestles with this idea.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Emma continued to entertain no doubt of her being in love. Her ideas only varied as to the how much. At first, she thought it was a good deal; and afterwards, but little. She had great pleasure in hearing Frank Churchill talked of; and, for his sake, greater pleasure than ever in seeing Mr. and Mrs. Weston; she was very often thinking of him, and quite impatient for a letter, that she might know how he was, how were his spirits, how was his aunt, and what was the chance of his coming to Randalls again this spring. But, on the other hand, she could not admit herself to be unhappy, nor, after the first morning, to be less disposed for employment than usual; she was still busy and cheerful; and, pleasing as he was, she could yet imagine him to have faults; and farther, though thinking of him so much, and, as she sat drawing or working, forming a thousand amusing schemes for the progress and close of their attachment, fancying interesting dialogues, and inventing elegant letters; the conclusion of every imaginary declaration on his side was that she <em>refused</em><em>him</em>. Their affection was always to subside into friendship. Every thing tender and charming was to mark their parting; but still they were to part. When she became sensible of this, it struck her that she could not be very much in love; for in spite of her previous and fixed determination never to quit her father, never to marry, a strong attachment certainly must produce more of a struggle than she could foresee in her own feelings.  </p>
        <p>“I do not find myself making any use of the word <em>sacrifice</em>,” said she.—“In not one of all my clever replies, my delicate negatives, is there any allusion to making a sacrifice. I do suspect that he is not really necessary to my happiness. So much the better. I certainly will not persuade myself to feel more than I do. I am quite enough in love. I should be sorry to be more.”</p>
      </blockquote>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>