<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-07-02T10:40:28Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hhtwxi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_29_2020/fwokebh/</link>
  <title>Contrasting the Acknowledged Insanity of Katya with the Unacknowledged Insanity of the Western Media</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>It's all good practice, citizen. </p>
      <p>One advantage Ruskies with their low trust have, however, is the reasonable assumption that your family knows the news anchor of State-Owned Channel One, <a href="https://mtdata.ru/u27/photo94F2/20579966369-0/original.jpg#20579966369">Katya</a>, is lying, and Katya knows she's lying, and her superiors know she's lying, and the whole system is founded on the tacit agreement that pretty much everyone even mildly intelligent knows that this is all lies but we have to get access to a centralized lie outlet to synchronize our half-spirited going through the motions anyway. And we all know Katya lives in the Maldives and thinks that Russia is kind of a sucky place to live in, and the CEO of Channel One is pretty vocal in his cynicism and scheming to frame a narrative, but also dispassionate about it, and Putin's spokesperson Peskov is not so much covering Putin's ass when he pushes some harebrained geopolitical talking point when pressed, but almost darkly hinting at being a crook in a system of crooks; he even looks <a href="http://img2.eadaily.com/c650x400/o/9fb/502e620371cc4586faacffd3e0690.jpeg">comical</a>. To steelman, this blatant hypocrisy is <em>a defense from fanaticism</em>, an inoculation against the frenzy of political hivemind. I used to think less of it, but in fact it's a reasonably sophisticated social technology. Kolmogorov option can actually work in Russia, and the lowliest drunkard can imagine himself witty for participating in it when needed and ridiculing it otherwise. And also, you learn our simple social contract: Big Brother does not love you. There is, in fact, no Big Brother. There are specific opportunists, who don't hate you but also don't care about you. Purges won't come. Relax, citizen. And long live Mother Russia. Heh heh.<br />
Meanwhile the Western media, in conjunction with its many non-official tendrils, appears to try and brainfuck the populace into genuinely believing the insanity, into seeing four fingers where there are five, because such is the greater cause. It is too clever by half, too well-honed to not cut into the flesh. I am uncertain if the higher-ups know of their hypocrisy, and if they do, whether the fresh journalists and political pundits pumped out by the academia will be able to learn from them that the greater cause amounts to rhetoric around empty space. It can all lead to a nightmare.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, affluent Russians are chuckling and cashing out, while the brainwashed affluent Westerners might well fight to the death in defense of the monster which moves their eyeballs; and not like they have anywhere to retreat. High trust has its perks.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>