<post>
  <author>Krytan</author>
  <date>2020-06-30T16:41:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hhtwxi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_29_2020/fwho3sm/</link>
  <title>The Power of Pointing Out Hypocrisy</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Boomers, left and right, are both enormous believers in the power of pointing out hypocrisy. They seem to believe that if they can point out a contradiction in the beliefs their opponents claim to hold, or point an inconsistency between their words and deeds, that's it, the battle is over. It's only a matter of time before the American public looks up and realizes their opponents are hypocrites and completely abandons them. Naturally this has no effect whatsoever today, because a belief in the presence of hypocrisy, and belief that hypocrisy is bad, relies on an objective systematic logical belief system that is largely forsaken today. </p>
      <p>Why do boomers keep going back to the hypocrisy well? I think it's because charges of hypocrisy were such an important part of their youth - they effectively destroyed the previous generation's moral credibility (in their eyes) with claims of hypocrisy and they desperately wanted to avoid being seen as hypocritical. So their most treasured virtue was - authenticity. </p>
      <p>The other thing is that pointing out your opponents hypocrisy is really, really easy. It can be done safely in a few minutes from the comfort of your living room. It's a pleasant fantasy that those with slightly above average intelligence can engage it : they can use their superior intellect and education to defeat massive political movements by pointing out the internal and inherent contradictions, all without getting out of bed! Of course, that's wrong. </p>
      <p>-----</p>
      <p>You know who isn't surprised by this surge of angry iconoclasm at all, is the alt-right.  They predicted years ago that it would start with statues of confederates and rapidly escalate to statues of George Washington and Thomas Jefferson and then expand even further from there. It is the inevitable result when you've successfully linked white people and white supremacy. To support statues of white people is to support white supremacy, since all white people are white supremacists, and to remove statues of white people is to remove statues of white supremacy.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>