<post>
  <author>mcjunker</author>
  <date>2020-07-06T14:35:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hm1kjn/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_06_2020/fx3p03n/</link>
  <title>Hamilton Cringed</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I was honestly shocked by my reaction to Hamilton.</p>
      <p>My sister fucking <em>loved</em> it, heart and soul. Has the soundtrack memorized, hums it while she does the dishes, references it constantly, went to a show to celebrate when she got engaged. I assumed that there had to be some kind of artistic value to it.</p>
      <p>I watched the first fifteen minutes on Disney+ and I physically cringed. It was not merely unappealing, it made me actually angry.</p>
      <p>What shocked me was the thought that shot through my mind as they rapped and danced about Hamilton’s backstory- “Oh, <em>this</em> is what ‘SJWs’ mean when they rant about cultural appropriation.” Not Englishmen stealing from African rituals for dinner parties, or white American brides wearing Japanese kimonos, or anything ethnic based like that. That, I could generally care less about- the number of people in the world who invest their personal identity in kimono wearing is vanishingly small and are probably glad to be signal boosted.</p>
      <p>But this horror show on my television set was quite plainly a bunch of petit bourgeoisie cosplaying as ghetto birds for the entertainment of the super rich. Fuck, it was practically minstrel shows reborn: filtering the low-status, crude, but very genuine joys of the lowest of the low to show off to the dominate social class who would never bump into them in their day to day life.</p>
      <p>A diversely colored assortment of actors, <em>rapping</em> and <em>rhyming</em> quite <em>rapidly!</em> You don’t see <em>that</em> in our gated community!</p>
      <p>In a flash, I got it. The appeal of old school minstrel shows. It lets rich people slum about enjoying lower class music and dance, but modulated so as not to offend anybody’s sensibilities. No need to grapple with a song about the heartache and terror of growing up hearing gunshots outside your window every day, or a beatboxer scream seething hatred at the cops who round him up and abuse him on a regular schedule, or a jaunty party mix about getting drunk and fucking whores, or anything to make an upper class listener uncomfortable or angry.</p>
      <p>I remembered my first reaction upon hearing about Hamilton years and years ago- if you’re really elevating rap and associated black and lower class culture to the front stage of the art world, why can’t you lower ticket prices or set up more showings across America so that the actual kids who grew up loving rap and spontaneously creating new strains of it on their stoops and corners can see it and participate?</p>
      <p>Answer found. It’s not art meant for poor people. It’s art aimed at people who would normally despise and call the police on poor people, but are in the mood for something fresh and exotic to watch.</p>
      <p>(What’s really fucked up is that now I’ll have to lie and tell my sister that I can’t view it because “We don’t have Disney+.”)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>