<post>
  <author>The_Fooder</author>
  <date>2020-07-02T18:51:21Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hhtwxi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_29_2020/fwq5kln/</link>
  <title>A Firsthand View of Gang Culture at Work</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>An anecdote:</p>
      <p>There was one kid, who I liked a lot, but like most of the kids, was usually trying to act hard or like a comedian. I think one of his parents lived in the suburbs and he was between the city and suburbs a lot so was finding it extra difficult to fit in. He started going to <a href="https://www.usnews.com/education/best-high-schools/illinois/districts/chicago-public-schools/sullivan-high-school-6587">Sullivan High School</a>, which at the time was a hell on earth from what the kids told me. There might have been three different gangs, I don't recall.</p>
      <p>Anyway, this kid came in one day and started throwing gang signs, which he hadn't done before. There was a pretty strict 'no gang signs' rule at our program, so I pulled him aside and said he had to leave that at the door. Then I said something to the effect of, "You're a smart kid, you've got a lot of potential, why are you doing this gang stuff?" He told me that he was getting picked on and beat up regularly at school. He had a cousin in a gang who said he could help protect him if he hung around the gang." Essentially, the old cliche of you either pick a team or you're meat. I realized that this stuff wasn't simply for protection, but also tightly packaged in the history of these families, it was 'what one does'. My naive view was that it was mostly about power and money, but it goes much deeper than that and is far more useful to these kids than trying to 'be good' or 'participate in society.'</p>
      <p>Another anecdote:</p>
      <p>One of the younger kids, I think 10 or 11, stopped coming in every day. One day I saw him about a block away just sitting on his bike. I asked why he didn't come in and he said he was making money. He didn't want to give the details, but I guessed he was holding for the actual dealers and he grudgingly admitted it was so. I knew the older kid (around 18, who it turns out, was trying to use our program to recruit kids) and told the younger kid that other guy was taking advantage of him and it was dangerous. He shrugged his shoulders and said he'd rather have the money....because of course he'd rather have the money. When you're 10 and your parents are poor, everyone around you is poor and someone says, keep this in your pocket and come here when I signal you, then why not? I totally get it. Who cares about what the future might be like when you can get the money now.</p>
      <p>I could go on and I'm sure a lot of this stuff sounds totally cliche, but in the context of actual living people, it was shocking to me to see it happening, understand it was rational and have nothing better than a vague argument that it could come back and bite them down the road. I completely understand why teenagers thing adults are idiots, because largely, we are, and I had to re-calibrate my messaging to be 1) much more narrow, specific and localized and 2) targeted at the stuff I actually could control. Then, of course, I ended up deserting all of them when I went back to school (at the humbling age of 34) and got a real job and moved out of the neighborhood. I kept up with a few of the kids, who are now adults and it's been a few good stories with a bunch of terrible ones. It turns out I was unable to be a reliable neighborhood figure; regardless of my intentions I was always an outsider.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>