<post>
  <author>thisismymilitaryalt</author>
  <date>2020-06-30T20:30:56Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hhtwxi/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_29_2020/fwihd1o/</link>
  <title>The Interplay of Race and Race Narratives in the US Military</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="https://warontherocks.com/2020/06/reflections-on-the-curse-of-racism-in-the-u-s-military/">Reflections on the Curse of Racism In The US Military</a>
      </p>
      <p>The article touches on some major culture war issues in the Army: self-selection of minorities into non-combat arms, the dearth of non-white officers in the upper echelons, and the push to remove Confederate symbols from the ranks. I'd like to focus on the first two.</p>
      <p>I'm currently assigned on recruiting duty and the self-selection of minorities is anecdotally true. The majority of our infantry and 18X (Army SF pipeline) enlistments are white males. Females and minorities are generally more interested in roles with post-military skills transference (mechanics, intelligence, finance, etc). Relative to our sister units, we get tasked with generating the largest share of combat arms contracts because that's what sells out here. <a href="https://www.duffelblog.com/2012/06/first-non-filipino-culinary-specialist-breaks-barriers-screws-up-constantly/">Heck, the complete lack of white cooks is a running joke</a>. </p>
      <p>The authors' assessment on why there are so many white males in senior leadership relative to the rest of the force is also spot on. The Army privileges combat arms over the other segments of the force and rightly so (says the POG). The purpose of the military is combat and having the combat arms personnel lead the overall force makes a certain amount of sense. </p>
      <p>Where I think the article breaks down is its prescription for getting more minorities, particularly blacks, into combat arms. I can't speak for the other services, but the Army has recognized that its personnel make up is largely white, middle class, conservative, and southern. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/02/us/army-recruiting-tech-industry-seattle.html">Starting in October of 2018 the Army made a dedicate push in urban, liberal areas</a> in an attempt to both fill the ranks and correct the cultural overbalance. While I can't disclose the actual numbers, it isn't going well. Recruiters are fighting against a lefty narrative that the military targets minorities and the poor as cannon fodder for forever wars fought on behalf of rich whites. Some of my fellow commanders assigned to these cities have their recruiters transit to and from work in civilian clothes just to avoid having to deal with confrontational protestors. I get the feeling that for some, military racism is tautological and any attempts to prove otherwise are just more proof of the military's inherent racism. </p>
      <p>I don't have a silver bullet for any of this. Having a more representative cross-section of the US is ideal, but the ranks need to be filled and the Army will fill them with any qualified applicant it can, regardless of socioeconomic status or ethnicity.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>