<post>
  <author>Ame_Damnee</author>
  <date>2021-04-08T15:03:59Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mke4zb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_05_2021/gttfw0u/</link>
  <title>Christianity versus "womanist theology."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm not entirely certain if the phrase "dumb shit" is permissible to be used on here, so let me know.</p>
      <p>Anyway, I am not particularly outraged because this is precisely the kind of dumb shit progressive "theologians" (and I do very definitely intend to use scare quotes here) like to come up with all the time.  Since the 90s or so, when "stations of the cross" for Gaia instead of Christ were trendy environmentalist progressive liturgies in liberal Christian denominations (a fad that seems to have faded, since I can't even find any examples by currently Googling), this is the stuff that C. S. Lewis described in "The Screwtape Letters":</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>About the general connection between Christianity and politics, our position is more delicate. Certainly we do not want men to allow their Christianity to flow over into their political life, for the establishment of anything like a really just society would be a major disaster. On the other hand we do want, and want very much, to make men treat Christianity as a means; preferably, of course, as a means to their own advancement, but, failing that, as a means to anything—even to social justice. The thing to do is to get a man at first to value social justice as a thing which the Enemy demands, and then work him on to the stage at which he values Christianity because it may produce social justice.  </p>
        <p>... What we want, if men become Christians at all, is to keep them in the state of mind I call "Christianity And". You know—Christianity and the Crisis, Christianity and the New Psychology, Christianity and the New Order, Christianity and Faith Healing, Christianity and Psychical Research, Christianity and Vegetarianism, Christianity and Spelling Reform. If they must be Christians let them at least be Christians with a difference. Substitute for the faith itself some Fashion with a Christian colouring.  </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>There is also the sort of cleric or associated with religion type, as described below:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The two churches nearest to him, I have looked up in the office. Both have certain claims. At the first of these the Vicar is a man who has been so long engaged in watering down the faith to make it easier for supposedly incredulous and hard-headed congregation that it is now he who shocks his parishioners with his unbelief, not vice versa. He has undermined many a soul's Christianity. His conduct of the services is also admirable. In order to spare the laity all "difficulties" he has deserted both the lectionary and the appointed psalms and now, without noticing it, revolves endlessly round the little treadmill of his fifteen favourite psalms and twenty favourite lessons. We are thus safe from the danger that any truth not already familiar to him and to his flock should over reach them through Scripture. But perhaps bur patient is not quite silly enough for this church—or not yet?  </p>
        <p>At the other church we have Fr. Spike. The humans are often puzzled to understand the range of his opinions—why he is one day almost a Communist and the next not far from some kind of theocratic Fascism—one day a scholastic, and the next prepared to deny human reason altogether—one day immersed in politics, and, the day after, declaring that all states of us world are equally "under judgment". We, of course, see the connecting link, which is Hatred. The man cannot bring himself to teach anything which is not calculated to mock, grieve, puzzle, or humiliate his parents and their friends. A sermon which such people would accept would be to him as insipid as a poem which they could scan. There is also a promising streak of dishonesty in him; we are teaching him to say "The teaching of the Church is" when he really means "I'm almost sure I read recently in Maritain or someone of that sort". But I must warn you that he has one fatal defect: he really believes. And this may yet mar all.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>To hazard a guess, I think our womanist ecumenical psychologist is one of the "Father Spike" types, but without the 'fatal defect' of really believing - or rather, it is not Christianity that is her religion, it is the progressive doctrines on race, sex, gender and - if the discussion on "wokeness" will pardon the use - the whole bundle of "wokism" that is her true faith.  If you look at her potted bio, the terms give it all away: "womanist theology" is distinct from "feminist theology" because feminism is Too White (there's a Hispanic/Latina version called "mujerista theology"); "ordained by an independent fellowship" seems to be the Protestant/non-denominational version of the 'woman priests' in Catholicism, at the very least it points to "doesn't want to be/is not permitted to be associated with a particular denomination or church group" and you can guess they mix'n'match their own grab-bag set of doctrines based on personal preferences and no other tradition.</p>
      <p>She is telling God in this 'prayer' all about how He got things wrong when He incarnated and commanded us to "love your enemies, pray for those who persecute you".  And no, there is no "get out of judgement free card if I make White people the exception to your commandment to love our neighbors as we love ourselves".  That's the sticky part of real Christianity: oh, that lot over there are awful terrible mean people? they did really bad things in truth to our lot?  tough, they are also your neighbours and you must love them.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <strong>38</strong> “You have heard that it was said, ‘An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth.’ <strong>39</strong> But I say to you, Do not resist the one who is evil. But if anyone slaps you on the right cheek, turn to him the other also. <strong>40</strong> And if anyone would sue you and take your tunic, let him have your cloak as well. <strong>41</strong> And if anyone forces you to go one mile, go with him two miles. <strong>42</strong> Give to the one who begs from you, and do not refuse the one who would borrow from you.  </p>
        <p>
          <strong>43</strong> “You have heard that it was said, ‘You shall love your neighbor and hate your enemy.’ <strong>44</strong> But I say to you, Love your enemies and pray for those who persecute you, <strong>45</strong> so that you may be sons of your Father who is in heaven. For he makes his sun rise on the evil and on the good, and sends rain on the just and on the unjust. <strong>46</strong> For if you love those who love you, what reward do you have? Do not even the tax collectors do the same? <strong>47</strong> And if you greet only your brothers, what more are you doing than others? Do not even the Gentiles do the same? <strong>48</strong> You therefore must be perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>She's not a Christian.  Once we understand that, she can write whatever prayers and rituals she likes, it's a free country.  The same as any of the various Satanist movements can write prayers (if they feel like doing so) about how much they can't stand Christians.</p>
      <p>Looking up Mercer university, which she is associated with, it is a private university in Georgia which was connected with the Baptists (not the Southern Baptists, one of the other conventions) at its foundation but was never a seminary, and has since severed its connections to become "a university in the tradition of...", rather like contemporary American Catholic universities.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Mercer, founded by early 19th-century Baptists, ended its affiliation with the Georgia Baptist Convention in 2006 after 173 years. Before the affiliation ended, Mercer had an independent board of trustees; the convention provided financial support but did not control the university. The lack of control caused friction, with Mercer resisting restraints on social issues while the convention saw Mercer as becoming secularized and not conforming to its values.</p>
      </blockquote>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>