<post>
  <author>EfficientSyllabus</author>
  <date>2021-04-06T21:31:35Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/mke4zb/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_april_05_2021/gtm8t31/</link>
  <title>Drowning People in Pdf Link Dumps</title>
  <category>
    <li>knowledge</li>
  </category>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>For most people (who don't wake and go to sleep thinking about this stuff) HBD and Holocaust denial are fairly similar beasts. I'm sure you're aware there are forums and websites that provide detailed articles with scans of pages that look like administrative documentation from WWII, photos etc. They link to each other, cite books, documents, "debunk" other sources etc.</p>
      <p>Would you agree that it's a reasonable thing for a normal person to dismiss these without digging through the details and debunking all the claims therein by doing independent research? You know, at some point you have to take your education and general cultural environment for granted and take them as the starting point. If you notice problems in the world, it can be more important to take action and advocate for causes you find important to help other people, instead of studying fringe online theories in detail that fly in the face of everything you were taught offline.</p>
      <p>Another example: faking of the Moon landing. There are also lots of websites and communities online who have stacks of documents that could fill books, talking specifically about particular photos, samples, training locations etc. Do you think we should expect every well informed citizen to become familiar with the detailed arguments of the Moon landing deniers and how to debunk them, or it's best to just expect them to accept what they learned in history class about this event?</p>
      <p>Do you think one should only become an advocate for woke causes once they are a "leader" (according to your terminology) on anti-HBD, i.e. have familiarized themselves with the collected works and stacks of documents and references of the pro-HBD community?</p>
      <p>In any fringe community (let's take this a neutral description of widely out-of-mainstream acceptable views), be it Holocaust denial, fake Moon landings, flat Earth or HBD, the following pattern emerges. Normal person waddles in the place, asserts that the topic of discussion is nonsense, people who believe this are obviously either idiots or evil, because it all flies in the face of what every normal person knows. They then get a link dump and copypastas in their face, names and dates, and bullet points etc., which totally overwhelms the person. Now they have two choices. Spend the effort to dig through all that and respond to all of it individually, tracking down counterarguments, fact-checking things, perhaps necessitating going to physical libraries (which would become something of a part-time job for days or weeks), or they can just leave and learn the lesson that these are fringe obscure obsessive people who build these piles of nonsense crackpottery.</p>
      <p>I think ultimately the onus is on those who claim something that is outside the mainstream to convince the majority. That does not simply mean drowning people in pdf link dumps.</p>
      <p>I'm not saying fringe theories can never be true. Of course heliocentrism was once heresy and widely outside the mainstream acceptable view, but it was true (at least truer than geocentrism). However, by opening the door in which your theory can enter someone's mind, you also make way for various other fringe theories.</p>
      <p>Why would anyone want to spend all the effort to dig into this? I can't see any potential upside, but lots of downsides. First, the sheer effort should not be underestimated. Evaluating research is hard work and requires specialized education in statistics, experiment design, potential sources of bias, common misleading tricks etc. Second, it's just repulsive to think about for many. Also, having all that kind of stuff in your browsing history and pdfs on your hard drive would not reflect well on you if someone found it. And so on. I can't really envision any woke person who would genuinely think this is a good use of their time.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>