<post>
  <author>asdfasdflkjlkjlkj</author>
  <date>2020-10-01T22:46:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g7c8qtj/</link>
  <title>A Chestertonian Intellectual Journey</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I didn't find my way to Alexander from Yudkowski, and to be honest, I've always found the truly R<em>ationalist</em><sup>tm</sup> side of things to be a bit odd. I picked up a Chesterton recommendation from a poster here, actually, who had noticed how frequently Scott and the posters here referenced him, and wanted good starting points. From that post I read Orthodoxy, and fell in love immediately. I was raised in a very ideologically motivated background -- entirely self-confident, purely rational, materialist as a goddamned cinderblock, blood-curdlingly revolutionary, utopian Marxists -- and I felt that Chesterton understood in a way that I had come  to realize how <em>nuts</em> these sorts of people were. Of the lunatic, he says something like, "His mind moves in a perfect, but very narrow circle." Like most truly great and charismatic writers, he is a joy to read, because he takes joy in life. Not only is he joyful, he is an optimist, and an optimist not <em>despite</em>, but actually <em>because of</em> the world's contradictions -- which, let me tell you, is quite a fucking relief after more than two decades of revolutionary "the contradictions are too strong, Sir! This whole goddamned ship is about to go down!" ringing in your ears.</p>
      <p>Around the time I read him, I had been reading both Dostoevsky and Jordan Peterson, who are both gloomy to a degree, but who were helpful, and spoke to me seriously when I was in a very dark place. When I read Chesterton and loved him so much, I started to wonder why it was I had gravitated unconsciously towards Christian thinkers. I still don't know completely -- I am completely secular,  and will almost certainly die without an ounce of belief --  but I think that while they all presented what was to one degree or another an absurd view of life, a picture of an incomprehensible, corrupt, and often fallen world, despite this, they found reasons to keep going forward which were very unlike the utopian faith of my upbringing, whose practicality I could no longer accept on rational grounds. It was very Chestertonian,  in a way: the Marxists' heads were up in the clouds, while the Christians seemed grounded in the Here and Now.</p>
      <p>I also feel that Chesterton cured me, once and for all, of any attraction I'd ever had to ego death or psychoanalysis, which were stupid non-cures to my problems that the culture I inhabited pushed me towards in the depths of my sadness. How so, exactly, is more than I'll write here.</p>
      <p>It was a surprise to find out he was such good friends with Hillaire Belloc, about whom I knew nothing besides that he'd written an essay I happened to love. I've since read a little about the Catholic revival in England, and it seems it included quite a few interesting people.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>