<post>
  <author>d4shing</author>
  <date>2020-10-01T05:50:12Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g79dx6o/</link>
  <title>If you're not willing to stand for principles even when they produce a policy outcome you don't like, are they even really your principles?</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This is really interesting - thanks for sharing.</p>
      <p>As you say, <em>Gonzalez v Raich</em> is really just a modern day 
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wickard_v._Filburn">Wickard v Filburn</a>. Lopez and Morrison were about finding limits to the commerce clause, but rather than revive some pre-New Deal jurisprudence as Breyer warned in dissent, the Roberts court seems to have lost interest. No, no, they seemed to say - we are not actually interested in reviving pre-New Deal jurisprudence. This case cites to <em>Erie</em> and <em>NLRB vs Jones &amp; Laughlin Steel</em>, which isn't going pre-New Deal, but it's getting closer than <em>Gonzalez v Raich</em> was willing to.</p>
      <p>(As an aside, I always understood New York vs US to be about commandeering and not really the commerce clause.)</p>
      <p>Anyways if you're some sort of principled constitutionalist libertarian, shouldn't you be happy about this outcome? I think this has legs because it's clever - they're doing the nominally liberal thing by striking down a law against suing gun manufacturers, but they're doing it by invoking conservative jurisprudence in a way that if more broadly applied, would more strongly advance the right's preferred Commerce clause jurisprudence. If it gets affirmed by the 3d Circuit (dominated 8-6 by Trump and Bush appointees vs Clinton/Obama ones), then it will create a circuit split (see the 2d Circuit caselaw that this judge expressly considers and rejects) which is a pretty irresistible reason for the Supreme Court to grant cert. And then you'll have Sotomayor and Kagan and Breyer voting to uphold the PCLAA and maybe nobody else. But I think they'll all appreciate the irony.</p>
      <p>If you're just viewing this through the lens of "what's best for gun enthusiasts and gun manufacturers" then ok sure it's bad. And look at the hypocrisy in Gonzalez v Raich on display by Scalia and Kennedy -- both of them are happy to invoke the limits of the commerce clause to strike down parts of the Violence Against Women Act or the Gun-Free School Zones Act (voting with the majorities in Lopez and Morrison) but god forbid anyone get baked. Were their politics just, guns good, weed bad? It reminds me of a tweet I saw the other day, where someone talked about how in law school classes, when the professor asks "So why did Judge [X] decide this way", it was considered unsophisticated to answer because he's a conservative and he wants the conservative policy outcome/result. I think the power of this decision is that it subverts that paradigm. If you're not willing to stand for principles even when they produce a policy outcome you don't like, are they even really your principles?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>