<post>
  <author>dwaxe</author>
  <date>2020-10-01T21:55:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g7c3a93/</link>
  <title>On Election Integrity: An "Election" Is Really Thousands</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Nearly all articles on this topic on both sides (including your post) fail to acknowledge the most fundamental fact about US Elections that makes this topic much more complicated than any high-level claims about "our election" could hope to address: We don't have one election, we have thousands. Each state has their own quirky rules about how they conduct their elections, each county has its own way of administrating those rules, and sometimes individual precincts have their own quirks as well.</p>
      <p>Some counties utilize trivially hackable voting machines. Some states require mail-in ballots to have multiple layers of privacy so it's impossible to match the address on your letter to the vote within. Given the myriad quirks, there's no question that some of them will look gamable.</p>
      <p>What this means on a high level is that if you're making a negative claim about "election integrity" by pointing to individual cases where a process has gone haywire, you're not saying much about US elections as a whole. Conversely, if you're dismissing concerns about "election integrity", you're not actually defending something that exists in the first place.</p>
      <p>The decentralization of our elections also limits the upside for any potential bad actors. Something that works in one county will not necessarily be scalable to the next county over. If one county buys crap voting machines, and the next one over buys a slightly different crap voting machine, it's already at least twice as hard to manipulate another county's worth of votes. If one county's mail-in ballots are suspicious, you can easily cross check with similar counties.</p>
      <p>What's more, if this issue weren't being politicized by a sitting president who's pretty far behind in polls, this decentralization would be celebrated by conservatives. We have this system because each state has the right to decide how to hold their own election, a right I'm sure Republicans would be defending if claims of insecure polls were coming from the other side. Come to think of it, we don't even have to imagine -- all the fights about making voting easier or harder in particular states would not be occurring but for this fact of our system. Ask yourself if Trump would be making this an issue if he had a secure lead in the polls.</p>
      <p>Just today, Democrats are complaining about Texas' Republican governor reducing the number of ballot drop-off locations to one per county, so that everyone in Harris county (pop. 4.7mil) has to drive up to an hour (probably more in traffic) to a single downtown location if they want to drop off their ballot to vote. Meanwhile, Oregon automatically sends every registered voter a mail-in ballot without any need to request it. This is our system at work -- decentralized for the states to decide. If you want to be ideologically consistent in defending actions like this, you ought to also accept and defend the fact that this system will in some places have failure modes. Likewise, if you want to claim these actions are wrong, you ought to admit that the ultimate end of your agenda is to federalize pieces of election administration. Picking and choosing which decentralized decisions to defend based on either voting accessibility or claims of fraud is understandable in the most egregious cases, but if you find someone complaining only about one side of them, they're being nakedly partisan.</p>
      <p>tl;dr: If you're reading a claim about "the election" singular, the author is probably missing something. Speak of US Election<em>s plural</em> to make it clear what you're claiming.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>