<post>
  <author>gattsuru</author>
  <date>2020-10-01T01:33:08Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g78ptfq/</link>
  <title>A New Addition to the Commerce Clause</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>The Commerce Clause gives the federal government power over (as you might guess from its name) interstate commerce, and has been read by the courts notoriously broadly.  The most notorious examples <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wickard_v._Filburn">involve</a> growing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonzales_v._Raich">plants</a> for use on one's own property, but there's a reason it's become compared to <a href="http://volokh.com/2006/06/28/the-herpes-theory-of-the-commerce-clause/">Herpes</a> among libertarians.  It allows <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_v._Darby_Lumber_Co.">minimum wages</a> for products manufactured totally within the bounds of a state, <a href="https://www.ca10.uscourts.gov/opinions/14/14-4151.pdf">regulate animals that live only in a small portion of a single state</a>, and <a href="https://www.ca4.uscourts.gov/opinions/184660.P.pdf">assaults that happen when a person is engaged in interstate commerce</a>.  Its most effective realm has been the "dormant" commerce clause, which limits state laws impacting interstate commerce, but that area is its own toothy monstrosity.</p>
      <p>During debates over the Affordable Care Act, many Tea Party-affiliated groups argued that the expansive read of the Commerce Clause would make someone's broccoli consumption the provenance of the federal government; of course, this was absolutely wrong.  Instead, that went under the tax power, and then mandated insurance washed the precise question of brocolli through a handful of corporations under the auspices of Wellness Programs.</p>
      <p>That's not to say that there are no limits to the Commerce Clause. There are, of course, a few explicitly or implicitly overturned cases involving <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carter_v._Carter_Coal_Co.">coal mining</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_v._Virginia">insurance</a>.  There have been a handful of decisions limiting it that still remain, in at least some sense, 'good law': <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_v._United_States">the federal government can not require states to take title of nuclear waste</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murphy_v._National_Collegiate_Athletic_Association#Subsequent_developments">nor ban them from making a law allowing a behavior that was not banned under federal law</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_v._Lopez">block <em>all</em> gun possession off private property within 1000 feet of a school</a>, or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_v._Morrison">create a private cause of action for interpersonal violence</a>.  ((Though some of these limits apply only in the most minimal sense: <em>Lopez</em> in particular was replaced nearly instantly, with the theoretical differences between the two statutes basically never applied; similarly, the nuclear waste thing got... weird.))  </p>
      <p>We have a new addition: <a href="http://www.pacourts.us/assets/opinions/Superior/out/J-A23024-19o%20-%20104558198114689518.pdf">a lawsuit claiming defective design, revolving around criminal actions performed by a third party in Pennsylvania, filed against a gun manufacturer in Illinois</a>.  </p>
      <p>To be blunt, this is not a good decision.  Nor is it some new principled stance.  Libertarians might be fascinated by the concept of overturning <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price%E2%80%93Anderson_Nuclear_Industries_Indemnity_Act">other</a> laws <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Aviation_Revitalization_Act">changing</a> liability <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnuson%E2%80%93Moss_Warranty_Act">or jurisdiction</a>.  But it won't happen: like the various rational-basis-with-bite one-offs, it's tailored to this specific law and no other.  At least one of the judges has not shied away from federal preemption of state law in non-gun contexts before.  Indeed, despite its length even this decision is not merely political but lacking: severability analysis overlooks a few parts of the PCLAA (such as the mandate for trigger lock sales), just as their litany of failed lawsuits overlooks the Remington v. Soto case.  It's obviously never going to invalidate other gun control laws passed under the commerce power.</p>
      <p>I'd like to say this gets overturned, but then again, the Pennsylvanian Supreme Court <a href="https://www.pagunblog.com/2018/01/25/pa-supreme-court-usurps-legislative-prerogative/">hasn't exactly covered itself in glory recently</a>, and SCOTUS didn't take Remington v. Soto, either.  In the short term, it's hard to say it matters.  Product liability law is exceptionally complicated (and worse than normally in Pennsylvania, which mixes state-level strict liability with federal 'reasonableness' standards), but barring far more aggressive political decision-making than even this terrible opinion, it's hard to see a <em>Greenman</em> level standard coming about in the state, and the theory of liability here (or in any recklessly criminal action) wouldn't win a lawsuit short of that.  But in the long run, if it's allowed to persist, even failed lawsuits will be ruinous.</p>
      <p>Worse, it would near-guarantee a Californian take on overturning the PCLAA, and California's notorious both for the strictest of strict liability in general and arbitrary, sometimes <a href="https://www.govtech.com/public-safety/California-Supreme-Court-Upholds-Bullet-Micro-Stamping-Law.html">impossible</a>, ideas of 'reasonable' gun safety.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>