<post>
  <author>greatjasoni</author>
  <date>2020-10-01T03:19:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g790xxm/</link>
  <title>The birth pangs of a cyber demon come to reap the fruit of our sins</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Why aren't you afraid? I share your contempt. I share your disgust. I strongly agree that this Democracy is a sham. I despise the ruling caste. But like you say, the price is paid in blood. </p>
      <p>What this insane molochian system we call Democracy has done is suppress the legitimate democratic will of the mob so that our betters in the Cathedral can rule us. We aren't ruled by glorified call centre workers. The ruling class and the incentive structure cucks them into call centre jobs because those men don't have any real power. Collectively the aristocracy has settled on a few specific rituals parasitically grounded in the democractic rules, that they might keep things running in a stable manner. And while largely this caste rules like a chicken with its head cut off, who are we to say we are worthy of overtaking them? I support the current sham democracy precisely because it is a sham. I don't want democracy at all. </p>
      <p>We aren't worthy yet. There's no institution of smart truth seeking people with stable reputations capable of trudging through the wreckage of the collapse. The closest to that as far as I can tell is the Chinese Government, not a comforting thought. I don't find your prediction for a post civil war US from our other conversation any more comforting. I don't find honesty comforting. I'm terrified.</p>
      <p>You think Trump and Biden are idiots, compare them to the mob. Then compare them to the powerful machiavelians <em>not on your side</em> eager to exploit chaos. You're outnumbered. This "honesty" is not a stable situation. It's a tipping point, and God only knows where it's going to take us. But wherever it does I don't want a legitimate democracy. I want another sham run by capable people. </p>
      <p>You make a lot of moral claims about what we <em>should</em> look at. On some level I agree that if we are going to be so presumptuous as to larp at democracy we should see what it actually entails. But what is to be gained by larping? I have a job and I get a paycheck and I spend it on bread. It isn't my responsibility to rule. If I can't keep it together without a tv puppet show then my rulers have a responsibility to give it to me. They have their job and I have mine. </p>
      <p>I look at the future and I see a coming <a href="https://youtu.be/gQaafNForNs">calamity</a>. Past whatever might be happening in this country soon, there will be unprecedented technological changes in our lifetime that will grant unimagined power to sovereigns. I don't trust our rulers with that power. I don't trust this culture with that power. I don't trust myself with that power. I pray that it goes to someone worthy. At the time when we should all be becoming as worthy as possible the ground falls out from under us. No one even believes in the concept of worthiness. Maybe this is fate giving us the fire we need to temper ourselves so that we may be ready to face the greater disaster ahead. But this is fucking terrifying. This is insanity. I need 9 layers of ironic detachment just to process any of this. I aspire to save the world with songs and finger paints but mostly I don't want to die. Whatever that shitshow was, it wasn't a good sign. These are the birth pangs of a cyber demon come to reap the fruit of our sins. It's going to kill us all and you're giving a speech about honesty in immaculate prose. Why aren't you afraid?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>