<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-10-01T01:25:44Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j165sq/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_september_28/g78p0nt/</link>
  <title>IQ denial is a luxury belief</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>OK, but why did you write that comment? I've authored countless comments of this kind, too, and now that I wonder about that I don't like the answer. The primary opponent that I addressed has <em>never</em> relented, literally not even once. I could sway some undecideds, but I imagine most of them regressed back to their community's mean right after that. What was the point? To be right on the internet?  </p>
      <p>I think we make an error of the same kind as these denialists. We do not stop to reflect on the issue, and proceed to "educate". Come on. Were she motivated to share some legitimate knowledge about IQ testing, she'd have read a book, it's not like Google has already censored Arthur Jensen's <em>Bias in Mental Testing</em> (though Wikipedia is being cleansed of heresy as we speak). Instead she snarks against a feeble-minded strawman. She's not dumb, her entire persona is built on being a "smart girl". Maybe it is prudent to consider that her behaviour is rational in its own way.  </p>
      <p>Here's what I think. The thing is, <strong>IQ denial is a luxury belief</strong>, it's universally viewed as a high-status position. It is painted as very sophisticated and nuanced (ha, those knuckle-draggers really believe the complex wonder of human intelligence can be measured with a bunch of stupid questions and described in a single number! heh! what next, grandpa, calipers?), as morally responsible (because it defangs certain racist arguments) and even as scientifically authoritative (Vox says experts say!..). Such image is disseminated top-down from academia and reputation mills (awards, "watchdogs") to journalism and low-brow media (where it's processed into clever-sounding but ultimately retarded arguments), and serves to manufacture a consensus reality. Most of the normal folk are not sensitive to these signals, as they have to deal with physical reality more. But the "midwits", the educated, self-conscious, information-hungry beyond their ability to process, half-clever, premium mediocre strata which makes up the bulk of this Tibees' target audience, are <em>very sensitive</em>. For middling intelligence, memorisation seems to be the whole of understanding. They try to distinguish themselves from the foolish masses (and often enough their own parents) who don't even know what's being said on the news, who don't listen to experts and teachers! The same people watch TED, unironically say "woo I fucking love science" on Reddit, participate in book reading challenges and are very easy to mock like I do now, precisely because it's very easy to stereotype them. In their nervous pursuit of intelligentsia status symbols, in the eternal chase of the Middle after the appearance of High while glancing jealously into each others' sheets, they <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1410.8001">synchronise near-perfectly</a>. As such, "science communicators" and "public educators" who wish to succeed just need to pander to their sensibilities, and they know exactly what those are. </p>
      <p>The whole premise of "science popularisation" is bogus. A minority with actual interest in science is typical-minding the rest, the masses of people who watch "educator" YT channels to feel better about themselves and to gather smart-ish trivia to drop at parties. These folks come in with a pretty clear general concept of what a <a href="https://www.durham-lab.com/news/lab-dei-statement">real sciencey</a> educator believes (the latest update of morality package from CNN-NBC-NYT, essentially), and they will leave if they hear any heresy such as <a href="https://youtu.be/J94epkdB_i4">this</a> or th.. damn, AltHype's videos <a href="https://youtu.be/PuMerbKJRwc">are gone from YT</a>. Thus, the competition on the field where science educators, Contrapoints and Shaun Breadtube types and smarter twitterati play amounts to spinning the prejudices of their base into more and more intricate forms, with greater number of fascinating epicycles and adornments. An uruk-highmidwit "enlightening" the populace, for all the camera work and clever scripts, is more like queen ant than Prometheus: locked into the hive's mechanism, with no more agency than a regular drone. </p>
      <p>(As for why the authorities in high places <a href="https://heterodoxacademy.org/seizing-means-knowledge-production/">such as Harvard</a> have engineered this pseudo-intellectual fashion, it's a very interesting question indeed. You may ignore this part of my model or handwave it somehow, that'll be better for you).</p>
      <p>Like they say in Russia, <a href="https://petr8.livejournal.com/14775.html">«Nothing can be fixed here any more. Lord, burn it!»</a> Not much to add to this. I'm thinking of how to rescue the truly smart and truth-receptive youth from the pit of snarky gossipy verbal midwittery and into the realm of actually reasoning about phenomena and ideas and matter, like natural philosophers should do. One presently investigated way is to aid the dissemination of memes like "soyjack", parodying the quirks of this caricature yay-science crowd, lowering the status of Tibees and her ilk. Examples <a href="https://twitter.com/DissentMan/status/1310812522685984768?s=20">1</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/KirkegaardEmil/status/1308177264748703745?s=20">2</a>. It's not enough and I implore everyone who already agrees with me to at least think about other ways. Hopefully this isn't crossing into "rallying for a cause".</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>