<post>
  <author>LawOfTheGrokodus</author>
  <date>2020-10-01T02:50:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/j2z5sh/my_trip_to_ghana/g78y213/</link>
  <title>Best Practices in Child Online Protection</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So what are the best practices in child online protection?</p>
      <p>I focused on six main categories of threat to child online safety, broadly defined:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Child sexual abuse material (CSAM): The term of art for child pornography and similar things. The risk isn't so much kids being exposed to it as the harms of material featuring some child still circulating on the internet, and the concerns that the availability of and demand for it results in more IRL victimization.</li>
        <li>Grooming: Relationship-building for the purpose of future exploitation. Grooming is usually referring to sexual grooming, but there's also extremist grooming.</li>
        <li>Cyberbullying: Kids mistreating each other through social media, online, etc.</li>
        <li>Age-inappropriate content: Practically speaking, whatever the government doesn't like and wants to ban "for the children". Less cynically, this most commonly includes pornography, extreme violence, and excessive gaming.</li>
        <li>Data privacy: In most places, children (with a cutoff that's different everywhere) are granted stronger privacy rights than adults, as they aren't considered to be responsible stewards of their personal information yet, and there is some adult who has guardianship over them.</li>
        <li>Cybersecurity: Compromise of youths' computers. These threats usually aren't directed at children specifically, but kids may be particularly vulnerable (I remember thinking a password of all asterisks would be really clever and unguessable).</li>
      </ul>
      <p>I went over a bunch of existing efforts to deal with each of these and tried to assess their effectiveness, though there usually wasn't enough evidence. I tackled this from a more libertarian perspective because I thought that stance was underrepresented in these discussions, and because I'm more congenial towards the libertarian view in cases where I trust the government less, and I certainly don't trust the governments here. I tried to think about unintended consequences of laws or policies and ways that they could be abused.</p>
      <p>CSAM is illegal pretty much everywhere, and there's extensive efforts to stamp it out. But that fervor shouldn't trample people's privacy and it shouldn't harm innocents. Microsoft's <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/photodna">PhotoDNA</a> system is a pretty good way of identifying CSAM without looking at everyone's images unencrypted, though it does suffer from the limitation that it can only identify images similar to ones in its corpus of CSAM. Therefore, it's good for law enforcement to send CSAM they find on to the PhotoDNA project for logging so that it can be caught in the future. Attempts to ban end-to-end encryption to foil the undetectable exchange of CSAM are wildly misguided: they would massively damage everyone's privacy and security, and people who want to transmit CSAM can just encrypt it locally and bypass the ban. Laws against CSAM sometimes are used against teens in consensual sexual relationships who send each other sexually explicit images of themselves. This application of the laws is obviously wrong and the laws should be written to prevent that from happening. Kids: remember, just because you can have sex with someone doesn't mean you can legally send them a nude photo!</p>
      <p>Grooming can be a bit tricky because the nature of it often lies in the purpose, not the actions (if it turns into sexual predation or terrorist attacks, those are crimes on their own). The other challenge is that the first step of it is pretty universally "build trust with the victim", so getting the victim's cooperation can be difficult, and they often won't tell people what's going on. Mandatory reporting laws, though well-intentioned, can actually backfire by making kids less willing to come forward with concerns they're not sure how much they want to escalate. The International Centre for Missing and Exploited Children has some model legislation for sexual grooming, which is a good start, though I think there's some parts of it I take issue with. One unusual way to fight grooming is through shows like Catfish and To Catch a Predator, which can make people more aware of the possibility that the person they're talking to may not be on the level. As with CSAM, laws against grooming can be applied in bad ways, such as to criminalize disapproved-of relationships. I also listed some yellow and red flags kids might want to keep an eye out for.</p>
      <p>Cyberbullying is prevalent, but it's actually really rare on its own. Almost every victim of cyberbullying is also a victim of conventional bullying, so perhaps efforts should be directed towards the broader problem of bullying, in the hopes that any effectiveness there will spill over to cyberbullying. Unfortunately, stopping bullying is hard because kids are jerks. There are a few anti-bullying programs that show some promise in scientific trials, such as the Olweus Bullying Prevention Program, the Viennese Social Competence Program, though I can't vouch for the quality of those studies. Only Finland's KiVa program was tested specifically on cyberbullying, and it did okay at helping with that. Kids: the best way to fight cyberbullying is to not do it yourself. If you're the victim of it... er, save documentation of it? Really, I don't think there's any advice I can give you that will help. Parents and teachers: take this stuff seriously. Don't have a culture where your kid gets the crap beaten out of them and a video of them is posted online and you say on your kid's behalf that you forgive the perpetrators as they continue to victimize your kid. (Actual story from the conference.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>