<post>
  <author>roystgnr</author>
  <date>2021-06-28T21:56:38Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/o9edtt/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_june_28_2021/h3dd7xo/</link>
  <title>"You get pregnant on Mars, it's too late."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>you get pregnant on Mars, you go back to Earth and go through the pregnancy there</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You get pregnant on Mars, it's too late.</p>
      <p>Mars' surface is exposed to to 10-20 REM/year, about 30x what the NRC says is safe for a fetus, but even in a small colony you can tunnel into the omnipresent regolith to hide from it.  Space around Mars orbit is exposed to 40-120 REM/year, and every millimeter of spacecraft shielding is painful to accelerate or decelerate.</p>
      <p>With a large wealthy colony you could get around the radiation concerns (via cycler stations: you take a cramped and poorly-shielded but brief shuttle trip to the station and then you live in heavily-shielded relative comfort during the long transfer to Earth) but there's no getting around the orbital mechanics concerns: travel between Mars and Earth takes months.  By the time you get to Earth your baby's long past the differentiating-blob-of-cells stage.  In fact, if you wanted to take a cycler and you didn't time it right you might not even be able to make it to Earth before your due date.</p>
      <p>If 1/3 gravity turns out to be insufficient for pregnancy then the best bet might be space stations in Mars orbit.  Less delta-V for the shuttle to get there (and negligible delta-V use by the station itself) would make it cheaper, and the whole station could be a huge roomy centrifuge because you wouldn't have to worry about bearings like you do with a ground-based centrifuge.  The station itself could be heavily shielded even more cheaply than a cycler (because the shielding likewise goes into a single stable orbit and stays there, but the orbit is easier to get to and maintain) - or, if we're doing any radiation remediation of Mars itself (I've seen studies of proposed EM radiation shield-generating satellite; it would take a big nuclear reactor but it wouldn't take magic) then space stations in low Mars orbit would share in the benefits.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>