<post>
  <author>Capital_Room</author>
  <date>2020-07-17T01:10:31Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fybbkju/</link>
  <title>Analyzing "White" Culture</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Yeah, I saw the infographic a couple other places online. And, having read some other discussions on this — and recalling some other things I've read, as well as a bunch of life experience and experiences by family — I'm going to offer a little bit of a defense.</p>
      <p>I come from a much poorer background — and live in much poorer circumstances now — than most people who comment here. (I frequently want to tell some people here to try spending a few hours in line at the welfare office listening to people's conversations.) One point — if I remember correctly, Scott made it in an SSC post at one time — is how much modern Western society is built around ability to navigate bureaucracy. I have a relative who works at a branch library in the poorest part of town, and who has often had people come in to use the computers for Internet access, to access government webpages for applying to benefits or such, and who've needed massive assistance as, for various reasons, they find navigating these systems to be too cognitively demanding in one way or another. (For that matter, I'm pretty smart and even I have difficulty dealing with Social Security sometimes.)</p>
      <p>Note the "future orientation" bit of the graphic, and consider those people with high time preference and low ability to delay gratification. Or consider trying to explain the benefits of insurance to someone with difficulties with counterfactual thinking. Or look at several of the points on the "communication" bit at the bottom: "avoid conflict, intimacy" "don't show emotion," "be polite." Then consider the major stereotypes of East Asian cultures. Suffocating levels of conformity, restraint and industriousness, schools full of kids obeying pointless rules in excruciating detail at length, people hiding what they mean and feel behind levels of polite indirection. Now consider that to many folks with lower levels of impulse control and ability to delay gratification, this is <em>exactly</em> what "White Culture" as described by the infographic feels like <em>all the time</em>. I once recall someone talking about various people's stereotypes of the US, and that Latin American stereotypes tend to resemble either American stereotypes of Germans — dour, humorless, obsessed with order and precision — or Japanese — uptight, sexually-represssed workaholics (who watch a lot of porn).</p>
      <p>One of the sharpest counter-criticisms I saw to the criticisms of the infographic was that too many of these critics seem unable to accept that some people might <em>genuinely</em> view these elements of "white culture" as <em>bad things</em>. That someone might <em>actually believe</em> that a life of passionate spontaneity lived moment-to-moment is better and more virtuous than one built around delayed gratification and careful deliberation on long-term consequences. Or that when someone argues that a workplace demanding punctuality is imposing "white" notions of time over the more "<a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/2017/04/clemson-diversity-training-expecting-people-arrive-time-culturally-insensitive/">fluid</a>" sense of time some other cultures have, they might genuinely believe that "<a href="https://tulanehullabaloo.com/51652/intersections/business-professionalism-is-racist/">polychronic work environments</a>" with a "a different prioritization of family and relationships over capitalist productivity and work demands" are <em>better</em> than a "40-hour work week… built to allow white men to succeed at work."</p>
      <p>I'm also reminded of a relatively-Westernized Native friend of mine and his disagreements with more "traditional" cousins of his vis-a-vis reciprocity versus exploitation of outsiders. Or, for that matter, just consider the Norse: plenty of well-developed laws and rules, prohibiting things like theft or burning down people's houses… which didn't stop them from looting and burning the homes and carrying off the wives and daughters of people across the sea. For some cultures, honest dealing is only for your ingroup, and cheating outsiders for everything you can is praiseworthy.</p>
      <p>The argument is that these traits are simply those that make for individual success in a modern, industrialized capitalist society. Well, I see four counter-arguments.</p>
      <p>First, that this is somewhat circular and chicken-egg: these traits make for success in and industrialized capitalist society… meaning the kind of society built mostly by and for people with a "white culture" which values and promotes these traits. Secondly, success by what metric? Who is more successful: the woman with the high-status career, six-figure paycheck and lavish big-city apartment… she shares with her four cats? Or the much poorer Amish farmer with seven kids who finds contentment in his work and his faith? Or the man who recieves government welfare benefits… and is a respected scholar of the Torah in his ultra-Orthodox Jewish community? How "successful" is Scott? <em>Whose</em> metric of success do we use?</p>
      <p>Well, one can then point to the success of Western/"white" Culture as a whole, which then comes down to pretty much two things: success over competing cultures, and material plenty. On the former, well, the infographic itself has a "competition" category, with  "Be #1" and "winner/loser dichotomy," as itself part of "white culture." And further, don't many of the people who criticize "white culture" frame "success over competing cultures" as being "better" at colonialism, imperialism, etc., and thus, again, a <em>bad thing</em>. And as for material productivity, this <em>mostly</em> speaks for itself… but, again, consider the Amish example above. Note that the technological development behind that material success falls under the "master and control nature" under that competition category. I certainly know that emphasizing an alternate value of "harmony with nature" is often associated with some non-white cultures, for example, Native Americans (locally, we get bombarded with plenty of anti-copper-mine TV ads with a Native narrator going on about how their culture has 'for countless generations lived according to the rhythms of the salmon, in A Place That Has Always Been.') And, well, "White Culture" certainly is proving less successful if your metric for success is <em>Darwinian</em>…</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>