<post>
  <author>Doglatine</author>
  <date>2020-07-20T14:20:35Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fynsria/</link>
  <title>Matching vs Bonding in Relationships</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>And emotional/social Intelligence might play a large part in that</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>First distinction worth making: there's a big difference between the traits helpful for finding partners ("Matching") versus the traits involved in making relationships work ("Bonding"). Some people have very few problems with the former but lots of problems with the latter, and vice-versa.</p>
      <p>Second distinction I'd flag concerns Emotional Intelligence. Maybe someone has done a more systematic factor analysis of this, but at a first pass, I'd want to distinguish (i) prosociality (kindness), (ii) social cognition (identifying others' mental states, responding appropriately), and (iii) charisma (≈ lack of awkwardness).</p>
      <p>I think it's interesting to think about how these three factors map onto the Matching vs Bonding.</p>
      <p>(1) <strong>Prosociality</strong> mainly seems helpful for Bonding and not particularly relevant for Matching. Partly this is because interpersonal virtue isn't particularly erotically attractive to most people, and Matching is heavily driven by eroticism. By contrast, Prosociality seems really important for making relationships work longer term: effortless and spontaneous generosity and benevolence is the marker of a good partner and good relationship, and no-one wants to be <em>married</em> to a selfish jerk, even if they want to fuck them. This is why, incidentally, I think the whole line about how Incels' problems are due to their moral defects is bullshit; Incels aren't pissed because their partners all leave them after 3 months, they're pissed because they can't get a date to begin with. In any case, I'm not sure Prosociality can be taught to adults, except perhaps by traumatic and transformational life experiences. Certainly, <a href="https://aeon.co/essays/how-often-do-ethics-professors-call-their-mothers">moral philosophy doesn't seem to help.</a></p>
      <p>(2) <strong>Social cognition</strong> seems like a generally helpful skill for both Matching and Bonding. Being able to anticipate people's desires and reactions, correctly reading people's body language, identifying which lines of conversation went down well and which went badly and adapting, etc. - this stuff is <em>critical</em> for a good first date, but will also reduce day-to-day friction in a relationship (if paired with prosociality at least). While some people seem to be effortlessly gifted at social cognition and neurodivergent people may face greater challenges than average, I think a lot of it can be taught by experience. I probably went on 30-40 first dates over a three year period of being single and my ability to do things like gauge how the date was going dramatically improved. I suspect, however, that these improvements are mostly domain specific - I could give a similar story about how my pedagogical social cognition (e.g., being able to tell when a class I'm teaching is engaged by the material) improved over my first few years as an instructor, but I don't think there was much if any synergy between this and the gains to social cognition I picked up from dating! Likewise, the kinds of social-cognitive skill that I've acquired over a decade and a half of serial monogamy make my marital life a lot easier - I know how to have a constructive argument, for example, and how to identify the times when my partner <em>really needs me</em> but doesn't want to have to ask, but again, I think this is something you have to learn on the job. One mild complication for learning to be better at social cognition, though, is that a lot of people don't seem particularly willing to adjust their behaviour. Example: I have a friend who routinely offends people by making way too many sexual comments in conversation (he'd say he was doing it semi-ironically). But when I suggested to him that he knock it off if doesn't want to gross women out, he said it's just a part of his personality and he wants a woman who loves him for it. Sure, that's fine I guess, but don't complain to me when you don't get second dates. I see a lot of similar resistance when you tell people to e.g. tune down their intense nerdiness on first dates or not get too clingy too quickly, etc..</p>
      <p>Anyway I don't know how much of a role social cognition deficits play in the Incel phenomenon, but it's probably at least moderately significant. In particular, I think there's a vicious circle that a lot of Incels get caught in: if you can't get dates to begin with, you're not going to learn the relevant knowledge, and you're not going to be gain the dating "XP" required to level up, so to speak, making you progressively less dateable as time goes by and your peer group/romantic competitors get comparatively more socially skillful. I think the only simple answer to this is to do the dating equivalent of "grinding": aggressively and relentlessly put yourself in romance-relevant first encounters (in appropriate contexts, obviously). Start up conversations with strangers at bars and clubs, attend singles events, sign up to every dating app out there (just don't try it at work, in hobby communities, with friends, or on strangers in non-romantic settings, e.g. the gym or the street). If you're an unattractive man you will be shot down repeatedly but you will at least be gaining useful skills and (in the long run) confidence that should allow you to 'catch up'.</p>
      <p>(3) Last of all, there's <strong>Charisma</strong>. Note that I'm using the term in a narrow sense, specifically excluding those aspects of charisma that can be explained in terms of prosociality or social cognition (e.g. empathy). Instead I mean something purely aesthetic: a lack of awkwardness, a certain flair and style and way of talking and acting that puts people at their ease. I think Charisma in this sense is honestly a huge deal and is probably the primary determinant for Matching success for men once looks have been taken into account. It's even relevant for friendships: there have been some very smart and kind people I've met that I've not been motivated to hang out with because they're just kind of... socially weird-acting, I guess? It could be anything from the fake-sounding way they laugh, to the shuffling way they walk, to the very nasal way they talk, to their habit of constantly touching their face and looking at their shoes during a conversation. Likewise, there are some people who just have natural charisma - they stride into a room and crack this big, easy, relaxed smile and suddenly everyone wants to be their friend.</p>
      <p>Charisma is kind of bullshit and unfair, but it's a real and powerful phenomenon and you can't pretend it doesn't exist. One reason it's so powerful, I suspect, is that it's it's a hard to fake signal, which in turn suggests it may be hard to teach and hard to learn. Still, I think there are some simple little things you can do, like record yourself having a conversation and try to identify which of your facial expressions look good and which look awkward, or what verbal or motor tics you might have that make you seem weird. But if your 'weirdness' barometer isn't well calibrated, you might not be great at spotting this stuff, so you'd be better off asking a charismatic friend you <em>really</em> trust (but be prepared to feel <em>crushed</em> when they tell you: learning about your uncharismatic behaviours is very likely going to feel bad if it's going to be helpful). There are also a few practical things you can do to improve your Charisma. I've found teaching and other forms of public speaking to be very helpful, just because you get a lot of rapid real time feedback about what forms of self-presentation are good for generating warmth and engagement in your audience. I also did eight years of acting (just as a hobby), which was frankly fantastic, because it teaches you to become more aware of how you hold your body and how you speak, and once you're used to doing this it becomes easier to modify them for specific personal purposes in future. And while I'm not musical myself, I've heard similar good things about singing and dancing as ways of improving one's core self-presentation.</p>
      <p>I suspect Charisma - along with looks - is the main issue in the Incel phenomenon. Most of the persistently sexually dissatisfied men I know are kind of awkward and weird-acting, even if they're decent and kind human beings, and I think it's a large determinant of their lack of success. This is a shame because, as I say, Charisma isn't easy to teach. I guess one bit of good news is that Charisma is less important for Bonding than it is for Matching: that winning smile, that devil-may-care laugh, or that Byronic toss of the hair may be sexy as hell but they're not going to help you resolve an argument about whether to get a foster kitten or why you didn't respond to an urgent text for 12 hours (well - I say that, but my wife still occasionally uses her Charisma to win arguments - that playful pout, that deep eye contact and wistful sigh - but I suspect that's partly just due to the positive associations I've built up towards her mannerisms over the years). In any case, to the extent Charisma is the stumbling block for some Incels, they can at least draw comfort from the fact that they're (probably) not fundamentally unlovable - once they can establish the initial erotic attraction, other traits like prosociality, social cognition, and, y'know, being an interesting and accomplished person come to the fore.</p>
      <p>Oh, and finally, a bit of self-promotion: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/g0m1z1/the_donts_of_dating_romantic_advice_for/">my dating guide for contrarians</a>!</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>