<post>
  <author>FCfromSSC</author>
  <date>2020-07-20T02:40:17Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fymdh8k/</link>
  <title>The Higher Satisfaction</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Is there evidence they were any happier? I can't imagine how it could possibly be determined that we are at below the average level of happiness through the rest of human history.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Suicide, substance abuse, mental illness, possibly stuff like crime? Homelessness? Political unrest, rioting? All of these things seem like stuff that doesn't happen when people are happy.</p>
      <p>I mean, I'd argue that increasing time spent on "fun" is itself a decent measure of declining happiness, as "fun" and fulfillment tend to trade off against each other, but obviously I wouldn't expect you to agree with that. Still, take a look at the Amish. It seems pretty clear that they're having a lot less "fun" than the average modern, yet something about their lifestyle keeps them highly cohesive anyway. What's going on there, in your theory?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I've never experienced any sort of pleasure or 'fulfillment' that isn't adequately captured by the concept of 'fun' and I'm having a hard time imagining what that would even look like. </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>One of the most obvious places I see the difference is in various forms of entertainment. </p>
      <p>At the most basic level, I see this in the experience of viewing porn, versus making art. Both are pleasurable experiences, both are, in a sense, pointless, both can involve a sort of hunger, a drive that pushes one to participate. Still, the physical pleasure of masturbation, while intense, is of a very different kind to the euphoric glow from viewing a freshly-completed painting. The former leads reliably to a sort of vague disgust at the time wasted, while the later lingers and builds, even in the long-term.</p>
      <p>In fiction, I've found that I can very much enjoy trashy fanfic, and I can enjoy really high-quality fiction, but the enjoyment is again of two distinctly different kinds. The trashy fanfic, I've come to notice, is very clearly just pushing buttons in my brain, and relatively crude ones at that. The high-quality fiction, on the other hand, generally leaves me feeling that I've gained insight or experience or knowledge in some important way, that I am somehow increased or expanded in a long-term way by having read it. I enjoy both sorts of experiences, but as I've grown older the difference between them has only grown more stark, and I find myself chasing the trashy stuff less and less, and even swearing off whole genres because I feel they're a waste of time.</p>
      <p>Video games, again, show the same pattern. I've been a gamer most of my life, and I've played a lot of different games for a lot of different reasons. But as I've grown older, I see the repeating patterns, and I see the methods of psychological manipulation more and more clearly, and while the immediate fun remains, I find myself actively avoiding games I know I'll enjoy, even games I know I'll be actively obsessed with, because that obsessive "fun" is, in the end, less fulfilling then things of longer-term value, like making art or learning new skills.</p>
      <p>Likewise with spending time with people. The most rewarding experiences I've had with other people haven't been "fun", in the sense of playing a game or, I don't know, partying or whatever. Teaching my sibling's children art, or teaching them how to play D&amp;D, or teaching them how to code, have easily been some of the most rewarding experiences of my adult life. The D&amp;D in particular is a really good case of this, because the fulfillment didn't come from the details or events of the game, it came from sharing something I love with other people, and seeing them love it too, and knowing that now this is a thing we share and probably will for the rest of our lives.</p>
      <p>These deeper layers of fulfillment weren't always obvious to me. I remember pretty clearly the point when I realized that I would rather spend a couple hours talking with someone, than playing a video game. I remember being surprised at that realization, because up till that moment I would have said that there's always time for conversation later, gaming was too much fun to put off. I don't know, maybe it's an age thing, or an experience thing.</p>
      <p>Anyhow, does this answer your question at least a little?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>