<post>
  <author>HighResolutionSleep</author>
  <date>2020-07-17T06:47:39Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fyc4ios/</link>
  <title>Explaining the Foundational Myths of Female Purity</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>This post was originally intended as a reply to <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fy99mn8/">this post</a> by <a href="/u/zzzyxas">/u/zzzyxas</a>. However, it grew so long and far away from the original complaint and toward my own agenda that I felt it was no longer fair to tack it on as a direct reply.</p>
      <hr />
      <p>Female sexual purity is an important foundational myth to many, many ideologies—it would appear as though that Woke is one of them.</p>
      <p>It's powerful, because the human imagination lacks the capacity to resist it. There was a controversy long, long ago that I believe perfectly illustrates this human weakness.</p>
      <p>Back when Christian fundamentalism was the Big Bad Moralizer everyone was afraid of (remember that?), there was a row among secular, feminist, proto-Woke spaces about a Christian religious school teaching their students that <a href="https://sojo.net/articles/top-5-best-and-worst-bits-christian-sex-advice">girls who fraternize with too many boys are like lollipops dropped upon the ground too many times</a>.</p>
      <p>To early Woke, this was clearly misogyny. Both Christianity and Woke viscerally agree that women and girls are sweet and wonderful like lollipops, and that men and boys are dirty and gross like the ground. However, where they disagree is what happens when they collide.</p>
      <p>The Traditional Christian culture holds the supremacy of female sexuality as contingent and worldly—tied to reproductive burdens and bound to certain mating standards. Woke disagrees, and asserts that the supremacy of female sexuality is much more metaphysical in nature, and cannot be tarnished by virtually any degree of contact with the unclean—and to suggest otherwise is misogyny.</p>
      <p>The obvious and conclusive rebuttal to both would be to assert that there is no supremacy of female sexuality to begin with—but as remarked earlier, this is not something that readily avails itself to the human imagination or its passions.</p>
      <p>Barring that, just about the only thing that can challenge Purity is open displays of women prancing among the filth and <em>enjoying it as though it were as wholesome as they</em>, which is why these social regimes are quite censorious with this kind of content.</p>
      <p>This may give you the impression that I enjoy or at least approve of "Misogyny Kink" or others in its genre. I don't. In fact, I think it's ultimately counterproductive. While it may embarrass an incumbent or insurgent Purity regime, it ultimately ensures that the same phenomenon will recur yet again.</p>
      <p>You see, I don't just think that this genre is just degrading to women: I find degrading to <em>men</em> as well. Don't mistake this for a TradCon tract. I think that it's degrading to men <em>per se</em>—not merely <em>degrading to men because it's degrading to women and it's men's duty to protect and uphold the sanctity of women's sexual virtue and failing to do so makes you less a man.</em> It's degrading to men because it, as usual, casts male sexual desire as negative. As in Woke, masculine sexual energy is gross, degrading, and filthy—and as a man you must conquer it to become a real human bean. And if you don't—well, that's kink/misogyny, and that's degenerate/problematic.</p>
      <p>So far as I can tell, those who oppose pornography do not do so on the grounds that there are healthier ways for men to express their desire and for women to enjoy receiving it—but rather that it is the desire and its expression itself that is vulgar and profane. I don't suspect that they would be in favor of porn in which a woman receives a hot facial because it's fulfilling and affirming to her sexuality, if such a thing ever existed. I imagine they'd peg it as even worse: <a href="https://4w.pub/women-are-being-trained-by-porn-to-like-degrading-violent-male-centered-sex/">trying to get women to enjoy something they ought to regard as horrifying.</a> Porn is degrading because semen is degrading.</p>
      <p>Incels and RedPillers love to haze Purity folks with <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/all-about-sex/201001/womens-rape-fantasies-how-common-what-do-they-mean">those statistics on women's rape fantasies</a>. I'll admit it's fun to watch their hurried explanations fail one after the next. Repressed abuse: refuted. Sexual suppression: refuted. Sexual liberation: refuted. This part is more speculative on my behalf as it's not my experience to say, but what if it really isn't the rape part of a rape fantasy that gets a lass going? I wonder if it's the covetous, immediate, voracious nature of the act that's alluring. </p>
      <p>But if that's so, why <em>rape</em>? I suppose one could suspect that it's difficult to get more rapacious than rape itself, and I imagine that the hyperbole of fantasy has something to do with it. However, I can't think of single genre in which masculine desire is cast as a positive force. At best, it is cast as something that is desired either in spite or because of its filth. ("Take it, slut!") Women may, among other pleasures, enjoy being desired by men in specifically the carnal capacity, to be jealously possessed, urgently needed, and sublimely satisfying. But it's also gross. Perhaps the half-ubiquitous female rape fantasy is the confused synthesis?</p>
      <p>However, in this capacity, it fails to refute the central premise of the Purity myth. This is the block that must be pulled for the whole tower to collapse, but the misogyny/rape/bdsm/whatever genres ultimately reinforce it. They don't insist that male sexuality isn't gross; they insist that it's okay for women to like gross things. This means that any victory it achieves over Purity will be temporary and fleeting. It doesn't reject the act as a sin; it turns the sin into a spectacle and celebrates it as such. One can only wonder how much sexual repression has been wrought by this characterization, and how much freer not just men but women would be without it. Heaven knows how sterile "romantic porn" can be. What if he fucked her hard <em>and</em> they kissed? At the same time????</p>
      <p>Or perhaps I'm dead wrong, and female sexuality really does tightly cluster around the antipodes of <em>only wants a man to hug and finds male sexuality frankly a little frightening</em> and <em>wants to be beaten, raped, and treated like a cheap sex doll.</em> I also don't know if it's neurologically possible for humans to separate male desire from impurity, but I suppose it doesn't hurt to dream of a rosier future.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>