<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-07-20T22:57:25Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fypj75s/</link>
  <title>Why Debates Are Not Duels</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>He is pushing the other person outside of negotiation territory and into conflict. It's remarkably close to a primitive challenge to a duel! </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I respectfully disagree. </p>
      <p>The important thing, perhaps the thing most necessary to understand the disconnect and apparent futility of rational appeals to SJWs, is that these debates are empathetically <em>not</em> duels and in fact are the exact opposite tradition arising from an utterly incompatible mindset. Sometimes the procedure becomes confusingly similar, but the incentive structure is very different. </p>
      <p>Duels are competitions in strength (or wit, like in chess; or knowledge of truth, like in the idealized hypothetical-deductive science) between individual contenders, even when they are public; your blows go straight to the target, without any mediator. These struggle sessions are <em>performative</em>, even when done in private, because the representation of the judging and rewarding society (that we, as you surely remember, live in), like Big Brother, is always present in the modern man's mind and this collective power, not one's individual strength, is recognized as the source of legitimacy.<br />
The advocate is not arguing with the prosecutor, nor is he trying to convince him, despite occasional appearances: they're both talking to the judge and jury, talking <em>past</em> each other. In the court of public opinion we have the same dynamic, but far less demand for verifiable truth (after all, being individually right is merely a form of individual strength), and the distributed, implicit nature of social justice movement means that everyone is prosecutor, advocate and defendant at once, in some sort of rhetorical superposition. The purpose of the communication, therefore, is to shift your density towards the most advantageous and powerful role.<br />
Can you see which one that is?  </p>
      <p>(I suspect Foucault has figured this all out in 100 times more detail.)</p>
      <p>
        <span class="md-spoiler-text">It's also hilarious that duels were a stereotypically European noble practice, while clever lawyering and performative opinion-making is strongly associated with Jews; yet look at "IDW" and you see, basically, a bunch of Jews like Harris and Weinstein brothers who say "hey guyz, let's debate this rationally and see whose hypothesis comes out on top, OK?" to a mob of Twitter hivemind nodes playing out the most-liked reactions to keywords, without concern for truth, such that the undemanding audience be convinced. Hard not to feel sorry for them.</span>
      </p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>