<post>
  <author>procrastinationrs</author>
  <date>2020-07-20T13:25:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hufif8/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_20_2020/fynn6yf/</link>
  <title>Fake Identities, Incels, and Relationships</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Therefore I would argue that EQ:Interpersonal Relationships is similar to IQ:Academic Success, i.e. it is not the only important thing, but god help you if you are missing it.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I have trouble conceiving of a world in which this would be true. I suppose in a world where the only question is men meeting women, and men were all sociopaths who would benefit from emotional intelligence because women weren't, it could be.</p>
      <p>There may be some incel-adjacent or pre-incel men who <em>just</em> want to have sex, but in that case it's a mystery why those men don't just hire prostitutes, as that's a fairly easy way to meet that goal. </p>
      <p>It seems to me that most men want to have some kind of relationship, or at least have sex with a woman who wants to have sex with them. People on the lower end of the empathy scale don't, but of course men on the lower end of the empathy scale are often considered to be at an advantage in attracting women.</p>
      <p>Most people benefit from modifying their behavior a bit to be more attractive but "a bit" is all <em>most</em> people <em>have</em> to do. One accentuates positives and minimizes or disguises some weaknesses. Suppose that for some particular person that wasn't good enough to do the trick, and add as much "emotional intelligence" to that person as you like. What that person would be called on to do -- and "advice to incels" often sounds this way to me -- is to manufacture a fake identity a woman would want to have sex with. When he's with a woman he suppresses all natural instincts. He looks for cues and responds with whatever behavior will attract. Gradually the woman is tricked.</p>
      <p>A man doing this over a long period would, in effect, live his life next to the relationship between the woman and the fictional persona he has created. He would would receive some of the physical benefits but few of the emotional ones. And there would be constant worry about slipping up.</p>
      <p>This is probably how many low-empathy people live (although perhaps with higher confidence due to the lower stakes) and there are probably many low-empathy people, but that doesn't really address the problem of a man who is not low empathy but perceived as a "creep" or non-entity by women. High "EQ" doesn't <em>necessarily</em> solve the alienation problem. It <em>may</em>, if increased understanding alone results in natural positive changes in behavior, but I don't see why that would be guaranteed.</p>
      <p>There is a degree of self-change a given person can effect without feeling alienated which defines the sandbox most of us play in. I suspect that lower amounts of empathy generally correlate with higher such degrees. A lot of "game" type advice seems to have a hidden step 0 of "be less empathetic". I'm not sure where the confidence that that is possible comes from unless it's just the lack of understanding that people differ in that way.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>