<post>
  <author>ThirteenValleys</author>
  <date>2020-07-17T19:17:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fye1kgx/</link>
  <title>On the "Noticed Class(es)"</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>Most culture warriors at this point are familiar with the 'Men are Generic, Women are Special' trope. Feminists focus on how 'generic' men can live their lives on their own terms and avoid unwanted attention while 'special' women are alternately coddled, sexualized, or harassed; anti-feminists focus on the specialness of women affording them various social privileges including double standards in sexual assault and custody laws, the cutthroat nature of the dating market, and a general presumption of innocence and niceness, while 'generic' men are ignored and kicked to the curb, their problems are laughed at, their desires are seen as inherently threatening, and they turn to drugs, suicide, or violence at greater rates. The point here is that the narratives are two sides of the same coin. Women wouldn't get the good <em>and</em> the bad sides of being women without their 'Specialness', same with men and their 'Genericness'. (This is one of many things Mainstream SJ theory can't deal with, due to its deranged insistence on 100% monodirectional power structures.)</p>
      <p>Is there a similar relationship between white and black Americans?</p>
      <p>It's not a stroke of genius to point out that the history of white American pop culture is basically the history of <em>black</em> American pop culture with a 5-10 year delay. Or that basically every 'cool' trait is associated with blacks and every nerdy one with whites, or that the vast majority of fights about pop cultural representation and portrayals are about black people. Some use these facts to argue that blacks are actually culturally <em>dominant</em> in America; everything revolves around them and their culture and their status. Black activists and their allies scoff, saying that if we're so dominant, how come so many of us are in prison, get attacked by cops, can't get a job, and so forth? </p>
      <p>Well, if you're the Noticed Class, just like with women, the people who notice you are going to be people who both love <em>and</em> hate you. The white teenager who desperately wants cool-guy cred <em>and</em> the racist cop who assumes you're a threat, the Hollywood executive who wants to surround himself with what's hip and trendy <em>and</em> the neighbor who calls the cops on you for walking your dog. If you're in the Noticed Class, like with women, you don't have one without the other. </p>
      <p>And like men, white people have their own double-edged sword to deal with; while it's true most people won't single you out for your race (way less true than it used to be, obviously), it's also true that most people don't care about your race <em>at all</em>, even when there are social or cultural ills that are plaguing your race in <em>particular.</em> Your culture might be accepted as ambient noise, but that's all it ever will be; no one will ever <em>care</em> about it. </p>
      <p>(Of course, America is more than just black and white, but I'm of the opinion that those are the two 'Ur-ethnic groups' here, not just historically but in terms of how most of the other groups define themselves.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>