<post>
  <author>Verda-Fiemulo</author>
  <date>2020-07-16T21:20:43Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fyamhpd/</link>
  <title>Delving into the Works of Bloom and Leo Strauss</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>So I've been on a bit of Straussian binge recently. I think I'm still digesting all the ideas, since they're all quite novel for me, and I'm not necessarily sure I agree with him and his acolytes on most things, insofar as I understand them. However, I certainly found them provocative and interesting.</p>
      <p>I've had a sort of meandering reading path - I started with "The Closing of the American Mind" and halfway through decided I needed to check out "Persecution and the Art of Writing" and "Philosophy Between the Lines." I'm still working my way through all three books, but I'm almost done and I thought I'd write up some brief thoughts on them.</p>
      <p>First, my thoughts on "The Closing of the American Mind."</p>
      <p>I find it interesting what a different time Allan Bloom seemed to be writing from, as a professor in 1987 who had seen all the pre- and post-war cultural shifts. Several of his complaints still feel like they could be written in 2020: specialization has replaced the ideal of a classical liberal education, most Americans have never encountered the big ideas in Continental philosophy or European literature in any real way (and when they do it often is only in passing, through watered down words that have only spread through pop-cultural osmosis) and culture has shifted so much that the models of relationships and ways of life in "classic" literature are often so removed from the student that they fail to see how they have any relevance to the modern world. However, his world is quite alien to me as well.</p>
      <p>He talks about the sexual revolution, and how most students don't think sex is that big a deal and are all having enough to satisfy themselves. While we certainly still inhabit a post-sexual revolution world in terms of attitudes towards sex, it's interesting that the Millennials and Gen Z are now having much less sex. Bloom's Freudian laments about all the sexual energy and ambition that students used to sublimate in their pursuit of liberal education being diverted to actual sex doesn't ring true in a world where 30% of college age men have never had sex, and people are losing their virginities later, putting off getting into romantic relationships and substituting porn for actual sexual satisfaction. His diagnosis feels "wrong" in retrospect, but maybe I'm not giving him enough credit.</p>
      <p>His thoughts on race relations, sexual equality and LGBT issues are fascinating to read in a BLM, #MeToo, anti-TERF era. While Bloom seems to be suspicious about the success of affirmative action in making African Americans a natural and normal part of campus life, and he certainly has a bone to pick with the Black Power movement that forced changes to university culture (more on that later), it seems like he thinks most of these issues have pretty much played out and accomplished what they wanted. Colorblind racism, while not a huge success, wasn't a failure in Bloom's eyes - white students considered black students equal, even if white and black students self-segregated, and there was always a lingering doubt as to whether the black students had gotten in on their own merit or due to affirmative action. Sexual equality was also a qualified success, and gay people had managed to get their sexuality accepted as just another "alternative lifestyle" in campus life. It's interesting that while Bloom sees negatives while regarding them all with a detached academic benevolence, he doesn't really seem to identify the fault lines what would later be drawn in each of these areas.</p>
      <p>He doesn't predict the rise of modern identity politics (though part of the book deals with the effects the forms of identity politics in the 60's and 70's had had on campus), and he didn't realize that colorblind racism, egalitarian feminism and "gay-as-alternative-lifestyle" thinking would all come under attack as not good enough. One can hardly blame him perhaps - he was writing in a time with no internet, in the middle of the Cold War. Who writing in that time could have foreseen what was coming around the corner?</p>
      <p>Bloom's take on the McCarthy era is fascinating and contrarian. For Bloom, far from representing the most repressive moment in American intellectual life, it was the last gasp of the American-European Golden Age of intellectual life. It was an era when America was the last torchbearer of classical European education. Many European professors had fled the wars of that century and taken up residence in American universities, bringing the best aspects of European learning with them - while the old-style European university was papered over by totalitarianism and fascism, and even where this wasn't the case, it was ravaged by war. There was no Black Power movement, the counter-Enlightenment didn't have a hegemonic stranglehold on the social sciences and humanities, and real differences of opinion were possible and common.</p>
      <p>What struck me the most was that the "modern" phenomenon of students demanding accommodations and changes in curriculum is much older than I had thought. His descriptions of the 1969 occupation of Cornell University by armed students demanding changes in curriculum feel like the stories of "SJW" students doing the same within the last 10 years. The main difference is that the students today don't occupy buildings while brandishing guns for the most part - instead their weapon is social media. They ferment outrage, and let that guide the colleges' decisions.</p>
      <p>While I've been suspicious of claims about the erosion of intellectual diversity and free exchange of ideas and pursuit of knowledge in universities, this book certainly gives me a lot to chew on. If nothing else, it's an interesting perspective.</p>
      <p>I have fewer thoughts on "Persecution and the Art of Writing" and "Philosophy Between the Lines", which I'll treat here. </p>
      <p>I think the focus in both these books resonates well with Scott's thoughts on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200115140200/https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/10/23/kolmogorov-complicity-and-the-parable-of-lightning/">Kolmogorov Complicity</a>. They concern esoteric writing by philosophers. This is not metaphysical esoterism in the "mystical" sense common in New Age thinking, but simply the act of hiding one's real ideas and arguments behind contradiction, riddles, poor arguments, etc. When reading these, I immediately jumped to the question that I'm sure all readers do - are these works themselves esoteric, and if so what are they trying to say beyond their exoteric meaning?</p>
      <p>I'm sad to say that I don't have a firm conclusion on this subject. Just a lingering doubt that I might be missing something (and something big at that) in all three of these books. Combing over them for repetitions with slight differences, deliberately poor reasoning, careful wordings filled with implication, and building up of a strong case only to dismiss it with a weak argument - all of these things seem like they could be interesting and rewarding tasks, but I'm not sure that I'm up to them, and my "Straussian lens" is not polished enough that I think I would get far even if I did. All I am left with is questions, and vague sense that I misread all three of these books and failed to grasp something in the process. Maybe that's part of the intention?</p>
      <p>Even if I did miss something, the exoteric ideas about the change of Western civilization as seen by a professor in 1987, and the recognition that many of the great writers throughout time have hidden their real ideas by various means either to avoid persecution, to ensure only the "worthy" would read them, to protect society from dangerous ideas, or to ready society for a political revolution are interesting food for thought.</p>
      <p>EDIT: Typos and grammar.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>