<post>
  <author>wondroustrange</author>
  <date>2020-07-17T03:28:01Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/hq9eh0/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_july_13_2020/fyboxoo/</link>
  <title>On Straussianism - Saving the Author</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I am somewhat familiar with Straussianism, and have always been tempted by it, though I am by no means an expert. One thing that strikes me about it is that, if we stick to a purely strategic level, it’s an ingenious hermeneutic designed to combat insidious tendencies in what became the postmodern style of reading/ deconstructing texts. While people like Foucault and the post structuralists were soon to declare the death of the author, Strauss was (plausibly) able to save the author by recouping the contradictions and internal tensions of the text on the level of a concealed, but highly unified intentionality. In other words, the work is really the work of that  author, and he has something specific and delimited to say to us, and we can understand him or fail to do so. His words are not an endlessly deferring, productive playfulness.</p>
      <p>On the basis of the esotericism thesis, Strauss is able to ‘deconstruct’ texts with at least as much cleverness as any postmodern interpreter, but with this key difference: while postmodern interpreters give voice to an utterly Dionysian impulse that has no author or speaker, but just is the play and deferral of language revealing and revelling in its own divinity, Strauss’s readings give voice to one of the only several longstanding possibilities of combinations of positions taken by the highest sorts of minds as they’re unified by pragmatic intentions and theoretical longing. This sentence is not well said. I mean, Strauss’s reading of what the author is ‘really’ saying is (in my reading) always a kind of archetype of the pragmatic mind at the highest level as it engages x y and z historical contingencies. His readings deconstruct texts, but always within certain limits and in the horizon of recurring political problems as they are inflected by new historical circumstances. If that makes any sense...Strauss’s authors ‘play’ with us, and are full of trickery—but to some definite end.</p>
      <p>In short, Straussianism becomes more reasonable as a hermeneutic the more one buys into/ sees the contours of the   ‘one great conversation’ he reads all truly great authors/ thinkers as participating in. That conversation is of such a nature that it wasn’t or isn’t always prudent to display it too openly. But Strauss would have had to see himself as ultimately risking imprudence in bringing this to our attention, since he claims to be helping us see what great minds thought best hidden. That he openly published the esotericism thesis must say quite a bit about what he thinks our historical situation is.</p>
      <p>*Edited to add a few more thoughts for clarity.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>