<post>
  <author>DeanTheDull</author>
  <date>2021-01-28T00:32:13Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l4ii8x/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_25/gl0vlif/</link>
  <title>The EU's failed (?) attempt to bolster its image with COVID vaccine development</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'm honestly not sure what your point of dispute (or what the dispute is) here, unless it's a critique solely of the company(ies) the EU signed contracts with, but that might be because I'm taking another context into it- the EU's own diplomatic posturing.</p>
      <p>The EU is led by Europhiles who really, really want to be taken seriously on the global stage. They define themselves in contrast with the Americans as much (or more) than in European commonalities, and making the EU a pillar of the next global order is a reoccuring theme in their diplomatic, economic, and naval-gazing strategizing. Be it 'set the standards' or making Europe a 'digital power' or so on, the EU toots its own horn on how relevant it is and will be, and COVID was no different.</p>
      <p>Last year, a theme of the year once lockdowns became the international norm was the race for a cure. Being the power to produce (and export) a COVID cure was, well, a power project akin to the space race- it would be a demonstration of political power (to start the process), technology (to develop it), economy (to produce it on a scale of hundreds of millions), and altruism (to share it). To be 'first' was a goal, which is why Russia proudly approved <em>two</em> vaccines (by skipping the sort of multi-phase trials that the US and Europeans require).</p>
      <p>The EU tried to be a player in that race. It took the lead (and responsibility) away from individual european countries in order to have a European candidate. It made it's deals on European terms, trying to work with European champions, through European institutions and in the name of... well, I think you get the point. After a decade of European bungles, from economic hashes in the South to repeatedly losing in the cyber-race to losing the chance of even having the UK as a satelite a wish-washy Brexit trade deal, this was the chance for the EU to come together and show what it could do, better than anyone else!...</p>
      <p>...by a relatively unimpressive meh that not only fell behind their erstwhile independent cousins the Brits, or even the questionably effective Chinese, but that American bafoon Donald Trump, whose new york salesmanship of Operation Warpspeed really did look like such compared to sophisticated Europeans. This was the EU's chance to show it could deliver results, and now it's... blaming the European Champions it chose.</p>
      <p>As a prestige project, the EU's efforts are a boomerang that just hit them in the head.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>