<post>
  <author>DuplexFields</author>
  <date>2021-01-30T07:53:11Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l4ii8x/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_25/glcjta0/</link>
  <title>My Little Pony: Goalposts Are Moving</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>What made MLP:FiM special was how it demonstrated diversity and harmony, inclusion and sincerity, in ways that weren't preachy or overwrought. And I fear all those lessons will be shat upon by the way they write the sequel series, starting with the upcoming film.</p>
      <p>For example, the ponies' Christmas-analog holiday is already a sociological lesson in inclusion. A long time ago, the cloud-walking pegasi controlled the weather, the unicorns raised the sun in the morning and the moon at night with horn-magic, and the "earth ponies" (those without horns or wings) grew the food. Over time, there was imbalance and oppression, and emotion-eating monsters ate their hate and started freezing their fair land. Each tribe sent a delegation to search for greener pastures. But when they found a verdant paradise, that land started to freeze too as they argued whether to call it Unicornia, Pegasopolis, or ... Earth. (The earth pony explorer was not the brightest bulb.) They brought their hatred and division with them, and so the leaders of each delegation froze solid. But their underlings became friends, and the warmth of their friendships melted their leaders and saved the day. They named the land "Equestria" and their towns in the new land grew and prospered. This was over a millennium previous to the setting of the show, but the main characters star in a "Heart's Warming" pageant in season 2 to tell the audience that story.</p>
      <p>In the modern day of the story, the earth ponies were at a distinct disadvantage by not having hand-equivalents, yet that tribe weren't looked down upon by the pegasi or made to feel "less than" the unicorns because of it. Neither did they demand some sort of social justice as compensation for not being able to take jobs requiring the use of telekenetic magic like the unicorns, nor job that could use pegasus flight, cloud manipulation magic, or wings-used-as-hands. But this series was created in 2008 and that episode aired in 2011.</p>
      <p>There were also lessons about not judging a book by its cover (a zebra shaman moved into a home just outside of town, coded as an African immigrant), judging a book by what's inside (a gruff griffon treated Rainbow Dash's friends like garbage, and Rainbow had to realize her old friend was no longer good for her), and respecting other cultures and actually listening to them (a pony colony out west planted an orchard in the buffalos' sacred stampede grounds). Later in the series, they made friends with members of other species and even started a school where ponies and non-ponies could learn together, despite segregationary rules for schools in the kingdom.</p>
      <p>The show also showed off different ways to be a woman. Athletic, agricultural, artistic, academic, apprehensive or amiable, each of the ponies had their own likes and dislikes, their own fears and dreams, their own way of fitting into pony society and making a way for themselves. There was a young pegasus whose flight disability was quite apparent, and was mocked by the Mean Girls at her school, but she wasn't a <a href="https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/WheelchairWoobie">Wheelchair Woobie</a>, nor was she treated as <a href="https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/InspirationallyDisadvantaged">Inspirationally Disadvantaged</a> (warning: TV Tropes) by her friends or peers.</p>
      <p>By the end of the series, the main characters were running the country and opening it up to international trade and visitation. The timeskip episode which wrapped up the series showed off the now-cosmopolitan capitol, Canterlot, twenty years hence when there were dragons, yaks, changelings, and other sapient creatures wandering the streets in peace and harmony, and making friends with ponies.</p>
      <p>So, for this new movie and series to take place in the self-same future hard-won by the protagonists of the original series, something needs to have gone terribly wrong. Was the new princess, whose very magical essence and purview was friendship, just incompetent in embodying harmony, which the universe itself granted her a demigodhood to watch over and safeguard? How could friendship have fallen so far in so short a time?</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>"The movie’s main character, for example, is an activist working to make the pony world a better place."</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The first series ended with the pony world having been made a much better place in the first place! (Last place?) If they don't have a good answer for how friendship failed and harmony halted for the other species of the wider world, they'll see their surprisingly robust fandom dwindle to nothing in a matter of one or two seasons.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>