<post>
  <author>FCfromSSC</author>
  <date>2021-02-02T22:09:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l9xgxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_01/glsesmq/</link>
  <title>Promising us an effort post about "policy starvation."</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>America is perfect but is hijacked by pedosatanists and once they get jailed then america will be great again but we can't really tell you what policy will change to make that happen.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Compare the following:</p>
      <p>
        <em>America is hijacked by racist white supremacists and once they all get cancelled and defunded we'll finally have peace but we can't really tell you what policy will change to make that happen again.</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <em>America is hijacked by sexist misogynists and once we change the rules to remove their legal protections we'll finally make life livable for women, but we can't really tell you what policy will change to make that happen again.</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <em>America is hijacked by corrupt wall street executives, and once we change the tax laws and regulatory schemes we'll finally get a handle on wage stagnation and inequality, but we can't really tell you what policy will change to make that happen again.</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <em>America is hijacked by gun companies and their NRA-bought stooges, and once we enact reasonable gun control measures we'll finally get a handle on gun violence and spree shootings, but we can't really tell you what policy will change to make that happen again.</em>
      </p>
      <p>
        <em>America is vulnerable to international Islamic terrorism, and once we spread democracy to the middle east we'll finally get a handle on Islamofascist ideology and restore security to all Americans, but we can't really tell you what policy will change to make that happen again.</em>
      </p>
      <p>...These can be generated arbitrarily for pretty much any live political issue. Not "because the other side is worse". Not "because both sides". We have not had unambiguously good policy options pretty much anywhere in at least a few decades.</p>
      <p>There's a phrase I've been slowly working on an effort post about: "policy starvation". The idea is that to function, politics needs policies for people to invest their hope in. Those policies are provided by leadership. When leadership loses credibility, their policy proposals no longer work as a container for the public's hope, and you get policy starvation, a growing desperation among the public that Something Must Be Done that can't be channeled constructively through moderate methods, and instead leaks through into blossoming extremism.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>