<post>
  <author>HelloGunnit</author>
  <date>2021-02-02T19:25:34Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l9xgxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_01/glrpp8b/</link>
  <title>A police officer's understanding of anti-poice sentiment</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>I'm afraid I still don't understand your point. How would anti-police sentiment have that effect?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Not OP, but I am a police officer in a large city that had about a 250% increase in shootings last year, with most of that increase coming after the anti-police riots started in June;  I'll try to lay out the link as clearly as I can for you.</p>
      <p>First, and most directly, the massive increase in anti-police sentiment  led to massive and continuous riots in many American cities.  These tied up huge numbers of police who would otherwise be on patrol, responding to and investigating homicides, and otherwise deterring potential shooters.   When two thirds or more of your on-duty officers on a given night are deployed to prevent anarchists from burning down your precincts and courthouses, you don't get a lot of regular policing done.</p>
      <p>Second, this anti-police sentiment has made officers very reluctant to do proactive police work (<em>especially</em> with the demographic most like to be committing and suffering from the homicides).  Why would you stop or otherwise engage with a suspect (or any person, for that matter) in a situation where, if the encounter went poorly and you were forced to use lethal force, you would be hyper-scrutinized, and potentially scapegoated with unjust discipline, threats to your life and your family's safety, or politicized prosecution?  Screw that, instead you just answer your 911 calls and try to keep your liability to a minimum by doing as little as is required to keep your paychecks and pension coming.  There is no longer any reward for doing proactive police work, but there is massively increased risk.  </p>
      <p>Now, when you have whole cities full of officers adopting this approach, it does not go unnoticed by the local criminals and gangsters.  They know that there has literally never been a better time to do the sorts of things that can often end in homicide and get away with it.  So, want to settle an old score? Want to make a move to secure your gang more territory?  Want to expand your dealing operation?  Why the hell not?  You're probably going to get away with it.  God knows Officer HelloGunnit isn't going to bother you if he doesn't absolutely have to.  He wants to keep his job, which (due to the broken and paradoxical incentive structure created and fostered by the current anti-police mania) means he needs to avoid actually doing it.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>