<post>
  <author>JTarrou</author>
  <date>2021-02-01T12:31:54Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l4ii8x/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_25/gllb43u/</link>
  <title>What the working class wants</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>Overall, I suppose I'm left with this question - What do you want then?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I must confess here, I have to split the answers between what I personally want and what my best guess is about what my fellow working class wants. Personally, I don't want anything. I'm fine. I make enough money to pay my bills with enough left over to feed my hobbies, I live in an unremarkable neighborhood with low crime. I have a good relationship with a lovely wife. I am respected among my peers. What follows is largely under the assumptions I make putting myself in the shoes of my co-workers and friends. Some, no doubt, would like to rise to the middle classes, but aspiration is not strong among the working class. It certainly isn't with me. </p>
      <p>The first thing I try to impress on people is that the working class does not give much of a fuck about really, really rich people. In abstract, they might dislike displays of wealth (or like them), but they only get pissed off when the rules are blatantly rigged (like with the current GME thing). Their ire is reserved for two groups (described as they might think of them), snooty puritanical middle class bigots who use purported racism to justify their class hatred and underclass degenerates who make their lives hard daily. The working class doesn't want the jobs nor the lifestyle of the middle classes, but a little less raw hatred, bigotry, and open discrimination wouldn't go amiss. I think I can boil it down to respect. The middle classes do not respect the people who fix their cars and their toilets, sell them their groceries, grow their food, protect their communities. They hark back to the post war period not just because union jobs had relatively good wages back then, but because work was easy to find, labor was in demand, and the society at least paid lip service to the working man. It was a position of some respect to be a family man with a steady job. The biggest loss is not monetary, but status. </p>
      <p>But the big thing, and the reason why facile "just increase the social safety net" solutions are never going to be popular with the working class is that it lumps them together with the underclass. You're offering someone whose whole life is a struggle with the discipline to avoid sliding into that category a free ride there. The working class is intimately familiar with the various problems of the underclass, many of them grew up underclass. Almost everyone has family members who slid into that category. Working class success is being able to move your family away from any and all underclass people. Offering to subsidize them to stay poor and live in crime-ridden neighborhoods next to thieving, drug-addicted neighbors so they can watch their kids become petty criminals or worse is very generous, but deeply misguided. </p>
      <p>I have to go to work, I'll edit this later with some proposed solutions.</p>
      <p>Edit: I asked around work a bit today to see what my co-workers thought would be the best policy to benefit the working class. Answers were varied and sometimes contradictory, and were fairly balanced politically. Some wanted higher or lower minimum wage, some UBI, some free healthcare. Trade and labor protectionism got some support (mostly from the older people), and at least one vote for "disband the government". Greater welfare spending had no mentions, and nothing for any educational programs, EITC increases or small business support. One co-worker did sort of allude to what I've been saying about relative status, saying something like "the problem with working service jobs is that customers are assholes".</p>
      <p>On a personal level, my read is that the things that would help the working class most is high labor demand, greater social status, and a change to social mores about public interactions with workers. Whatever the arguments for and against immigration, it's bad for the working classes specifically. I've played with the idea of a hybrid UBI/EITC where the government could match some percentage of earned wages below certain thresholds. Stronger worker protections and higher minimum wage would benefit current workers, but perhaps at the cost of reducing the access of the underclass risers to the working class. And that brings me to one final thing. Reducing/incarcerating/segregating the underclass from the working class. Once more, the trade-offs may not be worth it, but purely in terms of what would benefit the working classes, safe, secure, low crime neighborhoods is a big one. This is probably well beyond the reach of current politics, but it's huge. As ever, the problem with being poor isn't a lack of money, it's having to live near the sort of people who tend to stay poor.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>