<post>
  <author>KulakRevolt</author>
  <date>2021-02-01T18:28:55Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l9xgxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_01/glmpiyl/</link>
  <title>How to steal an election without stuffing a single ballot box</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>(I’m sorry if this is snarky, but I don’t think these ideas can be expressed without heat)</p>
      <p>So pretty much every single political movement in history has endorsed positions wild enough to be considered crazy by anyone not in the movement.</p>
      <p>To take examples from the left:</p>
      <p>The idea that Climate change will not just cause large amounts of economic and human damage (predicted at 3-5% of recurring GDP per annum by 2100 last I checked) but will literally render the earth uninhabitable, is not supported by any study I know of and the only reason they aren’t considered Doomsday cultists and conspiracy theorists for thinking so... is because the political class and climate scientists find them useful.</p>
      <p>Likewise the people who believe trump was Litterally a russian asset.</p>
      <p>Likewise the people who believe “Murdered by cop”, is a major cause of Black male deaths. (I’ve literally seen people claim that this is why black teens have such a high mortality rate.</p>
      <p>Or the feminists who believe 20+% of women will be raped in the 4 years they’re in college.  Or the feminists that believe the 72 cents on the dollar “For the exact same job” talking point unironically. Or the feminists who believe.... sorry I won’t pick on the feminists, but if you’ve hung out on the internet you’ll know the list.
.</p>
      <p>And lets not even get into the stuff Fascists, Communists, and Libertarians literally believe.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Believing utter and complete bullshit that is demonstrably false but is a simpler, more inflammatory, easier to understand, and better for organizing... thats Standard Operating Procedure for any modern political movement.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>The remarkable thing about the right isn’t the crazy demonstrably false delusions, its how long they desperately clung to “Facts and Logic” as if arguing about Austrian economics, the wage gap, or any of their white papers would ever effect anything.</p>
      <p>As if there is a single institution left in America for whom “Arguing the facts rationally” could ever work for anyone the regime didn’t want to win.</p>
      <p>“Oh you have tons of citations are incredibly well researched, and want to present the facts and logic you’ve assessed. Sure that worked so well for James Damore. Oh you think there is a blatant constitutional violation that attacks the very foundation of American society and you can prove it? Sure that worked out so well for Edward Snowden.”</p>
      <p>The “No you can’t just make up claims about a stollen election, a president Involved in Sexual extortion schemes, all to sell out the country to a hostile former Communist Bloc power, and then have hundreds of thousands of your supporters show to riot and attack people in the street”
<a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trump-inauguration-protests-idUSKBN1540J7">Is a bit rich</a>. I mean it wasn’t as if Trump himself was forced to hide in the white house bunker in the past year because of a riot in response to Fentanyl overdose actively misreported as a police murder or anything.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>The Election 100% was stolen. But it was stollen via the selective criminalization of 1A protected activity such that you could attend BLM events but not Church or your friends weddings, the justification of this suspension of fundamental political liberty with the justification “You can do everything online” combined with the active pressuring of every Social media and online institution to censor and ban anyone who disagrees with the regime, the changing of the voting process to one that favours the demographics of one party over the other, often via unconstitutional means and in direct contravention of the will of state legislatures.</p>
      <p>The election was 100% stolen because there is no such thing as a “Free and Fair election” in a fascist society which has suspended freedom of assembly.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>The fact that Red Tribers are switching to the “factually inaccurate but morally correct” talking point that the election was literally stollen via fake ballots is nothing new, directly on par with everything else we’ve seen this century, completely analogous to what our “Trusted institutions” did after the past election, and pretty much a 1-1 borrowing of all the rhetorical techniques, conflations, and willful ignoring of demonstrable reality that has been prettymuch standard in State Funded University Courses and Federal Circuit courts since I was a wee university Student hearing about this Milo Yiannopolis and Jordan Peterson fellow citing the statistics you’re not allowed to cite, for the very first time.</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>Welcome to the low trust society. Were even if the institution is not actively cheating you <em>this time</em>, its better to lie and hurl the accusation than surrender territory for when every other institution fucks you later.</p>
      <p>We could have avoided this. The Tea-Party and Everyone was happy to have a debate on the “facts and logic”. The PraggerU, Dave Rubin, and Ben Shapiro even made brands out of it and were uncomfortable with the whole Trump thing when it happened... but nope they got sneered at and chased off campus.</p>
      <p>So if “72 cents on the Dollar” and “Climate change will kill us all in 12 years” is the acceptable level of academic discourse, if the Pisss-Tape rumours are the standard for national news, and blatant conspiracy theories the standard for getting fucking FISA warrants, if the constitution means so little that AMENDMENT 1 gets selectively suspend for everyone during an election year on the basis of whether the elites find your cause useful or not.... </p>
      <p>why should the country rubes hold themselves to a higher standard?</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>