<post>
  <author>maiqthetrue</author>
  <date>2021-02-01T22:25:14Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l7m9gj/friday_fun_thread_for_january_29_2021/glnpu36/</link>
  <title>The central cultural importance of striving</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I think in a sense it's our whole society.  We're all pathetic in a sense simply because our society has long since stopped really <em>striving</em>, and certainly doesn't demand much of most people.  Which I think is how almost everything has gone a bit sideways.  </p>
      <p>I'm reading a good bit of older (like Greek and Roman old, though I'm reading Confucius as well) and what's striking to me is the earnestness with which they approached all parts of their lives and what they demanded their followers strive for.  Nobody really thinks that this stuff is 100% achievable, nobody expects to be a Stoic sage or a Buddha.  Nobody expects to be virtuous 100% of the time.  But I think the striving for such things is good for individuals, and as a collective healthy for society.</p>
      <p>I think that's what attracts me to things like classical texts and martial arts and philosophy.  The honor is in the difficulty, the striving to achieve something difficult for a noble purpose.  Engineering can be great -- if the thing being built is a worthy thing.  Musk building a ship to push humanity into space is a noble, high calling.  Tweaking the iPhone 12 into the iPhone 13 by removing the earphone jack is a vapid use of brainpower.  Being virtuous is a noble thing, a war in some cases with the part of your psyche that wants to take the quick and easy path.  A person, male or female who puts themselves at risk for a noble cause is noble.  The guy who does the same for thrills is just an adrenaline junkie.</p>
      <p>In the absence of a real need to develop those kinds of things, most things we do end up being basically masterbation, in the Fight Club sense.  It's really just going through the motions of doing things that were, at one point, there to propel you to be ready to do the right thing, or to make you into the kind of person who would.  But because of how society is at the moment, with no goals to strive for, no standards to maintain, and no real difficulties to face, there's no benefit to doing those things other than your own private hedonistic pleasure.  And besides which, a lot of these activities have been reduced to play acting.  Sword fighting becomes fencing, which is by this point a glorified game of tag played with bendy bits of metal.  Philosophy has become closer to being nothing more than a word game played by PhDs rather than a way of living that people were expected to do.  Reading difficult books doesn't matter much because most texts you'd encounter outside that book club are much simpler.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>