<post>
  <author>Rov_Scam</author>
  <date>2021-01-29T02:06:40Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l4ii8x/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_25/gl6hd9w/</link>
  <title>How the GameStop short squeeze came to be</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I'd say it's a war against the stupid decisions certain investment firms make that end up having significant effects on the economy if left unchecked. Jim Cramer said the other day that the number of short positions taken on the target companies was untenable and that any firm worth its salt should have realized that. Short squeezes aren't some new thing that we're just hearing about now; they've been around forever and supposedly sophisticated investment firms should be aware of them and the risks associated with short positions more generally. The very idea that a hedge fund would have so much exposure in a single position that it would bring down the entire company is absurd. (Yes, I know that in short positions the exposure is theoretically unlimited but you still need a mitigation strategy).</p>
      <p>The underlying issue is that the funds in question saw shorting these companies as enough of a sure bet that they were willing to overcommit. When that mentality starts to infect the industry the resulting culture change can put the entire industry at risk. Look at what happened prior to the 2008 financial crisis: Mortgage-backed securities were thought to be basically sure bets for a variety of reasons that seemed fairly reasonable at the time. Even the ratings agencies and insurance companies didn't see a problem. But when it turns out that these things are worthless and they've been bought and sold and packaged and repackaged so many times that the banks themselves aren't even sure how much exposure they have and the whole system goes to crap because of it.</p>
      <p>It's not too hard to imagine a scenario where the kind of shorting that Melvin was involved in leads to a similar outcome. Imagine hedge funds started making a ton of money on shorts that were 138% of float or higher. This is unusual, but the conventional wisdom (which is being made up on the fly) becomes that the higher the percentage, the surer the bet, and this pans out enough to be a reasonable belief. The practice soon spreads to regular investment firms, and becomes commonplace enough that it's sort of a self-fulfilling prophecy—if there are a lot of short positions on a stock, the market as a whole avoids it and the short positions make money. Enough money, in fact, that large investment banks have no problem lending these funds money to buy regular stocks on margin. Eventually, though, a heavily-shorted stock has an unexpectedly good quarter or something and the short position loses money. This triggers investors to start looking into the fundamentals of other heavily-shorted stocks and they start finding ones that are undervalued. A wave of short squeezes ensues, driving a number of funds out of business. Except that a number of major banks have lent billions of dollars to these funds that they can now never hope to get back, etc., etc., and before you know it an obscure sector of the financial markets has now led to a global economic meltdown. There's probably a number of technical reasons that this particular scenario is unlikely to happen, but if you'd suggested in 1997 that the subprime housing market would trigger global financial collapse people would've told you you were nuts. </p>
      <p>My overall point is that when the smart money gets out over their skis like this someone has to play sheriff so that the damage is limited to the funds themselves and not the economy at large. The fall of Melvin Capital isn't going to cause a recession in and of itself. At the very least this should be a sobering reminder to firms that it's wise to limit your exposure, even if you think the investment can't fail.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>