<post>
  <author>SandyPylos</author>
  <date>2021-02-02T03:38:20Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l9xgxr/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_february_01/glou86y/</link>
  <title>Physical versus mental coercion, propaganda and myths, truth and lies</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>But, is there a better explanation for why their purported beliefs appear so detached from reality?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>One thing that I recall picking up from Chomsky is a point that, as the hegemonic power of control through physical coercion has declined, it has become ever more necessary for a society to exert control over the minds of its individuals.  This is done through schools and institutions, but principally through the media.</p>
      <p>In Orwell's <em>1984</em>, we note that the outer party is more indoctrinated than the proletariat, because the proletariat has no power, and there is no need to indoctrinate the powerless.</p>
      <p>Not that such a thing would be possible.  If you have ever spent much time with the working and underclasses, you know that they get most of their information not from sanctioned sources, but from one another - word of mouth, facebook, email, rumor and innuendo.  Like the old game of "telephone" what is whispered in one ear emerges unrecognizable at the end of the chain, propaganda entering the informal information networks of the lower classes swiftly and inevitably shifts, twists and inverts into forms utterly alien to the intent of its creators.</p>
      <p>The professional class, though?  The credentialed elite?  They sip pure propaganda straight from the source.</p>
      <p>I am going to posit something - a conspiracy theory is a <em>myth</em>.</p>
      <p>What kind of information can survive the constant trolling and miscommunication of the rumor mill?  Not one that is based on facts.  Dry facts would quickly be misremembered or just forgotten.  A signal that evolved in such a high-noise environment would not depend on facts for its continued existence.  It would be a malleable story.  One capable of adapting to any number of facts in support, losing those facts, and then adopting the opposite of those facts.  A story that depends on critical facts - that's not going to survive long in a game of telephone.</p>
      <p>What will survive?  A story that reflects the lived truth of those passing it on.  A story that provides meaning to those passing it on.  A story that serves the needs of those passing it on.  A <em>myth</em>.</p>
      <p>The situation we currently have in America, then, is one where the upper classes believe in propaganda, and the lower classes believe in myths.</p>
      <p>Are we seeing the Republican leadership expounding more myths?  Well, that just indicates that the Republicans are becoming a working-class party.  Back in the 70's and 80's the conspiracy theories were mostly on the left - the FBI killed Kennedy, the CIA created crack and HIV.  Welcome to the partisan inversion.</p>
      <p>I am going to suggest something else as well.  The propaganda of the upper classes consists of true facts carefully orchestrated to tell a lie.  The myths of the lower classes consist of false facts that through a savage process of natural selection have evolved to tell a truth.</p>
      <p>He that hath ears to hear, let him hear.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>