<post>
  <author>VassiliMikailovich</author>
  <date>2021-01-30T03:12:42Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/l4ii8x/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_25/glbtawr/</link>
  <title>GameStop stock and the market as a Potemkin village</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>[PREFIX: I AM NOT GIVING FINANCIAL ADVICE DO NOT MAKE FINANCIAL DECISIONS ON THE BASIS OF A SINGLE REDDIT POST]</p>
      <p>So <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/TheMotte/comments/l4ii8x/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_january_25/gl0luyp/">two days ago</a> my prediction was 75% that most of the people piling into Gamestop and related shorted stocks (AMC, etc) were going to get hosed before next Tuesday, 25% that they break the financial system. Over the past day or two it seems like the former position has become somewhat overrepresented, which makes some sense on a community so closely connected to rationalism. Yet the latter is looking more likely than it did than it did then so I'd like to put forward some of the plausible reasons that this could break the market before it breaks the "retail investors" in heavily shorted stocks.</p>
      <p>The biggest issue is that stock prices in 2021 are <em>already</em> disconnected from whatever you think the "real value" is. The question I was asking a few days ago was "Is Gamestop <em>really</em> three times more valuable than Valve?" but the question I started asking this morning was "Is Tesla <em>really</em> three times more valuable than Toyota?" and frankly the difference appears to be that in Tesla's case it was big hedge funds and investors squeezing shorts whereas now it's regular idiots on the internet squeezing shorts. In a 0% interest rate, yield starved environment there's no particular reason why you can't keep an unprofitable company going indefinitely on pure speculation (hence why the percentage of "zombie corporations" is up to 20%) so long as people don't cash out all at once. The supply of money is enormous compared to the number of "financially disfavoured" stocks even if the stock market overall is theoretically overvalued.</p>
      <p>Once upon a time short sellers would have brought things back in line, but after a decade of short sellers being demonized for causing markets to crash they've been put in a position where shorting is public information and a sufficiently large crowd can replicate a big Fed announcement or an actual bailout. Even if you think the a stock is a house of cards you can't easily short it without risking comically outsized losses, so the best you can do is say "I think this is a house of cards!" and hoping people decide to sell. The only conceivable downward pressure is from the holders themselves deciding to sell spontaneously. So this is the key question: <em>how many squeezers are prepared to lose all the money they put in</em>? </p>
      <p>The theory is that this is just a get rich quick scheme and it'll burst just like the Dot Com bubble or any other speculation, with the clever Wall Street guys taking the shirts off of dumb laymen. If we were playing by conventional, pure profit motive in a cutthroat environment game theory then I'd agree. But I'd posit that there are two distinct differences:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>Most of the people buying aren't doing it on margin, and the ones who have been have already been squeezed at the low at a seemingly insufficient volume to cover the shorts. Normally speculative bubbles burst when the big guys decide to start jacking up the margin requirements and making calls to force players to either drop a position or start losing money but if the stocks are purchased with cash then none of those tricks work. The Hunt Brothers failed to corner Silver because they were buying with borrowed money instead of cash but if they hadn't been vulnerable to margin calls then presumably they could have held onto their silver hoard and kept prices high long enough to make the US financial system cry uncle (or until they just went full FDR and started seizing silver)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Ironically, the fact that retail investors by definition aren't trading professionally means they aren't constrained the way professionals are. They aren't obliged to consistently have a performance of +x% over y period of time or risk getting laid off, they don't have industry standard predetermined portfolio allocations, they aren't constrained (yet) by traditional SEC regulations on market manipulation and if they lose 100% on a trade they can shrug their shoulders and say "Guess you can't win 'em all". <em>Especially</em> if that money is money they otherwise would have spent on some useless consumer goods or overpriced booze at the bar or strippers it's easy to write it off as a loss, a kind of "pandemic compensation" lottery ticket with <em>much</em> more favourable odds. Multiplied by millions of people and you've got what would happen if you had a major bank that could pump any asset unbound by decades of convention and SEC regulation that also happened to be at least partially unconcerned with pure profit. </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>In fact, if the retail investors don't get the hint that they're supposed to flee en masse like a traditional Wall Street panic then the professionals will have to start getting involved themselves to maintain any reasonable amount of yield. If there are enough disciplined/crazy/gambling shares that aren't willing to sell and can't be forced to sell then in a world where financialization is king the professionals (at least the smart ones) who were best at finding the intersection of "undervalued", "safely leveraged" and "memeworthy" could be the ones to rake in cash much like how traders profit by accurately predicting rate cuts, quantitative easing and bailouts. Personally I don't see how someone who wins at the market because they knew that the Fed was going to cut rates and engage in QE or because the US Government decided they were big enough to receive emergency liquidity is any more representative of a legitimate or sustainable market strategy than the guy who understands internet culture and can decipher "meme stock strategy" before the herd does, but at least the latter isn't beating the general public and legitimate underdog short sellers to the benefit of the politically connected, he's beating clueless, flat footed zombie investors to the benefit of (statistically) young anti-establishment types.</p>
      <p>We've already seen what could be the beginnings of this phenomena. ZoroHodge (replace the first and third o's with e's, Reddit hates him!) was making tweets about the possibility of the "most shorted" stocks surging at the expense of everything else and indeed two weeks later (<a href="https://www.zorohodge.com/markets/crypto-jumps-january-hedgies-suffer-greatest-stock-short-squeeze-history">https://www.zorohodge.com/markets/crypto-jumps-january-hedgies-suffer-greatest-stock-short-squeeze-history</a> same procedure) that's exactly what happened: two days after some random guy on the internet published a list of the most shorted stocks (up to then a basket no professional had bothered to track) they were up 100% in just two days and the most shorted on the Russell 2000 were up a mind boggling <em>1400%</em>.</p>
      <p>Regardless, there's pretty clear evidence that the "they're just ruffians who only caused minor damage" crowd is seriously underestimating the situation. The Goldman VIP fell in perfect lockstep with the rise of the "most shorted" basket while the S&amp;P500, Dow and even <em>bonds</em> simultaneously collapsed. I'm not saying it's <em>certain</em> that there are a ton of huge institutions that are still sitting on massively losing shorts that have been selling literally everything they have to avoid margin calls but that's <em>sure as hell what it looks like from the outside</em>. If all those overleveraged shorts felt safe because they had special deals with their brokers then it sure seems strange that they aren't sticking with the "safe fundamentals" and ignoring the craziness of a few "minor" stocks.</p>
      <p>The title of <a href="/r/wallstreetbets">/r/wallstreetbets</a> is fitting because it really does represent a bet. On the one hand is the conventional wisdom backed by most of the financial establishment and posters here that the market is efficient, that the disproportionate losses of retail traders under "normal conditions" are the result of professionals being inherently more knowledgeable and that current market prices are basically representative of reality. On the other is a wacky coalition that started with a bunch of internet memesters with money to burn that increasingly picked up support from the "wacky outsiders" of finance: the bitcoin billionaires, the gold and silverbugs, the permabulls, the permabears, crazy Chinese financiers and Elon Musk that all came to the conclusion that the current stock market <em>isn't</em> representative of reality and that with enough volume <em>we can prove it</em>. </p>
      <p>I may disagree with the EMH (except in its absolute weakest form, maybe) and <a href="/u/greyenlightenment">/u/greyenlightenment</a> most of the time but there's one thing he's right about: if you <em>really believe</em> that markets are efficient at all then you can't just dismiss all these moves as "irrational exuberance". At least consider the <em>possibility</em> that decades of impositions and constraints from the half dozen Federal financial regulators, not to mention short pressure from the biggest players, have created a Potemkin village of a stock market.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>