<post>
  <author>Cheezemansam</author>
  <date>2020-05-30T01:34:45Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fs9i0yj/</link>
  <title>Shameful Police Acquittals </title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>In virtually every one of these "white officer kills black man" blow ups that I can think of, either it turns out the shooting was justified (Michael Brown), not actually murder (Eric Garner, Freddie Gray), or the police officer goes to jail ( Laquan McDonald, Walter Scott). The officer who killed George Floyd is in the process of being held accountable.</p>
        <p>
          <strong>Walter Scott</strong>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Yea, he was charged <strong>after</strong> a video surfaced that showed that the official police report was a lie. And not "resisting arrest when he wasn't moving much" but "Running the literal opposite direction". How many times has an officer gotten away with it when there isn't a video? That is a big part of the concern.</p>
      <p>For some "Manslaughter/etc." that seems pretty objectionable, but no guilty verdict:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>
          <strong>Philando Castile</strong>
        </p>
        <p>Killed while reaching for his drivers liscense, ostensibly <em>at the direction</em> of the officer. Officer claimed he was reaching for a gun. He had no gun.</p>
        <p>Aquitted</p>
        <p>
          <strong>Aiyana Jones</strong>
        </p>
        <p>Police kill a girl while conducting a raid. They lie that the grandmother "made them do it" by hitting the gun; evidence contradicts this.</p>
        <p>Mistrials/Aquitted</p>
        <p>
          <strong>Kenneth Chamberlain Sr.</strong>
        </p>
        <p>Medical alert necklace was inadvertently triggered, police broke in (despite objections from Chamberlain, who denied help), tazed and shot him. One of the officers shouted "<strong>NIGGER</strong>" while banging on the door</p>
        <p>No indictment</p>
        <p>
          <strong>Rekia Boyd</strong>
        </p>
        <p>Off duty officer approached group of 4 individuals, later discharged firearm at them, claiming someone had a gun. No gun was ever recovered. Multiple witnesses testified that he appeared drunk.</p>
        <p>Judge gave a rare directed verdict, as the prosecutor had <em>under</em> charged him (it could not have been recklessness, if he was guilty it <em>must</em> have been 1st degree murder).</p>
        <p>
          <strong>Timothy Russell and Malissa Williams</strong>
        </p>
        <p>Thirteen police officers fired at Russell and Williams 137 times while they were in their car at a parking lot of a middle school after a car chase. The was no gun/shots fired at the police officers.</p>
        <p>Primary officer aquitted</p>
        <p>
          <strong>John Crawford III</strong>
        </p>
        <p>Was holding airsoft rifle, someone called 911 saying he was waving it at people, video evidence shows that John <strong>never</strong> pointed it at another customer. Officers arrived and killed him.</p>
        <p>No indictment</p>
        <p>
          <strong>Laquan McDonald</strong>
        </p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Yes, the officer was found guilty but they covered it up:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Police had initially reported that McDonald was behaving erratically while walking down the street, refused to put down a knife he was carrying, and lunged at the officers. <em>When a court ordered the police to release a dash cam video of the shooting thirteen months later, on November 24, 2015, it showed McDonald had been walking away from the police when he was shot.</em></p>
        <p>Guilty of 2nd degree murder</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>I agree that in general a lot of these stories are far from the "black and white; police can straight up murder black people and get away with it" but there are incidents where there have been some terribly objectionable police shootings but no verdict.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>