<post>
  <author>CriticalDuty</author>
  <date>2020-05-30T22:26:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fsd3d20/</link>
  <title>The American Dream: Anti-Blackness Mingled With Feigned Respect</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I occasionally peruse a forum that I will not name here, and which can best be described as a haunt for intelligent, high-functioning racists who like to think of themselves as several cuts above the drooling riff-raff of Stormfront, Vanguard and associated sites. There is another user's post from around 2013 that I am posting here, both for relevance and as a starting point:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Blacks are responding to American social and moral pathology - they are being inundated with culturally and historically nonsensical mixed messages.</p>
        <p>Blacks for the first three centuries after the settling of the New World were instructed that they were entitled to White patronage, in exchange for servile obedience and upright behavior. Quite suddenly, they were ripped out of this paradigm and told they were ''equal'' to the White man and forced to compete with the White man as free labor.</p>
        <p>Of course, this circumstance was untenable, and it resulted in mass-incarceration of blacks and other dysfunctional social conditions.</p>
        <p>The problem is that Whites pretend to hold Blacks in high esteem and carry on this affected pose of ''equality'' - Blacks discern this and it both confuses them and provokes them to rage.</p>
        <p>An interesting comparative juxtaposition is how the Japanese traditionally look at Burakumin - Japanese don't pretend to like the Burakumin, and don't feign any belief that they are ''equals''. However, the Burakumin were and are free to pursue their own endeavors, and some actually become and became quite wealthy. However, it would not have occurred to anybody to make-believe that these people are viewed as anything other than ritually unclean and basically inferior.</p>
        <p>For all the Karl Popper-esque horseshit about traditional societies being ''closed'' and thereby oppressing the emotional and intellectual lives of people, its actually Anglo-derived societies that elevate lying to a moral imperative. This has very serious social and political consequences.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Now obviously the post is filled with various claims that can be challenged, and you can go ahead and do that, but I would derive the following points from it:</p>
      <p>1) Post-emancipation, descendants of American slaves found themselves in a labor market where they were competing against workers who had much more cultural, social and economic capital. This includes immigrant workers; the popular image of Ellis Island-era immigration might be Vito Corleone arriving as a stowaway with nothing but the shirt on his back, but a lot of immigrants did come to America with <em>some</em> amount of capital - they would need to, crossing the ocean isn't free - and more importantly, a lot of immigrants had contacts in the old country that they could tap for resources to help them in America. Who were black people going to call on in Africa? </p>
      <p>There's some truth to the Coatesian narrative that a degree of <em>anti-blackness</em> has always been mixed into the American Dream; non-black immigrants, including Asian and Latin American immigrants, had a much easier time forming connections with the institutions of the white American mainstream and drawing benefits from the American economy. Immigrant communities often did intermarry and form closer connections both with each other and the white mainstream, but there existed a stigma against intermarrying with black people, sometimes unsaid, sometimes explicit. Of course, in many parts of the United States there were legal barriers as well, but intermarriage rates suggests the stigma lasts into the present day.</p>
      <p>If you could break up the economy into demographic components, the "white economy" and the "immigrant economy" found ways to profit off each other, and the "black economy" wasn't able to draw these benefits. Some black economic ventures were also destroyed in race riots, but contrary to narratives about how, for example, Black Wall Street would have been a gamechanger, I don't think they would have lasted in the long run. It's the racial equivalent of what happened with NAFTA - peasant farms in Mexico aren't going to compete with giant American agri-corps, they're going to be crushed underfoot by them, and their remains are going to be swallowed up into the larger entity as a re-branded possession. The same goes here; without an astonishing degree of protectionism that would probably resemble a separate economy entirely, institutions that are formed by black people for the purposes of building black communal wealth are going to be undercut, driven out of business or consumed by larger white-dominated institutions that have greater and more favorable access to capital, vendors, markets and the like. </p>
      <p>And not only do the descendants of Caribbean slaves come to the United States with some amount of capital, but their kids disproportionately <a href="http://archive.is/nTku#selection-249.0-249.403">receive</a> benefits that were earmarked for the success of the descendants of American slaves - </p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>While about 8 percent, or about 530, of Harvard's undergraduates were black, Lani Guinier, a Harvard law professor, and Henry Louis Gates Jr., the chairman of Harvard's African and African-American studies department, pointed out that the majority of them -- perhaps as many as two-thirds -- were West Indian and African immigrants or their children, or to a lesser extent, children of biracial couples.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>2) I wish I could remember where I'd seen it, but I once saw a post somewhere that the hallmark of upward mobility in America is acquiring the ability to curate how many black people are in your life, and that's probably true. I have an aunt who lives in a wealthy zipcode of New Jersey with my cousin; this aunt once told me a story, from back when she and my uncle had much less money, about how her car broke down one afternoon in Trenton (more than twenty years ago, when my cousin was just a toddler). It was just her and a little girl waiting on the streets of Trenton for a mechanic, with some of the locals gathering around to check out the lady in the broken car. Hearing this story was, I think, the first time I ever heard someone use the phrase "sweating bullets" in a conversation. Now my cousin is all grown up, my aunt and uncle are much richer, so she's living a cosseted existence in a suburb just outside Princeton and sighing about how white the area is. At the same time, she's a student at Fordham who splits an apartment with friends in Hell's Kitchen because she does not want to live anywhere near the Bronx or Harlem. </p>
      <p>Simply put, there are a lot of people who talk about how they value diversity and black lives who will go to whatever lengths are within their means to avoid living near too many black people. I don't blame them at all, but you can see how this might rankle black sensibilities - if you live in a neighborhood that middle class people don't want to enter and poor people can't wait to leave, your opportunities and resources are going to be restricted, but at the same time you're fed constant cultural messaging about your social desirability and cultural vibrancy. This dissonance has to have an explanation, and if the obvious explanation of "safety" can be stigmatized in polite discourse as an unacceptable dog-whistle, then the only narrative anyone is going to hear is about deliberate economic deprivation of black neighborhoods by deceitful whites.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>