<post>
  <author>Gloster80256</author>
  <date>2020-05-30T18:28:00Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fsc0b9m/</link>
  <title>Slavery's Legacy, and Black Culture's Incompatibility With Bourgeois Experience</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I have a different take - which is however still compatible with the systemicity of the problem.</p>
      <p>Slavery and Jim Crow had seriously wounded and molded black culture, to a point where it became, in places, incompatible with the standard bourgeois<sup>1</sup> existence. </p>
      <p>There was scarcely any common culture to speak of at the beginning, with slaves brought in from all corners of the world and the only real shared basis in the experience of slavery itself. And slavery changes people. It eradicates dissent mercilessly - and thus makes honesty impossible. It teaches those suffering under it to hate and sabotage and cheat the hierarchy. It tears apart families and makes mothers self-reliant and children fatherless, with overseers as the nearest replacement. It certainly shifts time preferences to very near horizons. And social customs and institutions of the survivors adapt to those realities.</p>
      <p>When the direct oppression goes away, the social institutions do not. With a biological frequency of about 0.00000000015 Hz, these things have a laaaaaaaag. There is an immense culture of learned practicality surrounding almost any human activity, from finances (what do you eat? do you cook? where do you buy? how often? how much do you stockpile? do you invest? do you impulse-buy pacifiers when stressed? etc.) to education (is there an inherited family trade? an academic tradition? brotherhoods of craftsmen? who teaches you how to wear a tie?) to family (when do you start dating? when do you start having sex? when do you have kids?) And all these things have a real, cumulative effect on the trajectory of one's life and the likelihood of ending up as an MD, manager or a judge - or in front of a judge. And people don't just jump into the customs of the dominant culture. They naturally don't feel like it to begin with, but more importantly, this stuff isn't taught anywhere. A glimpse of it appears in the mainstream culture, but the bulk is and must be transmitted by a literal tradition from one generation to the next. Uncles teaching you how to ride a bike, because their uncle taught them as well vs. uncles teaching you how to drink because they also started drinking in high school. The Normal Everyday Things that form your structure and your worldview.</p>
      <p>So contemporary American black culture is still coming out of a modus vivendi optimized for a time of oppression and therefore in some of its aspects incompatible and in a chronic conflict with the mainstream ideal and the structure of binding rules erected in its support - which is precisely the phenomenon commonly referred to as "systemic racism". It can't be really blamed on the living, on either side of the racial divide, but it still noticeably affects their lives disparately.     </p>
      <p>(And we could get into how much is this enabled by people who taboo certain aspects of the issue, make honest discussion impossible and so condemn us to blind solutions that do not address, or outright perpetuate, the core problems.)    </p>
      <p>​</p>
      <p>1 The Marxist-flavored word was chosen carefully, as it connotes exactly the right breadth and focus of the term: Respectability, affluence and influence - and with them snobbery, loyalty to the system and obedience to its rules. The image of the Proper Citizen.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>