<post>
  <author>hanikrummihundursvin</author>
  <date>2020-05-31T13:53:49Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gtj8qu/race_and_justice_much_more_than_you_wanted_to_know/fsf7evs/</link>
  <title>Thoughts On Disparate Racial Sentencing</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>I don't think I ignore it in that sense. I ignore the narrative that disparate racial sentencing is often used to support. Your position isn't based on disparate racial sentencing being a horrible issue that needs fixing. It's about conflating that issue with the idea that the justice system as a whole is horrible and racist and emotionally validating the mythical narrative of racism in the justice system. My position is that the racial sentencing gap isn't enough to validate that narrative at all considering all the other factors that show little to no racial bias.</p>
      <p>Just take a while and wonder, with a justice system that is hyper aware of the racial differences it deals with, how does such a bias come about. Are judges, jurors and lawyers racists in disguise, but only expressing it when it comes to sentencing?  I find all of my objections to the idea that a 10-20% disparity(half of which is explained by initial charging decisions) is in any way a meaningful number that validates anything to be confirmed when looking at videos like these:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LLi7jsZHSgY">A homicide isn't just a homicide.</a> A defendant isn't just a defendant. Just watch the clip to the end. Do you have to wonder why Moses doesn't get a chance for parole and instead gets life behind bars? Now what if he cried and said sorry? No really. It must be because of his "ethnicity", right? Has nothing to do with the victim. It's just a 'homicide'.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k8QIY0dM5HA">This one is also very insightful.</a> "He should get the death penalty" after witnessing her mothers murderers laughing in court. But doesn't this racist recognize the racist sentencing disparity she is helping to perpetuate?</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xmIC1hWYrbA">I mean, how many times do you think lawyers tell their defendants to not smile?</a> We should ask sometime. And find out if there is a racial disparity. </p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OYXBwITsQ1k">Stupid remorseless people exist of all colors though.</a> The question is about the rate at which they exist compared to others.</p>
      <p>Now lets have a look at the flipside:</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xh-ugcTcnwQ">He said he was sorry.</a> He had been sorry 2-3 years prior but never had he been 60 years in jail sorry. So he wore his most respectable grill and said 'my bad'. Saved his life.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2TeIGZ2VIf4">"His answer gave her a little piece of justice"</a> From death to life by saying you're sorry and not smirking like a moron.</p>
      <p>So the tl;dw is, the automatic assumption that any disparity that isn't immediately explained when looking at decontextualized data has to be down to racism is stupid. Courtrooms are highly contextual, emotional and fragile. Your notion of blaming racism is born out of you already believing the narrative. A narrative that is not validated by data, but a narrative that seeks to validate itself none the less. This narrative is your belief. And you are not self aware of it being a belief. That is a problem.</p>
      <p>So I just want to take a moment to really appreciate how you seem to be imbued with the same odd and disturbing notion displayed in the article. It's actually surprisingly helpful since you are a bit more on the nose than the author of the article.</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>Does the fact that there are more "black criminals" mean mean that black people who commit crimes should receive longer sentences for the same crime by sin of their ethnicity?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Just read this. Again and again. <strong>THE SIN OF THEIR ETHNICITY</strong>. To answer your extremely out of place question, no, I don't think that. But... how do you know that this is the reason? Like, how on earth... Why is this your default assumption to fall on when the data hasn't explained everything at once that it's racism lurking in the shadows? Especially considering we just read an article that makes great note of how complex the debate on the topic is.</p>
      <p>My position is simple. Criminals going to jail is a good thing. And now, an added position: harsher sentences for criminals who smile in court and laugh in the face of their victims relatives is a good thing. I would not reduce a single year for the kinds of animals who mock the victims relatives just because some racial disparity exists or is perpetuated by it. I don't care if acting properly and respectfully towards your fellow man is a construct of 'whiteness' that is inherently racist. Do you? Should a grieving family just take mockery from their loved ones killer on the chin in the name of racial justice? Just take a moment to appreciate how fucked up the context of that question is.  </p>
      <p>I mean, what is your proposed solution when you don't even know why the 'problem' exists.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>