<post>
  <author>Ilforte</author>
  <date>2020-05-30T06:09:24Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fsa6am8/</link>
  <title>Suppressing Riots is Difficult Politically, Not Practically</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <blockquote>
        <p>is there any particular evidence that this is actually true?</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Pretty calm here in Moscow: no riots, ever. One reason is that Russia is not an effectively biracial country like US (we have quite a few Central Asians, though). The other is that the state is low-key darkly hinting that Rosgvardia and FSB are armed to the teeth and perfectly willing to crush any number of civili – er, American agents – with <a href="https://defendingrussia.ru/upload/images/ckeditor6/_%20-%20Copy%20135.jpg">things like this</a>. Even calmer in Chechnya. Calm in many, many places with worse safety, equality, police professionalism than USA. There was Moldbug's quote I think, about the power of the mob that disappears like morning dew in the face of aerial munitions, can't find it, but it would've been apt.  </p>
      <p>There's a world of difference between a proper insurgency and mere out-of-control mob. Insurgency requires popular support and energized core of grimly determined people with hatred so hot it barely clouds their thinking; and no matter how much oleophobic coating is grinded off smartphones in angry tweeting about racial injustice these days, it's not hard to understand that this is largely performative. The outraged people are not determined to get deep into violence, and those on the ground intend simply to vent some anger, have fun and loot consumerist niceties as part of the mob. Mob is not an insurgency. Mob acts like the meanest and basest thug you can find in a backstreet: it pounces on weakness, indecision, expressions of shame and guilt, jumps a sucker when it sees one; but when smashed on the nose, it quickly retreats. Police all around the world are trained in riot control, and it's a very well developed field. You don't even need to be powerful as much as you need to be obviously brutal, scaring the lawbreakers, rapidly delivering pain to the boldest ones. Thus – traumatic guns, water cannons, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Active_Denial_System">this promising gimmick</a>, pepper spray. Did you ever pepper-spray an aggressive hoodlum? I did once. It was the funniest thing, he just stopped his assault, rotated in place and <em>busily</em> walked away – apparently, it didn't incapacitate him but delivered the message. The spray is made in USA, by a police-oriented firm (Sabre). US is pretty good at this sort of stuff.  </p>
      <p>The failure to suppress riots has nothing to do with intrinsic difficulty and everything to do with politics. The police is not confident in what it's supposed to do, because the chain of command is dysfunctional, media is inciting more riots, suddenly you have to worry about how it'll be seen in the other states, what if you're thrown to the dogs for doing your duty after all, and why not just lose the station instead of shooting and – God forbid – killing someone... Thus, they kinda go through the motions half-heartedly, and lose control. </p>
      <p>It's not such a big deal. Than again, "Berkut" in Ukraine could easily suppress another mob, but tarried too long (for much the same reasons), and it turned into a real insurrection. So, well.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>