<post>
  <author>miley_cyrus_superfan</author>
  <date>2020-05-30T18:43:22Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fsc2ze9/</link>
  <title>Steelmanning Systemic Racism as an Explanation</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>To steelman the systemic racism argument: </p>
      <p>Systemic racism doesn't have to descend from slavery / Jim Crow. As an analogy, those who claim systemic sexism don't generally argue that it is a result of historic coverture. </p>
      <p>At the general level, institutions are designed by humans. Those humans act based on their own experiences and the feedback they get from vocal stakeholders. That leads to institutions that are adapted to the needs of the people who created them and people whose voices are heard. </p>
      <p>You can see clear evidence of this basically everywhere, for both the left and the right. Government organizations are run for the benefit of their employees. Zoning is set up based on the preferences of cranky 70 year olds with time on their hands. Etc.</p>
      <p>Black people have not been the ones designing institutions. Black people's voices haven't been heard to the extent they want. So institutions have not evolved in a manner that takes black needs into account to the extent black people want. </p>
      <p>If you aren't black, you may not see any reason why black needs are different from white needs. However, many black people believe their needs are different and it seems reasonable to trust them on that. If there is a widespread belief among black people that institutions are not meeting the needs of black people, then I'm inclined to believe there is some truth to that.</p>
      <p>Based on this view, here are responses to your points. </p>
      <p>1,4) There is no clear reason why places with more severe systemic racism 60 or 200 years ago would have more systemic racism today. Institutional rules / regulations / culture have evolved dramatically in the intervening decades. To the extent there are more black people in the South, it's entirely possible that there is less systematic racism there.</p>
      <p>2,3) The idea that systematic racism is the entire story is a weakman. I doubt most proponents of systematic racism believe there is no non-systematic racism. More broadly, almost all explanations for racial differences can be used to motivate systematic racism: if group X underperforms in Y for reason Z, then reason Z should also mean they are less effective at shaping institutions and so institutions evolved in a manner inconsistent with the needs of group X. EG: If you believe that redheads underperform because red hair offends Hanbir the pigeon-god, then redheads underperforming should also mean they are less effective at shaping institutions and so institutions should not meet the needs of redheads.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>