<post>
  <author>miley_cyrus_superfan</author>
  <date>2020-05-29T21:42:06Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fs8t5ve/</link>
  <title>Examining Evidence of Anti-Right Wing Social Media Bias</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <a href="/u/CarryOn15">/u/CarryOn15</a> posted a question asking for evidence of anti-right wing social media bias. I thought this was interesting and deserved a top level post. My response: </p>
      <p>In general it's hard to find bias. As an example, suppose you wanted to show that company had a culture of sexism and was biased in hiring and how it treated customers.</p>
      <p>How could you do that? It's actually hard. Almost all of the evidence you could find is circumstantial. Unless the company is really, really dumb you won't find examples where they wrote down "Did not hire this person as they were female." Most decisions are squishy and it's easy to cast sexist decisions as not sexist and vice versa. So what could you do?</p>
      <p>1) You could find comments by people in charge that seemed to show sexism. For example, if execs at the company said they hated women/feminism/feminist icons, most people would see that as evidence of sexism. </p>
      <p>2) You could look at the employee base. If they hire only men, that suggests there may be a discrimination issue. More damning might be if they fired people who spoke out in favor of women's issues or supported feminist causes.</p>
      <p>3) You could look at specific decisions. Did they hire man A over more qualified women B? </p>
      <p>4) You could look at overall policies. Do they create policies that penalize female employees? Do they require all employees to be able to lift 100# despite that being irrelevant for the job? (Redlining is a good example for race.)  </p>
      <p>5) You could look to anecdotes. Note that asking men whether there is discrimination isn't the right thing to do here because they likely won't see it. You need to ask women, both customers and employees.</p>
      <p>None of these are great. There are almost always legitimate, non-discriminatory business reasons for every action and you as an outsider will not grasp the fullness of the challenges the decision makers faced, their information, or what was really going on in their head. You just have to sort of look at things and draw a pattern.</p>
      <p>So let's look at 1-5 for social media sites. </p>
      <p>1) Do we see a strong ideology amongst tech leadership? I'd say that is certainly the case. You regularly see people in high positions at these companies taking "strong" political stances in favor of the left. E.g.: The person managing Twitter's fact checking appears to have posted "We fly over those states that voted for a racist tangerine for a reason", claimed there are actual Nazis in the white house, etc. <a href="https://www.msn.com/en-ca/news/newspolitics/twitters-head-of-site-integrity-compared-kellyanne-conway-to-nazi-leader/ar-BB14FBuI">https://www.msn.com/en-ca/news/newspolitics/twitters-head-of-site-integrity-compared-kellyanne-conway-to-nazi-leader/ar-BB14FBuI</a> E.g.: The leadership of google saying that Trump's election is offensive and conflicts with Google's values (this appears to be an undoctored video) <a href="https://www.breitbart.com/tech/2018/09/12/leaked-video-google-leaderships-dismayed-reaction-to-trump-election/">https://www.breitbart.com/tech/2018/09/12/leaked-video-google-leaderships-dismayed-reaction-to-trump-election/</a></p>
      <p>2) Do we see tech employee bases that are ideologically skewed? I'd say that's clearly the case. We see a massive inbalance in donations within tech companies <a href="https://image.businessinsider.com/5c013d4841cfd8135e6f5f5e?width=600&amp;format=jpeg&amp;auto=webp">https://image.businessinsider.com/5c013d4841cfd8135e6f5f5e?width=600&amp;format=jpeg&amp;auto=webp</a><br />
We see employees who support rightwing causes publically face significant pressure. EG: <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/quora/2014/04/11/did-mozilla-ceo-brendan-eich-deserve-to-be-removed-from-his-position-due-to-his-support-for-proposition-8/#459d60402158">https://www.forbes.com/sites/quora/2014/04/11/did-mozilla-ceo-brendan-eich-deserve-to-be-removed-from-his-position-due-to-his-support-for-proposition-8/#459d60402158</a></p>
      <p>3) Do social media sites take actions that indicate bias? I see evidence of this, but it's never clear as there is always a lot going on. I see Twitter censoring / putting warnings / fact checking Donald Trumps tweets but not the tweets of other extremely popular posters for similar infractions. I see Reddit blocking conservative forums (e.g. the donald), changing their algorithm to deweight their posts, etc. I don't read TD, but the actions that lead to that forum's removal seemed to me (at the time) to be of a similar nature to accepted posts on left wing forums.</p>
      <p>4) Are social media site rules constructed in a way that gives excessive leeway to left wing preferences? This is hard to say. I believe social media sites are more to the left than general culture in enforcing political correctness (which is a left-wing thing). The formal policies have often protected groups favored by the left. For example, a post like "Christians are a disgrace to America" would be fine; "White people are a disgrace to America" would be fine; "Black people are a disgrace to America" would not be (note that formal rules have been updated to be less unbiased in this manner, yet enforcement doesn't appear to be.) In many cases, even factual posts are not acceptable, for example I would expect "Black people commit murders at 5 times the rate of white people" to be deleted on most forums but "White people commit rape at 5 times the rate of black people" to not be deleted.</p>
      <p>5) Do we hear stories of problems? This is certainly the case, however, there are always people who claim discrimination. I don't associate with either the left of the right. I rarely break the rules of forums. My personal experience has been that a factual articulation of an extreme left wing view point doesn't lead to censorship but an extreme right wing view point does. </p>
      <p>In conclusion, I don't think the evidence is damning, but I believe there is significant bias. I'd be happy to hear more informed opinions. I'd love to see an adversarial collaboration on this actually. (Note1: The question of whether this bias should be allowed is different)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>