<post>
  <author>Slootando</author>
  <date>2020-05-30T18:33:32Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fsc1azb/</link>
  <title>Why Large Relationship Age Gaps Are Less Controversial With Younger Males</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>There are two parties with “skin in the game,” to blockade older male access to younger women/teenage girls, whether via laws or cultural norms.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Protective parents of daughters, not wanting their daughters to get poached by older males, especially if the poaching is done by potentially low-status men</strong>. Young women/teenage girls may be poor status detectors, and/or their local evaluation of male status may map poorly outside to more general contexts (e.g. her gym teacher may seem high status to a teenage girl, but likely not to her parents).</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Older women, who (correctly) see younger women/teenage girls as a robust, even superior, source of sexual competition</strong>. As an example, the OkCupid graphs of male vs. female preferences come to mind, where 20 year-old women (with 20 being the lowest limit for the graphs) were generally the most preferred by men, regardless of male age.</p>
      <p>Parties for the converse are non-existent, or at least are much smaller and weaker. Parents are generally not as protective of their sons when it comes to sex, if they’re protective at all. Eggs are expensive; sperm is cheap.</p>
      <p>Older men tend not to view younger men/teenage boys as a general source of sexual competition. For example, the corresponding OkCupid graph showed a linearly increasing relationship between female age and their preferred age for men.</p>
      <p>Generally, the strongest source of objection for older female-younger male relationships come from those calling for equal enforcement, if society will be in the business of policing relationship age-gaps: Your rules enforced selectively &lt; Your rules enforced uniformly &lt; My rules.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>