<post>
  <author>ThirteenValleys</author>
  <date>2020-05-31T05:35:18Z</date>
  <link>/r/TheMotte/comments/gq50mo/culture_war_roundup_for_the_week_of_may_25_2020/fse91qb/</link>
  <title>Viruses Do Not Care About Signaling</title>
  <body>
    <div class="md">
      <p>
        <em>Now it's a customizable, clearly visible signal</em>
      </p>
      <p>I think you're missing EdgeCityRed's point. </p>
      <p>Viruses do not care about signaling. They will really invade your real body and kill you. Wearing a mask first and foremost is a guard against that real thing. </p>
      <p>Now, they can be a signal. Almost anything can be. But if you put the signal first, and the actual thing second, you end up with a profoundly perverse worldview in which goodwill, generosity and charity do not exist, they are literally all fronts in a soulless, heartless game of social status. </p>
      <p>And to what end? So you can dunk on a few hypocrites here and there? Is <em>never trusting anyone's motives are genuine ever again</em> worth that? I mean, who fucking <em>cares</em> about the signal? If Alice wears a mask because she doesn't want to get sick and Bob wears one to satisfy his ego, <em>they're both helping people not get sick.</em> Why does this <em>matter</em> so much, that every good deed has to be dissected like a dead frog in 8th grade biology? </p>
      <p>Any concept that can encompass both 'wearing something that helps you and your family to avoid a deadly virus' and 'Posting on Twitter about 'healthcare heroes' six times a day' is not a concept. It's a lizard-brain expression of spite and contempt directed at people you find viscerally annoying.  </p>
      <p>(Since this subthread is already burning pretty hot I'll throw another coal on the fire. Saying that feminists don't love equality, they just hate men, or that the left covers for failures in the Black community by blaming everything on whites--<em>that's</em> not a signal, oh goodness no. No way saying <em>that</em> on a forum full of people who agree with it is a sign that you want to be accepted or that you're acknowledging the local shibboleths. That's just <em>telling it like it is.</em> Signaling is endemic to all human behavior, except mine. OK, sure.)</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</post>